<u who="#CUMMINGS">So this is <persName>Emily Cummings</persName> speaking with <persName>Juanita [F.]  Ramsey-Jevne</persName>. I am in the <placeName>Rauner Special Collections Library</placeName>, and she is in <placeName>Telluride, Colorado</placeName>. It’s Monday, <date when="2015-10-26">October 26^th^, 2015</date>.
    
    So first I want to say thank you for speaking with me today. Why don’t we start off with some biographical information? What were your parents’ names, and where were you from?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">My father was <persName>Charles Ralph Ramsey</persName>, and my mother was <persName>Waneta Mae [Vieritz] Ramsey,</persName> and I was born in <placeName>Little Rock, Arkansas</placeName>, in <date when ="1958">1958</date>.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Okay. And what did your parents do for a living?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Well, my father was a salesman, an insurance salesman, but he died in <date when="1963">1963</date> of cancer, and then my mother—didn’t work, we just kinda got by—from then on.</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Okay. And what kind of area did you live in?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">We lived in <placeName>Joplin, Missouri</placeName>, after—it was right before my father died. He moved us to <placeName>Joplin, Missouri</placeName> which was a town of about 40,000 in southwest <placeName>Missouri</placeName>.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">And were you living in a suburb or a—</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Oh, we were living in a small, kind of typical <date when="1960">1960s</date> neighborhood, where everybody had—it seemed like, had four kids. Kind of a lower- —lower-middle-class neighborhood of tract housing, [cross-talk; unintelligible].</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">And—</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Go ahead.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">I was just going to ask: Did you enjoy growing up there? Did you like sort of your neighborhood and the area you lived in?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Yeah. We had a great neighborhood and really good schools.  And it was a saving grace. My mom had mental illness, so it was a—inside the house was—was rough. But outside the house, it was great, so thank goodness.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Okay. And so can you talk a little bit more about what it was like inside the house?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Oh, that’s a whole ’nother story So my mom was undiag- —it’s a big story—so my dad died, and my mother had been suffering from mental illness, although I was too little to know it, and then after he died, there were no other adults around. There were no relatives. We didn’t—we didn’t know anybody in the town. So her—her mental illness got worse and worse and worse as we grew up. And we didn’t know she had it.
    
    But luckily it was this town where kids could get jobs, and there was a grocery store and a Laundromat nearby, so considering it was so rough inside the house, we were really lucky that as soon as we walked out the door, it was a pretty supportive world to be able to just—and it was an era when nobody asked too many questions, so—excuse me. [Coughs.] We were able to get jobs and keep ourselves together. And then eventually, in <date when="1975">1975</date>, we were able to get her some help. And—and—and that was—that was great.
    
    But my husband [<persName>William R. “Bill” Jevne</persName>; Class of <date when = "1966">1966</date>, Tuck <date when="1967">1967</date>], who as you know is a veteran of the Vietnam War—when we got together, we used to joke that—excuse me [clears throat]—I have to get a drink of water—we used to joke that he was a veteran of foreign wars and I was a veteran of domestic wars, because [chuckles] of my childhood.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">But we—my mom got help. She always had to take medication, but she’s one of the people who, with medication, lived a happy and productive life, and we all reconciled, so—it was pretty miraculous.  But, like I said, we could talk for hours about _that_.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">[Chuckles]. So what—</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">What _is_ interesting is my mother was a World War II Marine [in the <orgName>U.S. Marine Corps</orgName>]. She was a woman <orgName>Marine</orgName> in <name type="event">World War II</name>. And so was my father.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Oh, wow. Oh, okay. That’s interesting.</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">And that’s [cross-talk; unintelligible]. And, as you know, my husband was a <orgName>Marine</orgName>, too, so—</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Mm-hm.</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">And that plays—</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">And so what—</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">Go ahead.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">I was just going to ask: What kind of mental illness did your mother have?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">She was diagnosed with schizophrenic [sic].</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">You know. And she had auditory and visual hallucinations when I was growing up. I mean, you know, she—she really had a—you know, left untreated, it’s a pretty wicked thing to go through. And so it was a very confusing childhood. [Chuckles.]
    
    She said she saw something, and we didn’t, but if we didn’t agree with her, she would get very angry and just you know, nobody—none of us know.  She didn’t know, you know, what was wrong with her. To her, it was all real.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Right. And did you have any brothers or sisters growing up?</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">I did. I was the youngest, and I had two twin sisters and an older brother. And he just missed going to <name type = "event">Vietnam</name>.</u>


<u who="#CUMMINGS">Oh okay.</u>


<u who="#RAMSEY-JEVNE">He went into the <orgName>[U.S.] Air Force</orgName>, but the war ended before he ever served overseas.</u>

