<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="BLAYDON"/>
        <person xml:id="COLLINS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="COLLINS">This is <persName>Riley Collins</persName> at the Rauner Special Collections Library in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>. I am currently speaking with Professor <persName>Colin</persName> [C.] <placeName>Blaydon</placeName>. We are conducting an interview with <orgName>the Dartmouth Vietnam Projects</orgName> [sic] to learn a little bit more about the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> era and as it relates to the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> community. And it <date>August 19th, 2016</date>.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I am currently in <placeName>California</placeName>. We’re doing this by telephone, and I am in <placeName>Grass Valley</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Great. So, Professor <persName>Blaydon</persName>, where—where were you born?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I was born in <orgName>Newport News</orgName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, in <date>1940</date>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">All right. And—and what was it like growing up in—in <placeName>Virginia</placeName>? What was your family like?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It was in an interesting part of <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, on what’s called the <placeName>Peninsula</placeName>, sort of between <placeName>Williamsburg</placeName> and <orgName>Newport News</orgName>, along <placeName>the James River</placeName>. It was rural country, mainly farms, and my father was a naval architect and marine engineer who had come there, who was originally from <placeName>England</placeName>. Went to university in this country and then was hired by <orgName>Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Company</orgName> [now <orgName>Newport News Shipbuilding</orgName>], which builds a lot of [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Navy</orgName> ships, so it was both a rural, Southern community surrounding what was a large industrial operation, working with the military and with a number of military bases around there. So it was an interesting—interesting place to grow up. It was both part of the great modern military-industrial complex and also the rural <placeName>South</placeName> at the same time.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Did you notice any—any tension that might have been caused by that between, you know, people maybe from, you know, where their parents were sort of more agricultural versus people whose parents were, you know, involved with the military base or the ship works?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No, we were all kids. There wasn’t any particular tension. But for what—the families had varied experiences, but it was a relatively small community, so that we all pretty much knew each other well. And I went from kindergarten through high school basically with the same group of kids, and with whom I’m still in touch <date>today</date>, so, no, it was a remarkably harmonious community, with some of the challenges, of course, that—around issues of racial disparities that came from the fact that this was still a very segregated Southern community.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. That—that’s interesting. How—how aware of you—or how aware were you of sort of segregation at this time, or how did you really notice it, growing up?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It was impossible not to know it and not to feel—have a sense, a feeling that there was something strange about the relationship between the whites and the blacks, because it was defined by the institutions of segregation and the presence of—of just pervasive racism. Middle-class families, which mine was, typically had black servants, even though we were not well-to-do. We were solidly middle class, and I was born right at the end of the [Great] Depression and the beginning of <name type="event">World War II</name>. And so we had “help,” as it used to be called, for black maids and black men who worked on the grounds of our home, and that was actually fairly common.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Did your—did your father ever think it was strange, coming from <placeName>England</placeName> and then—then be plopped sort of in <placeName>the American South</placeName>? Did he ever comment on anything regarding segregation?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, my father was a—was a very disciplined man. I think I have a sense of his values, and as a boy growing up, I would try and provoke him into answering the question you’ve just asked, <persName>Riley</persName>. And one other thing that you noted about that place is that these were topics that were highly charged, and people were very careful in speaking about them. And my father, not having been reared in the <placeName>South</placeName>, having come there from <orgName>the University of Michigan</orgName>, where he went to school, and having as a boy been raised in <placeName>England</placeName>, I think he was particularly careful about language that he used. So when his son, myself, would try to goad him into really telling me what he thought, he always managed to deflect the questions. But I know from his life, from things that he did, actions he took—I’m quite sure I knew what he thought, but I never heard him say it.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and would you be comfortable sharing that here, or—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes, I think my—my father was a dyed-in-the-wool liberal Democrat, which was different—<placeName>Virginia</placeName> was heavily Democratic politically, as was the entire <placeName>South</placeName>, as a legacy of the [American] Civil War. But the Southern Democrats were not what you would characterize as liberal, so my father, for example, was very active in <orgName>the Democratic Party</orgName> locally. I remember our—we—our family in [unintelligible] were enthusiastic supporters of <persName>Adlai</persName> [<persName>E.] Stevenson [II</persName>] in the election of <date>1952</date>, when he ran against General [<persName>Dwight D.] Eisenhower</persName> for the presidency. And that was a controversial position because <persName>Stevenson</persName> was not a popular figure in that conservative <placeName>South</placeName>, and my father, on that subject, was quite open about his support for <persName>Stevenson</persName>. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right. </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Very traditional. We had—it began in kindergarten, and we would go right through and graduate from high school. There were no middle schools in <date>those days</date>, so you went to—you went from kindergarten through elementary school, through seventh grade in one of several very small elementary schools. The one I went to was called <placeName>Hilton</placeName>, <placeName>Hilton Village</placeName> [Elementary School]. It was a small, actually planned community that was built in <name type="event">World War I for</name> the professional staff who worked at the shipbuilding company that built a lot of the <orgName>Navy</orgName> ships. So it was an unusual little community that looked a bit like an English village plopped down in the rural <placeName>South</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Interesting, yeah. And if you don’t mind me circling back sort of towards the origins of your—your town and your father coming over to <placeName>Virginia</placeName>—so you said he was involved in sort of building ships. When—when did he come to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>? Was that before <name type="event">World War II</name> or after <name type="event">World War</name> I or—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah, it was—actually, it was—he came as a boy. His father, my grandfather brought the family over in—in <date>1910</date>, just before <name type="event">the First World War</name> broke out, and they first came to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. So his older brother was <date>seven years older</date>, and he was old enough to actually have served in <name type="event">the First World War</name>, and he and his older brother were very close, but—so his major childhood impressions were—came after he came to <placeName>Canada</placeName> at <date>seven or eight years old</date>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. And during <name type="event">World War II</name>, then, was your father still employed at the ship factory, or was he—did he get deployed overseas at all, or—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No, he was—he was a [<orgName>U.S. Army] Reserve</orgName> officer. He had taken <orgName>ROTC [Reserve Officers’</orgName> <orgName>Training Corps</orgName>] when he was at <placeName>Michigan</placeName>, so he was a captain in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Army Reserves [sic; Reserve] and was called up at the beginning of the war. But it was discovered then that he had very high blood pressure, and that, coupled with the fact that he was building aircraft carriers and troop transports involved in doing that, he ended up being discharged from the <orgName>Army</orgName> because of his high blood pressure and was given, I believe, some sort of, you know, special category about critical occupation because of his role in the shipbuilding industry. So he never—he never went on active duty during the war.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">All right.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, I made a—a choice that later actually determined how I came to be involved in the military during the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> era. I decided that I wanted to go to [<orgName>the U.S. Military Academy</orgName> at] West Point, and our local congressman knew my father. My father got me an interview with him. He nominated me to <placeName>West Point</placeName>, and I went to <placeName>West Point</placeName> when I graduated from high school.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And what—what motivated you to—to do that? Why—why <orgName>West Point</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I don’t know. The world you grew up in that <placeName>South</placeName> had a lot of sense of history and a lot of military history. I still to <date>this day</date> will describe it—you know, it felt like the war had ended <date>the weekend before</date>, and the war I was referring to was <name type="event">the Civil War</name>. So you grew up sort of immersed in that history, which still felt very present. Many of my childhood friends—you’d go into their homes, and there’d be portraits hanging on the walls of their grandparents, great-uncles in their Confederate uniforms. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">So a couple of questions: First, were a lot of your friends also considering careers in the military? Like, do you feel like this was common for people growing up in your community?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">A number of them did. Most of them went through <placeName>ROTC</placeName> if they went to college. Not a lot of my classmates went to college. I’d say a fairly small minority did. A number of them did get commissions and went on active duty. A number did enlist and served as enlisted men. But we were of an age—I graduated from high school in <date>1958</date>, so we were of age to have been in the <orgName>Army</orgName> in our late teens to <date>early twenties</date>, in the era of—after <placeName>Korea</placeName> [<name type="event">the Korean War</name>] and the major buildup for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So those who served basically went in, served a period of time, and then—then left.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did—I guess sort of <placeName>America</placeName>’s experience in <name type="event">the Korean War</name> would have been while you were still in—still growing up. That would have put you at, what, thirteen to fifteen while that war was going on., something like that?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes. Yes, it was.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Did—did news of that shape your view of the <orgName>Army</orgName> at all? Or were you aware of what was going on?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It did. <name type="event">The Korean War</name> was very present. I was a teenager who read a lot of military history, and some of the writing about <placeName>Korea</placeName> was being done at that time, and I read sort of basically all the major books and was very aware of it. I was very interested in topics of military strategy and things like that.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. Interesting. It sounds like it was a very military-oriented community.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I never thought I would do anything else. I think my father had very much enjoyed his university experience. I think in part he enjoyed it so much because, given his family circumstances and the way he came over, it was unlikely that he would have gone to a major university or any university. But when he won a scholarship from when he was a student at <orgName>Cass Technical High School</orgName> in <placeName>Detroit</placeName>, he won the scholarship and was able to go to the university if he studied marine engineering and naval architecture, because that’s what this specialized scholarship was all about.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">—and so it was, in a sense, an odd choice of career, and I think it was the opportunity to go to a good university and have it paid for that led him into that particular line of work and that career that he spent his entire working life at.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Interesting, yeah.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">And as a result, he was a rabid <orgName>University of Michigan</orgName> alumnus. He listened to all of the football games, and once a year we would travel to <placeName>Ann Arbor</placeName> for the last big game of the season. So I always knew I was going to go to a university, and my father did his best to make sure that that was going to be <orgName>the University of Michigan</orgName>. But that was not to be.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Wow, yeah. It sounds like quite a trip, going all the way from <placeName>Virginia</placeName> to—to <placeName>Ann Arbor</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It was.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and yeah, so—so you ended up going to <placeName>West Point</placeName>, interviewing with your congressman, getting the nomination. But you mentioned you—you didn’t love it there. What were—what were sort of your first impressions of <placeName>West Point</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, the way <orgName>West Point</orgName> works is you go there <date>the beginning of the summer</date>, and you go through what effectively is pretty intense basic training that you would if you were going into the <orgName>Army</orgName>. But if anything, it was even more intense because of where it was and, you know, who made it up. And so the summer was fully military training, and the academics would begin at the fall.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah, it sounds like a pretty good deal for someone who didn’t really want to be in the <orgName>Army</orgName> but still sort of had that binding commitment.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Exactly. And it was more, I think, that I didn’t particularly want to spend <date>the next four years</date> at <placeName>West Point</placeName> because I ended up going into the <orgName>Army</orgName>. I stayed in the Army Reserves and didn’t—afterwards, and didn’t actually resign from the <orgName>Army</orgName> until, oh, <date>the early 1970s</date>. And I—I was very involved in all of that, with the military during <date>those years</date>. I am—I mean, “enjoyed” is sort of —given what was going on at the time is sort of an odd thing to say, but I very much appreciated my <orgName>Army</orgName> service. I was very involved in it, and I was in effect in the <orgName>Army</orgName> from <date>1958</date> until <date>the 1970s</date>, even though I had decided not to complete my education at <orgName>West Point</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">But it—it was sort of a little ironic.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah, that’s—that’s really funny. So you transferred to—to <orgName>UVA</orgName>, then, in <date>1958</date>? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">That’s correct.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and what was it like sort of making that transfer? Did you find that you enjoyed UVA a lot more?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I—I did. I definitely had a sense that I had—that to make a choice like getting into <placeName>West Point</placeName> was hard to do, and then changing my mind in a very short period of time and getting out was something I was sensitive to, and embarrassed by—you know, that I had done this, charged off to do this and then changed my mind. I didn’t think it reflected particularly well on me.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">So you—you did have sort of an active campus social life in addition to your studies, then.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I did. In <date>those days</date>, what you did is your social life was imported from the women’s college that were within a bus—a <date>half-day</date> bus trip from <placeName>Charlottesville</placeName>, so similar to <orgName>Smith [College</orgName>] and <orgName>Radcliffe [College</orgName>, now <orgName>Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study</orgName> at <orgName>Harvard University</orgName>] girls coming to <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah, it does sound like there’s a lot of parallels there.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">There were. And there were units both for <placeName>Naval ROTC</placeName> and <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC, and Air Force ROTC. So there were a lot of people who—who did that. But most of us came out—we graduated in <date>1962</date>, and in <date>1962</date> there was not a big demand for junior officers in any of the branches of service. And I can only speak for sure about the <orgName>Army</orgName>, but when you got commissioned as an <orgName>ROTC</orgName> officer in <date>1962</date>, your service commitment was to spend <date>six months</date> on active duty and then <date>seven and a half years</date>—or maybe it was <date>six and a half</date>, for a total of seven; I don’t remember—in the <orgName>Reserves</orgName>, because there were not sufficient demand for junior officers on active duty in <date>1962</date>. <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> had not fully erupted. That buildup really didn’t seriously begin until <date>1965</date>, so most of us who went into <orgName>ROTC</orgName> served for <date>six months</date> and then served the rest of the time in the Reserves.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and so when—when you graduated—and you had studied engineering, you mentioned—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—what did—what did that <orgName>Army</orgName> sort of do with you? Where did you go after graduating?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Okay. I was commissioned in the—in the [<orgName>U.S.] Army Corps of Engineers</orgName> as a—as a cadet. I was a cadet officer in the <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. I commanded the ceremonial drill team and all, because one thing I had learned at <placeName>West Point</placeName> was sort of all of the—the basic military skills and stuff like that, so I knew a lot of that before I ever got into <placeName>ROTC</placeName>, and most of the other—and the other people did not, so I enjoyed <orgName>ROTC</orgName> and was very active in it.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah, it sounds like in some ways good timing, depending on how you look at it.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes, exactly.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">So—so you—you won this national scholarship, and the fellowship—was it specifically for studying a certain branch within STEM [science, technology, engineering and mathematics], or was it just for anyone with science and mathematical background more generally?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No, it was a special—a special branch. It was sponsored—it was sponsored by different science and technology entities in the federal government. A big bunch of them were sponsored by <orgName>the National Science Foundation</orgName>, and the form of those fellowships is what the other agencies follow. The one I was awarded was what was then the [ <orgName>U.S.] Atomic Energy Commission</orgName>, so it was the nuclear technology, both weapons and—and nuclear power stuff. I’d been an engineering student. I had an engineering degree, and I’d taken a bunch of courses in nuclear engineering, and so the fellowship that I won was given by <orgName>the Atomic Energy Commission</orgName> to not specially say I should study nuclear engineering, but it turned out that that turned on my choice of graduate school.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and so which university did you end up wanting to go to?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, I applied to three, and I got in all three. I applied to <orgName>the University of Michigan</orgName>, to <orgName>MIT [Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>] and to <orgName>Harvard</orgName> [University]. And I ended up—I got into all three. <placeName>Michigan</placeName> and <orgName>MIT</orgName> both had big engineering programs, and they—as soon as they saw my fellowship, slotted me into a nuclear engineering graduate program. And I remember going to <orgName>Harvard</orgName>. After I’d been down interviewing at <orgName>MIT</orgName> about what it would be like to go there and they explained to me the program, I went up to <orgName>Harvard</orgName> and met with them, and the people in what was then called <orgName>the Division of Engineering and Applied Physics</orgName> at <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, and asked them what would my course of study be at <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, and the response was, “What would you like it to be?” And I decided this was my kind of place.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Would you mind giving, like, a brief synopsis of what modern control theory is, for maybe people who aren’t quite as specialized in math as yourself?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Right. It was—it came out of actually—it was a traditional—a mathematical tradition, if you will, that came out of <name type="event">World War II</name> and the field that became known as operations research, which was apply basically mathematical quantitative analysis to solve particular problems. So they were the ones who were famous for developing the patterns for the bombing raids, for the submarine warfare programs, for planning the logistics to the military operations. So it became a sort of an applied mathematics specialty, trying to look at complex systems and looking at how to optimize certain criteria in the way that you organized activities within those systems. And it’s what then led me later to what I ended up doing during <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, when I did go on active duty.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and what was it about modern control theory that—that really grabbed your attention? What—what did you really enjoy about it?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, basically it was solving interesting and complex problems in a rigorous manner. And so it was both mathematics, but in some ways it was also always impinging on larger issues of public policy. Initially, it was all about the military, but it ended up being a tradition that was applied to problems in the social, you know, sector of how to deliver services and—because basically it was saying, “Here’s a set of circumstances, here’s something that’s operating within that system, and here’s a criterion for evaluating how well it does. How do you optimize, to maximize that criterion? How do you optimize the activities that you are trying to organize within that system?</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And, yes, so how did <orgName>Harvard</orgName>’s modern control theory program sort of relate to—to the developments in the rest of the country? Was <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, like, particularly cutting edge, or was there a professor there that—that you worked with particularly closely, anything like that?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">There were. <orgName>Harvard</orgName> and its—what they called their applied physics groups and their applied mathematics group—that played a major role during <name type="event">World War II</name> and the aftermath, with close ties to <placeName>Los Alamos</placeName> and the development of the [atomic] bomb and the development of tactics used during the war. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Interesting, yeah. It sounds like, you know, there’s a strong <orgName>Harvard</orgName> connection to the [President <persName>John F.]</persName> <persName>Kennedy</persName> administration, where—I mean, obviously, President <persName>Kennedy</persName> went to <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, I believe.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And a lot of his advisers also had—either went to <orgName>Harvard</orgName> or <orgName>MIT</orgName> and sort of had this strong connection, so it was interesting to hear how that played out.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">And I—I took a bunch of seminars from a bunch of those people when I was a graduate student that were far—well away from my hard-core mathematics and physics courses that were the bulk of what I was studying, but I was fascinated, and so I took part in a number of graduate public policy seminars dealing with issues, primarily of science policy, that were people who were very active—faculty who were very active as advisers in—you know, of course by this time it was the [President <persName>Lyndon B.]</persName> <persName>Johnson</persName> administration.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and were a lot of your classmates sort of on that—that similar—similar track? You know, like, STEM majors who—who also took public policy classes on the side? Was that common?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No. They were STEM majors. They were hard core. And very good. No, you realize that if you had done well in—in college and thought you were maybe pretty good at that stuff, you suddenly found yourself in a cohort where you realized what it meant to be really, really smart. And so my—my classmates in the classes I was taking were very focused on their—their STEM interests and careers, and relatively few with sort of a fascination with the public policy issues. I think I was interested—I don’t know, just—I was naturally interested in all of that stuff, and I think <persName>Harvey Brooks</persName>, who was my adviser, liked having a student who was interested in his other, larger life, not just in his role as a physics researcher and teacher but as a shaper of public policy dealing with scientific policy issues. So he encouraged me, and I—and I—I took a bunch of those seminars. And one of them was one that led to what I did during <date>the Vietnam years</date>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And so in terms of the actual progression of your studies, you—you went to <orgName>Harvard</orgName> and became interested in modern control theory, and you first just pursued a master’s degree, correct?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">That is correct. And <orgName>Harvard</orgName>—different universities did it different ways. In some cases, they had a very formal progression: master’s degree followed by a <persName>Ph.D.</persName> And—and <orgName>MIT</orgName>, for example, and <placeName>Michigan</placeName> both had a very formal master’s degree, and it was also a terminal degree. So you were pretty well qualified to go out and—and do what you had been studying, with a master’s degree. A number of people would go to those places with the intent of getting a master’s degree and then getting on with their careers, not then going on and taking—finishing the <persName>Ph.D.</persName> and going to a research and teaching career.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">So I did that and got my master’s degree in <date>1966</date>, in <date>June</date>, and then stayed through <date>the summer</date>, finishing my—my dissertation and went on active duty in <date>the fall</date>, after I had gotten my dissertation pretty much wrapped up. And then came back for graduation to receive my degree in <date>June of 1967</date>. So my master’s is in <date>’66</date>, and my <persName>Ph.D.</persName> is in <date>’67</date>, but that doesn’t at all reflect sort of the pattern of <date>the years</date> that I spent working on one and then completing the other.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right. And, yeah, so when you did sort of finish your degree work in—in <date>’66</date>, you then had to go to your military service—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I did.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—because of the deal you’d made with the—the military before. And so how did they decide what to do with you at this point, or where to put you? And— did you have any—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It is all a little bit mysterious to me, to tell you the truth. Initially, I was going on in a traditional capacity of someone who had taken <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, had been a second lieutenant. While I was in school, I was still—I was in the Reserves, but my assignment was to go to graduate school. But I was accruing service credits, so along the way, I got promoted to first lieutenant. So when I was graduating, I was a first lieutenant. Still mostly likely a standard assignment would have been a platoon leader or a—a company staff officer. And, of course, in ’66 the buildup was roaring along. It really began in <date>’65</date>. I think by <date>the end of ’66</date>, the early part of <date>’67</date>, there were 50,000 troops in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And that had really begun in <date>’65</date>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">And so along the way, my—the initial indications of what I was going to do was that I was going to go to one of the big basic training bases and joined either a combat engineer or infantry platoon as a junior officer. And the—but my orders got changed along the way.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And do you have any idea how that happened or—or is just sort of the military works in mysterious ways?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No, I—I did. I played a somewhat proactive role in that. I wanted to use what I had been studying, and in my last semester in residence, in <date>the spring of 1966</date>, there was a seminar being taught on national security policy, and I was interested in it. I knew I was going on active duty. It was being taught by actually a fairly newly famous professor, who had just written a book called Nuclear Weapons and Foreign Policy, and his name was <persName>Henry [A.] Kissinger</persName>. And I—I asked to audit—because I didn’t need any more course credits—the seminar, and he allowed me to do that. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Wow! That’s incredible. And—and so how do you think Secretary <persName>McNamara</persName> [which he mispronounces as <orgName>mac-nuh-MAH</orgName>-ruh instead of <orgName>mac-nuh-MARE-uh</orgName>] or at least his staff became aware? Do you think it was <persName>Alain Enthoven</persName> who—who really pushed for you—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—to be on that staff?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah, it was <persName>Alain</persName>—basically, it was—the request was signed by Secretary <persName>McNamara</persName>, but the request was actually from <persName>Alain Enthoven</persName>, who was by this time now officially the assistant secretary of defense, systems analysis. And he was staffing up the systems analysis group in the office of the secretary of defense. So when I say I was a staff aide to Secretary <persName>McNamara</persName>, I was part of a group of about—eventually it ended up being around a hundred people, who really worked for <persName>Alain Enthoven</persName> on this systems analysis staff. But we were all staff officers in the office of the secretary of defense.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And what was your work like when—when you were involved in this—this office? Or I guess, did they—they hired you right in <date>’66</date>, sort of after you finished your degree work but before you were actually awarded your degree.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">That is correct.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And they were able to—to sort of get your military service to be transferred to <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName> rather than putting you on active duty sort of as an officer leading troops. And so, like, what was your—your work like initially? What was it like being a part of this office as they were assembling it?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I—I was an officer. I would say of this group that formed the systems analysis staff, about half of us were active duty officers. A number of them were career officers. A number of them had seen combat service already. And then the other half were civilians, some, like myself, coming out of Ph.D. programs. A handful had been <orgName>Rhodes Scholars</orgName> but were civilian. Some of them were <orgName>Rhodes Scholars</orgName> who were military officers. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and so what exactly is meant by “intelligence matters”?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Okay. What it was really—it was systems analysis,—</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">—so what we were—what we were doing, we were looking at the systems. Probably the best known thing that that group had done—and this had been done before I got there—was not looking at <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> but looking at <name type="event">the Cold War</name> and <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> and working at what would be a nuclear confrontation between these two superpowers and how would it play out, what should be our strategy. And what the <persName>McNamara</persName> administration had discovered was that each branch of service was sort of a world unto itself, so the <orgName>Army</orgName>, the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Navy</orgName>, the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Air Force</orgName>, the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> were all separate and distinct. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Wow, that’s incredibly interesting. I’ve got plenty of questions to go off of there, but one that strikes me right away, sort of as you were talking about systems analysis—is there any, like, example of, like, a specific problem that you were able to optimize that—that you remember, that you could maybe talk about to just give, like, a concrete sample of how this kind of thinking plays out?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes. Probably the most—the best example was one that—that directly involved the war—was that—of course, a big part of the—of the force that was being brought to bear by the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> was, you know, that we had command of—of the air. We had war planes that were attacking, you know, infantry units of the—of the Viet Cong and <orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName> in the <placeName>South</placeName> and strategic targets in the <placeName>North</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah, that’s—that’s incredibly interesting. I—I have lots of questions, but the next one I’ll ask you is—and you might not be able to speak to it, speak to this, but—so you were working on this model of sort of how do we figure out how many drones we need to send out in order to be able to evaluate effectively whether or not our bombing campaigns are working in <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>. What—what is the ultimate metric that—that would have been used, though, to determine whether or not these bombing campaigns were successful? That might have been outside the scope of—of what you specifically were working on, but—but I guess I’m just curious.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No, it was crucial to it. It’s a very good question, <persName>Riley</persName>, because basically what we were building was a mathematical optimization model, so we built a model of how the reconnaissance worked: how the flights were, and if you sent a drone off on a particular path, how successful were they going to be? And it was a probabilistic model. Okay, what was the probability of cloud cover along that route, or getting a <persName>SAM</persName> missile shooting down one of these aircraft so that it didn’t succeed?</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. So—so what—what was he sort of accusing you of being involved in, or what was his—his theory, if you don’t mind talking about that quickly.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Say the question again, <persName>Riley</persName>. I’m not sure I understand.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. Yeah, so you—you just mentioned that I believe his name was <persName>Steven Hersh</persName>. Was that correct?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON"><persName>Seymour Hersh</persName>, “<persName>Sy” Hersh</persName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS"><persName>Seymour Hersh</persName>. Right.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah. H-e-r-s-h.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">He—he came to your office and asked to talk to you about your work on the bombing campaigns in <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>, and he sort of had—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—sort of a conspiracy theory. Did—did you ever talk to him about that or—or remember sort of what—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, I listened to him. I listened to him, and I wasn’t sure what I could or could not say. It turns out that what he was thinking of I actually had no knowledge of, and I had to tell him that. And the story he was telling me that he said was about to come out in <orgName>The New York Times</orgName> <date>Sunday</date> Magazine [sic; <orgName>The New York Times Magazine</orgName>] just needed somebody else who had been there and saw this going on. He just wanted me to confirm that his story was correct.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. That’s—that’s extremely interesting to me because it sort of touches on this—this popular fear that I think started to emerge during <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> that sort of dealt with mission creep, this idea that, you know, as we got further and further involved in <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, the military’s priorities sort of strayed a little bit away from—from national defense or public interest priorities. And there is this sort of collective fear that, you know, the military was getting out of hand, and some of <persName>McNamara</persName>’s sort of, you know, turning to systems analysis, turning to a more number-driven approach sort of obscured I guess the national interest in the war and led to this sort of over-involvement in the war, beyond what was actually necessary for national security, and therefore the sort of unnecessary loss in life of American soldiers in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">The—the answer is that we were all very aware of the national debates and concerns that were going on. I mean, all of us came from campuses. Many of us later were in academic careers back on those campuses, where many of these concerns were being voiced, and so we were very aware of the environment we were operating in. And, you know, it—the—you know, the protests, <orgName>the National Guard</orgName> [of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>] ending up ringing the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> when there were protesters out front. You know, those of us who were on the staff and sitting inside the building knew a bunch of the people who were outside, protesting the war. And we understood where they were coming from.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah, that’s—that’s a very interesting perspective. I think you—you were coming from a very unique position to be able to—to speak on sort of—sort of this sort of contested legacy of <persName>McNamara</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">By the time I got there, those tensions were largely resolved. From what I heard in <date>the early days</date>, they were certainly there. “Now, who are these pointy-headed, you know, academics who are coming in?” And, you know, what on earth did they know? But what had happened by the time I got there is that many of the officer corps were themselves—you know, there was a big tradition of sending sort of the best and the brightest, if you will, of the officer corps to graduate school programs, to those military colleges, but—you know, to <orgName>MIT</orgName>, to <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, to <orgName>Berkeley</orgName>, to <orgName>Stanford</orgName> [University] and then, you know, to continue on with their careers in the military.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">And, you know—and the other one was at one point I stayed in the job but stayed for <date>another year</date> as a civilian. I was a <orgName>Reserve</orgName> officer. By this time, I was a captain. And I was going to a meeting with a group from the <orgName>Joint</orgName> staff, so all military, and me representing <orgName>the Office of [the</orgName>] Secretary of <orgName>Defense</orgName>. And this group had been meeting—it was a series of meetings, and this was maybe the fifth or sixth in a series that was going to continue for a while. I’m not even remembering exactly what study it was.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">—the tensions—</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">—the tensions and the recognition of it were there, but it sort of—you know, in a sense, they were s because there were as many senior officers sitting around that table—you know, there were at least a half dozen of them that also had Ph.D.s from the same universities, and they were career military officers, so, you know, they were us, and we were they. But the tensions were still there.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right. Yeah, that’s incredibly interesting.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Okay. If you want to do a follow-up, I do have some things, <persName>Riley</persName>, that I’ve got to do. I would say there are things we have not touched on that ought to be of some interest. Have to do with—more directly with <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. We’ve talked about my experience in the war, in the job that I was in. I could give you a quick summary, if you want to do it right now, or if you have to get to class or an exam, just say so and we can pick up later.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Right.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">But the topic I would talk about would be basically—I think I mentioned have some acquaintance with what happened at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> with the eruption of the campus unrest in <date>the spring of 1970</date> around [<orgName>the] Kent State [</orgName>University shootings] and what happened to <orgName>ROTC</orgName> on the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> campus and what I knew about that, because I knew about it later because I knew the people involved. That. And then some involvement of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> faculty in <placeName>Hanoi</placeName>, with the [<placeName>Vietnam</placeName>] <orgName>National University</orgName> in many—<date>later years</date> about collaborating with them to open a business school that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> faculty helped with. Those would be the two main things that—that I would think might be useful in this record.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. And—and one more thing that comes to mind is you were a professor at <orgName>Harvard</orgName> for a little while, after your time at <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName>, correct?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I was, yes.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">I’m sure there were—there was campus unrest on <orgName>Harvard</orgName>’s campus as well, which—which could be of interest to us, just sort of to see how—how <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>’s campus protests sort of fit into the broader framework of college campus protests in general. </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And so I think that can also be—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">And I—I arrived at <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, at <orgName>the Business School</orgName>. I’d been on the other side of the river as a graduate student, so my <persName>Ph.D.</persName> was in sort of <orgName>the arts and sciences</orgName> side of the university, on the other side of the river from <orgName>the Business School</orgName>. And I came back to teach at <orgName>the Business School</orgName>. And I came back in <date>the fall of 1969</date>. <placeName>The Kent State</placeName> eruptions were <date>the spring of 1970</date>, and so it was in <date>the spring of my first year</date> teaching at <orgName>Harvard</orgName>. And the campus <date>that spring</date> shut down its courses, suspended its courses and abolished <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. And so I was there, having just come back from my participation in these activities involving the war, and as—as an officer to find myself as a faculty member on that campus when that was going on.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. All that sounds intensely interesting, but unfortunately you—you were—hit the nail on the head, and I do have to get to class soon to take an exam.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Okay. Send me a message and tell me when would work, and I’ll promise to keep it within an hour. I thought  would keep this short, but you touch an important part of my life, and I can’t resist talking about it, so I’m happy to do it if it’s useful for you.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Send me a message, and tell me when, and we could even do it over <date>the weekend</date> if you wanted to do it.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Here, let me end the recording of our interview, to be continued later.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">This is <persName>Riley Collins</persName> at <orgName>Rauner</orgName> [Special Collections] Library at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>. The date is <date>August 22nd, 2016</date>. I am here with Professor <persName>Colin Blaydon</persName>, conducting an interview for the Dartmouth <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> Project. </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I am in—in <placeName>California</placeName>, in a little town called <placeName>Chicago Park</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Awesome. </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, I had been on active duty for <date>two years</date>. I went off active duty <date>the end of 1968</date>, but stayed in the same position on the systems analysis staff, as a civilian through—to finish up some things I was working on—through <date>the following summer</date>. And at the—at the end of that, I went to <orgName>the Harvard Business School</orgName> as an assistant professor, teaching first quantitative analysis and then finance and—and started doing that in <date>September of 1969</date>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did you sort of always know that you would want to transition to academia while you were at <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName>, or did this just sort of—you just sort of— </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—stumbled into it?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah. No, pretty much I did. I’d gotten my <persName>Ph.D.</persName> at <orgName>Harvard</orgName> in applied mathematics before I went on active duty, and my intent always was to return to a career in academics.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Okay. And—and so your—your active duty military service ended in <date>1968</date>, which sort of—you had negotiated that beforehand with <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName>, correct?—sort of how long you would be serving on active duty before they let you go back to Reserves, or sort of—or did they put you in the Reserves after that or sort of end your military career ?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">They did.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—altogether?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">My active duty ended in <date>November of 1968</date>, and the agreement had been—or my—my commitment was for <date>two years</date> of active duty and then moving to the Reserves, so I was a captain on active duty until <date>November</date> of ’68 and then became a <orgName>Reserve</orgName> officer not on active duty at that point but stayed in the same job until—until <date>September of 1969</date>, when I started teaching at <orgName>Harvard</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Okay. Cool. And when—when you switched to <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, what was the—the campus climate like there at the time in terms of student attitudes toward <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, at this point, you know, the—it was nearing the height of the—of the campus disaffection with regard to the—to the war and student protests, and, you know, the—the draft around that time was pretty much at its peak, and so a lot of—of- strong feeling about the war.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Okay. Did you ever have students sort of question you about your time at <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName>, or people who were particularly curious about what—your role in <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes. When I began teaching, I was teaching in the <orgName>MBA</orgName> program at <orgName>the Business School</orgName>. A large number of the entering students were in fact people who were returning from active duty. Many of them, combat veterans from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, were coming back, and these were people generally who had been junior officers, had gone through <placeName>ROTC</placeName> as undergraduates, had gone to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and were coming off active duty and applied to <orgName>the Business School</orgName> to come back and get their MBA.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did the students at the undergraduate college treat you a little bit differently than the graduate students, or—or were there discussions with you regarding the war a little bit more—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">No, not—not really. Because I was over there, I was closer to it and to what was going on and some of the student protests that were being held, but I think it was largely by the nature of what I was—was teaching. And, again, most of my—the students taking my course there, because it was an advanced statistical decision theory course—they were largely graduate students in statistics, mathematics or economics, but there were a number of juniors and seniors who also took the course, but by nature, sort of of the course and that—that it was in—being a highly technical course, there was not much interaction or discussion about what was going on on campus or about attitudes towards the war.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Did your, like, coworkers, the other faculty at Dart- —or at <orgName>Harvard</orgName> ever talk about the student protests with you?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Not until <date>the spring of 1970</date>, and that is when the campuses really erupted about the war. It was when the shootings at <placeName>Kent State</placeName> occurred, and in <date>that spring</date>, basically all of the campuses erupted in opposition to what had happened and to the war, and that was true across the campus. At that point, there were no real difference in sort of what was going on in the graduate school, in the undergraduate school, in <orgName>the Business School</orgName> or the undergraduate college. It was all very similar.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And so—so you mentioned that there was a faculty debate going on within <orgName>the Business School</orgName> as to how to respond to the student unrest. What were sort of the two sides of that debate, and where did you fall on it?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">The two sides were basically were we really going to shut down classes or not? And by the time the discussion got very far along, it was pretty clear that there was a broad consensus that we were going to shut it down, and the question began to be more: How were we going to handle it, and sort of what our goals were going to be. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Did you feel like sometimes the students were targeting not just sort of the top level policy makers who were making the decisions on <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> but also soldiers, officers and more mid-level policy makers, like yourself, who were participating in the war?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I think they did, but it was expressed—the students, particularly undergraduate students—their views were not that nuanced about the different roles people were playing. It was much more a strong gut reaction against the war, about, you know, all of the horrible things and damage, you know, and—and death that was being caused by this war. And so there was a lot of just lashing out, probably. Particularly the strongest sort of expressions of it were, you know, the—the student demonstrations where the troops were vilified as “baby killers,” you know, and—and so it was—there was a lot of strong feeling, and it—and it came out in that way. So it was not a very differentiated view of who you were if you’d been a veteran. The undergraduates sort of lumped everybody all in the same pot, as best I could tell.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did you feel like the graduate students then had more nuanced positions on it, maybe because a lot of them were formerly soldiers themselves?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes. There is no doubt about that. The discussion on the—at <orgName>the Business School</orgName> student body was much more sort of a reaction to the horrors of <placeName>Kent State</placeName>, definitely an abhorrence of the war and wanting to see it ended, but it was not the same feeling about the role of the—the troops in the war that was present in the undergraduate student body because they were—the undergraduates were, in many ways, reacting to the pictures that were coming out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, the stories that were coming out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and a lot of blaming of—it seemed in our minds, anyway—the combat—the American combat troops who were there and what some of them were doing. <orgName>The Business School</orgName> wasn’t that reaction. Their reaction was more about the horror of the war, ending the war, and the reaction to what had happened at <placeName>Kent State</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did you ever feel sort of personally vilified from—from what some of the undergrads were saying about soldiers or—or military personnel throughout the war?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Not really. You didn’t see any people, including people who were still on active duty and being sent to school as graduate students, and there were those on campus. I mean, nobody was going to wear their uniform or anything that indicated their—their identification with the military and walking around the campus. That was for sure.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And how long were you a professor at <orgName>Harvard</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">I was there for <date>four years</date>, and I left to go back into the government. I actually took a <date>two-year</date> leave to go back in <date>the summer of 1973</date>. There was a new group being established at <orgName>the Office of Management and Budget</orgName> that was trying to establish more disciplined management practices at the—at the cabinet level in the government. And there was a new division, actually a group of four different divisions, each called <orgName>a Presidential Management Division</orgName>, that was established in <orgName>OMB</orgName>, reporting to <persName>Roy [L.] Ash</persName>, who was the president’s chief economic adviser and had headed something called <orgName>the Ash Commission</orgName> about management in the federal government. So <persName>Roy</persName> was in the-in the West Wing. He was the president’s chief economic adviser and also the director of <orgName>OMB</orgName>. And he and his team put together these divisions. They were brand new. They were supposed to help instill some more disciplined management oversight of the cabinet departments. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and so the task force that was responsible for coordinating our policy towards the evacuation efforts—was that just run by <orgName>the Office of the Management and Budget</orgName>, or is that sort of like an inter-agency working group?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It was definitely an inter-agency working group. In fact, it operated out of the operations center in <orgName>the State Department</orgName> [sic; <orgName>U.S. Department of State</orgName>]. It was not even operated out of the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> or any of the other military- or <orgName>White House</orgName>-related command centers. It was operated actually out of <orgName>the State Department</orgName>. The person who was picked to head it was <persName>Julia</persName> [Vadala] <persName>Taft</persName>, who had been an official at HEW and at <orgName>the State Department</orgName>. And she was the senior person running it. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And what was your—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">So that’s the full spectrum.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">What was your role within the—this group?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, I was basically seconded [pronounced seh-CON-ded] from <orgName>OMB</orgName>. I had—I had let them know that I was leaving <date>the end of the summer</date> because my academic leave was going to be up, and so I’d always taken the job with the idea that I was only going to be there for <date>two years</date>. So basically I was more an individual than part of an official group. I was still overseeing the division that I was the head of, but I was spending a lot of time at the command center, working on first trying to coordinate what was going on in setting up the camps in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName> and then working to build support in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> for taking in the refugees and working with the different organizations.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And so were you sort of in more of a managerial role, rather than sort of doing more systems analysis, quantitative work like you were doing for <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes, very definitely. I mean, it was, you know, just a lot of people from across the government ended up being active in this, and you would spend time over there, manning the desk, making calls, trying to coordinate stuff that was going on, and then you’d go back to what was your regular job to do and take some part in what was still going on in the day-to-<date>day</date> business of your job, whichever department you had come from. So it was a collection, actually, of probably a couple of hundred people from a lot of different departments in the—in the government that ended up being the group working out of <orgName>the State Department</orgName>, running the resettlement—the evacuation and resettlement program.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did you feel like the government was prepared for the evacuation of—of Vietnamese refugees or did it feel a little bit more ad hoc, as though they hadn’t done as much preparation as they should?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Well, I don’t know what they sh- —what should have been. It was clearly unanticipated on this scale, so it was very ad hoc. It was being invented day by day. Somebody would come up with another bright idea for a resettlement center or getting another group involved with us. And so it—it was very—very ad hoc, being invented along the way. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did you feel that—that your work or the work of the working group was generally successful?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">It was. I think it was remarkably so. <persName>Julia Taft</persName>, who has since passed away, became something a hero of—of this entire effort and then had, for <date>a number of years later</date>, a fairly distinguished career in issues of refugees and <placeName>U.S.</placeName> policies with regard to refugees that began to extend well beyond just what had happened in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but as other refugee populations emerged from wars going on around the world, this sort of became her career, and she certainly was an expert in it and was highly regarded. And she passed away <date>several years ago</date> now.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And did you ever have the opportunity to meet her or work closely with her?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Oh, yes. No, I knew her, and I knew her husband well. Her husband was <persName>William Howard Taft IV</persName>, and Will was a lawyer who had been the general counsel at <orgName>HEW (Health Education and Welfare</orgName>). Had been general counsel I think when <persName>Elliot [L.] Richardson</persName> was secretary and then <persName>Richardson</persName>, who was the attorney general at the time of <name type="event">Watergate</name> and part of the famous <date>Saturday</date> Night Massacre—Will was on his staff, but then Will worked for <placeName>Casper</placeName> [<persName>W.] Weinberger</persName>, who became a secretary of <orgName>HEW</orgName> and then later the secretary of defense, and Will later became deputy secretary of <orgName>defense</orgName>. So I—I worked a lot with Will, more so, actually, than with <persName>Julia</persName>, his wife, but they were—yeah, I knew them well.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Awesome. Yeah, so after your—your time at the <orgName>OMB</orgName>, then, you sort of went back to a career in—in academia. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">That’s correct.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And—and one thing you were mentioning to me earlier was, in particular, a lot of your work in—in academia is probably a little bit outside the scope of the purpose of this interview,—</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">—but you were mentioning that while you were a professor at Tuck, you took part in projects run by <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> to—to help build economic development in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Is that correct? Can you tell me a little bit about that?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes. <orgName>The Tuck School</orgName> had done a couple of things like that. In the period when I was dean, we had helped get a—a business school, an English-language, international business school started in <placeName>Japan</placeName> in <date>the late ’80s</date>. And in <date>the ’90s</date>, when <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> began to open up more, <orgName>the National University of Vietnam</orgName> decided it was going to start a business school. And a <orgName>Tuck</orgName> faculty member, [<persName>Joseph A.] “Joe” Massey</persName>, who had been in international trade stuff and was an <placeName>Asia</placeName> expert—he had been on the staff in the embassy in <placeName>Tokyo</placeName>. But he came to talk in <date>the early ’90s</date>, having been the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> trade representative for—for <placeName>Japan</placeName> and <placeName>China</placeName>, actually, and began teaching international business matters.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">And was it ever awkward or were you ever questioned for your background during <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> as sort of a participant in the military effort?</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Only a few odd things, just a few incidents, like I—I took a couple of my <persName>Tuck</persName> colleagues, and we visited what I think they call their <orgName>National War Crimes Museum</orgName> [sic; <orgName>Museum of Chinese and</orgName> <orgName>American War Crimes</orgName>, now <orgName>War Remnants Museum</orgName>], basically, you know, documenting what the Americans did in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, in this museum. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Yeah. That’s—that’s extremely interesting, especially considering sort of the renewed importance of Vietnamese-American relations in—in <placeName>the Asian Pacific</placeName> now.</u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes. And I now have friends in the private equity business, a good friend who is a partner in something called <orgName>Mekong Capital</orgName>, who is a senior adviser—I think we called him special fellow of our private equity center at <placeName>Tuck</placeName>, who teaches as a guest lecturer in our course on private equity. And he has established a private equity investment fund in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> because of what he and his partners see as the business opportunities there. </u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Certainly. Yeah, that’s really fascinating. </u>
      <u who="BLAYDON">Yes, I think—and you’ve got to get on, and so do I, <persName>Riley</persName>, so I appreciate this. If you have any further questions or things you want me to elaborate on, certainly feel free to get in touch, and I’ll look forward to seeing the transcript.</u>
      <u who="COLLINS">Awesome. Here, I’ll—I’ll hit—or I’ll hit “Stop Recording.”</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
