<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="BROOKS"/>
        <person xml:id="FARKAS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="FARKAS">This is <persName>Sandor Farkas</persName> talking to [<persName>Timothy H.] “Tim” Brooks</persName>. It’s <date>Tuesday, March 15th [2016</date>] in Webster Hall at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>, over the phone.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">My parents were <persName>John [ W. R.]</persName> and <persName>Olive [Bradbury] Brooks</persName>. They were married in <date>the 1920s</date> and lived in <placeName>Hampton</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, which is where I grew up. My father was a sales manager for a car dealership owned by my uncle.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you have any siblings?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yes, I have two older brothers, <date>10 and 12 years</date> older than I.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Now, can you tell me about your hometown?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS"><placeName>Hampton</placeName> is on the coast. <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> has a very short coast [chuckles], but it’s a—halfway between <placeName>Boston</placeName> [<placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>] and <placeName>Portland</placeName> [<placeName>Maine</placeName>] and kind of a small town but a suburban town. The trains and things run through there with [Interstate] 95—that does now, that sort of thing. So it’s—so it’s fairly suburban, I guess you would say, although in <date>the 1950s</date> it was a—it was a typical small town in a lot of ways. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, did your father or any—or your mother, for that matter—or any other relatives fight in <name type="event">World War II</name> or <name type="event">the Korean War</name>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">My brothers were both in the service. My father was not, nor my mother. She was—she was a part-time teacher but mostly a homemaker. But both of my brothers—as I say, they were <date>10 and 12 years</date> older than I, so they were in the service as enlisted men during <name type="event">the Korean War</name>. They didn’t—they weren’t on the front, but my older brother was in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Air Force</orgName>, and he was stationed in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, where he met his future wife, and my middle brother, <persName>Peter [G. Brooks</persName>] was in the [U.S.] <orgName>Army</orgName>, and he was in <placeName>Korea</placeName> but after the truce.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So growing up, did you have a close connection with them? I mean, they were pretty significantly older.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. Well, they were kind of like adults to me [chuckles] by the time I was, you know, <date>8 or 9 years old</date>; they were already in college or out of college, in the service or getting married and out of the house. I had a somewhat choppy childhood in a way because when I was <date>11</date>, my father died rather—rather suddenly. And both of my brothers, as I say, were out of the house by then, so it was just me being raised by my mother.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So one more kind of question about your brothers: What did they tell you about their time in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> and the <orgName>Army</orgName>, respectively?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not much [chuckles], not much. My older brother, [<persName>John B.]</persName> “Jack”—who was the one who was stationed in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>—he was really, you know, less connected. He was older and went off to—he got his degree at UNH [<orgName>University of New Hampshire</orgName>], and then he went to get a master’s degree and eventually a <persName>Ph.D.</persName>, and he moved out of town with his—with his bride.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you said you went to two different schools, one of which was kind of a magnet school and one of which was more of a blue-collar school. Can you tell me how your plans for after high school evolved through that time? Did you always want to go to college? Was that an expectation?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It was—it was an expectation. Both my brothers had gone to college. I had a stellar high school career. I was top of my class. And it was—and I wanted to. [Chuckles.] So it was—it was never a question. The only question was paying for it because we didn’t have much money, but—but, yeah, it was assumed, as the—as the—I was the valedictorian of my class—it was assumed I would go to college. And—and that’s what I wanted to do.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what interests did you have in high school? Did you have any sense of what kind of a career you wanted to go into?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">As I say, I was very good at math. I even went to an advanced studies program up at <orgName>St. Paul’s School</orgName> to study advanced calculus and things they didn’t teach in my school, so I was very good at that. But it was never something that I kind of wanted to do [chuckles] particularly. I liked to write. I was very interested in the music industry. A lot of teens are interested in pop music and so forth, but we had a subscription to <orgName>Billboard</orgName> [chuckles] as a school kid and was interested in the charts and how it worked and so forth. So that turned out to be important to me later on as I was making my career choices. But I was interested in the music industry and—although we didn’t call it that then—in entertainment and—and something kind of—either business or science oriented.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Now, obviously, you ended up at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but can you tell me how that worked its way into your college applications?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. It was kind of a strange turn of events. You know, life sometimes takes turns you don’t expect, but that can be a good thing. And I was assuming [chuckles] I guess, because both my brothers had gone to <orgName>UNH</orgName>, that I would go to <orgName>the University of New Hampshire</orgName> as well. It’s nearby, just kind of the obvious place.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So did you get a chance to visit the campus in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> before you decided upon going to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">That’s a good question. I don’t remember going there. It’s possible I did. But I certainly was not familiar with what the—I mean, it was nothing like the Dimensions Weekend or the kinds of things we have now. I certainly wasn’t familiar with, you know, the kind of environment that I would be in there, only that it was a very well-regarded college, nationally as well as in <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>. Had a very good reputation, and people spoke highly of it. And it would combine the kind of interests I had in a liberal education because I was very interested in writing as well, as well as—you know, it wasn’t a—it wasn’t a school that had any kind of media program, but not many schools did then. So I was more focused on pursuing my technical knowledge.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you describe your first impressions of the campus, what that first—<date>those first weeks</date> or <date>months</date> were like?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. It was a—it was a completely different environment than I was used to, but by this time I had been kind of shuttered around enough that I was used to being out of the house [chuckles] and on my own, as I explained, so that didn’t bother me particularly.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. So you described the different commitments. Obviously, you had, I would say, strong math skills and other kind of technical skills. Did that make you—did that ever sway you towards the <orgName>Navy</orgName> or <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>? I mean, those seem like they might have been choices that were more in line with your interests, possibly.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, if—if they all had been equal, I might have opted—I don’t think I’d opt for the <orgName>Navy</orgName>; I’m not that much of a sailor. But I might have opted for <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>, possibly, but <date>four years</date> versus two seemed like a no-brainer. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I had no thought of making the military a career, but—and it was assumed that I would serve in the military—I would—one way or another, or be drafted, so—so it was—you know, What’s the best way to do this? And as I say, I wanted to be an officer. I thought it was worth the time that I would put into <orgName>ROTC</orgName> to go that route rather than the enlisted route as, as I say, my brothers had done. So the <orgName>Army</orgName> seemed like the obvious one.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely. So back to that activities fair. </u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">When you signed up for <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, were you legally kind of committing to that? Did—you said the score—they gave you a scholarship, so did the <orgName>Army</orgName> also contribute in that manner?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No, no, there was—the school—from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, I had a work scholarship, so I worked in the dining room—dining hall, and that helped pay—and I also had several scholarships, smaller ones, from—from high school. I had won a whole bunch of scholarships, actually. [Chuckles.] And none of them were particularly large, but when you put them together, and you put them together with the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, you know, work program and, you know, with whatever money my mother could scrape together, that—<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> wasn’t as expensive then as it is now. That managed to get me through. I did have to work—I worked for <date>my first three years</date>. I didn’t work in <date>my senior year</date>. But I worked rather regularly in the dining room. But <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, no, there was no scholarship associated with that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">From the information you already provided, it seems like that was very important to you. You actually wrote a book on it. Can you tell me what enticed you about radio that day?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Initially, it was my interest in—in music, I think, and the music industry. I’d been making—and serving local record shops, even when I was in high school and doing, you know, high school top ten or something in the dining room, for the enjoyment or annoyance of my classmates. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what did you do, coming into the station?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I initially volunteered to help in the record library. They had a big record library of <orgName>LPs</orgName> and <date>45s</date> [respective record formats],  which had to be organized, and there were new boxes of records coming in all the time, and you had to go—reach out to the record companies. And there was—what was it?—a Top 30 list, I guess, that was compiled <date>every week</date> for the disk jockeys to play. So I did that. I eventually took over as the record librarian. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not generally. The news department did a lot of interviews, especially in <date>election years</date>. <date>Election years</date> were a big, big deal, and the <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> primary was a big deal, too. We had an Election Night, where we’d take over a ballroom somewhere and set up tables, you know, for different areas and have students posted out to polling sites and the campaign headquarters, calling in results as they came in. That was a big operation.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Wow! So a lot of information. Let’s see, what was your taste in music back then?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Oh, I was a rock and roll kid, of course. [Chuckles.] I don’t know if you have any courses on this or anything, but when was in junior high and so forth, when I was a kid, it was all [singers] <persName>Patti Page</persName> and <persName>Jo [E.] Stafford</persName> and that kind of stuff. In <date>1955</date>, suddenly rock and roll just burst on the scenes with [<persName>William J. C.]</persName> “Bill” Haley and then <persName>Elvis</persName> [<persName>Presley</persName>] and [<persName>Charles E. A.</persName>] “<persName>Chuck</persName>” <persName>Berry</persName> and all those folks.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So kind of a strange question here: You said you did this—this program of older music, and you mentioned, you know, a night of—or an hour of <name type="event">World War</name> I music or other things like that. Was it in- —I mean, looking back, was it interesting to see what, for example, <name type="event">World War I or World War II</name> music was like? Did you get any sense of a kind of—the military from the military music?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I wouldn’t say there was much of a tie to the military there. The military was always in the back of my mind because, again, on the assumption that I would have to go into the service one way or the other, but, no, the interest in older music—I have a great interest in history, too. I’ve written books about that. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">How did you get those records?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, as I say, many of them were either loaned or donated to the station by local residents. They were cleaning out the barn, or they had had a collection of—they were mostly 78s—you know, the records that came before <date>45s</date>? I don’t know how much you know about this business. But the kind of record that came before <orgName>LPs</orgName> and <date>45s</date>, <persName>microgroove records</persName>, were ten inches, and they were 78 rpm [revolutions per minute] records. They spun very fast and had steel needles and stuff. And those had been produced since the turn of the [<date>20th] century</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you said you interviewed <persName>Johnny Cash</persName>? </u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What was that like?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">That was a lot of fun. You ought to listen to the interview on my website. It’s short. It’s about four or five minutes. And there were—there was a show called <persName>Hootenanny</persName> on one of the television networks that was taping at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. They would move around to different campuses around the country. And I think it was over at Webster Hall, which is now <persName>Rauner</persName> [<orgName>Special Collections Library</orgName>], I believe.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That’s where I am right now.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Okay. Well, there was a stage there, and there was, you know, seats and an audience and stuff. Kind of a moderate-sized auditorium. And the TV crew set up there, and he was going to be the star attraction on it. The dressing rooms were down underneath the stage, so it was, like, down from where <orgName>Rauner</orgName> is now. And I was sent—I don’t know why, but I was sent over to do an interview with him. We usually did do interviews with musical acts and celebrities who were passing through if we could.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah, it was my fraternity. I never pledged at a fraternity. I was a little afraid I couldn’t afford one anyway, because, as I say, money was kind of tight. But the radio station was a regular place you could go. You could hang out. You know, guys went out to dinner together and road trips together and things like that, as well as, you know, working at the station.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So speaking of distractions from academics, did you have any relationships while you were at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">With—what do you mean? With—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">With any women I know that students used to travel down to <orgName>Smith [College</orgName>] and <orgName>Mount Holyoke [College</orgName>] and other—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not—not serious ones, no. I mean, because it was an all-male school—I wish it hadn’t been, but because it was an all-male school, either you went on road trips to <persName>Smith</persName> or something, or you waited for Green Key Weekend or one of <date>the weekends</date> when—when girls would arrive by the busload. That was pretty much it. And, you know, my mistress was the radio station, in a lot of ways, so nothing any—nothing that endured. [Chuckles.] Let’s put it that way.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me how that evolved?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, as with a lot of things, you—you try things out, and it’s not involuntary servitude; if you don’t like them, you can move on to something else. Because I had a adviser in high school who gave me some—the <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> tests or something and said, “Well, you’re very well suited to be an engineer,” so I went into that. But after I took a couple of courses in it, I decided this wasn’t for me. It was a course where we were designing an on ramp for a super highway. And I don’t know if you know anything about this, on ramps take a lot of design. They have to be a certain angle. They have to be a certain kind of tilt to them so the cars don’t run off them, and all that kind of stuff. Lots of formulas and lots of calculations. And I just decided I’d rather drive on an on ramp than design one. It just didn’t seem that interesting.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Oh, and— and English—I should say, English as a secondary—looking back, maybe it should have been the primary because I’ve written eight books and I do a lot of writing now. But that was my secondary interest.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you had mentioned that you were at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> during a primary? Were you very political at that point in your life?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not particularly. I’m more interested in the process than—than the ideology. And the station, as I say, was—was very, very focused on being professional, and professional means—or at least meant then—that you’re non-partisan, that <date>you’re</date>—just the facts, that you’re getting both sides of every issue. And the station—you know, through its history, even in the tumult of <date>the late ’60s</date> and <date>early ’70s</date> and the antiwar protests and so forth, had an absolutely firm rule that no reporter for the station could take sides, who could join protests. If they did, they couldn’t be a reporter for the station. “We have to be independent. We have to be a neutral voice.” And each side was mad at them for that reason [chuckles] because the antiwar students wanted the station to be an antiwar voice, and the—there were a lot of pro-war students, and they wanted, you know, the other.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So did you have much—were you very aware of the [<name type="event">Vietnam] War</name> at that point? I know it was fairly early, so—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No. As a matter of fact—and I might have written this somewhere—in <date>1960</date>, when I matriculated, most of us had never heard of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, or maybe we had heard of it. You know I was fairly aware of what was going on in the world. But it certainly wasn’t on our radar. And even in ’61, ’62, ’63, when we had advisers there and there were some battles in which Americans were killed and so forth, it was still a very peripheral event in the world. The big news was <name type="event">the Cuban Missile Crisis</name> and the assassination of [President <persName>John F.]</persName> <persName>Kennedy</persName> and, you know, things like that. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Were there any Vietnamese students or, for that matter, East Asian students at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> that you recall?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not that I remember. It was a pretty white-bread school. [laughs.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. Were any of your friends or any other people from <orgName>DCR</orgName> also in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No, I don’t remember any that were. There might have been one or two, but none that were in my circle, certainly. Most of them—some of them were—were in—a fair number of them were in fraternities or had other activities. Some of them, like me, were kind of, like, all-consumed by the radio station. But I don’t remember any others in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—I mean, you mentioned a bit about what the classes were like. Can you tell me what different activities constituted being in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, what I remember of it—and it’s a long time ago, and it wasn’t the center of my world, so the memories are kind of faint on this, but what I remember primarily are those classes, which were in a classroom, and it was taught by usually a sergeant, and, as I say, they were—they were—they were gut courses. And going down to the—the field once a week, maybe, to—to do some formation drills and—and practice some things, like assembling weapons and things. And an occasional bivouac out someplace.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And do you recall—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">There was no—I mean, there’s a thread going on now online about war protesters. I don’t remember anybody protesting it or, you know, expressing their disdain for military. I mean, there’s some that had no interest in the military, of course, but the war protests hadn’t begun yet, and there was no kind of negative connotation attached to being in the—in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> that I recall.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Now, you said there was a sergeant. I assume there were other staff. Did they ever share with you, or <orgName>ROTC</orgName> in general, their experiences?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I don’t remember that they did. I don’t remember that they did. They had a—as the military tends to do, they had a very rigid and regimented course outline that I guess came down from the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>, very generic, about what you were supposed to study and how you were supposed to study it, and it didn’t particularly fit, I don’t think, a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> student body. It was meant to fit everybody and therefore fit nobody [chuckles] very—particularly well.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So did you have any friends in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>, people you were kind of closer with?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not particularly, much more the radio station. I can’t even tell you now who the people were that were in <orgName>ROTC</orgName> with me. I—I think there were one or two that I knew from the dorms or something like that, maybe even one from the station that was also in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>, but it was basically a different group than the ones that I mixed with elsewhere.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Around how many people were there?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It was a fairly small group. Now, remember, I was in <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC, so there was a separate <orgName>Navy</orgName> and a separate Air Force ROTC, too, but in the—in the <orgName>Army</orgName>, I would say that it might have been, I don’t know, 20, 25 people, something like that, I guess.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. And do you remember where the office was, or the classroom was?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I have no idea where the classroom was. The—the office and where we drilled was down by the athletic field, and I think there was an office down there somewhere, where the sergeant was headquartered or something. We didn’t hang around there. That was just going down for, you know, some drill practice or something, or maybe to get on a bus to go over to <placeName>Lyme</placeName> [NH] and bivouac or whatever.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So were there any larger <date>summer</date> training exercises that you had to attend?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. Well, in addition to what I just mentioned, which were occasional, in your junior summer, I guess it was—this is <date>the summer</date> after your junior year—you had to go to basic training, and that was at <placeName>Fort Devens</placeName> [<placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>], and that was for <date>several weeks</date>. I’m not sure exactly how many, <date>four weeks</date>, something like that. And that was a shock to the system, too, because that was—I mean, that was regular basic training. [Chuckles.] You know, that was—that was—it was hard work. And for people who aren’t particularly athletic, like myself, I was—it put you through a regimen that you weren’t familiar with. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So do you have any other thoughts on your <date>last year</date> at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, kind of your concluding time? Were you sad to leave? A little bit ready to get on with life?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">You know, I was certainly sad in one sense. I made some real friends there. As I say, this radio station had been very important to me, and I was leaving it, of course. And, you know, I found <persName>Hanover</persName>, for all its freezing cold and snow [chuckles] and everything, probably worse then than it is now, to be a congenial place.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So did your mother and your siblings come for graduation and commissioning?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">[Laughs.] Oddly enough, my—my mother, who had studied to be a teacher in <date>the 1920s</date>, but at that time they would not allow a woman to have a <date>four-year</date> degree. (How times have changed!) So she only did <date>two years</date>, and therefore she could not get a full-time teaching certificate, so she went back to college. She went to <orgName>UNH</orgName> and finished her degree that she had started—teaching degree that she had started in <date>the ‘20s</date>, when she was a younger woman. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">There was—there was a gap—like, I graduated in <date>June</date>, and I was due to report I think in <date>August</date>. I could be wrong on that. <date>Late July</date>. But there as a month or so there that I was back home, kind of getting my stuff together.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What was your own background, by the way?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">My own background?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Whether—your family. Were they kind of an old <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> family?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah, we know a lot about my mother’s family because in <date>the late 18th century</date>—or <date>the late 19th century</date>, around the <date>1880s</date> or <date>’90s</date>, they commissioned a book to be written about the family history. And the book survives. This is something what a few middle-class families did then, apparently. So they had been in <placeName>America</placeName> and in <placeName>New England</placeName> since <date>the 1600s</date>, and then the guy traced them back from there over to <placeName>England</placeName> and <placeName>Scotland</placeName>, and they traced them back through the ages, back to the <date>1200s</date> or something. So a long history, in <placeName>America</placeName> a long time and in <placeName>New England</placeName> a long time. That’s on my mother’s side.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, after <date>a year</date> at <placeName>Fort Bragg</placeName>, we got our orders to deploy to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. The—as I say, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was not an issue while I was at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>’64</date>. And ’64-’65 it was just starting to glimmer and starting to emerge in the press, and I think <placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin</placeName> [incident] was—was the summer of ’64, wasn’t it? </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yup.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Or <date>the early fall</date>, something like that? And [President <persName>Lyndon B.]</persName> <persName>Johnson</persName> was elected, of course, in the fall. And after he was elec- —he didn’t—he didn’t run on a <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> platform, certainly. But after he was elected, that’s when the build-up started, in <date>early ’65</date>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So rewinding just a little bit, when you realized there was the prospect of deploying to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, was that something you wanted to do, didn’t want to do or were ambivalent about?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It was—it was just orders. [Chuckles.] It was not something—at that time—this is long before [the] Tet [Offensive] and long before <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> got, you know, all over the news as—as a bloody mess, so I didn’t see it, and I don’t think those around me saw it as a terrible thing. It was obviously going to a war zone, so that was, you know, not the best—and some people feel more—feel badly about that or feel scared by that. I didn’t. And most of us didn’t. I mean, you’re twenty- —I don’t know about you, but you’re <date>22 years old</date> and you’re indestructible, you know? [Chuckles.] And this could be an adventure.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So speaking of new experiences, you got off the plane in <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName>, you said.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yup.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did you go into <placeName>Saigon</placeName> after that?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">When I first arrived, I—I went to <orgName>the 362nd Signal Company</orgName> headquarters, the unit I was attached to there, to get my orders. And I seem to remember—I might have stayed a night or so in—in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. But I—I pretty quickly deployed down to <persName>Binh Long</persName>, to my new base. And later—and—and got to know the peop- —you know, took over down there, met the people there, understood what my responsibilities were down there and my reporting responsibilities. There was an occasional company commanders meeting in <persName>Vũng Tàu</persName>, so I would fly from Binh Long up to <persName>Vũng Tàu</persName> to the 362nd company headquarters to meet with the CO </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what was your first impression of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, of <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, of <placeName>Binh Long</placeName>, of the people, of the climate, of the culture, of the food, all that?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Now, the first impression was It’s hot and it’s humid in this place. <persName>God</persName>, is it humid! Everything is sopping. [Chuckles.] And I got to my base in <placeName>Binh Long</placeName> and found—and I had, you know, officers’ billets, which is a little straw-roofed huts with individual rooms in it for the—for the junior officers. And it had a wardrobe in it, which had a light bulb in it, which was on all the time. What’s that for? That’s to keep your clothes from rotting. [Chuckles.] The heat from the light bulb is enough to counteract what otherwise would be the stifling humidity that just rots everything it touches. So that’s kind of what it was like. So there was a certain getting used to the climate there. Now, I’ve been back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> since, and that—that’s in the south. That’s in the delta. The whole country isn’t like that. But the climate was the first thing that struck me.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you describe kind of the day-to-<date>day</date> runnings of your post at Binh Long?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Pretty boring [chuckles], actually. There were certain reports we needed to—to fill out and send in to company headquarters. We had to read the meters. There was—these were big, rack-mounted communications equipment. And for something serious or a real breakdown, we had <persName>Guy</persName> who was our contractor, the civilian, but for everything else it was basically, you know, monitoring, maintaining and reporting. And I was bored out of my gourd in no time at all with that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what was his name?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">His name is [<persName>Alan R.]</persName> “<persName>Al” McKee [Class</persName> of <date>1964</date>], <persName>Al McKee</persName>. He later went into <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>. Became an ambassador, actually. But he was the assistant station manager, and he got me a shift in the morning. Now, this is totally without orders or without even the knowledge of my CO, but in a war zone, as I said, you could do lots of things. If I went out to the landing field and there’s a chopper about to take off and they say—they say, “We’re headed for <placeName>Saigon</placeName>,” I say, “You got room? Can you give me a lift?” And they say, “Sure, Lieutenant, jump in.” [Chuckles.] You know, just like that. I mean you don’t need orders. I mean, you just—the way you want to go. I mean, you’re supposed to be where you’re supposed to be if something happens, but they’re not watching you, and particularly as an officer, you’ get an awful of latitude.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What was your—oh, sorry, sorry, I didn’t mean to interrupt.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah, until <date>one week</date>, a company commander at <persName>Vũng Tàu</persName> announced there was going to be a meeting of detachment commanders. We all needed to be in <persName>Vũng Tàu</persName> on <date>Sunday</date> to meet with him. So <date>the week before that</date>, I recorded my show so they could play the tape while I was not able to come in <date>that week</date>. And I flew up to <persName>Vũng Tàu</persName> to meet with the company commander.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What was your show like? What—what did you do?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Oh, boring as could be. It was <date>Sunday</date> morning, and the format was to play very calm kind of hangover music, you might say, so it was a lot of <persName>Jo Stafford</persName>. There was, you know, folk songs, maybe the <orgName>Weavers</orgName>, things like that, no—no rock and roll on Sunday morning, but it was radio.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now the <orgName>Weavers</orgName>. So—I mean,—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">You remember the <orgName>Weavers</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Of course I remember the <orgName>Weavers</orgName>. I grew up in <placeName>New England</placeName>, in <placeName>Western</placeName>, <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>. So that is, I would say, sometimes on the verge, sometimes quite explicitly antiwar music. Was that cool to play?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">The Weavers became antiwar. In <date>the early ’50s</date>, when they had that first burst of fame for <orgName>Decca Records</orgName>, they were singing very generic folksongs, “Goodnight, <persName>Irene</persName>” and “So Long, It’s Been Good to Know You” and “On Top of Old Smoky,” things like that. They started as a—as a left-wing protest group in <date>the ‘40s</date>. They were called <name type="event">the Almanac Singers</name> originally. [<persName>Peter</persName>] “<persName>Pete” Seeger</persName>, of course, is well known for his—his political views.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. So the culture at—in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, at the radio station, versus the culture in your unit—were they very different? Was there anything kind of specific you remember about the radio in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, certainly in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>—I mean, those who were out in the field, even if it was in—in a base like mine in the delta—referred to “<placeName>Saigon</placeName> soldiers” with some disdain because they tended to have much more cushy accommodations. They had an office they went to, and they went home at night and had a nice place, and it was relatively safe. So it was considered a softer assignment.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—oh, yeah, absolutely.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Usually—usually <placeName>Saigon</placeName> was the place that you would go for, you know, nighttime fun, so to speak. It was bustling. It was full of Americans. Weapons were not allowed in the central city area. I mean, there were military police, and there were people around, but it wasn’t like it was filled with people with guns on their hips. So it was safer. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So to get to that in a moment, but just a couple lingering questions about—about <persName>Binh Long</persName> and <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. You said in <placeName>Binh Long</placeName> you didn’t get off base into local town much or at all?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Not much. I did go in a few times. As I said, I went to this <orgName>Vietnamese Army</orgName> base and taught English there for a while, but—and I think we had a couple of meetings where I and the base commander and a few other officers met with <orgName>Vietnamese Army</orgName> commanders and had a dinner, ceremonial dinner. We’d all raise glasses and clinked to each other’s health and that sort of stuff.	So occasionally we’d go into town, but usually on official business of some kind.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I remember—if I could just add—I remember <persName>Binh Long</persName> as a town specifically, not a city. When I was there <date>last fall</date>, we went through <placeName>Binh Long</placeName>, and they said it had 700,000 people! So either it was a lot bigger than I remember it, or it’s grown an awful lot in <date>the years</date> since, because it certainly was not one of the principal cities of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> when I was there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what kind of food did you eat? Did you eat <orgName>U.S. Army</orgName>—the wonderful <orgName>U.S. Army</orgName> style rations? Did you have kind of more American style food, or did you ever try Vietnamese food?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It was very much American food, and the military made every effort to bring in familiar food for—for the troops, so every base would have a, you know, a snack shop or something. You could get a milkshake, you’d get a hamburger, stuff you’re familiar with from home. And that was always available on any military installation or bases, and USOs [United Service Organizations], too, in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, for that matter. So it was mostly American food. I think on occasion, particularly on these ceremonial dinners that we’d have once in a while, we would have Vietnamese cuisine, but, no, it was—it was overwhelmingly American food.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. And when you did kind of take some time off in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> or after you had done your radio show and—or possibly hang out with your peer from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, did you do much, as you said, night fun, go out to bars or anything like that?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I did a few times with friends of mine, but I’m not really a bar crawling kind of guy [chuckles], so not a lot of that. I wanted to see the sights of the city to the extent I could, within the safe area. And, in fact some of the pictures that I took then of street scenes and—well, one of the central parts of the city is—is the opera house, opposite which there is a long, verdant boulevard, very French in appearance. And I remember taking pictures of that. It looked like <placeName>Paris</placeName>. And, of course, it had been French for <date>many years</date>, and the French built the city to look like <placeName>Paris</placeName> in a lot of ways.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, as I say, I was in—in the delta, in <placeName>Binh Long</placeName>, so I would fly up to <placeName>Saigon</placeName>—and on the—on the pay runs, they would have a plane for you. It was usually either a single-engine light plane or a chopper, a “Huey” [<orgName>Bell UH-1 Iroquois</orgName>, or HU-1]. And I would fly up to <persName>Vũng Tàu</persName> and fly to <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName>, and we would go up into the <placeName>Highlands</placeName>, <orgName>Buôn Ma Thuột</orgName> and <persName>Đà Lạt</persName>, <persName>Pleiku</persName>. There are—there are cities in the <placeName>Highlands</placeName> that are very different. It’s almost like being in the mountains back in <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, in a way. Much cooler, pine trees, lakes and things. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, you—as you’ve related, it sounds like you got a great opportunity to see a lot of different types of Vietnamese towns, kind of a lot of different aspects of the war. I mean, do you have any—any additional kind of things to say about that, the contrast between different places? Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, the impression I got was the same as I’ve related to you from my experiences in <placeName>Binh Long</placeName>. That the—in <date>1965</date> to <date>1966</date>, when I left, the—the Vietnamese that I encountered, that I did business with—and I would meet them at these—at these sites too—they would be, you know, helping out there in various positions—was that they were—they were very friendly to the Americans. You have to remember, they had been at war since <date>1945</date>, or actually since <name type="event">World War II</name>, when the Japanese occupied their country.  And then—then there was a French war, and the French killed a lot of people and they killed a lot of French until [the Battle of] Điện Biên Phủ in <date>the mid ’50s</date>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">They had no use for all this electronic stuff. But they could use the money, and they wanted it to keep coming, and so it was kind of—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you carry any firearms at all? Did you receive any kind of defense training?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Oh, yeah, yeah. Every—every member of the military has arms training. I don’t know about the chaplains [chuckles], but everybody else certainly does. Maybe they do, too. So, yeah, I had—I had marksmanship training, at which I was terrible. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Probably not called the same thing, but something similar.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It designates by position what every person is assigned to have. And in my case, as a detachment commander, my official weapon was a M14, which is a big, heavy rifle, at which I couldn’t hit anything. Maybe if I threw the rifle at them I could hit them, but [chuckles] in terms of hitting a target, I was not a good aim. And this thing—especially when I started doing my rounds as the pay officer, it was just—it was just an impediment. It’s so big and so bulky and so awkward. But that was my assigned weapon.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">M1 carbine?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. Ah, No, it’s—it’s well, generically it’s a carbine. It’s a small rifle. I’m not sure. I think it was a civilian rife, actually. Much shorter barrel, not nearly as heavy, but a long barrel. And I was much better at hitting things with that, actually. And so I paid him 20 or 30 bucks or something. He was cycling out of the country, as I say, and you can’t take weapons home with you. So he had to sell it to somebody. So—so I bought that, and I had left the M14, the big old M14 in the arms room, and I carried the carbine around with me, and that was much easier.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you practice much in theater?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No. I can’t remember ever going to a firing range while in service. While on active duty.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. So—huh! So—I’m sorry, one more question about the carbine, just because I’m interested in that kind of thing. Was the firing mechanism somewhat similar to the M14? Kind—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Wow, that’s a good question. I seem to remember it as simply. I think the carbine, which took larger bullets and took a bigger magazine and so forth. As I remember—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">The M14 did.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah, M14, later replaced by the M16 [rifle], but the M16s hadn’t really spread yet when I was there, was—I think it had a more complex loading mechanism, but, you know, frankly I’m not sure. I don’t remem-—When I left the country in <date>the summer</date> of <date>’66</date>, of course, I sold it to somebody else who was just coming in or wanted one, and it got passed along that way to who knows how many other hands.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I don’t think I ever fired it. [Chuckles.] It was there for protection if I needed it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. Interesting. </u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Information. You mean behind the scenes or on the air or what?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So if <date>you’re</date>—if the purpose of the radio station was transmitting information, were you ever privy to that? Did you ever get involved in kind of personally transmitting that information?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, the—the—the purpose of the radio station was to entertain the troops.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, I’m sorry. I—I meant the radio—not the radio station but rather the post you were assigned to, <persName>Binh Long</persName>, the whole installation.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Oh, you mean the communication stations.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes, yes.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No, the content of what went out over the air—well, not over the air but from—from microwave tower to microwave tower was originated by the headquarters or whoever was—needed to make a phone call to some other base. Sometimes it was encrypted. And—and we—were were like the phone company. We ran the equipment. We did not listen to or originate the messages ourselves. Somebody didn’t come to our office and say, “I want to send this message.” They picked up a phone to the company headquarters and, you know, where/how they got there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Have you seen my write-up in the Class of ’64 book?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, so I was going to move to that next. Do you want me to kind of—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, I’ll just say that I wrote about some things—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">—in there. You know, the mystery of “Cookie,” Miss B, whatever happened to her. [Chuckles.] There’s kind of an interesting addendum to that story, actually. She was the secretary I was talking about before.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—before—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">All right.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">One <orgName>sec</orgName>. Before we go into that, I just kind of, for the purpose of the recording: So you came home after <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yes, I mustered out [cross-talk; unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Was that—were you given the option to extend that tour, or did you—in other words, did you really want to leave, or is that just kind of what you were told to do?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, the standard tour was <date>a year</date>. But in fact, after <date>ten months</date>, I think, if you kept your nose clean and had done a good job, you could cycle back before <date>the end of the year</date>. I remember that—[I was] talking to my company commander, and he said, “What do you want to do?” And I said, “You know, I’m willing to stay for <date>another month</date>. Is that all right?” And he said, “Sure.” So I stayed for <date>11 months</date> instead of <date>10 months</date>. Or <date>eleven and half</date> or something like that. So I didn’t stay <date>the full year</date>, although I did extend a bit. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">So that—that wasn’t something I was interested in doing. I had fulfilled my commitment now of <date>two years</date>. I was a first lieutenant now, and that was fine. And I knew that I had still an obligation for—to be in the Reserves [<orgName>the U.S. Army Reserve</orgName>] or <orgName>the National Guard</orgName> [of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>] beyond that, too. But in terms of staying on active duty, it never crossed my mind.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me about the trip home?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. The trip home, again, was on a jet. This time it wasn’t my unit that was going back; it was me and a whole bunch of other guys in a similar situation. And it was a commercial, chartered jet. It was very nice to get on that plane because it was so cool and dry [chuckles] after <date>a year</date> of, you know, drenched <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What was your reception at the airport and at home like?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">When I got home?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. What was—I mean, I know later in the war there were, you could say, mixed perceptions in the airport—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—on arriving home, but a kind of this side—earlier in the war, what was the reception like?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No—no problems at all. My mother came to pick me up, I guess, at the airport. There was no welcoming crowd or anything like that. When I got back home to <placeName>Hampton</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, my mother, you know, was so glad to see me in on piece, back, obviously, but she—you know, I saw all of her friends. She was in a number of clubs and things. She wanted to see the pictures and things, so I put together a slide show of—of sights of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and so forth. And they were interested in that, and, “Oh, <persName>Timothy</persName>, that’s wonderful.”</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—sorry, alright—let me just make sure—cool. Sorry about that.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah, sure. As I mentioned, Miss B, known affectionately as “Cookie,” was our secretary, and everybody in the unit knew her. There was nothing going on sexual that I’d ever heard or knew. She dressed very properly and was very polite. And when I left in <date>the middle of ’66</date>, she came out to the field, and I’m getting on the plane to leave or something, waved goodbye and that was that. Didn’t make much of it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Let me—do you mind if I just read it for the sake of the recording?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Sure, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Cool.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It was very touching and very emotional, as you can—as you could tell. When I received that, my first instinct was to write back, but there was nowhere to write back to. I suppose I could have tried to investigate and, you know, contacted the new lieutenant there and see if she was still there or try to track her down somehow, but this was at a point where I was trying to get my life together [chuckles], frankly. And not only didn’t I have a job, I didn’t have a career, and I wasn’t sure what I was going to do next. I was very busy, you know, tracking down leads and doing interviews and trying to figure out where I am I going to go from here.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah, yes. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">He teaches a course on <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, of course. He said, if I wanted to do that, he would—he would help. He would try to locate someone on the ground that might investigate for me, something like that. But he said to think about a couple of things. First of all, if I wanted to do this, I couldn’t do it kind of on an afternoon on the tour. I’d need to stay in country for a while, so I might have to extend my <date>three-week</date> tour into <date>another week</date> or something. But more importantly than that, he said, “There could be unintended consequences to this kind of thing. I’m not telling you not to do it, but I’m just saying think about it.”</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Thank you for sharing that.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Oh, yeah, yeah. The agreement was and the official line was that you had to serve <date>another eight years</date>? No, <date>another four years</date>, I think it was, in the Reserves: <date>2 years</date> active, <date>four years Reserve</date>. That was the rule.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. </u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Right. Well, from—from ’66 to ’<date>68</date>, while I was in <placeName>Albany</placeName> at this station, it was becoming much more on the news, and you certainly heard about all of the protests and the escalation of the war. The Tet Offensive, which was a huge deal, was in <date>early ’68</date>, which seemed to be—it’s ironic: it was not a military defeat, but it was certainly a public relations defeat of major proportions, where we were supposed to have everything under control, and instead our bases are being overrun everywhere, including the base I had been at in <placeName>Binh Long</placeName>. The sergeant major was killed, and the place was blown up.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">At that point, did you have an opinion about the war?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah, my opinion, was with most, was that it was a just war, that the domino theory was real, or certainly could be real. There was a major confrontation, of course, that I’d grown up with between communism and the free world, and it was scary. I mean, the—from the—from the shelters of the—the bomb shelters, the atomic bomb with <date>the ‘50s</date>, the Cuban Missile Crisis or—it looked like the world might blow up. I mean, even seeing a movie like On the Beach scared the bejesus out of you. [Chuckles.] I mean, This could be the end of everything!</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So next, you went to grad school, you said, at <orgName>Syracuse University</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. While I was working at <orgName>WTEN</orgName>—I should tell you this short story. I was—I was writing promotional copy, right? In a back room somewhere. And I saw that the program director, the sales manager got very excited when—when a little book came in, and they would run in the corridors and say, “We got a five! We got a five!” Or <date>next month</date> they would—a guy would slink out of his office and say, “We got a three.” “That’s terrible.” And I couldn’t figure out what it was about a three or a five that was driving these people to such paroxysms of [chuckles] excitement.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Hmm. So going back to <placeName>Syracuse</placeName>, though, were there any protests, antiwar protests during your time there?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Definitely. Definitely. It was—it was like a different world, certainly, than the world I’d experienced at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I stepped onto campus—<placeName>Syracuse</placeName> is a big school, of course, about 30,000, I think, there. There were protests. There were, you know, clenched fists. [Chuckles.] There were—there was a lot of marijuana. You could go into a theater and almost get high just breathing.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">How did that make you feel when you were there?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Part of me wanted to argue with them. Part of me thought that there’s no point. I mean, people who feel that strongly about something—nothing you say is going even be heard. You know, you’re something to make their argument to. [Chuckles.] That’s true <date>today</date>, unfortunately, in politics.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. </u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yes. After I got my master’s from <placeName>Syracuse</placeName>, through the good offices of this sales manager that I met at <orgName>WTEN</orgName>, I got the job with <orgName>WCBS-TV</orgName> in <placeName>New York</placeName>. <placeName>New York</placeName> was the center of the broadcasting world. That’s where you wanted to go. Everybody’s reading the—you know, the job section of <orgName>Broadcasting</orgName> magazine. How can I get to <placeName>New York</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So one thing I’ve been interested in, especially given your kind of deep knowledge of why people make certain—certain programming decisions, decisions in kind of broadcasting—the depiction of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in the media, in television and films, in other kinds of broadcast media—do you have any thoughts on that, given both your kind of extensive experience in broadcasting and your experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah. This is—this is something that Professor <persName>Miller</persName> and I had long discussion about [chuckles] during our tour, and he and I don’t entirely agree on this, I don’t think, although you could ask him his opinion. His—his premise—I think I’m being honest—fair about it—is that it wasn’t the media that lost <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> for us, that the media was actually quite balanced in its reporting. There were as many favorable stories as there were unfavorable stories about it. Even after Tet. And the majority of the stories were—were balanced.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Hello? I seem to—sorry.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yes?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry. One <orgName>sec</orgName>. I lost you for a second there. You said—you said, “Even after Tet,” and then the call cut out for a second.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Okay. Even after Tet, the reporting—if you analyze the stories, it was pretty balanced, okay? And there have been studies of that, that is the case.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[No audible response.]</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Can you hear me?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yep, yep.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Okay. And there’s a book written about that—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, yeah. I can hear you great. It is—am I not coming—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No, you’re fine. You’re fine. I just want to be sure.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I had one specific question about a movie.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Good Morning, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, which depicted something which, with—you’re—you know—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—involved in. What did you think of that film?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Well, it was a comedy film, of course. Dark comedy, but it was a comedy film. And—and not only was I on the radio at that same radio station [chuckles], but the real person on whom Good Morning, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was based—what was his name? I’ll think of it in a minute. [<orgName>Armed Forces Radio DJ</orgName>] <persName>Adrian Cronauer</persName>, I think it was. I think that’s right. Was there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS"><persName>Al McKee</persName>, my friend who got me the shift there, did and knew him and says that he—it was an exaggerated portrait of—of him. He was kind of a wild guy but not that wild, but that’s only second hand. I don’t know him personally. But in terms of a movie that was kind of riffing on <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, as I remember it, that’s fine. I wasn’t offended by it or anything like that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It was just our class.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—was it other classes?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">It’s unusual. It was—the idea came from, among other people, our class secretary, [<persName>Philip C.]</persName> “<persName>Phil” Schaefer [Class</persName> of <date>1964</date>], and his idea was actually Class of ’64 veterans, just that narrow group. And most of us on that trip were—there’s only 22 of us on the tour—were—we were all Class of ’64, and most of us were veterans who had been in the service during the war, not all in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> but in the service at that time. And wives.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I guess I have two questions—</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I just want to mention that of all these veterans, some were not in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>; they were in other theaters, countries during the war. There was I think only one who was act- —on our tour who was actually in combat in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So it was very enlightening to be with someone my own age, my own class, who had literally been on the front lines there at one of the major battles, of Khe Sanh.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">No. I think we—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—kind of beyond that.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">I mean, he knows a lot more about the—the details of the—of the political ins and outs of—but—but—the general—as I say, I kind of studied this back in <date>the ’60s</date>, and I’ve tried to learn more about it, especially after I got out of the service. So—and he’s—he’s very reasoned, and he’s very reasonable. He’s easy to talk to. And in terms of the French occupation in <persName>Dien Bien Phu</persName> and the <persName>Diệm</persName> regime, I—I—I think we’re in agreement. He knows more about it, but I don’t see anything that I would disagree with him on there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Wait, sorry, one <orgName>sec</orgName>. I just want to make sure this is recording, a little bit of a recording difficulty. Can you say something?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Testing one, two, three, four?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Pause.] Huh. Cool. Thank you. It appears that there’s a bit of a delay on both ends, so I apologize for that, but this is the—I guess the last question. So going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I mean, what was that like emotionally for you? Did you see it in a different way?</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Yes, yes, I discovered a part of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—I thought I knew the country pretty well, certainly the <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> part, from all those travels that I was on when I was there, but I realized in going back that there’s a lot more to that country that I was not able to see then: the cultural and the historic <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in particular. So, whereas in <date>1965</date> or ’66 I drove by <orgName>the Imperial Citadel</orgName> in <placeName>Hué</placeName>, this time we spent <date>a day</date> there, walking through it and so forth, which, again, you couldn’t really do as a soldier in a war zone, cause you’d be a target.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well, thank you.</u>
      <u who="BROOKS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I’m going to stop the recording.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
