<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="MARKOWITZ"/>
        <person xml:id="BROSS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So this is <persName>Hannah Markowitz</persName> in <orgName>Rauner</orgName> [<orgName>Special Collections] Library</orgName> on <orgName>Dartmouth College’s</orgName> campus. On the phone with me <date>today</date> is [Dr. <persName>Donald C.</persName>] “<persName>Don” Bross</persName> in <placeName>Boulder</placeName>, <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, and it’s <date>January 26th, 2017</date>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I came to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> from <placeName>Denver</placeName> along with 14 others. We had quite a contingent <date>that year, 1960</date>. I was born in <placeName>Oklahoma City</placeName>. My mother was one of eight children. My father had only one brother. He was <date>ten years</date> older than she. My mother was the first of the eight children to go to college. She was, like, number five. And that, of course, was the [Great] Depression, when we were just getting out—they were just getting out of the <name type="event">Depression</name> in <date>the thirties</date>. So my mother was born in <date>1920</date>; my father, in <date>1910</date>. And I always told my mother that the best thing she had done was to get me and her to <placeName>Colorado</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But my grandmothers stepped in, and I can tell stories about them, but it’s not probably relevant except for some insight about I think certain things that were valuable to me many, <date>many years later</date>, trying to understand how people grow up and how they’re cared for and what kind of qualities that derive from that care. I think it’s very useful to have these—to have that experience of having those wonderful women care for me.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">What brought you and your mom to <placeName>Denver</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, she was getting away basically from—from the—from <placeName>Oklahoma</placeName>. And we had—my older <persName>Aunt Edith</persName>—I was named after her husband; they never had children—he was <persName>Don</persName>. He was a sweetheart of a guy, an insurance adjuster. And they lived reasonably well for the—for <date>the thirties</date>, especially in <date>the forties</date>, because he was <orgName>the General Adjustment Bureau</orgName> manager for all of western <placeName>Oklahoma</placeName>. So if you’re an insurance adjuster, there’s a lot of tornadoes and floods [chuckles] and disasters, and he was a very cool guy: gruff on the exterior and just the sweetest guy underneath. And I was fortunate to have him as a mentor, along with a couple of my mother’s brothers. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, definitely.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—from within. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The only way they survived was they ran the cruiser aground, and I had—there’s pictures that I’ve seen online. Just in <date>the last year</date> or two, I started thinking, I wonder if they had pictures. And there’s pictures of these coconut logs that were put up in the bulkheads to keep—to allow the ship to go to sea again. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so they refitted her with a new bow, which was waiting for them, and they weld that up, and off they go again. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So imagine in <date>six,</date> <date>seven months</date> how much that is. But also in your mind’s eye, think about what it means to have work-capable military forces that can move around the planet with such massive energy and logistics in such a short period of time, and that was <date>over a half century ago</date>. And if you ever read [<persName>Alfred T.]</persName> Mahan’s <orgName>Sea Power</orgName> [sic; The Influence of Sea Power Upon History: 1660–1783] and you start looking at <date>the last 500 years</date> of—of human history and parts of why <placeName>Britannia</placeName> ruled the waves and what was such a crucial part of not only <name type="event">the Industrial Revolution</name> but—but the influence of <placeName>Britain</placeName> across the world—they didn’t have standing armies, but they had a very extraordinary naval tradition,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—great diplomacy and great commercial sector.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so—so think about that, and think about this cruiser going around at the very beginning of the war, when we were clearly outmanned, and caught wrong-footed. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so—so <persName>Jim</persName> finished up. He would actually be at Bikini [Atoll in <placeName>the Marshall Islands</placeName>], get irradiated and eventually would die as an atomic veteran but not until <date>many years later</date>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">He became a—he worked for a major swimming pool company, became their top contract guy, and he retired after spending over <date>20 years</date> as the chief engineer for <orgName>St. Mary-Corwin Hospital</orgName> [now <orgName>St. Mary-Corwin Medical Center</orgName>] in <placeName>Pueblo</placeName>, <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, where he moved his family—boy and a girl—to <placeName>Colorado</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And the executive officer, who was probably a lieutenant commander and very experienced and, after all, an officer, and <persName>Jim</persName> was just an enlisted man, said, “Who do you think you are?”” [Both chuckle.] So these engineers [Laughs] —how long it’s gonna take. He said, “Well, sir, that’s my opinion.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And, of course, it did. He cooked for <date>two days</date>. But the <orgName>XO</orgName> kind of kept his eye on <persName>Jim</persName> ever after.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">There are little stories of the cat-and-mouse game, how he would try to read <persName>Jim</persName>’s mail. And <persName>Jim</persName> got one of these typical senators who wrote their constituents when elections were coming up, and so he gets something, and the <orgName>XO</orgName> finds out because he has the postal clerk kind of keeping an eye on mail for this rebellious guy [both chuckle], and this made him back off because he wasn’t sure but what <persName>Jim</persName> knew the senator [chuckles], and <persName>Jim</persName> wasn’t about to let anybody know.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">He says, “I’ll do that.” [Laughter.] So <persName>Jim</persName> always stood watch on the evaporators. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">He was also a guy that later on, when I heard that there had been some reunions of the <orgName>Mini</orgName>, as she was called, that somebody would come up and say, “That’s the guy! That’s him! That’s the guy I was telling you about!” [Both chuckle.] Because he was such a funny—he was also extraordinarily good looking and in a very charming, kind of boyish way. And so he always, I’m sure, had a very good time [chuckles] whenever he had leave. Married a very extraordinary—his wife, <persName>Mary</persName>, is still alive. She’s in <date>her 90s</date>. Very beautiful woman. Beautiful kids.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so <persName>Jim</persName> just said—he says, “We’re really proud of you, <persName>Don</persName>, you know, to—to be—have gone through the NROTC [Naval Reserve Officers’ <orgName>Training Corps</orgName>] program and now you’re an officer.” He said, “Do you remember that movie, Mister <persName>Roberts</persName>? Have you ever heard of that, <persName>Hannah</persName>?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">No, I haven’t.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, [actor <persName>John U.</persName>] “<persName>Jack” Lemmon [III</persName>] and—oh, a famous—famous actor, whose name is escaping me. And he was Mister <persName>Roberts</persName>. And Mister <persName>Roberts</persName>—they were on this backwater supply ship in—in <name type="event">World War II</name>. That’s the setting. And there’s this kind of [fictional character,] Captain [<persName>Philip</persName>] <persName>Queeg</persName>, crazy captain. And there’s a palm tree that he had the crew water, and a bunch of other stuff. And <persName>Lemmon</persName> was kind of inept and this, that and the other. But [fictional character <persName>Doug] Roberts</persName> was an excellent individual person as a person. He wanted to get into the war because he felt that was he is duty and that he really wasn’t fulfilling the responsibility he could as the XO of this little steamer, you know?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So there’s tension between him kind of standing up for the crew and—against some of the silliness that really was unjustified. Made—it made him this kind of icon of—of—of a lot of people who looked at both enlisted and an officer behavior in the military. And anyway, it’s a very funny movie. If you ever get a chance, I think you’ll appreciate it.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah, I’ll check it out.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But <persName>Jim—Jim</persName> said, “Well, I’m glad you remember us to <persName>Roberts</persName> because if we ever find out that you acted any differently, I’m gonna come talk to you.” [Laughter.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So when I got on my first ship, the old—that tanker, the old <name type="event">World War II</name> tanker, I made sure that—the—the—the note that the captain sent to my mother was one thing. I didn’t worry about that. But I made sure, in a letter I wrote her, that she knew that the chiefs had invited me into the chief’s quarters to have a cup of coffee [laughs] <date>some months</date> after I got on this tanker, and I wanted to make sure that that word got back to <persName>Jim</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.] It sounds like the <orgName>Navy</orgName> and these stories from <persName>Jim</persName> played a pretty big role in your childhood, growing up. And you also mentioned that as [the son of] a single mother, scholarship was pretty important in looking at colleges.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So could you talk a little bit more about <orgName>NROTC</orgName> and how—sort of how you got to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and how you got involved with <orgName>NROTC</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, it’s a good—it’s good you wanted that background because then it makes the story easier now. So I was—I really—I was fortunate, and—and—and I was bright, and I was somewhat athletic and a bunch of other things, but I went to, like, —I think I went to almost a dozen schools before I graduated from high school. A lot of schools.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, my mother was married and divorced two more times before I got out of high school. She was a modern woman, in so many respects. She was so far ahead of her time. She was so beautiful that no guy could—almost no guys—there was a congressman for a while—he was a delightful guy, and he wanted to marry her, but she said, “I’m a little bit old. You need to have a young wife and have kids.” And it turned out to be the case.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I just—that’s why I could probably never be a pacifist. But my mother was very—she—she [chuckles]—not only did I babysit the children of doctors at <orgName>National Jewish [Health</orgName>] and—and <orgName>Christian Scientists</orgName>’ families and every other kind of Protestant denomination available—my mother knew about gay couples when nobody knew what a gay was.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And we had a wonderful African-American couple, <persName>Susan</persName> and <persName>Willard Bell</persName>, who she paid to, you know, iron clothes and things like that, and <persName>Willard</persName> to do little repairs around our apartment and things like that. They were lovely people. My mother was just totally open to human beings and cared about them. And I couldn’t help but be the same way.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I would finish—I took six majors, and I enrolled in [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Army ROTC [Reserve Officers’ Training Corps], so I was in <date>three years</date> of <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC while I was doing my other five academic majors.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Already in high school you were involved in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, because—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—I knew about—I knew that you could get to [<orgName>the U.S. Military Academy</orgName> at] West Point or to the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Air Force Academy</orgName>, which was just coming up in <placeName>Colorado</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Or to <orgName>the Naval Academy</orgName>, and you get a free education. So I thought, I better, you know, increase my chances. If I—this is the best way for me to get a scholarship, then I could do that. And—so then after school, I would get on my bicycle and go Tiffin Inn, which was a restaurant, and I was a busboy, and I worked there 25 hours a week. And even though it was minimum wage, it was enough over <date>a year</date> to get a little <orgName>Ford</orgName> coupe [both chuckle] for $200. And so my <date>last year</date>, I could drive.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And he was very demanding. That’s another story. Very interesting guy. And he called me in to say that my work in English [chuckles]—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—wasn’t re- —you know, a reflection of [chuckles] my scores on the tests. [Both chuckle.] But I did take, you know, <orgName>Advanced Placement</orgName> chemistry, and I was taking calculus—introductory calculus and all the—everything that they could throw, I was taking. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But we all turned out all right. And so—the other was <persName>Jeffrey Robinson</persName>, and <persName>Jeff</persName> was number one on the tennis team when I, as a last-minute, thought, I better do something athletically and ended up getting into a doubles team with a guy named <persName>Dave Magnuson</persName> [archivist note: spelling uncertain], who was raised by grandparents. I never heard the whole story, but <persName>Dave</persName> was just a really cool guy.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I couldn't say it quickly. I said, “Well, yeah, sure.” [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Can’t turn that offer down.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">No. So being <orgName>ROTC</orgName> was the worst thing in the world because you had these <name type="event">World War II</name>, itchy, greenish uniforms, and the next worst thing to be would be a nerd, and I was clearly running around with [chuckles; unintelligible] a bunch of other guys. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And, of course, he knew I didn’t. [Laughs.] Because he was very good. So it was all these activities, and doing the work as I said. And then all of a sudden, things kind of, like, mushroomed. And so I was elected to [<orgName>American Legion]</orgName> Boys State, I was elected to be president of <orgName>the Interclub Council</orgName>, and I was elected to be a cheerleader. And I’m still in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, and eventually I became second or third officer in that group.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">How—how had you heard about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, I had a high school counselor, but I mostly went and read about colleges.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, that’s—you know, that’s a great question you asked me. I forgot. There was this honorary high school frater- —service fraternity that was, quote, “religious,” but it wasn’t. It was ecumenical. But an insurance man had—you know, you’re going to think this is quite funny—in <date>the 1950s</date>, a good part of American adult society was pretty convinced that the younger generation was going to hell in a hand basket. As evidence of that, they could point to <persName>ducktails</persName> and <persName>Elvis</persName> [<persName>A.] Presley</persName> wiggling his hips and West Side Story, with the <orgName>Jets</orgName> and the Sharks [fictional gangs] fighting each other over a girl, and just one thing after another.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="BROSS">Just a great introduction, you know, to my first trip out of the—you know, the country.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> had offered me both a civilian scholarship and the <orgName>NROTC</orgName>. And <orgName>NROTC</orgName> allowed you to have choices between becoming a regular naval officer and be interleavened with <orgName>the Naval Academy</orgName> graduates, or go eventually into the <orgName>Reserves</orgName>, which is unique, and I think a very—very good idea that has fallen by the wayside.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so that pulled me in because it gave me choice. And only later, when I was in Kal[man H.] <persName>Silvert</persName> political science courses, he made this comment about, “Always make choices that give you more choices.” Then I realized that’s why I did it. But it also connected with the fact that I had seen some <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> graduates at <orgName>the Tau Sigma</orgName> [<orgName>National Honor Society</orgName>] meetings in high school, and they seemed like regular guys, and they seemed like, you know—they—they were capable and people you wouldn’t mind trying to learn from. And they’d gone to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—I—I—oh, I forgot. <orgName>The air academy</orgName>—I think I mentioned I had an appointment from a Republican senator. I went down to thank him <date>a couple of years later</date>, and he was very upset that I didn’t take it, and he asked me why I didn’t. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">For <orgName>the Air Force Academy</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">Because I would have been in the third class to graduate.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Anyway, so that’s a bit off—so—so this was useful, <persName>Hannah</persName>, in trying to understand why I believe in mixing things up in a way that people get different exposures. And right now it’s a good point to make. So I think I’ve been unusual in having the experience of being in <orgName>Army</orgName>, having great interest in aviation and then ending up in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, where the integration of all these armed forces branches, to me, was not—it wasn’t that you didn’t need to have identity, as <orgName>esprit de corps</orgName>, but it’s also necessary to understand comprehensively—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—what the services are about. And—that’s probably more than you needed to know. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">No, that was all—that was great.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So there I am.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—coming to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> from your upbringing in <placeName>Colorado</placeName>—you mentioned that your mom—that your mother was sort of very ahead of—ahead of her time. What was it like coming to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>? What was the culture like at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> when you got here?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Chuckles.] It was—well, for me it was a space shot. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The Congressman from <placeName>Wyoming</placeName>. <persName>Teno Roncalio</persName>, who was, by the way, the man who stood up and gave [<persName>John F.] Kennedy</persName> as the nomination—he was the—the <placeName>Wyoming</placeName> delegation was the ones that put <persName>Kennedy</persName> over the top, and that turned out to be important when I got assigned to the <persName>Kennedy</persName> <orgName>White House</orgName> as his helicopter was taking off when <persName>Fred</persName> [H.] Eidlin [Class of 2964] had his “Meet the Ambassador” program, and I carried his tape recorder <date>that spring of 1962</date>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So it took him <date>ten years</date>. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">That’s a lot of school.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">He was an incredible—oh, it’s a lot of money for—at that time, the ’20s. He was a marvelous person to go on a nature walk with. He could see bi- —he lived to his <date>’90s</date>. He was going out and doing voluntary work in the <placeName>Himalayas</placeName> in his ‘90s, as a physician. And he had a pharmacist by the name of <persName>Joe Morgan</persName>, and they had offices on opposite sides of—of the corner of Downing [Street] and Evans [Avenue] in <placeName>south Denver</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">That was brilliant.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">That was just the best.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But from that point on, my grades continued to go up, and eventually I ended up with high distinction in my majorette. But it was initially a shock. And—but here’s what <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was like: First of all, I may have mentioned earlier, I thought it was a bit of a monastery in <placeName>the North Woods</placeName>, very isolated, no women, and I thought that was—I increasingly thought that was a great tragedy [both chuckle] when you had to go <date>three and a half hours</date> over frost heaves to get to <placeName>Boston</placeName>, where there was life, or go to <placeName>Montreal</placeName>, the other way.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—at the 195 pounds at this time. But that changed me permanently. And—and I actually noticed this lieutenant who was really worried about me, and I happened to be the only guy who was playing anything like that at the time, and I threw this ball, and we got a touchdown, and I looked over, and the guy was looking at me. [Chuckles.] It was the first time, I think, he decided that the <orgName>Navy</orgName> should keep me. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">They would hit the deck, and the whole ship would shudder, and I looked at these guys as the arresting gear would get them, and their heads would be snapping forward. And this whole big—this sky—it’s not a very big plane, but you could just see the weight of this thing, you know, pulling everything forward and I thought, Boy, if his hook doesn’t catch, he’s—you know, he’s going to be in trouble. And that’s why of course they had full throttle when they came in, so they could shoot out the other side if they didn’t catch.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And meanwhile, down below, where the catapults are—those things are, like, standing two feet away from a locomotive that goes from zero miles an hour to 136—150 miles an hour just like that. The noise, the pressure, the—I thought, Hmm, there is a reason why these guys are paying twice the insurance premium—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—as other naval officers. And—and the training officer who gave us our last lecture was a chain smoker, and in these 30 minutes, as he was convincing us to become naval aviators, he completely filled his ashtray up and warned us about not doing things stupid and doing night aerobatics <date>the day</date> we get our wings and buy the farm perpendicularly by, you know, going into the deck because you get disoriented.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And you better really think about it. And so with that in mind, I went on my first cruise. It was a destroyer out of <placeName>Boston</placeName>. My <date>next-year’s</date> roommate was there, and I stayed with his family. And we went up to <placeName>Canada</placeName>, and it’s the introduction, the beginning of why the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, of all the services, I think, is unique, and it’s how quickly you become aware of a much wider world. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">There were things like that that are really not mentioned very often, but they—they do happen. And being on a radar scope as we went up through the Saint Lawrence Seaway and learning a lot about—you know, beginning to understand how much was involved in living on this little microcosm of a ship and be self-sustaining and literally depending all the time on each other.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You wouldn’t know <persName>Lou</persName>, but <persName>Lou</persName> retired as the dean of <orgName>the School of Foreign Service</orgName> at <orgName>American University</orgName> [sic; <orgName>American University’s School of International Service</orgName>] <date>about three years ago</date>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">He was invited to be the new dean in <placeName>Singapore</placeName> and then one of the former Russian republics, and, you know, he’s just an incredibly bright guy. He—<persName>Lou</persName> knew everybody by name and face when he arrived at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>1960</date>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Huh! That’s pretty impressive.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And would say hello to them! [Laughs.] Not surprisingly, he was elected to the <placeName>Palaeopitus</placeName> [Senior Society] and some other things eventually. But he and I were in the weeds. We eventually become the co-presidentes of <placeName>the Circulo Español</placeName>. And I won’t go any further to tell you about all the funny things we did.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—through that trip. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right, right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But at the same time, as a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> student—the average student is not going to have the experiences I had of going out in the real guys’ world of making a destroyer engine room work or navigating or doing anti-submarine warfare, understanding the sonar and doing gunnery practice, and doing the complexities of the manual labor as well as the skill, all of these things that are part of modern human life. And it was a lot going on. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But it was mutually agreed that he probably wasn’t fit for naval aviation. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Either way.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.] And so here’s what’s interesting, though, is as soon as that <date>summer</date> was over, I had to get myself to <placeName>Peru</placeName>. And so I—[Walter] “<persName>Walt” Smith</persName> was from <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, and his family was up here getting him, and he agreed to take my suitcase to <placeName>New York City</placeName>. Unfortunately, somebody broke in and stole all my clothes [both chuckle], so had to get clothes and get on a plane. I had hops, lady hops that got me to <placeName>Florida</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">This is in <date>1962</date>, or—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It’s a very interesting time. I had not only a wonderful Romance language professor, [<persName>Robert H.] “Bob” Russell</persName>, but <persName>Frank</persName> [R.] <orgName>Safford</orgName> had come to the campus as a Latin American history professor. And <persName>Kal Silvert</persName>—we learned about <persName>Kal Silvert</persName>. We heard rumors that this very outstanding Latin American scholar was coming to campus. <persName>Lou</persName> found out about it and he had shared it with me, or I found out about it and I shared it with him. But somehow <persName>Kal</persName> arrived in time, because I was, you know, not immediately going in—we only had <date>six weeks</date> of training that <date>summer</date>. I think I probably stayed in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS"><persName>Hannah</persName>, I think I went over just to introduce myself and told him that I wondered if I might write him when I was in <placeName>Peru</placeName>, and I said, “Because I’m not sure what kind of a project I should do for my political science credits.” </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And he was wonderful. He—he just said, “Listen, just stay off of balconies [laughs] when they’re having street demonstrations and things.” And I looked, and he had this scar on his left cheek that he got when he was diving under a car in <placeName>Buenos Aires</placeName> [<placeName>Argentina</placeName>] during a riot. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And you’ve read my essay?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, I did. It was—I definitely got the sense that he was—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Influential.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—an impressive mentor and very influential, as you stated in the essay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Did it the warmth come through?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes, definitely. And all the—all the letters that you quoted from him, especially.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah. So there I was on my moon shot, my—my second moon shot in <date>as many years</date>. Well, not quite. Yeah, in <date>as many years</date>, <date>two years</date>. So the first moon shot was <placeName>Hanover</placeName> [chuckles], and the next one is, What in the world?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It was a very poig- —yeah, a very poignant, a very—somewhat illuminating story of the use of—of pharmaceutical companies doing human subject research in <placeName>Africa</placeName>. And I was just—I—I was exposed to this in <date>1962</date> because a very good friend of <persName>Javier</persName>’s gave a ride up to <placeName>Trujillo</placeName> [<placeName>Peru</placeName>], and he was basically dumping pharmaceuticals out of <placeName>Europe</placeName> and <placeName>Latin America</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I took one of them. Got deathly ill. [Chuckles.] Decided I’d rather have the diarrhea. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Chuckles.] I mean, anyway, there was just all—there was so much going on. You know, my first exposure to cocaine was to have <persName>Javier</persName> pointing out to me how people would have—like, people who chew tobacco had these little poufy, you know, little cuds or whatever they have? Wads that they put in their cheeks?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And what was going on is they’d take raw coca leaves and put a little piece of catalyst, I think in the form of limestone, in there, and they would suck at it <date>all day</date>, and as he pointed out to me, it would—it was a stimulant, but it also anesthetized your alimentary system so you didn’t get hungry. But it created hollow people. I mean, I won’t go any further. I’m just saying that would not be your typical military exposure.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right, right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I see—you know, see through his binocular vision of both language—and, again, I’ve got this physician, who I find enormously impressive in terms of how he saw the complexity of his—his—his people and his population and his patients. And I saw people with things like—either had elephantitis [sic; elephantiasis] or possibly leprosy. I mean, I saw things I never imagined existed. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And the point is that when you say “underdeveloped,” we don't know what these words mean unless we actually experience what it means. So when people talk about turismo [tourism] or turista [tourist], it’s like only tourists get gastrointestinal infections. No, it’s endemic, not epidemic. Everybody has it almost all the time. The food is often adulterated. People don’t have immunizations.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.] And I was in a pensión [a boarding house], and twenty dollars a month, room and board. And they were from the rural areas and the urban areas, and they were always kidding me and trying to trick me and—but also trying to be friendly. I mean, it’s just all that mix.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah, yeah, <persName>mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, the way you got a shower is you had a—a reservoir for a toilet, with one of those little dippers. The water is quite cold there on the coast, and you would go in right before you were going to get a shower. You flip a switch, and when you thought it was sufficiently warm by that dipper, that you could get enough warm water [chuckles], you went and got your shower. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah, get out as fast as possible.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So, again, this interplay between these different exposures. And so I write—and you know the story: I write Kal, and he writes this marvelous thing back.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I end up writing this thing, and, of course, the Cuban Missile Crisis happens, and I reported in at the <orgName>Embassy</orgName>. What I did not say, and I know we record, so I’ll be a little thoughtful about this. I was approached by someone at the Embassy, a good, nice man, and he asked me what was going on in <placeName>Peru</placeName>. [Chuckles.] And he asked me such naïve questions, honestly, that I found it shocking.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And they were talking about the fact that people didn’t have places where they could urinate or defecate, and so people would have to go off to the side and do it. And they said, “That’s why they’re shameless.” Well, the poverty was extraordinary. The average income, national income was $127 a year at the time. Think about being in the military and going into an emerging economy without that experience.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But that—that’s just the beginning. <persName>Hannah</persName>, did you happen—I know you had lots on your plate—did you ever happen to find <placeName>La Violencia en Colombia</placeName> in the library?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I looked—I looked it up in the catalog, and it looks like they’ve—they have a sort of storage area where they keep a lot of the—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Special Collection books. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah. Not the Special Collections, but it’s, like, —I’m not sure what the name of it is exactly. But I saw that it was there. I didn’t have time to order it and get it brought back—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">That’s alright.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—and brought back to campus, but I saw that it was tucked away in the library somewhere.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I will just tell you some stuff there. It’s all in Spanish. Let me tell you about some of the pictures. There are pictures of men, women and children, all headless, laid out side by side like fish that were caught in a stream.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It’s horrific. So I go back—I go back, and it was <date>a full year</date> going to <persName>Kal</persName>’s courses, trying to make sense of things, continuing my Spanish. It was a better time to be back at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, <persName>Hannah</persName>. I—I no longer wanted to get away from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. I—I just thought, Boy, I’m not so sure. You know, I miss civilization, in a way. But by the time I got back, I realized I hadn’t had much time—<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> had let me go, if that makes sense.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And it was very rewarding. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I—I no longer felt as if I was just thinking these abstract kinds of thoughts. I actually had some grounding in the real world. And I got into <orgName>Ledyard Canoe Club</orgName> and had a great time with that both as a junior and a senior, and competed in the first invitational whitewater thing and eventually went down the <placeName>Connecticut</placeName> [River]. And all these things were just easier for me to do because I was no longer feeling like I wasn’t going to survive there or that I wasn’t going to—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—you know, do the things—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Right. And we knew about <persName>Hugo Blanco</persName>, the guy who created the Sendero Luminoso, which is the Shining Path guerilla movement. <persName>Lou</persName> had some thoughts about going to interview him [laughs], which we discussed at length, and I was able to convince <persName>Lou</persName> that I didn’t think this was good.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah. Did you draw the line there?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.] So here it is. Now I’m going to <placeName>Colombia</placeName>, and now $15 a day per diem, uniforms, receptions, dances, and flying around in our own private—what we call here a private aviation, commercial aviation planes, like the Aero Commander, which is a plane you could take one inch and feather the prop and still keep going. [Chuckles.] And flew thousands of miles—you know, 105 hours in the air is a long time anyplace.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So when the <persName>Llanos</persName>—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So your—sorry. Your trip to <placeName>Colombia</placeName> was—that was through the <orgName>Navy</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">All the military.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><orgName>I’m</orgName> now in <persName>Kennedy</persName>’s People to People [Student Ambassador Program], Persona a Persona—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right, yes. You did mention that in the essay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><orgName>Alianza para el Progreso</orgName>—yes, the <orgName>Alliance</orgName> for—<orgName>the Alliance for Progress in Latin America</orgName>. And I haven’t touched on his assassination and things like that. That’s going to happen that fall, when I returned. So that program still was in existence.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">It was—it was created by President <persName>Kennedy</persName>—</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><persName>Kennedy</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—at the time?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes, and it went away after he was gone.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><orgName>The Alliance for Progress</orgName>. And it was <orgName>the Peace Corps</orgName>—there were so many useful things, in my view, that he did [that] moved us away from “everything is thermonuclear war or nothing.” And so when people criticize the military, I think, Yeah, but how profoundly do you understand human nature and human history when you say that this is—this was a terrible thing? There’s a lot of terrible things. How do we manage the terrible things? And how do we manage ourselves?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">History in medicine is you take a history as part of your diagnostic workup, and it’s the personal history of that individual that was presenting symptoms and so forth. So history—there’s all kinds of words of art, and it takes a while to know what language you’re speaking, right?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But it was true there as well. And [chuckles]—I will just mention a funny thing: So this one flight we took to the Rio Putumayo. Was it that one, or was it <orgName>Amazon</orgName> [River]? I think it was—I think it was that—yeah, it was that one. They—we—we almost got into the trees when we landed in the first airport in a rural area of <placeName>Colombia</placeName>. It turned out that the copilot was in training.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh!</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So—[Laughs.]  So I heard this—people talking about this as we got off the plane to stretch before we got onto the next flight. We went through this scene, very scary, where the bottom drops out of this [<persName>Douglas</persName>] DC-3, and you correct, and you pick it up and you’re kind of “Rrrr, <persName>rrrr</persName>, <persName>rrrr</persName>, <persName>rrrr</persName>,” and then all of a sudden, the bottom drops out again. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Same guy, still in training. [Laughs.] And so—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I’m surprised you got back on the plane. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.] Yeah, this was like it’s something. And the last time, I—I—I became aware—it was a long time, as it turns out, to get down to the Ecuadorian border. No roads there and very long way up the <orgName>Amazon</orgName>. And it was very quiet in the plane. And I suddenly realized how quiet it was. Nobody was talking. And I looked out to the right, and there was triple canopy jungle right below—at least it seemed pretty close—feathered props. I will say it was close enough that I could see flocks of parrots flying in between the trees. And I heard people saying their rosaries. Very fast. Lots of them, clicking of the beads.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">If you survive the crash? [Laughs.] And all of a sudden there’s this enormous roar. Smoke starts pouring out of the engine that I’m looking at, and the whole plane tips over onto the right wing and then tips back over onto the left wing, and we swing around and burst into this opening of a little tiny jungle airport. [Both chuckle.] </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So we land—and landed. There was just this one little tiny tower with all the glass broken out. And the first men off—it was almost all men. They get off the plane. There was a few women. But the men all got down and kissed the pavement. [Both chuckle.] So the reason I’m telling you a little about this is we had a reception by the commanding officer, probably a captain in the <orgName>Army</orgName>. He had this strikingly beautiful wife, and we were all in this formal dining room. And he had this very fierce look about him [chuckles]. I don’t want to look at his wife. And then we start hearing this story about how these guys in these canoes were killed and that they had stopped this guerrilla movement.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Did you have intelligence? And I thought to myself, God, I hope they don’t look at his wife. [Both chuckle.] I mean, it was just—you know, remember, if you see that book and you see the savagery on both sides, and this—this terrible—if you had a house painted red, the people who were on the blue side might shoot you for that. Same thing from the other color.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">And it—yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—all through the country, right? I don’t think—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">It seems like this exposure definitely made you more critical and aware of things you would be doing later in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, especially?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I think, <persName>Hannah</persName>, more aware. I don’t think I’ve ever set out to be a critical person. I still believe, and I’ve always believed, that as much as possible, we should have things that speak for themselves.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But I think sometimes things become so overwhelmingly obvious that you get into the question of, well, why does it seem so obvious to me or to another person but not obvious to others? And that leads us into examinations of human psychology.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">And it’s important stuff.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So <date>1963</date> was this—this People to People program that you went on—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—through the Ar- —through the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, and then ’64 is when you graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, correct?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah. And I’ll tell you a little memory about that.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, please.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Since my name comes first in the alphabet, I was the one that had to say “Attention” as we got commissioned and got sworn in. And resonating through my head at this time—and everybody else—I read a lot of the essays. Most people were not aware of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but I could not help—by the way, I don’t know if you knew that <persName>Lou</persName>—<persName>Lou Goodman</persName> and I wrote a letter to the editor of the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> paper, saying—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, yes, I actually did—I actually did come across that in the—in <orgName>Rauner Library</orgName>. They have all the old issues—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—of The <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> catalogued—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Extraordinary.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—very well. Yeah, so I actually did get a chance—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You’re a very good researcher.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—to read that. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">What did you think?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">It was fascinating.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">This is the one about <placeName>Panama</placeName>, correct?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah!</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And of course I had traveled through there on—on, of all things, a Colombian oiler, fully aware of the irony of an American naval midshipman (that’s redundant)—a midshipmen, a cadet de la [unintelligible], —</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—going through as a guest of the Colombian government on one of their tankers. A little foreshadowing there, in a couple of ways. I just was very aware of that and going to <placeName>Cartagena</placeName> [<placeName>Colombia</placeName>].</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.] So going—by, yeah, I was really happy I came across that article, actually, in The <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and just the idea of the—sort of the individual versus the responsibility to the larger state or country, I thought was very interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">But—go on.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So I’m sitting there, or standing there, and in my mind was this phrase: “Santiago y a <orgName>ellos</orgName>.” That’s Spanish, and it’s right out of this [El] Cid Campeador, and it’s the beginning of the Spanish attempt to throw the Muslims out of <placeName>Spain</placeName>. And it was their war cry. Translated roughly, it’s “To Saint Peter and at them,” “in the name of <persName>Saint Peter</persName>, let’s get them.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I had this—it’s almost like I smelled incense. And I think it was my sense of concern and dread that we were getting ourselves into something that we didn’t know what we were up to. I know that doesn’t seem—that probably looks an awful lot like retrospect, but I can tell you, that was a distinctive memory, and I can’t explain entirely all the things that I was aware of that were making me think that we might be getting into something. And this was before [the] Gulf of <placeName>Tonkin</placeName> [incident].</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right, right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But you do know I asked for a tanker. I didn’t ask for a cruiser. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Why in the world would anybody with aspirations go to the service? Well, it turned out to be a good choice.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, no, I—I just wanted to get back to the—to that story you were about to tell, about your commissioning and I guess what the premonition that was in your mind at that time.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So you—you ac- —you entered the <orgName>Navy</orgName> or received orders for—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">In <placeName>New York</placeName>, at—the <name type="event">World’s Fair</name> was there. I met <persName>Lou</persName>, and I must—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS"><persName>Lou</persName> must have been utterly shocked when I got on this decrepit old ship. I mean, it looked run down. It looked—they were just coming out of a yard period, but you wouldn't believe it to look at this thing. The wardroom had no furniture [chuckles] to speak of. It turned out that the—the executive officer had a temper and had done a lot of stuff that meant that they didn’t have furniture. But that’s another story.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">And this—what <date>year</date> is this in?</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><date>Nineteen sixty-four, June</date>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. Later—<date>same year</date>, <date>same year</date>. So where did—where did you go from there?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, so we went to the <placeName>Caribbean</placeName> [Sea], helped refuel for training exercises. And during <date>the summer</date>, I was sent to firefighting school because I was made liquid cargo officer, which meant I was responsible for the major reason why we were a tanker. Half of the weight of the ship is 85,000 barrels of <orgName>Navy</orgName> special fuel oil; 17,700 barrels of aviation gas, JP-5; and 7,300 barrels of aviation gasoline in two very special tanks with spark-proof pumps, with CO2 insulation around them.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">So that helped, to get that straightened around. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah, it seems like an—an interesting dynamic there.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah. And started—I don’t know how soon, but it was very soon I ended up as junior officer of the watch. So I had this very vast, double columns of everything the ship had to do to get under way, which was quite instructive. It taught me a lot about how do we learn things? By doing, is one of the best ways. There was everything from you have to have, a ship of that age, light off their boilers four hours minimum before you get under way; otherwise, you crack out all the fire bricks. And, you know, it just—they have to seal up. This is an engine that has to seal up. So you had four boilers, and you could get underway with maybe two boilers, but that doesn’t allow you to go flank. And all the way up to the ship’s whistle, and just—never mind. So that was going on.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But the most important thing, probably, was being sent to firefighting school because I was the damage control assistant, so [if] we had flooding or fire, I was the officer who was supposed to handle all of that, including all the training. I had no clue.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And they would have three or four of these compartments in sequence, and your task was to put that out. And the way you did it in <date>those days</date> was you had these two-and-a-half-inch hoses with about 175 pounds of pressure—oh, hang on. [Mutters to himself.] Maybe 200 pounds of pressure. And these things were so ready to brain because they had big, bronze heads on them where you could open and close them off. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And then behind us were two more guys, and they had a gooseneck, which was the name for this extended device that would go out in front of us that would spray cooling water, which was—I can tell you, it didn’t entirely do the task, but if it hadn’t have been for that, it would have been a much more difficult task. As it was, it was very demanding physically.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Chuckles.] You are the fire department.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">You figure it out. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, you better have figured it out before. You really—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—needed—otherwise, how would you not panic? You wouldn’t know where to start! You wouldn’t have the technique. You wouldn’t know which equipment to use. I—I—that was such an invaluable lesson—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—about what’s necessary to live in the world we live in and how much we take for granted.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And, again, this notion of society and culture and microcosms, which is what you have on a ship. So that was a very valuable experience, and that was <date>just the first summer</date>. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And we head over to <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and now—I remember once—I’m an ensign. There was a guy whose name was <persName>J. J. Reddington III</persName>, from [College of the] Holy Cross. He was as wiry—he looked a little bit like he was a fanatic, a mad guy.  He was one of the funniest guys. He was I think Irish, but I don’t know for sure. But he had—he had a tongue on him that would—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—that would—would cut through class. [Chuckles.] I mean, he was so funny!</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And <persName>Reddington</persName> knew it—and he was like the closest thing to the—the guy I told you about—my uncle said—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—[unintelligible]. The difference was <persName>Reddington</persName> was in your face. His wife, <persName>Fonda</persName>—it was <persName>Fonda</persName> that was—one of his best roles ever as an actor. He was Mister <persName>Roberts</persName>. But <persName>J. J.</persName> was much more in your face, especially with “the <orgName>Hog</orgName>.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well,—and what the chef called him, I won’t go into—I mean, I’m not going to give you his name, but his—the crew behind his back called him “the <orgName>Hog</orgName>.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, no!</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, he would invite them to talk about their sexual proclivities on the beach, and the captain had told me he couldn’t be on the bridge. He was not the paragon of a military officer. Right?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So there were little things going on in this little microcosm, including I end up with several African-American guys. I was perfectly happy to have them. They were competent. They hung one of my guys, you know, in one of the pump rooms, in effigy.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I know.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Was—were there a lot of racial tensions in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> at that time?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">There weren’t visibly lots, and I think as <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> came on and people started having to go to war together, there was less. But we are a society that has continued to deal with difference and struggled and succeeded and not succeeded, and failed. And you and I are living in this age, and we still deal with these issues. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And most of it, I think, on a <date>daily</date> basis didn’t interfere—but for the individuals discriminated against, it was a horrific thing. And it shouldn’t have happened.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So—so <persName>Reddington</persName> and I are up on watch one night. [Chuckles.] We had been refueling for, like, 30 hours. We were up high in the—you know, out of the water. But we were in the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>, probably not far from <placeName>Gibraltar</placeName>. And that’s an intensely congested area of sea lanes. You’ve got close separation between <placeName>North Africa</placeName>—from <placeName>Africa</placeName>, the northern coast—<placeName>Morocco</placeName> and so forth—and the tip of <placeName>Spain</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—drank a lot of coffee and saying, Holy smokes!  You know, I am making $200 a month, from which they’re extracting money for my food and my uniforms. Boy, I’m getting paid about 22 cents an hour, and they’re relying on us to not run into somebody.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.] Seems like a higher-paying job.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.] I mean, it’s certainly—it’s certainly tuition. It’s certainly an education.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">That’s true.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">At one time on that particular cruise, —</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, I end up just telling stories, and you say, “What’s the connection?”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">No, no, no, no. I’m—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Continue, please. Oh, I mean, I was just—if you were—if you were done speaking about that section of your service, I was going to jump forward a little bit, but if there is more that you want to highlight there, that’s also perfectly fine.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, I must say that we don’t—we should go back to requiring languages.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">And there’s many justifications for that. So we put into the southeast coast of <placeName>Spain</placeName> late that <date>next spring</date>, before we went back to the States. And by that time, you know, I had stayed and done the <orgName>Ouija</orgName> boards because a tanker can break apart in heavy seas from either hog or sag stress, which is eight tons per square inch or more. And every time you move big volumes of—of petroleum products around, you create stresses on the ship when it gets under waves.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And we had many fathoms, 150, 200 fathoms of water underneath us, so this is extraordinary. And I kept going back and forth, fathometer, radar, fathometer radar. You couldn’t see anything. It was all mist until the sun came out. It turns out we were in <placeName>Cartagena</placeName>, <placeName>Spain</placeName>, which is where the <placeName>Cartagena</placeName>, <placeName>Colombia</placeName>, comes from, of course.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.] Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Now, the whole purpose of this was—I mean, how many things are out there that we don’t have any sense about and you suddenly discover? But also how language was so valuable at that moment, because from that point on, the captain actually thought that I was—I could speak every language. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">No.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It stands for <persName>Cartago Noveno</persName>, which is <placeName>New Carthage</placeName>. And <placeName>New Carthage</placeName> was started by the folks that helped bring written language into the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And originally named for <placeName>Carthage</placeName>’s new city. So you have new city, new city, new city, new city—four stages of using that name before you get to <placeName>Cartagena</placeName>, <placeName>Colombia</placeName>. I didn’t figure that out for a long time.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Speak- </u>
      <u who="BROSS">Mmm?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, no, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So we were fueling the [USS] Boston, which was the flagship, and I was getting severely criticized, let’s say, by the engineering officer of the <placeName>Boston</placeName> for not putting out enough pressure to get this thing done. And so I did everything I could, including putting on a stripper pump, to get pressure.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And it just shows the kind of things that are happening all the time in that environment.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm. Speaking of—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So—yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—what you said about, like, the value of language and knowing the history and culture, I think in your essay you mentioned that when you did get your order to a Swift Boat in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you underwent this <date>two-month</date> training program that you believed to be very scarce and minimal.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">In some ways, yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I was just wondering if you could—if you could elaborate more on—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Sure.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—what—what that entailed and what it was like getting the order to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, I had applied for non-combatants, basically. Again, I had a lot of concerns about—didn’t even know what we were doing. And I couldn’t know that because I hadn’t been there. And at sea you don’t get much news. I—I was starved for news, but there was nothing I could do much to satisfy all. All the music was changing, and I knew that I was well removed from much of what was happening in society. Was trying to make up for it by absorbing as much as I could, right?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so anyway, we were back in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, this time in northern <placeName>Europe</placeName>. And in between, by the way, we had been north of <placeName>the Arctic Circle</placeName> and supported the laying of the buoys to detect the boomers coming out of <placeName>Murmansk</placeName> [<placeName>Russia</placeName>], and also had been to <placeName>South Africa</placeName>, where I got to observe apartheid first hand, probably the only—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—because we were auxiliary—the only <placeName>U.S.</placeName> naval vessel to go in past the quarantine for probably <date>20 years</date>. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">And what—what exactly did the letter—was in the letter?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It’s—I had alluded to it in my—in my essay.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You know, he and I had gotten to know each other only because he was the dorm chairman for <orgName>Cutter [Hall</orgName>], and I was the dorm chairman for <orgName>North [Hall</orgName>]. And we got to like each other, and everything that you read about <persName>Bruce</persName> in the essay, that his—one of his old girlfriends had written about him is—was true in my experience. And so I didn’t realize at that time that he’d been killed by the time I got the letter.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">But I was concerned. And I didn’t have much information, honestly, <persName>Hannah</persName>, because I hadn’t been in a position to read enough. But I knew that we were—there was a hot war starting up.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I think over time, you kind of get used to the idea of reading between the lines, and reading between the lines, I thought, This thing is <orgName>heatin</orgName>’ up fast. But I don’t quite understand—I know that it’s containment. I understand containment. But I also know that that’s an area that I know very little about. And I knew that if you were going to get into conflict of that nat- —of actually war, if you want to call it that or if you want to call it a police action—same thing—you know that I would—by this time in my life, even though I was still quite young—have formed a belief that you should know a lot [chuckles], if possible, about your enemies and about the context of the conflict.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I felt blind. So I guess I had pretty high expectations, and so when I got there, the running of the boat—you know, everything from the radios to the machine guns, the mortars and the characteristics of the patrol and understanding the interdiction and the role of [Operation] Market Time—that to me was not bad at all. In fact, we spent a lot of time doing those things. You know, you had to get familiar. You had to go out there and be able to be independent.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I did know—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So in light of—I’m sorry.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">That’s okay.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I was just—in light of your—in light of the letter from <persName>Bruce</persName> and your sort of lot, you know that there was something missing, sort of, it seems like. What—what still was driving you—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I was being trained.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—as you went into service.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, I still felt—I just a need, and that’s when I started going out and looking for other books, and I tried the library, which was skimpy, and I looked for a number of books, and I didn’t buy more than one, but the two that I remembered the best because each in its own way gave me information I didn’t have before. And you know about them. It’s the—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—as I said, the kind of propagandistic thing by <persName>Victor Pike</persName>, and the other was <name type="event">The Quicksand War</name>[: Prelude to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>], and I’m glad I had those two things before I went. At least it gave me a better—a little glimpse of what we were going to be dealing with.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But only a glimpse. I mean, I was used to speaking a language and learning—talking to other military officers, talking to ordinary people, talking to leaders, talking to people from all walks of life, in their language, and knew how people responded to you when you spoke their language if you were reasonably fluent.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And—but rarely have we seen that forethought. Why—why do we go kill people?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">What are we trying to achieve? Was it just building a wall against communist invasion? Well, haven’t we already learned that that isn’t going to do it?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You know, when you look at La Violencia en Colombia and you realize the intensity of the emotion and the depths and that these people are motivated by their experiences, and if you don’t understand what these experiences have been, how do you predict or understand how to communicate and behave with each other? I mean, this is a very long, extended discussion that we’re not going to be able to address in detail—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right, of course.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—because after all, I was learning on the job, and I was just starting to think about these things in the way you and I are now discussing them. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Did you think—did you feel like you were sort of the only—one of the few people to be considering these things at the time of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, when you were serving on either your—your <persName>Swift Boat</persName> there or combat base?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah. Well, so the stuff I sent you, <persName>Hannah</persName>, and I tried to give you—I know your task is to write—I thought of you writing a paper about <orgName>the U.S. Navy</orgName>, anyway so this is a good time to refer to some of the links I sent you.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And that led to Market Time. The—the fact that we had a 1,200-mile coast of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, and so they had to have a pretty major effort, and Task Force 115 had started to do this, because—and I’m going to come back to that. Why is this such a big deal?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—starving for medical supplies and even starving for food and salt and basics. And what’s the difference? Well, the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> coast—the difference is that the coast is just the coast; you can’t get around it. You cannot create a cordon successfully around the entire place. We were always going to be working on the edge. And they had—like <persName>Napoleon</persName> [<persName>Bonaparte</persName>] found out when he went into <placeName>Russia</placeName>—when you have defense in depth of that nature, that’s, to say the least, a very challenging proposition.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><placeName>China</placeName> is enormous. The rest of <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, you go back and look at what happened in <name type="event">World War II</name>. It’s a horrible place to fight in. Very difficult. And stopping enough supplies coming in over the land to completely isolate that area, if you’re just thinking in purely military and logistics terms, is daunting.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Now, that does not mean, however, that you shouldn’t care about the fact that you find a 100-ton trawler. Why? What does it mean to have a pound of explosives or ten pounds or a hundred pounds, a ton? How many—how many rocket- propelled grenades does it take to have a ton of rocket-propelled grenades? Who cares?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">A hundred yards.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Uh-huh, a hundred meters, more or less, right?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">While I was there, the RPG-7 came in. The rocket-propelled grenade 7, developed by the Russians—the way it works is it has a piezo[electric] crystal fuse in the nose. Any time it hits metal or something like that, it deforms. And it has this very hot, focused stream of metal, and that RPG-7 could go through 12 inches of homogeneous steel.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Or 100 inches of sandbags.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And you could carry six of them in a little bundle and walk around, and you could weigh 125 or [1]30 pounds and do it. Now, how many—you know, what would be a ton of those? And so you had 100 tons of cargo. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">No.</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><date>About 30 days</date>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">With <placeName>the Erie Canal</placeName>, how long did it take?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><date>Five days</date>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You’re pretty darn close. Four.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">What was the decrease in the cost of a ton of goods in the form of, say, grain out of <placeName>Ohio</placeName> or <placeName>Indiana</placeName>, as they were developing the farmlands and they would bring it over and ship it through <placeName>the Erie Canal</placeName>? How much did it decrease the cost of transportation? I’ll tell you: 97 percent.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I was going to say probably a decent amount.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So these are kinds of things that we don’t get taught. We have no reason to think about these things, especially if we never think about the military, if we end up in shipping or something like this, and we’re forced to come to think about these things. But it’s pretty potent, isn’t it?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You know, water transport has made a huge difference in the world. It continues to, and that’s why I put that in there, is to make sure that we didn’t get too narrowed in on thinking about things that were just part of the picture.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so if you have a bicycle, even in the worst trails, a Vietnamese porter could carry 100 pounds down the Hồ Chí Minh trail. But even so—and they did—even so, it’s just a heck of a lot easier if you could just bring your ship right up and drop off a hundred tons of stuff, right?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">There was a reason for them to be there. It looks like—my experience was there was probably about 15 attempts after this first episode. I think all but one of them got stopped. And I was on watch, way up north when, in my—in my division, I heard at midnight, around <name type="event">New Year’s Eve</name>, between 1966 and ’67, suddenly comes on line a call, in code, but not very much in code, pretty much plain language: “So-and-so, So-and-so, I’ve been shot! I’ve been shot!” And this is the Swift Boat who thought that they had an LST and it turned out to be a trawler and they just got real close and put a light on it, and immediately 762 shells go shooting right through—fortunately, the officer in charge had just jumped out of his chair before the shells came through. Knocked out his lights, and they took off in panic. And they tried to come back, and they engaged them. But that trawler I think got in. I think all the rest, one way or the other, got detected.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">So to the extent that even in—and in <date>1983</date>, in a subsequent major battle, they didn’t try to use the sea much to bring in additional supplies. The [Operation] Game Warden comes because they recognize that the rivers were just as important in terms of huge amounts of—of material and people being easily transported. Okay, so that’s how you get Task Force 116. But it wasn’t enough—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—because they would fortify banks and ambush, and that’s how you end up with these monitors and other armored vehicles with their bar armor. And the reason bar armor works, by the way, is that that rocket-propelled grenade, when it detonates—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—anytime it goes to that bar armor and detonates, that space of 12 inches that you used the bar armor—that expends the force and the effectiveness of the rocket-propelled grenade before it reaches the armor, okay?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">So that’s what they did. And if you’re on a river patrol boat or a <orgName>PCF</orgName> [Patrol Craft Fast], you kind of hoped that they would go through and not detonate by hitting an engine or a radio or a person or something like that. You hoped that somehow it would just hit and pass through, but sometimes that was a forlorn hope.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Would you mind talking about the PCFs just a little more?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Sure, and compare those to the PBRs [Patrol Boat, River] and compare them to the <orgName>Coast Guard</orgName> cutters. It was fortunate to serve with <orgName>the Coast Guard</orgName> because they had 85-foot steel cutters, a somewhat larger crew than we had, and they were self-righting. That means that if they turned over in a big storm, they would come back up.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The mortars also had—actually, I’m thinking I may have it wrong. It may be as much as 8,000 yards. But the mortars certainly had a comparable range. And now my memory is wrong. It was 4,000 or 8,000. But it was a long way, and I suspect probably stick with 4,000 yards because that’s a long way.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And it’s also—if you think about it, it’s like a 3-inch shell, and if a shell like that dropped into a living room, I don’t think anyone would survive not being wounded, and a number of people would be killed. So it’s a pretty big weapon for a little boat.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Hard to fire that mortar on a boat that’s wobbling back and forth. Not that easy with the machine guys. But it depends on the weather. It depends on where you need to direct the fire and lots of other things. But there’s plenty of—I think plenty of armament, especially if you had armor-piercing rounds. I think when they used just ball and they wanted to stop a steel-hulled trawler, that probably was unrealistic.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Uh-oh.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The worst example of that was one that went into a river mount. The bow hit the beach because you had big waves, and it was a rough sea, and the boat went stern over bow. I think they lost three dead, and I don’t think they recovered a lot of the weaponry or the entire boat.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Very agile, very low to the water. I think really for their purposes, they were better adapted than the <persName>Swifts</persName>, but the <persName>Swifts</persName> had the advantage of being cheap. And available. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I guess just what—what your—what the <date>daily</date> missions or what you perceived to be the day-to-<date>day</date> tasks on one of the PCFs was. I mean, you mentioned interdiction, for sure, but—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—but any—any—just any other specific stories about what you encountered from—on these—the Swift Boats.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So you have about a 20-mile stretch along the coast. It goes 12 miles out to sea. And you want to make sure that whatever is happening, you’re close enough or patrolling actively enough at all times of day and night to have a sense if there’s somebody going into the beach who shouldn’t be doing that,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—or if there’s vessels meeting off the coast that—why would they do that? Why would they be meeting? Are they handing off things? So your primary mission is to know what’s going on in that 20 by 12 mile area of ocean. And it’s fine when there’s nothing happening. You just have junk traffic, sampan [flat-bottomed wooden boat] traffic going—mostly junk traffic—going up and down, and once in a while you’ll see, a little further out, various sizes of tugs for tows, small steaming vessels and so forth. And so you want to make sure you know who they are and what they’re up to.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">I did find people carrying money in quantities that were not authorized by their documentation. I would sometimes see people with very soft hands, who were supposedly out fishing. I mean, there’s lot of little indications—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—about things that you would worry about.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">And was all of this just you learning—learning these little indications on the job? Did you—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, once in a while—you know, I had a Vietnamese interpreter once, and we caught somebody with a very large amount of money that we had to turn into the authorities. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">And—that was—that was most of it. I—I think it—the weather was the biggest problem because you knew darn well that the harder things got at sea, the more likely we were going to have to deal with something.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The long hours—to me, that wasn’t the issue. You know, you go out for 24 hours at a time, and you would just trade off your crew. We—we did things like—there was—for a while, there was a gasoline barge off of <persName>Phan Thiết</persName>, and it was a perfect target for a sapper [member of Viet Cong elite C-10 Sapper Battalion] to come in and blow it up and destroy the supplies for that part of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So we would hopefully unpredictably drop concussion grenades at different distances around it, in case there were any swimmers.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">We would sometimes—we sometimes carried <orgName>Army</orgName> liaison officers. Most of them didn’t like the sea [chuckles] in terms of getting seasick. You know, it was understandable. I mean, they didn’t have their sea legs, and so that wasn’t usually a very enjoyable sort of thing.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right, right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Could sometimes support the Vietnamese <orgName>Navy</orgName> activities. As long as you’re talking about the northern—<persName>Vũng Tàu</persName>—this is all pretty descriptive. As soon as you head south and you’re into the mouths of the [Mekong] Delta, things get a little bit more interesting, because it sounds simple just to stay on a patrol, and it is where the water is reasonably deep, and—and your radars, which are not outstanding, can help you define—even when it’s utterly pitch black, you know how close you are to the beach. You know that you can either see—we had night scopes—and/or your radar is going to pick up most activity that’s likely to happen in your area.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Once—the—the job, though, becomes much more complicated. When you go to the mouths of the delta, the tides are up to 13 and a half feet twice a day. It’s hard to imagine water that fills up a room and then empties the room twice a day—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—and with the force that that generates. So the Swift Boat had only a four-and-a-half-foot draft, but it could go aground ten miles off the coast at low tide.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The area was not fully charted. There was actually an area in our patrols, that we had to patrol, where it was just blank because a survey vessel that had gone in to detect the depth there was almost sunk by fire from shore.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So they had to withdraw, and so we had a blank spot. But even when you had—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">But you guys still patrolled there?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes, you had to. Also, the thing is that even with—even with charts, it could be very misleading because the sand and the mud and the silt coming down from the mouths of the <placeName>Mekong</placeName>—all these different rivers—would come through, flow out and be deposited, but then you would have the currents. Ocean currents are always prevalent, but also the winds and the waves and the storms. So it would not be long before the contours of the bottom had been shifted again.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">What it means is something like a small—a small telephone pole that the fisherman had learned to pile-drive into the silt, and so you have a crossbar and men, maybe one on each side, would go jumping up and down, and they would drive these poles into the silt. They were as long as they could get them. And when they were finished and they had a number of these, they would put them—they would all be lined up perpendicular to the flow of the current. So you have this line of these poles sticking up out of the river mouths. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">And they would just pull the fish up by—by loads. It was a brilliant economical use of human technology. And they showed up on radar at night [huh!] as bright points.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh. Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And that meant that when you were looking for the deepest places, where you wouldn’t go aground even at low tide, those were the obvious pathways. They weren’t lighted, but the radar—they were visible to you. However,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—always in my mind was: a perfect place for an ambush. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">True.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So you really had to think about what—how much could they set, and was there any activity around there that would say, I wonder if they put in a—you know, a mine or some kind of explosive, an IED [improvised explosive device] or similar kind of device. And there was traps in thinking—with not thinking it out clearly. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—and were they would similarly drop the nets. And we had one young officer who, on his very first assignment <date>that day</date>, went steaming out at 25 knots and launched his boats off of a sunken Japanese vessel—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Oh, wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—and left both his screws behind. And there he is, with men and ammunition having fallen off both sides of the boat. And he obviously wasn’t going to go on his mission <date>that day</date>, which, as they said in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> parlance, it ruined his whole day.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.] I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, Cat [pronouncing it CAT] Lo. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">So Cat Lo was—had Quonset huts, and they had supplies, and we had, to the north of us, both the Australian infantry and the <placeName>New Zealand</placeName> artillery that were supposed to be responsible, trying to make it more difficult for us to be attacked. But we always knew that this could happen, so we had barbed wire, and we were all ready to defend the base. But we weren’t as exposed as people would be, say, in I <orgName>Corps</orgName> or in the interior. But we knew it could happen, and so we had to be aware of it. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—where we would go on board a supporting destroyer and spend the night, one night, and then the next night we’d be out on patrol, so 24 hours in our boats, 24 hours in the destroyer. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And just went back and forth for <date>45 days</date>. But there’s <date>one period of three days</date> when the water was too heavy, and I remember edging the boat along the port quarter of the [unintelligible name of ship]. Very good captain. And he really wanted to give us some relief, and I think we’d been out for <date>two days</date> at that point. But as we came edging up along the side, the water was so steep at one point, my boats—I decided to take the <placeName>conn</placeName> on this, and I was handling the engines and the steering. And without me being able to control of it because of the intensity of the waves, we slid back slightly, and I looked over—out of the corner of my eye, and I could see the screws of the destroyer turning slowly off to the side of my boat. Clearly, didn’t want to be swept back into that.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And all of a sudden, the bottom dropped out, which made me worry. It was about a 20- or 25-foot drop. It made me worry that we would dismount the engines. Meanwhile, my—my fellow officers were on the radio saying, “Pull away! Pull away!” </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I had, by that time, decided they were probably right, and so we just, you know, quietly started edging back towards—to the shore, about five or six, seven miles away, so we could find a little bit of a <persName>lee</persName>. And I secured one engine, and then we just crept back and forth with one engine all along the coast there. It was 72 hours before we finally got off the boat.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow. And how many—how many crew members were on one <orgName>PCF</orgName> during—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Five enlisted and me.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—a patrol?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Five enlisted and me. So you had a radio man, you had a gunner’s mate, you had a boatswain, and you had two others.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Would you go out with the same five enlisted every time?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Pretty much, until somebody was short-timed and left, so a lot of these guys were made up of people who were ending their time in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, and so I did have two young men, <persName>Frank</persName> [J.] Furrer and [<persName>Robert E.]</persName> “<persName>Bob” Lorona</persName>, who were with me throughout the time I was there. There was turnover in the other positions.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">This—this might be a—a broad question, so feel free to answer it in any—in any way you see fit, but something that really interests me is how to—and I mentioned this in the e-mail a little bit—sort of how—how would you define or categorize the success of the—the <orgName>Navy</orgName> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? You know, we hear—I guess a lot of the things that I’ve read so far talked about the brown-water navy and how revolutionary it was. So how would you describe the success of what—what you were doing there in the <orgName>PCF</orgName> and all the work you were doing off the coast and in these small rivers and the delta?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The reason I wanted you to have that overview is because there were so many components to what was the <orgName>Navy</orgName>’s role. So Market Time, I think was significant. I tried to touch on why it was significant,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, yes, sure.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—because even though it didn’t keep all armaments out, it would have been worse if we hadn’t had Market Time, I think. And there’s some evidence for that.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—east and western—and all this. But I don’t see any other way that anybody’s efforts were going to succeed in, quotes, “winning.” I do appreciate the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> saying, “No one has ever won a fire or a war.” Wars should really be something you only do when you absolutely don’t see another option. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">If you look at the survival of <placeName>England</placeName>, I feel you have an example of what I mean. And the reason it matters is because in this age of a multi-polar world, we’re no longer in this east-west simplistic setting. It’s not simplistic in its actual experience, but, I mean, it’s just like a lot of the conflicts in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> were hidden over and papered over as long as we had an enemy that everybody agreed on. And then in <date>1989</date>, with the fall of the Soviet empire, a lot of these flaws and conflicts that had not been addressed adequately began to surface more and more and more.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">We as a nation state have to decide how to contend with this very complex world. You know, if the only tool you have is a hammer, the world looks like a nail. So if the idea is that, you know, you’re going to solve all our problems through the military, it’s—it’s wrong. It’s just not going to happen. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">If you decide there is no role for hammers, well, then you only construct certain kinds of things [both chuckle], and you can only deal with certain kinds of problems.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So you said—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So this is not very satisfying. <persName>It’s</persName>—it’s—it’s nuanced.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It is the idea that war is only politics by other means. It is about knowing why you don’t want to have militaries that are too isolated from their sustaining culture and population. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Did you—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">If you look at what happens to a place like <placeName>the Middle East</placeName>, the Shias and the Sunnis. They can’t develop police forces and militaries that actually are equally protective and serving of each of the religious communities.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Many of the major problems we confront <date>today</date> are from the militaries in <placeName>Latin America</placeName>, <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and <placeName>the Middle East</placeName> taking over. I’m just now reading <name type="event">The Fall of the Ottoman Empire</name> [sic; The Fall of the Ottomans: The Great War in <placeName>the Middle East</placeName>]. It’s—it’s a very interesting book, and it makes very clear how that part of <placeName>the Middle East</placeName> got into the position that it is and what people were reacting to.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">That’s so interesting that you—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—necessarily—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—that you bring that up because I’m actually in a—I’m in a class this term on Violence and Conflict in the Middle East, and we’ve spent the first, multiple <date>weeks</date> of the term looking at the fall of <placeName>the Ottoman Empire</placeName> and—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Good.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—the implications of that, and it really is all so related, —</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—which is—but—yeah. So it was just—just funny that you mentioned that.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, relevant hopefully.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, very relevant.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">When you were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">You said—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">The problem in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at the heart is that they—that they were not a well-integrated society, that there was these enormous fissures between the various—the various ethnic groups and religious groups. And the—you know—I mean, you can go way back and ask the question about colonialism, and I’m going to—I have a somewhat cartoonish perspective, meaning that I’m not as educated as I would like to be about this.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">After all, they bankrupted themselves for <placeName>the United States</placeName> to have a successful <orgName>American Revolution</orgName> just as a beginning of point, counterpoint. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I know. It’s funny, isn’t it? But, I mean, I think that <placeName>South Africa</placeName> and somebody like <persName>Nelson</persName> [R.] <persName>Mandela</persName> is only possible when you have a society that actually has some belief that this—that you can have that kind of change that isn’t just within one group; it is within more than one group. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I don’t think that <persName>Mahatma Gandhi</persName> would have been as successful in dealing with, say, <persName>mm</persName>, I don’t know, who do I—who do I act like I’m prejudiced against, you know? Pick somebody. Let’s say the—the Mongol hordes were running <placeName>India</placeName>. I don’t think that <persName>Mahatma Gandhi</persName> would have been as successful with his campaigns of passive resistance and, you know, resisting the collection of salt and doing so many things that he did had it not been for lots of things: certainly the weakened state of <placeName>England</placeName> after the war but also the fact that they had begun to understand each other,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—with lots of misunderstanding along the way,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—and that he understood what leverage he had. After all, the British had given up on <placeName>the United States</placeName>. And going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, think about where the British were during <name type="event">the American Revolution</name>. They could go up and down the coast. They could blockade us. We had just—we had some wonderful, you know, brief victories—you know, with <persName>John Paul Jones</persName> and, you know, the “Old Ironsides [USS Constitution] and things like that. But the fact of the matter is, if there hadn’t been <persName>Napoleon</persName> and lots of other things going on, they would have had—we would have had their undivided attention.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But they—they were confronted with the problem that we had an infinite depth behind us, and we were always moving deeper into the continent that the Europeans that arrived on <placeName>the East Coast</placeName> had begun to occupy. And there was a whole number of things. I mean, the reason we get <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> so cheaply, I believe now as I’ve read the history, that actually <persName>Napoleon</persName> wanted to sell the property. It wasn’t [President <persName>Thomas]</persName> <persName>Jefferson</persName>’s idea. They—they made him an offer that kind of like <persName>Jefferson</persName> couldn’t refuse—you know, $15 million to double the size of <placeName>the United States</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Going there.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—and going there.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I didn’t think I’d have the ability—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">So after—right, of course. So after—after going there and experiencing it, what—had your thoughts or opinions on it changed at all, or developed?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, they did at the time. First of all, I could not disclose my feelings if I was a training officer. Instead, I had to take everything I had learned and try to make the people who were going to go over there better able to (1) survive and (2) not commit atrocities.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Emotionally, cognitively, psychologically very complex. I had a good relationship, I think, with <persName>Roy Boehm</persName>. He I think wanted me to stay. And <persName>Roy</persName> was a very tough character. I—he—you know, when I was a patrol officer, I would sometimes swim under the vessels where you stopped and looked. I never asked my men to do that. There were a number of things I did that tried to give me insights, and I never knew that they would work, but I just kept trying.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">How long exactly were you there for?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I was there for <date>the year</date>. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BROSS">I got there in <date>the fall</date> of <date>’66</date> and left in <date>the fall</date> of <date>’67</date>, and I said that I had sold my 30 shares of stock when [Gen. <persName>William C.]</persName> <orgName>Westmoreland</orgName> said he saw the light at the end of the tunnel—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—<date>November 15</date>. And we had [the] Tet [Offensive] at <date>the end of January</date>. And back in the <orgName>Statesides</orgName>, some other officers and I could feel each other out a little bit and have discussions that were not matters of disloyalty but matters of trying to metabolize and understand what was going on, how to fulfill our role and do so responsibly, but not to set people up, not to have them marching off, you know, to—like I said, to <placeName>Saint</placeName>, you know, <persName>Peter</persName> or [Saint] James—to <persName>Saint James</persName> I guess it is—and at them, this kind of religious patriotism that’s so unthinking or a risk of being so fanatic—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—that you never ask yourself the question, Are we doing the right thing? Are we doing it in the right way? And so I canvassed for <persName>Eugene</persName> [<persName>J.] McCarthy</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But nobody knew it. My wife knew it, or my fiancée and then later my wife. But I didn’t go telling people. I didn’t wear my uniform. And of all the people I talked to—and I did it in a <orgName>Navy</orgName> town, so there was some risk of me running into somebody from the base, but one person challenged me. I said, “Well,”—I didn’t explain that I was still in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. I said, “I just got back.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And what I was doing was trying to raise discussion. And then I was immediately going to night school at <placeName>Berkeley</placeName>, and that was really the beginning of students challenging me. When I got to [<orgName>the University of] Madison[-Wisconsin]</orgName>, I was older than most students, even graduate students. It was very—they had the Dow [Chemical Company] demonstrations before I got there. It was a place where eventually, while I was there, the four students would blow up the math building because they were against violence.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And I tried to talk to the students. And I had one guy that I actually believe—who will ever know? And so you could say, “Well, that’s just [a] paranoid state,” but I actually think there was some guy who said he was in <orgName>NROTC</orgName>, and I thought that he acted a little bit like an agent provocateur. You know, it’s, like, one—the thing that kind of sealed it for me was one of the times of some of the worst riots, he came running up to me and said, “I just shoved a couple of pigs through a plate glass window.” I looked at him, and I said, “I thought you were against violence. I don’t want to ever see you again.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">He looked so ashamed and so crestfallen, all I could think of is this guy—I can’t ima-—he was so unlike these overly serious SDS [Students for a Democratic Society] and other kinds of students that I would sometimes run into, you know, who were just,—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—you know, as religiously fanatic and convinced as anybody could be that this was the most important conflict the world had ever seen and that only their personal sacrifice would end it, up to and including their death or mine, right? [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Did you try to be as open or as public as possible about your service—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">By the time I was out of the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, sure.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—and your opinions?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I mean, everyone knew kind of how I felt. That’s probably why, if I was indeed targeted to see if I was really over the top, that would probably be why, is that I had been in—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—parades, demonstrations, and I told the students how I felt. <persName>Bill</persName> was my closest friend in graduate school, and you know his background. His—his younger brother took the <placeName>Phoenix</placeName> [of <placeName>Hiroshima</placeName>] into <placeName>Haiphong</placeName>. [Chuckles.]  </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Sorry, I know you—I know you have told me about <persName>Henry Kempe</persName>, but just for the purposes of the interview, would you mind describing him and his work a little bit?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Sure. Well, Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName> hired me in—right after my own son was born in <date>1976</date>, out of the legal counsel’s office. And the conversation started out—it was <date>May</date>, like, 23rd or so of <date>1976</date>. And I was doing five different jobs at that time: working on my <persName>Ph.D.</persName>, working half time as a consultant to <orgName>the health department</orgName>, clerking for the <orgName>University</orgName> counselor for minimum wage, helping people buy and sell real estate, plus doing my <persName>Ph.D.</persName> actual research.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I want this job, and [chuckles] Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName> brings me into his office. You know, it was this—might have been a mother superior’s office for all I know. Most of the religious artifacts had been taken out. So they could have whole families living with us, three to four—four of them at a time. And we would treat them for <date>up to a half year</date> for the severe abuse and neglect that was happening in their families. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">That’s kind of breathtaking, isn’t it? [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.] It’s a good question.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">[Laughs.] It was a good ques- —yeah, I didn’t even say that I’m thinking fast, and I’m thinking, Hmm. Well,—so I said—he didn’t know that—anything about <persName>G. Keith Funston</persName> and <orgName>the New York Stock Exchange</orgName> or any of that stuff. I just said, “Well, Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName>, I suppose that if money was the most important thing in my life, I wouldn't have gone into sociology.” He nodded. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—he told me he had a hundred candidates, and he had graded everybody, and I was first, and he had given me what I won’t tell you because he didn’t want me to tell anybody. But basically he said, “Well, I think I made a good decision.” [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">But he would—he was extraordinary! And I came to know, over time, his—his—his story that he was born in <placeName>Breslau</placeName>, <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and he was—would have been about—let’s see, when was <persName>Kristal Night</persName>—was that—<persName>Kristallnacht</persName>. Was that <date>1938</date>?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[No audible reply.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">That sound about right.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I believe so, ’<date>38</date> or ’39.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, so—’38 I think is about right because that’s—that’s when his parents decided they had to get out of town. He—with his sister—and I think the idea was that he could finish high school. He was 15. He would finish high school, and then he would leave, because they were worried, with reason.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—where she was treated. So this guy was—there was a lot going on.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Did your—yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So he comes, at <date>the age of 33</date>, to become the chairman of <orgName>the Department of Pediatrics</orgName> at <orgName>the University of Colorado School of Medicine</orgName>. At that time, there was a total of three doctors. [Both chuckle]. He—we now have one of the top ten children’s hospitals in <placeName>the United States</placeName>. A very large department, noticed for a lot of things. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So coming back here to <persName>Henry Kempe</persName>, he is experiencing what I and others—I—I think it was <persName>Kit Olmsted</persName> [archivist note: spelling uncertain] at <orgName>Oxford</orgName>, a friend of the pioneers in child abuse in this country, called gaze aversion. You get presented as a doctor with a patient, let’s say an upper middle-class woman, who comes in, and you notice—you’ve had her for a patient for some time—you notice some bruises on her lower arms, she got long sleeves on but you still eventually see these bruises. And you get concerned about it, and you were running the differential diagnosis through your mind, and you’re thinking, Well, could it be coagulopathy? She’s taking aspirin or she has an underlying disease process, some medication I’d given her. Could these be defensive wounds? Her spouse is battering her? Is she drinking and falling down and we just don’t know it? I’ve never sensed that. But, you know, her husband is one of the vice chancellors, and you’re not, you know, at ease with these bruises because they could also be defensive injuries.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And that’s the term I was trying to get to, because <persName>Henry Kempe</persName> was experiencing, already in ’<date>58</date>, gaze aversion. People didn’t want to talk about human violence in the home. It was frightening, disturbing—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Did you and <persName>Henry</persName>—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Hmm?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Did you and—did you and <persName>Henry Kempe</persName> ever talk about your shared experiences with the military at all?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, no because I think he delegated it to Dr. <persName>Rembrandt</persName> [<persName>F. “Brandt”]</persName> <persName>Steele</persName>. He was never called <persName>Rembrandt</persName>. His name was [<persName>F.] Brandt Steele</persName>. <persName>Brandt</persName> was a marvelous partner for <persName>Henry Kempe</persName>. <persName>Brandt Steele</persName> was born in <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> [<placeName>Indiana</placeName>] in <date>1907</date>, of a businessman, but his grandfather was <persName>T. C. Steele</persName>, the American impressionist painter who did the <persName>Kellogg</persName> family. His grandmother was a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> who was part of <orgName>the Underground Railroad</orgName> in southern <placeName>Illinois</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And he was getting ready to go to <placeName>Europe</placeName> and <placeName>Texas</placeName> when his commanding officer comes up and says, “<persName>Steele</persName>, you’ve always been interested in why people do things. We’ve lost our psychiatrist. You’re going to have to be our psychiatrist.” So [chuckles] they get to <placeName>England</placeName>, and—and <persName>Brandt</persName> goes—again—he says, “Listen, I would like to go to an English psychiatric hospital and learn what I’m supposed to do as a psychiatrist.” And he said, “Aw, you can’t do that! We might have to bug out anytime. You have to stay here.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Unintelligible.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Very nice, quiet question, right? [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah! Started out strong.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah. Both of them had a way of opening up the conversation. [Chuckles.] And I said, “Well,” I said, “I didn’t lose anybody, and we didn’t commit any atrocities, but we did what we were responsible for doing.” And he just nodded. [Laughs.] </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">But you—you said you would—so you would talk to his close—close friend <persName>Brandt</persName> about—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah. I know he and <persName>Brandt</persName>—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—sort of making—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—helped each other—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—sense of—yeah.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah, and <persName>Ruth</persName>, because <persName>Brandt</persName> could talk about the nature of human violence and help <persName>Henry</persName> understand it and contend with it. And <persName>Henry</persName>’s first step when he began to solve this problem was to hire a social worker, because he had taught social workers, to make money when he was in medical school, and later he got—and then he—he tried—he tracked <persName>Brandt</persName> because he knew he was a great psychiatrist, that he helped set up major programs in <placeName>Colorado</placeName>. And he was quite <date>a few years</date> older than <persName>Henry</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS"><persName>Henry</persName> had done it. I mean, he—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Were there any specific—[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, when he told me about—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Were there any specific aspects of your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that helped you understand or start to make sense of human violence in a way similar to <persName>Brandt</persName>?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Mmm. No, it just made me aware of the conditions that might produce—you know, put people in a position where they found themselves defending—you know, committing violence. But he and I would talk about things like—you know, we say “self-defense,” and we try to understand violence. He said, “<persName>Don</persName>, what is one universal thing we can say about violence?” And I would—for a while, I had to stop and think. Eventually, I figured out what he really wanted me to be able to understand, that we disapprove of the violence of others, <persName>Hannah</persName>, and we approve of our own. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—in wars. And I fully appreciate and understand that. And we put people in these incredible situations, and that’s all the more reason for me that you don’t just send cannon fodder. You know, that’s—that’s not how we should think about these things.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Oh, really?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—which I really, really appreciate. It flew by. I was just looking at the recording and noticing how quickly that went. If there’s anything else you want to add, feel free. I just want to make sure I’m not taking up your whole day here.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, I couldn’t say enough about <persName>Henry</persName>, and there’s a lot to say. And as I said, I’ve actually written something about how he came to deal with child abuse and the effects of that. I will tell you a little bit more because I wanted this part to be part of how hard it is to deal with human violence and how it’s understandable that—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Right.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—Ivy League faculties want to throw military officers in training off their campus, because who wants to think about such terrible things? But why I also said I thought it was a reasonable—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, I definitely wanted to get back to <orgName>ROTC</orgName> and the decision that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> made.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So this to me is resonant of the experience that Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName> had when he tried to get people to deal with the violence in families, and as respected as he was, his colleagues really didn’t want him to do that. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[No audible reply.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Nothing!</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">That they weren’t right? Nothing?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Nobody—no- —I have found no evidence that anybody even read it, but if they did, they didn’t write the editor, nor did they write Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName> or Dr. <persName>Silver</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Nothing again?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, they did a little bit better than that. They rejected it as being unscientific. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">At least they got—they got a response that time. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">It’s breathtaking. Are you kidding me? A guy with his reputation—you know, with the scientific research he had accomplished, his wet lab research in viruses. It’s unbelievable. </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Which is the place where the battered child syndrome was first presented. <persName>Justine</persName>—last name, French, but I never met her—was a woman judge from <placeName>New York</placeName>, <persName>Henry Silverman</persName>, a medical student by the name of [<persName>William] Droegemueller</persName>, Dr. <persName>Steele</persName>, Dr. <persName>Silver</persName> and Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName> presented. It was about a thousand people, <persName>Brandt</persName> remembered. It was a large audience because these were well-known folks.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Not scientific?</u>
      <u who="BROSS">No, go back to the original answer. Silence. [Laughs.] </u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Nothing. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Not a challenge. As they were leaving—they had lots of friends, and someone would kind of come up and say, “You know, I think I may have seen a child like this once.” I mean, <date>last year</date> we had 650,000 confirmed cases and about 1,500 or 2,000 deaths.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So it was <date>1962</date> in <date>June</date> that the battered child syndrome was published in <orgName>JAMA[:The Journal of the American Medical Association</orgName>]. And in <date>the early 1980s</date>, <orgName>the American Medical Association</orgName> had a committee that decided to choose the 50 most important contributions of <orgName>the Journal of the American Medical Association</orgName> to American medicine in <date>its first 100 years</date>. And the battered child syndrome was one of those papers.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Is that enough? For now?</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah, that was—that was great. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I really appreciate your interest. I really appreciate your thoughtfulness and care in your preparation. I did try to send you a bunch of stuff because I know there’s a risk—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Thank you, thank you.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—yeah, that we—this gets to be too narrow in its understanding if you want to just focus on these military things. I do feel it’s been a great gift—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, I—I really appreciate that you—that you sort of gave me the—the wider perspective in talking about <persName>Kempe</persName> and everything that sort of came before and after as well. Going all the way back through his childhood experience was really interesting.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Well, you know,—and I mentioned <persName>Alice Miller</persName>. I won’t go through that again, but you know about that. And, you know, this idea—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">—of treating children with such brutality and not allowing them to develop a sense of empathy.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I mean, using gas against his own people and things like that. <orgName>The Denver Post</orgName> went on to say however, perhaps it helps us to appreciate, not justify or accept, appreciate in the sense of understand or have insight into how somebody raised in this fashion would come to believe that when they were in power, that they were literally entitled or justified in doing whatever they wanted to somebody else who opposed them or disagreed with them.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">We could go on, but we probably shouldn’t. [Both chuckle.] It’s enough for you to—I was left in the second generation of what Dr. <persName>Kempe</persName> and Dr. <persName>Steele</persName> agreed was a five-generation problem, to try to get to a better place. And I’m only in the second generation.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I feel that <persName>Henry</persName> left us [chuckles] with at least five generations more work.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.] At least.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes, exactly.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And by the way, just so—another insight for <persName>Brandt</persName>. The last—I can’t keep going on. So <persName>Brandt</persName> felt that, look, we as human beings have these essential drives of—of aggression and sexuality, and he thought another one might be difference, and he thought we react to difference. And difference is what is based on him being a physician in the old school before he becomes a psychiatrist and what he’s thinking about immune systems and how the body biologically responds to external pathogens.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">So anyway, that’s the kind of insights, spending time thinking about us and just—we’re—I said to <persName>Brandt</persName> once—I said something about reading [<persName>Daniel J.]</persName> <persName>Boorstin</persName>’s book on—The Discoverers. It wasn’t until the end of the book that we found ourselves. And <persName>Brandt</persName> said, “We haven’t discovered ourselves yet.” [Laughs.] “We still have so much to understand.”</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Did you—what did—[Laughs.] Yeah. Wow. That—that leaves me a lot to think about as well—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Good!</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">–which is great.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Good. That’s exactly—that’s the value, is to have somebody that actually thinks it’s interesting that people—being curious and having questions about people is such a wonderful gift, and that’s why I’ve appreciated the time you’ve given me.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yeah, I—again, thank you so, so much for agreeing to have this conversation. It was very valuable for me and I hope for you as well [chuckles], but—</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Oh, absolutely.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">—thank you so much for offering your time.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">I’ll tell you a quote from Dr. [<persName>Richard D.] Krugman</persName>. Dr. <persName>Krugman</persName> just retired as the dean of the medical school [at <orgName>the University of Colorado</orgName>], and he’s come back to <placeName>the Kempe Center</placeName>. He is the most successful dean we’ve ever had after <date>24 years</date>. They named the chair after him. He was the dean of all the deans of the medical schools of <placeName>the United States</placeName>. And <persName>Dick</persName> had a license plate that says, “NO ABUSE.” [Laughs.] And he talked about that and how we didn’t want to have any abuse for medical students, much more our patients or, you know, our staff.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BROSS">And so—so <persName>Dick</persName>’s a very smart, funny guy from <placeName>New York</placeName> and a <orgName>Princeton [University</orgName>] grad. He and I have talked a lot, but he—he has four sons and now seven grandchildren, and I still get—now I get to see him, whereas we—I’ve tried to stay out of his way for the time he was dean. But <persName>Dick</persName> would say, in response to the nice words you said, “Well, the pleasure wasn’t all yours.” [Laughs.] So thank you for your time.</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">Yes, thank you very much. It was so nice to speak with you.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">You can follow-up at any time, <persName>Hannah</persName>, if there is anything else you want to—</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I’m going to go ahead and stop—oh, great. Thank you so much.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Yes. [cross-talk; unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="MARKOWITZ">I’m going to go ahead and stop the recording now.</u>
      <u who="BROSS">Okay. </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
