<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="CAROTHERS"/>
        <person xml:id="ISAACS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">All right, this is <persName>Andrew [T.] Carothers</persName>. <date>Today</date> is <date>August 17th, 2015</date>. I’m interviewing <persName>John [D.] Isaacs</persName> by phone. I’m in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, and <persName>John</persName> is in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName> </u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Good. How are you?</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I’m doing well. So we’re going to start off the interview <date>today</date> with some biographical information, so let’s start with where and when were you born?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I was born <date>May 12th of 1945</date>, sort of the tail end of <name type="event">World War II</name>. I was born in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, and there’s a small story behind that. During <name type="event">World War II</name>, people forget—my father worked for the government, and during the war a number of government agencies were moved out of <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, just in case the Germans or the Japanese came bombing, we wouldn’t love the entire government at the same time. So we were moved—he worked for the [U.S.] <orgName>Securities and Exchange Commission</orgName>, so we moved to <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> for <date>about three years</date>, and that’s where I was born. More than you needed to know, but just for your information.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. And then I saw in the bio that you filled out that you then went to high school up in <placeName>White Plains</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>, so where did you grow up? Did you primarily grow up around <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> or did you move up to <placeName>New York</placeName> pretty early on in life?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">The answer I give frequently is I’m from <placeName>the East Coast</placeName>. <date>Three years</date> in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, then the family moved back to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, specifically <placeName>Silver Spring</placeName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, a suburb of <placeName>Washington</placeName>. As I said, my father was a government lawyer. And I went through elementary school, up to <date>age 12</date>, in <placeName>Silver Spring</placeName>. Moved to <placeName>White Plains</placeName>, new, another suburb, this time of <placeName>New York City</placeName>, in 1957—incidentally, <date>the same year</date> that the [then <placeName>New York</placeName>, now <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>] Giants and the [then <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>, now <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>] <orgName>Dodgers</orgName> left <placeName>New York</placeName> and went to <placeName>the West Coast</placeName>. And I went through junior high school and high school at <placeName>White Plains</placeName> public schools at that time. And my parents stayed in <placeName>White Plains</placeName> through the remainder of their lives, so I would go back and visit. So <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, <placeName>Silver Spring</placeName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, <orgName>White Plains</orgName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>, and <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, and that’s kind of up and down <placeName>the East Coast</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. Great. Well, that’s funny that you mentioned the <orgName>Giants</orgName> and <orgName>Dodgers</orgName> moving out because I’m from <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, so as a <orgName>San Francisco Giants</orgName> fan, we’re pretty happy about what happened in <date>1957</date>.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I won’t hold you personally responsible, but I’ll hold [Joseph] “<persName>Buzzie</persName>” <persName>Bavasi</persName> [pronounced buh-VAY-see]—is it?—and <persName>Horace</persName> [C.] Stoneham (I may have the names wrong) responsible for stealing the teams from <placeName>New York</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.] Yeah, yeah. And when you were in <placeName>Silver Springs</placeName> [sic], <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, what was it like growing up in <placeName>Maryland</placeName> and around <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, and with your father involved in government work, what was the environment like both at home and then at school and just—in that time, in <date>the late ’40s</date> or <date>early ’50s</date>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, my parents were fairly traditional in the sense that my mother usually stayed at home. As we grew older, she worked at a gift shop in <placeName>White Plains</placeName>, but she was home. She was the one who basically was in charge of discipline, making sure we studied and making sure we behaved and so on. My father was either busy at work or he was active in a lot of public interest organizations, various causes, from <orgName>American Civil Liberties Union</orgName>, [<orgName>National] Urban League</orgName>, prison reform, many other kinds of quote-unquote “good government” issues. So quite a lot, he was out, out of the house during <date>the day</date> but also out of the house during meetings, so the mother was the primary child rearer.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And you said that your dad was involved in a number of good government issues. Did he speak with you a lot about politics, growing up, and did his political beliefs and activism influence you as you became more politically active?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">That’s an interesting question. I’m not sure I can totally answer. I don’t know that we had many discussions, my father and I, about these kinds of issues, but certainly all four of his children—I have three siblings—all four of the children wound up on the left side of the spectrum, and that’s the way I grew up.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great, great. We’ll be interested to hear about those internships. And I think as we get to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> [College], we can talk about those, definitely.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, I think I’ve learned a lot more about the civil rights struggle since that time and not during that time. In other words, at this point, of course, I realized how dangerous it could have been and how a number of blacks and also whites were attacked for this civil rights work and having seen the movie <persName>Selma</persName> in <date>the last year</date> or two. But I don’t remember a particular fear that uh-oh, he’s gonna get himself in deep trouble there. I just thought it was another one of his strong—part of his belief in activism.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great, great. So let’s talk about your siblings now for a little bit. So you said you have three siblings. Are they brothers, sisters, older, younger?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes. [Both chuckle.] Older brother by <date>about five years</date> was involved in programming computers. That was his career. He wound up going to <orgName>Antioch College</orgName>, which was sort of a liberal, progressive—an unconventional college in <placeName>Yellow Springs</placeName>, <placeName>Ohio</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And were you close with your siblings, growing up? Did they influence you? Did you—you know, were you a big influence to them? Especially I’m thinking of your younger sister. What was your relationship like there?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">As with many families, we didn’t get along that well when we lived under the same roof, and when we had gone our separate ways to college and life beyond, we’ve gotten quite friendly, so <date>every couple of years</date> now we have a family reunion in <placeName>California</placeName> in <date>December</date>, around <date>Christmas</date> time, and go to each other’s—not all the time, of course, but significant events: marriages and <orgName>Bar Mitzvahs</orgName> and those sorts of things. So we are very close now. We weren’t growing up. And I’m not sure if I had any influence over them or they had much influence over us—over me. I’m sorry.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Cool.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">At least politically, you’re talking about.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That’s great.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yeah. So it sounds like—I have sort of an idea about your family. So I kind of wanted to go back to this idea of being from <placeName>the East Coast</placeName> and moving around, so you said when you were 12—correct?—you moved from <placeName>Silver Springs</placeName> [sic] up to <placeName>White Plains</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Correct. It’s <name type="event">Silver Spring</name>, by the way, without an “s,” not that it matters, but just so you know.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Silver—all right, <placeName>Silver Spring</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what prompted that move?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">My father had worked in <orgName>the Securities and Exchange Commission</orgName>, as I mentioned before, and went into private practice, corporate law in <placeName>New York City</placeName>. We had had a friend who was also a lawyer in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, and had gone on a similar move <date>about a year or two</date> before to <placeName>White Plains</placeName>, so we kind of knew about the area.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what was that move like for you? So at this point, you have lived in <placeName>Silver Spring</placeName> for <date>nine years</date>, and did it feel a little bit like you were uprooted and moved, or was it a natural transition, or what was the move like?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">In some way, the transition was eased—and this is something I probably should add in terms of life in <placeName>Silver Spring</placeName> and <placeName>White Plains</placeName>—I almost always went to a <date>summer</date> camp, one of these seven- or <date>eight-week</date> overnight places in <placeName>Lake Placid</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>, a great, progressive camp, where there’s horseback riding and canoeing and swimming and mountain climbing and arts and everything else. So when the move was made, I was off at <date>summer</date> camp, and I’m sure that helped ease the transition.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what was that next phase of your life like? What was it like living in <placeName>New York</placeName> and junior high school and high school? What was that experience?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, again, I’m talking about broader experience and my own experience. A lot of people—I remember high school much better than junior high school. One advantage of moving up in my seventh—I went up, and my first grade in <placeName>White Plains</placeName> was seventh grade, junior high school in those—in <date>those days</date>, seventh, eighth and ninth were junior; tenth, eleventh and twelfth were senior. I was a new kid at school, but everyone was a new kid at school. In other words, they had come from a number of different elementary schools in <orgName>White Plains</orgName>, so for everyone it was a new experience and meeting new people. So I didn’t feel I was coming to a situation where there were all these groups or cliques and I was the outsider.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. And you were saying that you were involved with debate and honor society. What did you learn from some of what you were doing in high school? What did you gain from some of those activities going into college?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Again, it wasn’t a formal honor society, but it was kind of an informal—I felt for <date>years</date> that the two most important courses I ever took—activities that I took outside of the classes—one was typing. Learning how to type made life much simpler ever since. This is before <date>the days</date> of computers, when they had manual typewriters and then electric typewriters but then moving on to computers was a very useful course I took during <date>one summer</date>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. And that gets into <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> a little bit. We’d love to sort of shift from life at home to life at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. But first, how did you end up at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? What made you interested in the school?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, I’ll give a couple of points in that. First of all, I felt I was reasonably bright and did well in high school, but I had a lot of friends who were so much brighter. [Chuckles.] In other words, I knew a lot of extremely intelligent people. My grades were good enough to apply to a few Ivy League schools, such as <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName> and some other schools. I can’t remember—I probably have a list somewhere, maybe <orgName>Syracuse</orgName> [University] was one of my eight schools in case I didn’t get into the other schools.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And why do you think that was, and what was the difficulty, like, in moving from a co-ed high school to an all-male college?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Because it’s very unrealistic to be in an all-male institution. This is a time you might be interested in dating and such things, activities, and that was pretty impossible. We had all these awful mixers, where we’d get a group of women coming in to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for <date>the weekend</date> or for the evening and we would go down to <placeName>Wellesley</placeName> [College] or [<orgName>Mount] Holyoke [College</orgName>] or <persName>Smith</persName> [College]. It was all so artificial.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">But I never felt—I don’t think I ever seriously considering switching schools. But, again, I probably should have gone to <orgName>the University of Pennsylvania</orgName> as it existed then and to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> as it exists now.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.] And so after you arrived at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, what were you involved in on campus? I know you said you did debate for <date>a couple of years</date>. In your bio, I saw that you did <orgName>ROTC [Reserve Officers’</orgName> <orgName>Training Corps</orgName>] for <date>a year</date>. How did you decide what you wanted to do on campus, and what did you pursue?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, I mentioned debating. Obviously, it was natural to from high school debating to college debating. I certainly like the outdoors, which—I mentioned, the <date>summer</date> camp I went to in <placeName>Lake Placid</placeName>—and <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> provided an awful lot of similar opportunities to go in the great outdoors. And I went on the freshman trip to [Mount] Moosilauke and did some mountain climbing occasionally and used some of the cabins there. So that was another activity.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yeah, I have a little bit of experience with that, myself. I think a lot of us do, when we arrive at college and all of a sudden those science or math classes are a little bit harder than they were in high school.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">[Chuckles.] That’s right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So going back to the <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, what did you not like about it, in particular?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I didn’t have any particular opposition to the military, but I certainly didn’t have any support for the military. It certainly wasn’t <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> that led to my objections. I mean, my <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name> feelings developed much more strongly toward senior <date>year</date> and then afterwards. I guess I just didn’t see the purpose of it. I didn’t see myself going into the military. And one of the things that I always objected to about military and to the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Foreign Service is ultimately how well you do depends on how well you get along with your superior. In other words, you’re always being rated by your superior officer, whether it’s the military or <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>. And that means you kind of have to kiss ass, to use the expression, and I was uncomfortable with that situation.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I’m sorry, one more thing: I wasn’t, at that point, nervous about the draft. The draft took hold of us more in junior and then senior year, and afterwards, where it came to be a dominant part of our lives.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And <orgName>ROTC</orgName>—just to clarify—it was your freshman year? It was your first semester on campus you joined <orgName>ROTC</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="ISAACS">One other thing about college—one of my other regrets at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is I didn’t join the fraternity system. I wasn’t part of a fraternity at all in high school. I wasn’t involved in college. I was a determined independent. But in retrospect, considering how important fraternity life was at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, I probably should have joined one. And I think there are some, a couple of fraternities that I could have fit in comfortably with. This whole idea of hazing, the other things you have to do to enter fraternities, at least in many cases, and a lot of the objectionable things fraternities do I’m sure I was not particularly interested in, and I was never a heavy drinker, either. In fact, I probably drank very little at all in high school. I did some in college but not a great deal.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And without the fraternity sort of creating a natural circle around you, where did you find your social circle on campus?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">People I met in the dorms and classes, the normal way. I mean, again, it’s the kind of the way I met people in high school in classes and in my community, and so it would be my dorms—at the dorm, people I knew in the dorms and people in my classes. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And this is kind of an aside, but I think you’ll appreciate this: <persName>Russell Sage</persName> is still around. It’s still beautiful, and it actually does have the fireplaces. You’re not allowed to use them anymore.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">[Laughs.] Okay. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">But they’re still aesthetically pleasing.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Okay. Good to know. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yeah. And so speaking of classes, you were a government major, correct?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Correct.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what got you interested in government?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, I think I’ve described it earlier. I guess I was always interested to some extent in government and politics and followed it since certainly high school, maybe junior high and before. I don’t know. It seemed to be a natural progression. I thought of history as a major, but I wasn’t sure where that led, and international relations wasn’t a regular course major. I think it was kind of an interdisciplinary course. You could put something together. But politics and government seemed to be natural for me.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure. And did you feel pressure from your family, with your family’s history of being active and involved in government, to sort of keep the family tradition going by being a government major and then—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">No.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—getting involved—no?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">No, I didn’t feel any pressure. I think—this is an analogy or metaphor, which you may or may not buy, but I think <placeName>the United States</placeName> is most effective when it sets an example for the world and lets people decide if they want it. They’re more likely to if they do it voluntarily, if they choose. And I think with the family, my parents set an example, and I liked it and adopted a lot of it, but it wasn’t—they didn’t pressure me. The only slight pressure I felt in senior year in college was whether to go to law school or not, but we can get into that, again, later.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure, sure. And are there any particular classes or professors that you had at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> that sort of shaped how you viewed the world or shaped what you wanted to get into after college?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Certainly some. There’s a guy named <persName>Larry [K.] Smith</persName>, who was an instructor—as opposed to a full-time professor in history, and I wrote—I think it counted as a two-course credit paper on the rise of <orgName>the Republican Party</orgName> in the <placeName>South</placeName>—again, hearkening back to both political science—it was a history class, but a paper on political science, really, and how <orgName>the Republican Party</orgName> developed from a small part of the <placeName>South</placeName> to eventually taking it over. So that—and then that same professor wound up eventually as chief of staff for Sen. <persName>Gary [W.] Hart</persName>, so I met him—I mean, I kept in touch with him in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, and worked with him in <placeName>Iran</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. And while you were at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, did you have a sense that you wanted to go into, go work for <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> or for the federal government or an interest in—you said—you were talking a little bit about potentially going to law school. I guess we can get into that a little bit. What was your thought process there as you got a little bit older in college and thought of post-graduation plans?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, at one point I put together a list of possible jobs, a lot of which had to do with <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, so politics was one, and government service was one, working <orgName>Capitol Hill</orgName>, working as a lobbyist. I was also interested in urban planning, so it was a possibility that I could go to a <placeName>Boston</placeName> or <placeName>New York</placeName> or some city to help in the running of municipal government. But everything seemed to point me towards public service in this choice, in this listing of possible jobs that I’d eventually go into.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. Great. And before we jump into your experience in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, which I would love to talk about, just a little bit more about sort of what it was like being at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in the <orgName>mid-’60s</orgName>, so in <date>1973</date> [sic] Ngô Đình Diệm and [President <persName>John F.]</persName> <persName>Kennedy</persName> are assassinated. In ’64, you have <placeName>the Tonkin Gulf</placeName> resolu- [<placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin incident]</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Sixty-three.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><date>Sixty-three</date>. Oh, yeah, yeah, ’<date>63</date>, and then in ’64 you have <placeName>the Tonkin Gulf</placeName> incident, and <persName>Americanization</persName> sort of begins <date>the next year</date>. What was the political atmosphere like on campus, and what were your thoughts about what was going on in the world as someone who is very interested in international relations?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Sure. Give me a ten-second break to get a bottle of water, and I’ll be right back.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Firstly, <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> wasn’t a major presence in <date>the early years</date>. I mean, I’m sure I followed it, and I’m sure I followed—well, the <persName>Kennedy</persName> assassination was one of those moments in history where I remember where I was, and most people remember where they were when they heard, sort of like <date>9/11 later</date> [the attacks on <date>September 11, 2001</date>] and, for some people, [President] <persName>Franklin</persName> [D.] <persName>Roosevelt</persName>’s death in <date>1945</date>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And then what happened senior year? So that would have been <date>1966</date>, ’67. What changed for you? What changed for your classmates then that made it a big deal?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I think people—and I considered myself politically engaged, but I think there are people more politically engaged and more sensitive to what we were doing in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and so the people organized a few protests, including maybe a <date>weekly</date>, quiet circle of people around the [Dartmouth] Green, to protest the war, during the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> graduation there’s a protest, and I participated in those, but I didn’t consider myself that active, and I didn’t consider myself so antiwar.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So at <date>the end of that year</date>, in <placeName>mid-’67</placeName>, you graduate <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and you go to <persName>Hopkins</persName>—correct?—the <persName>Hopkins</persName> program in <placeName>Italy</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">In <placeName>Bologna</placeName>, <placeName>Italy</placeName>. And let me say one thing there but to go back for one second, before I forget it—Unless I’ve already forgotten it—[Pause.] I’ll get to that point again.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so in <placeName>Italy</placeName>—or, first, before getting into sort of the activism in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, can you tell me a little bit more just about this program in Bologna? Because it sounds like it wasn’t necessarily a traditional graduate school experience. It was kind of a special trip.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">No, that’s not right. It’s like a lot of—well, first of all—I’m going back again; occasionally back and forth here—one of my best semesters at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was a term in  <placeName>France</placeName>, in <placeName>Caen</placeName>, C-a-e-n. And it was a great program, and I enjoyed it very much, the travel and the study over there. And so what this Bologna Center program was was <persName>Johns Hopkins</persName> was just transported with a bunch of students, both American and European, to <placeName>Europe</placeName>. But it’s like a lot of the foreign study programs for undergraduates and graduate students <date>today</date>, so it was a traditional program. We had courses on wars and courses on French history and courses on what’s going on in <placeName>Italy</placeName> and so on. So I would call it very much a traditional program, but a traditional program overseas. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="ISAACS">—it seems as though a very high proportion of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students and other university students go off to study abroad, undergraduate and graduate, and that’s what I did, but it was earlier than—it wasn’t quite so common then as it is now, but I certainly wouldn’t say that it’s not traditional.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. Okay, okay, yeah. I guess I misunderstood a little bit there. And what made you decide to want specifically do this program abroad, <placeName>Italy</placeName> versus a comparable program in the <placeName>States</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">As I said before, it ultimately became a choice between going to law school, which everyone I knew didn’t like, and <date>nine months</date> studying but not studying too hard and traveling around <placeName>Europe</placeName> and doing a lot of skiing with the European group of students. Interesting courses, interesting times, but not too hard work. And eventually I came to realize that, you know, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students on average were much higher quality than graduates in international relations. So it was more fun than law school would ever have been.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Nice, nice. Did being exposed to a lot of European students influence some of your political attitudes and beliefs and how you looked at international relations?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I’m not sure I can cite specifics, but I have to assume yes. I think most of the student body was anti-war, and the war was not popular in <placeName>Europe</placeName>. It was not popular in the rest of the world, kind of like our operations in <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>. <placeName>The United States</placeName> thinks we’re doing a great thing and helping the rest of the world, and the rest of the world looks at it and say, “Why are you doing this?” So I think it must have had some influence, not that there was anything direct, but I think the hostility in <placeName>Europe</placeName> had some influence on me. And when you go abroad, you tend to look at <placeName>the United States</placeName> from a little bit of an outside perspective instead of solely from within.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And through this process of going and looking from an outside perspective, that made you turn a little bit more strongly against the war? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">It was a gradual process. I’m sure that was part of it. And, as I mentioned, we had some demonstrations in <placeName>Bologna</placeName>. It jut kept growing and growing. As the war grew, we had a greater understanding of what was happening and felt—I think more and more information was coming out how the American leaders had misled the American people about the war, and we learned more about it. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><orgName>Gotcha</orgName>, gotcha. And then, so, while you’re at graduate school, you noted in your bio that that <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> came knocking and offered you a position, so what was your reaction to <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> coming to you, and what was your reaction to the option of being able to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> but through <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> and not through the military?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Very mixed feelings then, very mixed feelings in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, very mixed feelings now. As I was debating what the heck to do if the draft board came calling, I talked to a lot of people. I talked to <orgName>Quaker</orgName> counselors. I considered going to <placeName>Canada</placeName>, considered a conscientious objector, considered all sorts of options. And whatever the choice was that I’d make wasn’t a good choice, but it was being forced on me. No ultimate moving on beyond that.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. And so, then, after you accepted that position with <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> and you graduated from <orgName>the Hopkins Center</orgName> in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, you went back to <placeName>D.C.</placeName> for your training as a <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officer, correct?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Right. <date>The first year</date>, by the way, of graduate school was in Bologna. <date>The second year</date> was here in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, near <placeName>Dupont Circle</placeName>, where the <orgName>Johns Hopkins</orgName> campus was and still is. So during that time, there were more and more antiwar demonstrations. I never participated in the—I was never radicalized. I never was part of the Weathermen [formally, <orgName>the Weather Underground Organization</orgName>] or <orgName>SDS</orgName>—I don’t remember what <persName>SDS</persName> stands for—Students for a Democratic Society. I never was interested in pouring blood in the files of the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> or violent confrontation. But I was more engaged in the peaceful protest of the war in <placeName>Washington</placeName> <date>that second year</date>. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. I didn’t realize you had been back to <placeName>Washington</placeName> at <date>the end of ’68</date>. So <date>’68</date> was <date>a big year</date>, especially in <placeName>Washington</placeName>—right?—with the assassinations of <persName>Martin Luther King Jr.</persName>, [Senator <persName>Robert F.]</persName> “Bobby” Kennedy, [President <persName>Richard M.]</persName> <persName>Nixon</persName>’s election, and then a number of protests that did turn violent in cities like <placeName>D.C.</placeName> So what was your take on sort of <date>the year of ’68</date>, where, at <date>the end of that year</date>, a lot of people in the country felt sort of like all hell was breaking loose in <placeName>the United States</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">That’s because it was breaking loose. [Chuckles.] First of all, again, I was in <placeName>Bologna</placeName> ’67-’68. I believe the <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> assassination—yeah, I don’t believe, I know the <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> assassination and the <persName>Robert Kennedy</persName> assassination occurred when I was still in <placeName>Italy</placeName>. Now, that was <date>the first half of the year</date>. I don’t remember precisely when. So I missed the direct, I don’t know, impact of the assassinations, especially in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName> After <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> was assassinated, there were major riots in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, riots that scarred the city for <date>decades</date> after, but I was in <placeName>Italy</placeName> for that. And when <persName>Robert Kennedy</persName> was assassinated, I remember seeing a headline in an Italian newspaper, saying, “Kennedy Assassinated,” and I thought, That was <date>1963</date>. Why are they writing about it now? I didn’t realize that it was <persName>Robert Kennedy</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so you returned from <placeName>Italy</placeName> in the middle of ’68, are up in <placeName>Westchester</placeName> for <date>the summer</date>, come back, have <date>a year</date> at <orgName>Dupont Circle</orgName> with <orgName>Johns Hopkins</orgName>,—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—and then after that, in ’69, begin your year of training in <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, in preparation for going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Right. Actually, one other thing that happened during <date>the second year</date>—<date>the second year</date> of <orgName>Johns Hopkins</orgName> in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, at <orgName>Dupont Circle</orgName>, was I went for my <orgName>Army</orgName> physical in <placeName>Fort Holabird</placeName>, <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>. That also helped bring the war closer to me personally.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Right. And then I saw you noted in your bio that you did not get a medical exemption there, so that made the draft a little bit more real.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">It definitely was real. I mentioned <orgName>Quaker</orgName> counseling, and I mentioned a lot of us were searching for any possible way to avoid the war, including physical—some physical deformity, like flat feet, but none of that seemed to apply to me, so it seemed to me I had the choice: I was pretty sure that the draft board would draft me, and I wasn’t sure what I’d do in response to that until <orgName>the State Department</orgName> came along.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And in <date>1969</date> what training did you get in preparation for going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, some of it was how to be a <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officer, what diplomatic life was like and that sort of thing. An awful lot of it, the predominant part of <date>the year</date> was <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> language training. And while I was doing this <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> training, I participated in some of the—a couple of the great protest marches in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, usually as a—oh, it was marshal; in other words, someone to help keep things moving along, keeping things peaceable.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And were there ever any more consequences or a threat of consequences for this protest action from your superiors at <orgName>the State Department</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, it certainly didn’t stop them from sending me to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> to work for <date>thirteen and a half months</date>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">And I believe I was told that if I continued in <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>, I would have gone to my next post to <placeName>Tokyo</placeName>, <placeName>Japan</placeName>. I don’t know that there were any consequences, but what might have been put in my file, I don’t know. And I’ve always been tempted to try to look at my file and see what might have been put in there, but I don’t know. I mean, could these protests have been a black mark in my record, permanent record and hindered a career? I don’t know that. I wouldn’t be surprised, but there’s no evidence one way or another.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And clearly there were some other <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officials who were also protesting and, you know, who signed onto this letter, and did you find—amongst the people who were working at <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>, did they generally tilt one way? Were they pro-war, antiwar? What was the political environment like at <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">My major objection to <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers during <date>those days</date> was predominantly they felt the war couldn’t be won; it was a dumb war, but they didn’t feel the war was wrong. In other words, by that point I felt that what we were doing in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was morally wrong, was evil. We were killing a lot of people for a cause, and people should have been objecting to the war because—right or wrong, not because we’re losing the war. So in other words, I think people have kind of give up on the war, but they weren’t morally opposed, and I felt that was a distinction that I felt personally.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><orgName>Gotcha</orgName>, gotcha. Okay. And then—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I’m just trying to think: ’69, ’<date>70</date>, and <persName>Nixon</persName> obviously had been elected by <date>1968</date>. I don’t know exactly when <orgName>Vietnamization</orgName> began, the process of, in theory, turning the war over to the Vietnamese and start withdrawing troops, but I think it was widely accepted, at least among the Foreign Service officers, that we weren’t winning the war and it was time to begin getting out.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So was the sense amongst <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> that Vietnamization and decreasing American involvement was less turning it over to the Vietnamese so that they could win but turning it over to the Vietnamese so that when we withdrew it looked like it was a Vietnamese loss and not an American loss?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I would say I and others probably felt this more in retrospect than during that time. I mean, we spent <date>many years</date> building up a <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> military, building up a government, building up the economic infrastructure, and we knew the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> troops were withdrawing. We had—I felt, at least personally, and I expect most people had no idea what would be happening. I’m sure to some people it was clear that what we were doing is a cover for getting out, but we’re doing it slowly, and people knew the war was lost. But I’m not sure people—I assumed that once the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> got out, that <orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName> and the South Vietnamese government would collapse.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. Got it. So let’s—you know, we’ve been talking for a little over an hour. Let’s jump into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. First, do you want to take a quick break at all, or should we keep going?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Keep going unless you want to take a break.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Let’s keep going, then. So let’s jump into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So you arrived in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date>early 1970</date>? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yes, okay. So you arrived in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date>early 1970</date>, and what was the experience like of arriving in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, in retrospect, I always was amazed how my parents never communicated worry. Here, I was going to a war zone, where a lot of people were being killed, American and Vietnamese, and yet I never felt they were afraid for me. It’s interesting in retrospect. I don’t know why.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">So it was a very peaceful life in that province. Eight hundred refugees had been sent there, as I say, from <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>, by the South Vietnamese government. My job was to help to resettle them, moving from tents, which were there when I arrived. Eventually, they were given housing allowances and tin roof[s] and wood to build their own houses. 	</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">So anyhow—I sort of rambled here. But sent to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. First stop is the airport. Very quiet, peaceful. Central province. Very quiet and peaceful. Eventually—I was there <date>about six or eight months</date> in that province. Able to travel all over the province during <date>the day</date>. Not at night, because the Viet Cong controlled the night. Went into town, met people, had meals, we went swimming in the ocean. This is combined—a few soldiers and a few, just two or three of us civilians. And we went swimming with a couple of soldiers just keeping an eye on things with their guns handy, but nothing ever happened with that.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure. And just to clarify: Which province were you in, in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? What was the name of the province?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">It was called <placeName>Binh Tuy</placeName>, B-i-n-h; second word T-u-y. Along <placeName>the east coast</placeName>. The province to the south of us was called Vung-Tau, V-u-n-g, T-a-u, and that was a province managed by the Australians. In other words, <placeName>the United States</placeName> was the predominant foreign power in the country. Australians were managing one province, and the South Koreans were active in other parts of the country. But, again, along the coast, in a very rural area. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure. And <persName>Binh Tuy</persName> was south of <placeName>Saigon</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Pretty much due east.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Due east, okay. So on the coast, due east.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Right. Some of the most dangerous areas and the heaviest fighting were along the demilitarized zone between <placeName>North</placeName> and <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, which was an awful place to be and then in the delta, the very southern part, south of <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, again where the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> were very strong. I suspect there would have been more war, more engagement in the province I was in and the region I was in, but the <persName>Nixon</persName>-ordered cross-border operation—again, I think it was <date>1970</date>, while I was still in training—pushed the war to the west, so I was an accidental beneficiary of pushing the war to the west. I objected to the military incursion into <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>, but I directly benefited from it.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. And why you were helping resettle these refugees, what was sort of your day-to-day work like, and what were your main interactions with the refugees, or were you often interacting with the refugees, themselves, or—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes. Directly, we were visiting the tent camps and then visiting the settlements as the people were trying to build a house elsewhere, so, yes, I would go along as an American adviser, along with a refugee official, with whom I had a pretty good relationship, and we would talk to the refugees and see what we could do to help them out and help get some of the programs, American aid programs, directly to the people.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. And in the refugee—I forget the title that you said that he was, the refugee official. He was a South Vietnamese official?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes, <persName>mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. And in terms of—what did these interactions with these refugees change how you were thinking about the war? What was sort of your emotional response to working with these people who had been displaced from <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> and were now back in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">What I learned most about these refugees as well as most South Vietnamese people is they didn’t favor the North Vietnamese or <placeName>the Viet Cong</placeName>. They didn’t favor the South Vietnamese. They just wanted to be left alone, to get along with their lives and build towards the future. In other words, there was a strong ideological feeling in the government and the military, both Vietnamese and American, but for ordinary Vietnamese, they didn’t favor either side. They just wanted to be left alone. So that was one strong feeling I developed very quickly.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">—it was something designed for Vietnamese people to eat, but they wouldn't eat it, so they fed it to their cows and their sheep and other animals.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I think <orgName>Ford</orgName>, yeah.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Developed all these measurements of success: hamlet evaluation system and other systems that might have worked for <orgName>Ford</orgName> or might have worked for the auto industry and did not work in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And so, again, one of the things I was able to do is point to the lie of those statistics.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And, yeah, I would love to get into the interactions with reporters. That was one thing I was reading in the essay that you wrote. Was that essay for your 50th—for the 50th reunion magazine?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes, the essay I wrote was about that. And, again—I’ve already said this. I had mixed feelings before I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, when in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and still have mixed feelings. But one of the ways I was able to—and I’ll use the term “assuage my guilt” was working with reporters to provide useful information to them on what was really going on in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And how did you—so what was the thought process behind wanting to speak with reporters? So part of it was assuaging guilt, and was that the main driver behind wanting to speak to reporters?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">When I had signed up for the program and was going <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I talked to people about going and whether I should go or not, and I don’t remember exactly who, but some people suggested, “You know, one of the things you could do is report from within.” I don’t want to compare myself to [<persName>Edward] Snowden</persName>, and I don’t like what <persName>Snowden</persName> did in revealing all the secrets [regarding the types and volume of data collected by <orgName>the U.S. National Security Agency</orgName>], but the argument was being made to me, and I accepted it, was in some ways you can do more from within the “Green Machine” (and I don’t mean <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> but the <orgName>Army</orgName>) than from without, that there’s always—these days we use the term “whistleblowers”—there’s always room for whistleblowers to tell people what was going on. So it was both assuagement of guilt and I was told that I actually could provide a useful service.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Wow. And how did you find these reporters to get in contact with?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Again, I think it was some people in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, who told me, “Here are some reporters you could look up.” One of the reporters worked for sort of a news service, probably a left-wing news service. I must have been given a couple of <orgName>New York Times</orgName> and <orgName>Washington Post</orgName> reporters’ names. And I wrote about this in the essay. I had a lot of interactions with media since—at that time and since. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So clearly in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> leaking was one of the most powerful ways that you could contribute, but what was the risk that you were taking on by leaking this information to the press?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, I could have been caught. [Chuckles.] I could have been kicked out of <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>. I could have been kicked out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I mean, that’s the risk. If I had wanted a career in <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>, and I was always dubious I’d stay in for a full career, that career hope would have been terminated. And when I gave the story about the plan to move—oh, I don't remember—tens of thousands of Vietnamese around as a defensive maneuver, someone suspected me of that, but nothing ever happened. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what was the experience like being able to see information that you had leaked make it onto the front page of <orgName>The New York Times</orgName> and have a tangible impact on the actions of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> government in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">To use the term again, it helped assuage the guilt. I felt I was doing some good, even though I was part of a system that was not doing good. So the American military and the pacification program were negative, but I was able to undermine, in a small way—I don’t want to say it led to <date>the end of the Vietnam War</date> or anything like that—but in a small; way, I was helping to undermine the war.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And was leaking to reporters—was that a relatively common practice within <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>? Did you know other officials in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> who were doing it at the same time as you or what can you say about that?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I don’t know anyone else who was doing it. I can’t believe I was the only one, and if not—there could have been leaking also by American military officials, not just <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName>. And a lot of very aggressive reporters were going around, getting information on what was going on. I don’t know if you would consider it leaking, but I think a lot of people were talking to reporters, but I do not know of any other <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officer who took the path I did.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. And just to sort of go back real quickly—a question that I had about CORDS and sort of U.S.-South Vietnamese relationships—South Vietnamese, other—sorry—relationships, it sounds like there was a whole lot of cultures trying to work together here, but between the American culture and the South Vietnamese culture and then the different cultures of the variety of government organizations that were working within the pacification program, so what was the balance like there? It sounded like you were saying that the balance between—there was a cultural disconnect between <placeName>the South Vietnamese</placeName> and the Americans, but also what was the balance like between the variety of different American groups?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Good question. Can I have a two-minute bathroom break?</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Absolutely. Sure.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Can I just leave the phone off the hook and just come back, or do you want to take a break, too?</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure, we can just leave the phone off the hook. I’ll pause the recording real quick, and then we’ll pick it back up.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Okay. Thank you.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And we’re good to go. </u>
      <u who="ISAACS">There were vast numbers of Americans there in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, with a variety of roles. And obviously, not surprising in such a situation, there’s confusion, disorganization and conflict among the various branches. For <placeName>the United States</placeName>, the five hundred—and I think it peaked about 540,000 American soldiers, that was the top of the chain, the food chain. But those soldiers were divided into various ways, including some fighting the war, an awful lot back in bases and back in coordination efforts, but also in every province and every district there was supposed to be an American team that was shadowing, shall we say, the South Vietnamese people.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And the different elements of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> effort in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> gave different objectives for what they wanted to prioritize in the counterinsurgency effort, or were people pretty uniform in what they thought the best course of attack would be?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">No, there were major differences over military strategy, and there were major differences between the objectives of the military and civilians. This is a debate that was carried on then, and since then it’s been extended to <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and extends to <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>. Do you win wars through brute military force or do you win wars by civilian assistance programs, trying to build up the infrastructure, the South Vietnamese infrastructure, economic, military and government? The military, of course, tends towards military solutions; civilian tend towards non-military solutions. But disagreement over the best way to proceed—again, that has been reflected in future wars.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Right. So the pacification program, then, did not win the hearts and minds of the Vietnamese people.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Precisely. And it became ironic in more recent times when <persName>George W. Bush</persName>, as president, talked about winning the hearts and minds of the Iraqi people. And some people involved in the management of the <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> conflicts talked about this CORDS program, this pacification program in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> as the model for what we could do in <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and what we can do in <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>. But to me, if that’s the model, it’s a failure model. We were totally unsuccessful.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. And so before we move on from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, is there any sort of gaps in your experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that you want to touch on before we move on? Those are sort of some of the main ideas that I had.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Sure. You asked about the leaking, if that had many consequences, and the answer is I don’t believe it did. I mentioned I started out <date>the first six or seven months</date> in <placeName>Bình Tuy</placeName>, a small rural province. I was then promoted to regional refugee head in the town or city of Biên Hòa, which was about an hour from <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. So whatever I did in the province didn’t seem to negatively affect my chances for advancement in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so going off of the safety element in this, one thing you touched on earlier was that the South Vietnamese and Americans controlled <date>the day</date> and then the Viet Cong controlled the night. So what was that experience like?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">At least in the province I was and I suspect lots of other places in the country, but I’m sorry. Keep going.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">What experience was that like [sic], knowing that you could work with these refugees during <date>the day</date> but then as soon as, you know, sunset came around, the Americans really didn’t have that much power to, you know, influence the people that we were trying to help and that oftentimes, you know, as much as <placeName>the United States</placeName> would try these pacification efforts, as soon as night came around, <placeName>the Viet Cong</placeName> would come in and could be more influential to the population. So what was your reaction to that? And did that contribute to this feeling that what we were doing was kind of futile?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Absolutely. It certainly contributed to that feeling. It isn’t that  the Viet Cong did come in every night, but you knew that they could. If I would have dinner with some Vietnamese friends in the small town in the province I was in, when it started getting dark I said, “You better get home.” And it was practical evidence that we weren’t winning the war. We could be safe at certain times and certain areas, but we did not control the country, and especially we didn’t control the night. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And did any of the refugees and Vietnamese that you were working with tell you about any experiences they had had with the Viet Cong coming in at night?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">No, no one told me. One of the things I’m not proud of is, although I spent a year learning Vietnamese, I didn’t learn it very well, especially when I realized what the program was really like. So it wasn’t as if I could walk up to people and say, “Tell me about your experiences in <placeName>Phnom Penh</placeName>,” “Tell me about your experiences with the Vietnamese officials.” I didn’t have that ability. And when I was talking to people, Vietnamese people in those villages and the tent city and the houses, I was doing it with a Vietnamese interpreter, and it worked fine, but it wasn’t as if I could get the story behind the story. And I did not.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. Got it. And were there ever any instances where you were worried for your safety because of the Viet Cong’s power at night in this province?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">No. The only time—I mentioned the one time when there was an attack nearby in our province senior headquarters We had 30, 40 military and a few of us civilians. We thought we could be—in fact, that was the one time they told me—I was armed, at least with hand grenades. I was more afraid I would blow up me rather than anybody else.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">And I think I mentioned I didn’t carry a weapon. So that was a time of nervousness. And the other time is traveling over the jungles in helicopters. I always felt, and others did too, you’re vulnerable to get shot down. That probably happened infrequently, but it certainly happened. So those the main personal feelings of fear of being shot at or being killed that I felt. Most of the time, almost most of the time, almost all the time, I did not feel that way.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. Got it. Okay. So let’s move on, if you feel like we’ve adequately covered that experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, to your journey out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, because you had an interesting route to leaving the country.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I knew enough about bureaucracy that if I quit in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I’d be called in for <date>two weeks</date> of meetings with all sorts of officials, trying to find out what my motivation is, why I was leaving, trying to convince me I was making a mistake, and making my life kind of difficult for <date>those two weeks</date>. So in consultation with a couple of friends, including a reporter who, by the way, since then worked for <orgName>the National Catholic Reporter</orgName> in <placeName>Kansas</placeName> and still works there, worked out a situation of, nothing better to call it than deception—they regularly pay for <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> (that’s rest and recreation trips). And one time I went to <placeName>Australia</placeName>; one time I went to <placeName>Malaysia</placeName>, for example.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And did you find that you encountered any difficulties with the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> government or, you know, not necessarily retribution, because I don’t know how much they could have done at that point, but animosity from people you have worked with at <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> over leaving the country in this manner and then sending this letter to <orgName>The New York Times</orgName> to be published?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">There might have been some hostility or a lot of hostility directed to me by a few people at that time, but by that time I was blissfully traveling across the world for <date>three weeks</date>, in <placeName>India</placeName>, <placeName>Kashmir</placeName>, <placeName>Turkey</placeName>, <placeName>Israel</placeName>, a couple of other countries, I think, so there was no personal hostility directed towards me during that time, and partly because they couldn’t, and when I got back to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, I did not feel any hostility.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. And why did you decide to leave <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> when you did?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Partly selfish reasons. I think I turned 26 and/or the latest version of the draft—I don’t know if you knew that there was a lottery system and you got a low number, you’re likely to get drafted, and a high number, you’re unlikely to get drafted, and I had gotten a higher number in the latest—in the most recent draft lottery. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And you left in <date>1971</date>? Correct?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Correct.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. And the election was also in <date>1971</date>?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes. And it turned out to be an election between Prime Minister <persName>Thieu</persName> and Prime Minister <persName>Thieu</persName>—in other words, he didn’t have any opposition.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">So a one-party election. This happens from time to time in a variety of countries.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So, obviously, <orgName>Thieu</orgName> stayed in control, and what did you think about that election and really not having a competitive election in a country where we were trying to, you know, ostensibly instill a democracy?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">One more dramatic example of how we were trying to influence events and trying to bring democracy to <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> and we were unable to. Our hands, of course, weren’t clean in previous instances in the history of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, where we helped orchestrate the assassination or at least the departure from power of President <persName>Ngô Đình Diệm</persName>, D-I-E-M. I don’t know that we ordered assassinations, but we certainly didn’t stop it from happening. And this election was just one more—adding one more brick to the pile, shall we say.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so in <date>’71</date>, you leave <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, send this letter, and then what do you do—what do you do after that? You said you were traveling around the world for <date>three weeks</date>. What was that experience like, of having finally left <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, finally having sort of exited a war that you felt very morally opposed to? What was that like?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I can’t exactly remember, but I think it had to be somewhat “free at last, free at last.” I was a part of the war. It was a very mixed experience. I was fortunate in what I was doing, that I wasn’t threatened, didn’t feel threatened, but on the other hand, it still was a very difficult situation, full of difficult choices. I felt as part of <orgName>the “Green Machine</orgName>,” I think, and the <orgName>Army</orgName> “Green Machine” and not the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> “Green Machine.” And I was free of that, and then could move on with the rest of my life. I think that’s how I felt.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what did moving on with the rest of your life entail? What did you do after you got back from this?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Well, I think I mentioned before, I had some skepticism about <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> as a career. I thought it was a nice thing to do for two, three tours and then decide whether I wanted to stay in or not, but skeptical in part because I didn’t like the way you have to kowtow to your superiors. So I knew it was time that I could decide what I wanted to do as a career. In other words, I’d been to college, I’d been to graduate school, I’d been to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Now what would I want to do?</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what were you doing at that first job?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I was foreign policy legislative representative, so I was dealing with the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> budget, foreign policy issues by and large. I remember there was a sale of AWACs planes [airborne early warning and control aircraft; <orgName>Boeing E-3 Sentry</orgName>] to <placeName>Saudi Arabia</placeName> that was controversial. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I’ll be back again in two minute.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Sorry. At this point I’m drinking too much water. But I’m back.	</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">No worries.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I was also involved in some of the major controversy over nuclear weapons issues like building a new MX missile [LGM-118A Peacekeeper], which was a controversy that engulfed at least a certain part of <placeName>Washington</placeName> for <date>a number of years</date>, where the administration was proposing to build 200 and we eventually built 50 of them. There was controversy over building a missile defense system around the country. It was controversial at the time.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And were you involved with other antiwar movement—protests or, you know, other legislative initiatives after the war, in addition to—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Yes. By the way (this is connected), <orgName>the U.S. Congress</orgName> cut off funding, and it was controversial at that time, certainly in the executive branch and certainly with some conservatives, but by then, of course, Americans had washed their hands of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>. It was widely accepted that the war was wrong to fight and couldn’t be won and we should have been out of there a long time ago.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And getting into a little bit more about sort of some of your reflections n <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, how has <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> influenced your attitudes on American power and how <placeName>the United States</placeName> interacts with other countries?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I have been strongly influenced by my experience but also, talking to various military and civilian experts, that there are severe limits on American power. We may have been, and probably still are, the most powerful country in the world, certainly the largest economy, not the largest military but probably the most powerful military, and yet there are limits on American power, and <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> was a shocking experience to Americans because of that.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And do you think that attitude amongst military leadership largely comes from the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Absolutely. I think there was something ingrained, burned in the brains of the military then and ever since. I think the military—I always have been impressed by the military people I tended to meet, very bright and able and common sense. And I think that the military spent a lot of time studying the lessons of the war, as it always has done, studied the lessons of <name type="event">World War II</name> and <name type="event">World War I</name>, studied the lessons of <name type="event">World War II</name> and realized this was not the kind of war we should be fighting, this is not the kind of war we can win, and this is not the kind of war we should get involved in in the future. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And speaking of <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>, one person you talked about in your essay is <persName>Matthew</persName> [P.] Hoh [pronouncing it HAH], <persName>Matthew Hoh</persName> [pronouncing it HOE],—</u>
      <u who="ISAACS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—with whom you talked about your relationship with him a little bit. Do you think his experience, leaking information—or resigning from <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> in protest, getting a lot of publicity for that—have you talked—when you’ve talked to him, has his experience reminded you of your experience or do you think that the atmosphere and sort of the American attitudes on war and on American intervention led him to have a different experience?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I think what he did very much paralleled what I did, and when I read about what he did and when his resignation—he had fought—I think he fought in <name type="event">the Iraq war</name> and served as a civilian in <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> and was extremely competent but resigned when he felt we were not winning the war and we could not win the war. And he resigned in a major public way. Again, it was in <orgName>The New York Times</orgName>. So I saw him as a kindred folk, that what he did and what I did was a common experience.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Nice. And do you think that after <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and then, <date>a few decades later</date>, <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>—do you think we’re going to have another one of these experiences, or do you think that, you know, if <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> didn’t engrain it firmly enough in the American psyche, that <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> have?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I would give a more definitive experience. Until <orgName>the Islamic State</orgName>, I-S-I-S, I-S-I-L—again, all these different names—arose and brought more horrific, 1,000-year-old practices of slaughter of innocents, of occupying areas and wiping out peoples, of taking sex slaves, all the other things that have been reported—there’s an age-old dilemma the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> faces: A lot of awful things are happening in the world, whether it’s in <placeName>Rwanda</placeName> or <placeName>Middle East</placeName> now or <placeName>Crimea</placeName> [<placeName>the Crimean Peninsula</placeName>], where we have this feeling, “We gotta do something about it,” and it’s awfully hard as an American, with a can-do spirit, to say, “We can’t do anything constructive, so we shouldn’t do anything.”</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">On a somewhat unrelated note, you talked in your essay—now, this was another thing that you talked about that you’ve been involved in since <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that I found particularly interesting. You talked about how you’ve done some work on international initiatives with <persName>William Colby</persName>, who headed up the pacification program when you arrived as well as <persName>Robert McNamara</persName> and <persName>McGeorge Bundy</persName>, two men with whom I imagine you disagreed on quite a number of things, especially how <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> was being waged. So what was that experience like, to go from being, you know, in an antagonistic relationship with these leaders to then being on the same team as them?</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">Confirmation that life is full of ironies, confirmation that no permanent friends and no permanent enemies, confirmation that people I used to regard as war criminals in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> were actually doing some productive work I agreed with in other spheres, including nuclear weapons. It’s an odd situation. It was an odd feeling, but one of the major advocates for abolition of nuclear weapons was <persName>Robert McNamara</persName>, who was one of the chief architects of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">All right. Well, is there anything else about your experiences since <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that you want to talk about? Those were sort of the key points that I fixated on.</u>
      <u who="ISAACS">I’m sure there are other things that I could think of, and if I d and if I think they’re absolutely vital, I might call you, but I think you’ve been—you’ve been pretty comprehensive in the questions and our discussion at this point. So I can’t think of anything major that has been left out. I don’t know. If I think of something brilliant that I should have said, should I talk to you and would you continue, or not, the interview? I just ask. My sense is I won’t, but if there is such a—something I think of.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Definitely. Here, sure. Let me turn the recorder off, since I think we’re wrapped up.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
