<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="CUMMINGS"/>
        <person xml:id="JEVNE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So this is <persName>Emily</persName> [<persName>B.] Cummings</persName>. I’m speaking <date>today</date> with [<persName>William R.]</persName> “Bill” Jevne. I’m in <orgName>the Rauner Special Collections Library</orgName> at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>, and Mr. <persName>Jevne</persName> is in <placeName>Telluride</placeName>, <placeName>Colorado</placeName>. It is <date>Friday, October 23rd, 2015</date>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I was born in <placeName>Minneapolis</placeName>, <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>, and my father was—he’s dead now—was <persName>Franz</persName> [P.] Jevne [Jr.], and my mother was <persName>Helen Patricia Atcheson</persName>, but “Pat” Jevne was the name that she went by.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And what did your parents do?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">My father was a lawyer, and my mother was a homemaker.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So what kind of area did you live in in <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>? Was it suburbs? Were you in the city?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Suburb, upper middle-class suburb called <placeName>Edina</placeName> [pronounced ee-DINE-uh], a suburb of <placeName>Minneapolis</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right. And did you like growing up there? Did you have a nice house and a good neighborhood?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Yeah, my parents were, like, not—not wealthy but well-to-do and a very comfortable childhood just in terms of, you know, economically and everything. And, like every family, I guess we had our issues, but for the most part it was a pretty happy childhood. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. Did you have brothers or sisters?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, two brothers: one, <date>two years</date> older than me and one, <date>four years</date> younger.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So how did you like growing up with three boys in the house?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It was good. And we actually—we spent our—those were <date>the days</date> of when polio was a serious affliction, and if you could afford it, went north to a lake place in the summertime, and we owned a lake place with my dad’s sister and her family, which had four boys in it, so we were seven boys cavorting around at this lake place all summer long. Very, very kind of sports minded, as you might expect, with a lot of male energy in the family.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, wow. I’m sure that that was exciting. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So you said that you went to a good high school. How was your experience? Were you focused on academics or sports or what was your main focus going to high school?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Sports was really, you know, the focus of my life. I played—I played hockey, and I was on the tennis team. I tried to play football, but I was very small and they wouldn’t let me play. You know, I enjoyed skiing and golf and games, sports. It was pretty much my main interest. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So did your parents push you to get good grades, or did they push you to go to a good college?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">No, they—my parents were very loving but pretty relaxed about our choices, and it was—I was, for some reason—I don’t even—I can’t even tell you now—for some reason, I was very strongly motivated to go to an Ivy League college. I think I also applied to <orgName>Stanford</orgName> [University]. I don’t really know why, but it was—it was all my own idea.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So you mentioned that at your high school people went to pretty good colleges. I think you said 90 percent went on to college?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Did you find that it was competitive, or was it more of a loving community at your high school?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Oh, well, you know, I imagine that varied from person to person, but I—it was—I—I never had a very—I mean, I have a strong competitive streak, you know, in the sports sense of competitive, but I never put on myself—comparing myself to other people much for grades or anything like that. It wasn’t—you know, not that kind of thing, at least in my experience. I mean, maybe others were feeling that, but if they were, I wasn’t aware of it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So did you live in <placeName>Edina</placeName> for your whole life, throughout high school?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, all through high school and through college. My parents—you know, we—we moved I think once when I was growing up, but only about a block away, and so all through college—I think I was in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> when my parents moved into a house in—actually within the city limits of <placeName>Minneapolis</placeName>. You know, that was my residence, my official residence. But, you know, I spent <date>summers</date> in <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>, and, you know, fair stretches of time there—oh, into the <date>’70s</date>—but I—you know, but I liked <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>; I considered it my home, but I knew I was going to be living in the mountains someplace eventually. I was pretty much—yeah, I never really planned to—to live in <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> once I got through with college and the military.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Would you say that when you were looking into colleges you were focused on playing sports in college?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, I didn’t really have much—yeah, it was kind of a real outside shot for me. <persName>Hockey</persName> was the sport I loved most, but I was small and slow to mature, and I actually never made the high school hockey team. I kept playing, but I was on what they called <orgName>the B Squad</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, that’s a good question. One thing I remember is it seemed like all my college decision letters came on <date>the same day</date>, and <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was the envelope that I opened first, and I got in, but it was also the only one that I got in, the only school that I got into. So I think I would have chosen it anyway, but, you know, it was the only one I got into, so I didn’t choose it over other schools.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, I think that’s natural. A lot of people say that about their choice to go to college.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So had you visited <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> before you applied?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Sorry? I didn’t hear that.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Had you visited <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> before you applied?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">No, no, hadn’t visited any schools.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. But you knew that it was in <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> and in the mountains, and the woods were nearby.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. You know, things like <orgName>the Dartmouth Outing Club</orgName> were famous if you knew anything about Ivy League schools and stuff.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. All right, so you got to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> your freshman year. And what <date>year</date> was that?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">That was the fall of <date>’62</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And what was your first impression of the school?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, you know, it was very beautiful and a very pleasant campus. In <date>those days</date>, freshmen wore beanies, and when you arrived on campus, upperclassmen could, like, commandeer you to do chores for them at the beginning of <date>the school year</date>. It was mainly like moving furniture into dorm rooms or fraternities or whatever. And I was kind of lucky. There were five other guys from my high school that—that went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, were in the same class as me, and they were all—most of them were hockey players, and they were all—all good friends of mine. So, you know, I wasn’t—wasn’t completely alone.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So were you excited to get away from home because it was a new experience and you were excited about college, or because you were tired of <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> or living with your parents? What made you happy to leave?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It was more enthusiasm about, you know, the adventures of college, I would say. I wasn’t—no, I wasn’t really tired of <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>, and I got along great with my parents. So that wasn’t—that wasn’t part of it. It was just, you know, moving on to the next step in life.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I was really confident about it, so—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And did you join a fraternity when you got to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I did. In <date>those days</date>, you could only do that your sophomore year, so—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, it’s still like that now.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Oh is it? Oh, yeah. For a while it wasn’t, I think, but anyway, yeah, I joined. I was in Beta [Theta Pi, now Beta Alpha Omega], which at that time was—was a pretty solid jock house, but later on, you know, it got kind of gross there, and they got expelled from campus and everything, but we had more of a reputation of being kind of straight- —straight-laced jocks in <date>those days</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">And did you find that most of your friends were in Beta? Was that sort of your home base on campus?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, yeah, it was, yep. You know, I had plenty of friends outside of Beta, but—but it was—it was the center of my social life, for sure.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And you mentioned that you joined the hockey team <date>sophomore year</date>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yes. Yep.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So how did that change your experience, going from freshman to <date>sophomore year</date> and being a part of a team?	</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, it was—you know, I would say that was the highlight of my—of my—of my time at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. I just—I loved hockey so much. And I was just—I just felt blessed that I had the chance to—chance to play, which is not to say, you know, when you’re on a sports team there’s plenty of ups and downs with team spirit and everything like that, and so it wasn’t—I’m not saying that it was just all a bed of roses. But it was, like, the thing I would say I enjoyed the most at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, remember the most about at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, probably got the most out of at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. You know, a lot of the guys that I’m still in touch with from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> are hockey players, were hockey players. It was a big thing for me.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And in terms of the campus climate, because that period of time is sort of when [the] <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> [War] is ramping up, I guess you could say, did you feel the presence of antiwar—or what was the campus climate like?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, okay. That’s interesting, because I was thinking of that this morning before you called. It was a—it was a real cusp time there, you know? You know, people kind of lump the <date>’60s</date> all together, but the beginning of <date>the ’60s</date>, at least in a place as isolated as <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> was at that time—which, you know, the roads were a lot worse, and <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>—<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in a way was kind of farther away from things than it is now. At the beginning of <date>the ‘60s</date>, <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, you know, was more—wasn’t really  considered a war. It was just kind of an involvement and didn’t—there weren’t enough military over there so that it affected people’s lives. And it was in—it was in—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Sorry.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay. It was in ’64 that <placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin Resolution</placeName> was passed by <orgName>Congress</orgName>, and then in <date>’65</date> was when really a lot of, you know, the big troop buildup began, and so, you know, war protests, even in—in urban areas, I don’t think really—really got going until <date>’65</date>. And up in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, I don’t remember there being any kind of—any kind of war protests going on. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I went to <orgName>Tuck School [of Business</orgName>] as well. They had a program back then where you could go to <orgName>the Tuck School</orgName> after your junior year. They called it the three-two program. So I was actually at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for <date>five years</date>. And <date>the last two</date> were at Tuck, and I ended up with an M.B.A. [masters of business administration] there. So through <date>’67</date> for me, I didn’t really notice a lot of antiwar activity.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So you would say that there wasn’t as—really a shift or a noticeable shift over your time?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There wasn’t—you know, for me, there was not, no.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">No. And, you know, I think there were big shifts taking place at other—on other campuses, but I don’t think it really happened—it happened soon after at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, I know, because in ’<date>68</date> or ’69 they took over <persName>Parkhurst</persName>—protesters took over Parkhurst Hall. But there wasn’t really strong—and strongly evident when I was there, I would say.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And so you went to Tuck in <date>’65</date>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, I started—yeah, started in <date>the fall</date> of <date>’65</date>. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And how was that different than <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Oh, that was a lot different. [Chuckles.] In a way, it wasn’t. You know, I was a bachelor and lived in the dorm, and a lot of us that lived in the dorm down there were younger—you know, quite a few of us were—were <date>three-twos</date>, and in a way it was <date>our senior year</date>. So we were still up to the—up to the usual college hijinks. But there also were a lot of students who were, like, married, had been out in business for <date>a few years</date> and had come back. They were a lot more settled, a lot more serious about—about academic stuff. And I actually—you know, in hindsight I probably made a pretty poor decision to go there in the sense that I really had been going to school for too long, and I found it very hard to do the schoolwork. But the schoolwork—it was really challenging, and, you know, there were a lot of—a lot of pretty focused students down there, so I—I graduated, but I think I was probably pretty close to the—to the bottom of the class. And I was—you know, I was still doing kind of typical college stuff when there wasn’t really time to be doing that. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">[Chuckles.] So the culture at Tuck was much different for you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, the culture was—the culture was different, although there was plenty of fun, too. I mean, you know, there was the <orgName>Tuck School</orgName> bike race. I don’t know if they still do that. That was a crazy event. You know, we partied a lot.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">[Chuckles.] So your social scene throughout college was—would you say was important to you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I did lots of partying. I wasn’t very much of a—dating was a strange thing in <date>those days</date> because, you know, you—well, we did lots of road trips to women’s college, and—you know. But I—I was pretty—in terms of relations with—with females, I was a very shy and—you know, I never—I really didn’t have—I probably had less than ten dates in my whole <date>four years</date> at—at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. That was kind of a hard part of it for me. You know, I wasn’t very good at going to a girls’ school and going to a dorm and starting talking to girls and persuading one to go out on a date, which is what you had to do in <date>those days</date>. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right, [Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, it was more of a—you know, more of a men’s experience.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">No, I think I had—well, yes and no. I think I had pretty much—you know, one thing that—one good thing about <persName>Tuck</persName> was it kind of convinced me that business—you know, a career in business was not going to be very compatible for me, so I—you know, most—most <persName>Tuck</persName> graduates were, you know, getting jobs and going to work in business right out of—right out of it. But I never even—never had an interview, never really considered that.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So did you grow up with a sense that serving your country was sort of a civic duty, something that you had to do?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">[Knocking sound in background.] Yeah, yeah, in one [unintelligible] strictly practical sense in that, you know, [voice becomes <orgName>muffled]—there</orgName>’s quite a noise. You getting that noise?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yes, I’m sorry. That’s, I think, something coming from my side. I’m not sure what it is. [The noise becomes less loud.]</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Just from a practical sense, the draft was ubiquitous. You know, you could—you could avoid the draft by—by going for <date>four years</date>, by going to college and getting a deferment. But normally, you know, once that was over, you got drafted. So I just—you know, I just—I kind of—in a way, without even thinking about, without any patriotic motivation, I just figured, Well, I’m probably to go have—I’m gonna be in the military for <date>two years</date>. But then, you know, I also felt it was honorable and patriotic to serve in the military. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So throughout college, though, you didn’t do <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. You weren’t really military focused. You just thought that if the draft—if you were drafted, you would serve? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Well, so that’s how I was at the beginning of—of college, and then, you know, towards the end, when it came time to figure out what I was going to do next, you know, it was something more. It was, like, you know, becoming a <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> officer was an opportunity, something that I wanted to do, chose to do.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So you graduated from Tuck in ’67? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Right. Yes.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">And so can you give me the timeline of you signing up for <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, that all pretty much happened in <date>the spring of ’67</date>, and by the time I graduated, I had signed on the dotted line and knew that I would begin <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> Officer Candidate School down in <placeName>Quantico</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, in around the first of <date>November</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I had—what is that?—five <date>months</date>’ delay time, <date>four or five months</date>’ delay time, which actually—I don’t know if this is the time to talk about it, but it kind of dovetails with a friendship with another <orgName>Dartmouth Marine</orgName>. Do you want me to talk about that?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, sure. Just—go ahead.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay. So a really close friend of mine—I was Class of ’66 at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>; he was Class of ’67 at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. We had played together on the hockey team for <date>two years</date>. His name was [<persName>William S.]</persName> “Bill” Smoyer. Have you heard that name?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yes, I have.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, he’s kind of—probably of all the—of all the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> Marines that—that were killed in the war, he’s probably the most well known one.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And, you know, there’s a Smoyer [unintelligible] at the hockey rink and everything. Well, he was a really close friend of mine. And when—so he—he was going through signing up for Marine OCS at the same time I was. He must have been—maybe he was ahead—a little bit ahead of me because he got scheduled to begin <orgName>OCS</orgName> <date>around October first</date>, so I was <date>November first</date>; he was <date>October first</date>. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And had a really—you know, pretty fun—pretty fun—you know, we were—we couldn’t have been in a much more carefree situation. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">We’d made it—made it through college, and we knew exactly what we were going to be doing come <date>October first and November first</date>, and so, you know, we didn’t have anything to hear but have a good time, and we did have a good time. Not really a dissipated time. You know, we did lots of outdoor stuff and share of stupid things as well, but not—not too many. You know, it was a very good time, you know. So we were close. Yeah. So that—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So then you spent <date>the whole few months</date> that you had traveling, and then you got to training in <date>November</date>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Can you tell me a little bit about your training?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">About training, yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> officer training is pretty amazing. It takes place at <placeName>Quantico</placeName>—in <placeName>Quantico</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, which is a base just—it’s on the <placeName>Potomac</placeName> [River] just south of [<placeName>Washington</placeName>] <placeName>D.C.</placeName> And when you arrive there—well, when I arrived there, you know, I was immediately taken charge of by the drill instructors. And, you know, the first thing that happens is you’re just pretty much humiliated and reduced to, you know, probably the lowest form of humanity that you’ve ever experienced or that I had ever experienced because treated in a way that I had never been treated, you know, in my life before in terms of being dominated and commanded and humiliated by, you know, the people in power over me. Which was a very interesting experience, but, of course, it was what I was expecting. I knew that’s what the training was like, you know, so—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So how did they do that? What sort of actions did they take against you, or—</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, the very first thing is that you get herded into the barbershop and your head shaved, but not—not completely bald but really short. You never—to begin with, you—we didn’t go anywhere except in formation, and so, like, we were organized in platoons, which are about—I guess about 40—40 candidates. We were called candidates. And the guys immediately superior to us were—were staff NCOs, non-commissioned officers. We also had I think a first lieutenant platoon commander, an officer. But the ones who were really dealing with us all day long were our—our—our drill instructors, who were—were staff NCOs.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It was designed to—you know, to make us give up a bit of ourselves, and yet, at the same time, there were—you know, there was a lot to—to give us confidence. We were running obstacle courses and doing difficult things, and if you were—if you were good at doing them, which I was, then you got a lot of—you know, that. Nobody—nobody congratulated you for it, ever. Nobody ever got—you know, there was never a word of praise of any kind. But you could feel good about it. You know, I could feel good about myself, and I was—I ended up—I was platoon honor man, which means on the scores that we had on all the different stuff that we did, I had the highest score in the platoon, so I was—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There was a lot to—a lot to hold onto. At the same time, we were kind of being broken down.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">We understood why they were doing that, so, you know, that made it a lot more bearable.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. So you mentioned that you sort of knew what was coming and, again, you just said you knew why they were doing it. Did that make it easier for you, or did you really dislike your time in training?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">No, you know, that made it easier. Actually, there was a lot to laugh at, too. The DIs were really funny, especially if they weren’t dressing—if they weren’t dressing me personally down, you know, I could listen to what they were saying to other guys, and it was funny. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Like, what would be an example of that?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Oh—[Chuckles.] Well, I never went, in an inspection—we had—one of the DIs was named <persName>Sergeant Jones</persName>, and he was clearly a warm-hearted guy. You could just—you could just feel it from him. But he was—but he never said anything warm-hearted. And there was a guy named <persName>Hagerty</persName> in the platoon, and I don’t know, I think we were having an inspection, and <persName>Sgt</persName>. <persName>Jones</persName> found something wrong with <persName>Hagerty</persName>’s stuff, and he said—he was black. He said, “<persName>Hagerty</persName>, you’re a hog. In fact, you’re a hog and a half. In fact you would even make a good hog.” You know that sounds kind of stupid? [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But, you know, just the way he said it, and knowing him and everything, it was—it was—there was something funny about it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right. So you sort of made light of the situation.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I had another—actually, I had another really funny experience. My brother came to <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> OCS I think in the—in the class after me, and <date>the very first day</date> he was there, I was up by—some kind of free time. I was up in—in the bathroom of our barracks, and I looked out the window, and his—his platoon was in formation down below where I was, you know? And he was down there, and he saw me, and I saw him, and the DI was down there and just, you know, giving them the normal ration of shit that they give [chuckles]—give the new candidates on <date>the first day</date>. You know, that was—that was funny to me, to see my brother going through all that.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, to see your brother?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">[Chuckles.] Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So did you get pretty close with the men in your platoon? Did you make friends during training?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, yes and no. There was—there’s nobody—there was nobody that I—you know, I was close with guys within the context of what we were doing there, and we would go up to—you know, and we had liberty—weekend pass or whatever, and we’d go up to <placeName>D.C.</placeName> together and mess around. But there was nobody in that—in that class that I remained in touch with after I got out of <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There actually—that—my class is having a reunion <date>this weekend</date> out in <placeName>San Diego</placeName>, and, you know, I’ve been to one reunion of the—of the class. When I looked at who was coming to this reunion, there really wasn’t one guy there that—that I had been friends with, so—yeah, you know, there were plenty of guys that I liked and respected, but I didn’t make any—any lifelong friendships there.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So how long were at training for?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, <orgName>OCS</orgName> lasted for <date>three months</date>, and then we still—still at the same place, <placeName>Quantico</placeName>. At the end of <orgName>OCS</orgName>, we got commissioned as second lieutenants, so we were officers now. And then, still at <placeName>Quantico</placeName>, we went for I think <date>five months</date> to what’s called <orgName>The Basic School</orgName>, where—it’s where officers receive the actual training in the skills that they’ll need to be infantry platoon commanders.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And was that different—or how was that different from <orgName>OCS</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">That was way different. It was way different in the sense that we were officers. We got paid more. I think I was—as a second lieutenant, was getting $321 a month instead of $45 a month—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—as a <orgName>PFC</orgName> [private first class] in—in <orgName>OCS</orgName>. We—we lived in kind of like—we lived in—it was sort of like a college dorm almost, and there was an officers’ club for—for us right there, so with a bar and everything. You know, we had—it was—it was more of a—I wouldn’t call it a nine to five job, because a lot of time we did night—night work and stuff, but we were—whenever we weren’t actually doing <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> training, we were completely free. We could go wandering off base all we wanted, you could have cars and—you know, so it was a whole different level of just independence.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">That was—that was quite a watchword. At the same time, you know, we were also—we would, you know—like, if we were doing double-time marching, like running as a platoon, we might be singing, “I’m gonna go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I’m gonna kill some <persName>Viet Cong</persName>.” You know? So it’s kind of—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—a strange dichotomy between—you know, we were being trained to be killers and to lead killers, and at the same time, we were being told that the key to success was winning the hearts and minds of the people over there.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So you knew that you were going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and how did that make you feel? Were you excited about going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yup, I was—once again, you know, I—I achieved quite highly. I think I finished third in my class of 200 at <orgName>The Basic School</orgName>—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—which meant that I could have chosen any—any military occupational specialty [MOS] that I wanted. But I—my—I never had any—I never thought about anything else except being an infantry platoon commander, so I—I chose infantry as my MOS. And, you know, that was—was my total intention in joining <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName>, was to be a platoon commander in—in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And so it was just—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I really wanted to be able to interact with and relate to the people of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and there were interesting possibilities in <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName>, their—most especially something called combined action platoons, where there were Marines and Vietnamese kind of village soldiers in the same unit, and so anyway, I scored high on the language test, and as a result I was—my orders when I—when I finished Basic School were to go to an <date>eight-week</date> Vietnamese language school before going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Disappointed because you wanted to go through the language training?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, I really wanted—I was very—if I was excited about something, it was the language training, you know?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And [unintelligible] that that—that was really—to be able to speak the language and be able to, you know, deal with—with the Vietnamese people directly—that was something that I—I was very—very enthusiastic about and really regretted losing that—that opportunity.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So you mentioned this—and I’m sure we’ll get to it a little later, but at this period of time, after your training, did you feel that going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was the right thing to do for the country, that <placeName>the United States</placeName> were doing a good thing in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Yeah. Yes. And—you know, I—as I mentioned earlier, I—growing up in <date>the ’50s</date>, there was a real struggle and also—and also the <date>’60s</date>—there was a real struggle going on between <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> and the—you know, the sort of the communist world, including Communist <placeName>China</placeName>, and what was called then the Free World, which was, you know, the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> and <orgName>NATO</orgName> [<orgName>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</orgName>]. And, you know, the third world countries were sort of the battleground for that—some actual battlegrounds, like <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but there was also a lot of—a lot of more political stuff going on in third world countries all over. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Now, I’m just going to get into something here that’s pretty important for me. You know, I was a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> grad and a <orgName>Tuck School</orgName> grad, and if there’s one thing that I have learned, it was how to do research, you know? And I was a history major, so even historical research was something that I knew quite a bit about—how to do.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Something that I regret. I feel that if I—if I had done that, I would have made other choices.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well [chuckles], maybe as prepared—I think I was—I thought I was as prepared as I could be from training. Something that would have been really good—a good step to have in between would have been to have some stateside leadership experience—in other words, be a platoon commander at Camp Lejeune [<orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> Base <placeName>Camp Lejeune</placeName>, <placeName>North Carolina</placeName>] or <orgName>Camp Pendleton</orgName> [<orgName>Marine Corps Base Camp Pendleton</orgName>, <placeName>California</placeName>] or, you know, one of the—one of the bases in—in stateside bases, because then, in non-dangerous situations, I could have learned how to be—you know, there’s learning like you do in college or in—in, you know, military training, and then there’s the real nuts-and-bolts learning, which is what you get when you’re actually on the job or in an internship or something. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So it’s—you know, I didn’t know—I had no experience in actually leading men. Didn’t know enlisted Marines very well. You know, I had—I had a lot to learn, and I knew I had a lot to learn, and I knew that I was going to have to learn it under pretty—pretty tough circumstances.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, one thing that I—that I forgot to—to touch on. So when <persName>Bill Smoyer</persName> and I were traveling through the <placeName>West</placeName> before we—we star- —we went on active duty—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">In <date>’67</date>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>. And I have—had an uncle who lived in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, Uncle <persName>Bill</persName>. I’m named after him.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we stayed with <persName>Uncle Bill</persName> and <persName>Aunt Wilma</persName> and their—and their two kids. And <persName>Uncle Bill</persName> had been in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>—the [<orgName>U.S. Navy</orgName>] <orgName>Seabees</orgName>, in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, during <name type="event">World War II</name>, you know with the island-hopping campaigns in the <placeName>Pacific</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And he—and he was, like—this is not—literally not an exaggeration—he was—you know about the <orgName>navy</orgName> SEALs [<orgName>U.S. Navy’s</orgName> Sea, <orgName>Air</orgName>, Land teams]?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay, so—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—they were first called frogmen. You know, they did underwater demolition, preparing invasion beaches, removing obstacles.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay. So he was—and the first thing they did was reconnaissance of that. He and one other guy were the first guys to ever do that from the water. They disobeyed orders while they were doing a reconnaissance from a boat, because they didn't think they could get information—good information, and they went in the water and swam and figured out where all these obstacles were. And after that, that became the underwater demolitions teams and the SEALs—the frogmen and then eventually the SEALs.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So he was, like, this hero.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">He at one point won a pretty high award called a Silver Star. It’s not—it’s the third-highest decoration that you can have. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—basically that. As you can tell by listening to me, I—I heard him, but I—you know, I took no—neither <persName>Bill Smoyer</persName> nor I took any further action on what he said. It’s just an interesting thing that I had meant to touch on but didn’t.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So it didn’t really change your mind about going to training?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">No. No.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. Was he the only one who expressed that to you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. I think he was. He was the only one I remember, anyway. I know—well, another interesting fact was I never—the only thing—the only communication I ever had with my parents about this was to tell them—I had good relations with my parents, but in <date>those days</date>, you know, I don’t think young people consulted their parents very much about any decisions they made, and I made my decision to join <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> I think without ever letting my parents knew [sic] that I was thinking about it, or I don’t think even ever telling them about it until it was a done deal.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So it was—and—I don’t think they were too happy. Well, I’m sure they weren’t too happy about it. My father I think was—was kind of conflicted because he—he had been in the <orgName>Army</orgName> in <name type="event">World War II</name>, and he had a lot of the same feelings that, you know, I did about doing your duty and there’s some kind of adventure in—in—in being in a war and stuff. But at the same time, you know, I don’t think he really wanted me to be—well, I know he didn’t really want me to be in a war, being afraid for me getting killed.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I don’t remember the exact date, but it was right around <date>August 1st, 1968</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. And where did you land in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I landed in <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">What were your first impressions of <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, I had spent <date>a couple of days</date> in—in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName> [Islands, <placeName>Japan</placeName>] on the way over, which was kind of—you know, there’s a, just the, the heat and kind of humidity of <placeName>the Far East</placeName> is pretty amazing, and experienced that in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName>. And also got a lot of briefings about what was going on in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in the areas where we were likely to be assigned. And those were pretty scary, in the sense that there was a lot of—a lot of combat happening at the time.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">The guys on the flight were enlisted men, and the stewardesses were very playful with them and kind of made the flight a lot of fun.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But then we got off the plane at the <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> airfield, and the heat was, you know, a lot more intense than even it had been in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName>. And they piled us into some six-bys, which are big trucks with—canvas-covered trucks, and drove us through sort of the ramshackle bamboo hut residential areas that were surrounding <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, up to the 1st <orgName>Marine Division</orgName> headquarters, where I was assigned to the 1st <orgName>Marine Division</orgName>, and that’s where we were going to get more briefings and get assigned to our regiment, from which we would get assigned to our battalion and then our company and then our platoon.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And so that—we’re done for <date>the day</date>, with all that, and I go over to the officers’ club. This is still <date>the first day</date> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I go over to the officers’ club, which is just, you know, a bar hangout where officers can go in their free time, and I go in there, and I—I don’t know—I can’t remember if it was right away, but anyway, very soon after getting in there I run into [<persName>Robert C.]</persName> “Bob” Coury, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> Class of <date>1965</date> and then a classmate of mine at <orgName>Tuck School</orgName>. And, you know, overjoyed to see each other. We weren’t, like, super-close friends, but we were actually quite good friends. And I didn’t even know <persName>Bob</persName> was there.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But—so I run into <persName>Bob</persName>, and we say hi, and then he gives me the news that <persName>Bill Smoyer</persName>, who had left for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> a month before me, was already dead. He’d been killed in—killed in a big-scale ambush. You know, he was already dead.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">That was a—like—I’m not sure it’s the right word, but an epiphany moment for me when, you know, a moment of really deep, profound, undeniable realization comes along. You know, in an instant I felt the superficiality with which I had made all my decisions to join <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> and get involved in the war. And, you know, really what it felt like to me was I—up until that point, I had been approaching it maybe like with the same sort of mentality that I had been so enthusiastic about hockey about. And, you know, I suddenly knew what it was all about. It was about—about people that I knew getting killed, and then it was about other people getting killed who I didn’t know, but they were—their lives were just as valuable as the people that I—that I did know. And I also realized, There’s a fucking good chance I’m gonna get killed, myself.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I also realized that—that I had huge responsibilities in front of me, because I was going to be, you know, a big part of whether or not the guys under my command got killed or hurt. I also—like, in a way I threw aside my idealism at that point. And I don’t know exactly why, but for some reason, my—my heart just told me that what my—what my job was going to be was to keep as many <orgName>Marine</orgName> troopers under my command alive as I possibly could.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And confusion. You know, I didn’t know what it was like to lose a friend, you know? Yeah. So that was hard, very hard. And I—there I was in the officers’ club, and there was a bar, and I responded, as I think many young men my age would respond, which was to get blind drunk.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Like, passing-out drunk.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So that moment sort of put it in perspective for you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Sorry?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">That moment sort of put it in perspective for you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yup, yup, very sharp perspective.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">And so going forward from that moment, obviously it’s something that stuck with you. How did it affect the way you adjusted to being at the camp and being in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, if there’s one thing that stands out in my mind about an amazing way that we were there, it’s the word “resilience.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It was, like,—you know, we were so young and so full of—so full of energy that, you know, these—these really bad things would happen, and—and we were taken in, at least as fully as we could and still carry on with what our—what our jobs were, but, you know, sooner than you would ever think possible, we would find ourselves just fully absorbed in what it was we were doing: laughing with our friends, you know, whatever. Just back at it. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And when we’re—so we’re kind of on our side and we’re at such a steep level that through the porthole windows on the other side, I can see the ground, and we’re just spiraling down. And the reason, I found out later, is there was so much artillery fire going out of the—out of this combat base down there that the only way the plane could get into the landing strip was to kind of spiral down directly above it and—and come in that way. And also to avoid enemy fire, because [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">“There—there are gonna be things that happen out there that’s going to seem impossible to not cry, but don’t ever cry.” And I’ll tell you later about the time or two when I did cry, but it kind of—I don’t know, it exemplifies a lot about how you have to be to be in war and what you have to—what you have to put down just to get through it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So everyone who was already there was pretty realistic with you about what you were going to have to deal with?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, yeah. Yeah, I mean, I wasn’t getting a lot of—you know, I wasn’t—wasn’t getting a lot of information. I was just—they had some kind of a regulation that you had to be—when you got to <orgName>5th Marine Regiment</orgName>, you had to stay in the rear area for a certain number of <date>days</date>—two, three, <date>four days</date>—I don’t remember how many?—so I was just kind of in limbo.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So he went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah. So you had some time, then, to settle before you started going into, like, full missions?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yup.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">And what was sort of the culture or the tone like at the camp?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Ah, what an interesting question. Well, you know, the people who were there were what we called in <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> pogs [rhymes with rogue; a person other than a grunt] And there’s a big distinction between “grunts” and “pogs.” So the grunts were guys that were in the—in the infantry—in the infantry units, most of the time out in the field. Pogs are guys that have the jobs in the rear, and they’re relatively safe. And every grunt’s dream is to become a pog, so they get out of—get out of danger.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There’s just kind of a weird—weird regard for pogs by grunts. So, you know, the people who were there—you know, I’m saying this somewhat as a hindsight—the people there who were pogs—they were doing pretty boring—boring jobs, but they’re pretty glad to have the jobs. So I would say it was relaxed. And, you know, there were things going on. We were—that base was frequently getting rocketed and mortared. There could be night attacks. A lot of those pogs had to—had to serve on duty in foxholes around the—the outside perimeter of the base at night and everything. So it’s not like it was, you know—it wasn’t a totally safe environment, but it was so much safer than the <persName>bush</persName> that it was really pretty relaxed.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay, so that’s—<date>one day</date>, when it was my time to go out to the <persName>bush</persName>, the—my—my—my company was out on some kind of sweeper patrol, and there was not—hadn’t yet been arranged a way for me to meet them, so I got—there was a—there was a road that came down to An <placeName>Hoa</placeName> from <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, and it crossed a river about ten miles north of An <placeName>Hoa</placeName>, on a bridge called Liberty Bridge. And <date>every day</date> before the trucks used that road, there had to be what was called a road sweep, where, like, a platoon of Marines would walk up the road from <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> and another platoon would walk down the road from Liberty Bridge, and with mine detectors and security out to either side of the road to make sure the road hadn’t been mined and there weren’t any ambushes and it was going to be safe to travel.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So, you know, it was kind of a fact of life in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that you didn’t get attached to anybody or really trust anybody until you’d gone through some shit with them and knew who they were.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So I was coming in as a boot lieutenant, and I knew it. So, you know, the first thing we did, I think—we were on some kind of a—of an operation. I don’t even exactly remember what it was, but everything had been happening down in the rice paddies, but <date>that day</date>—well, the valley there—<placeName>the river valley</placeName> was surrounded on three sides by—by pretty high mountains, and for some reason, <date>that day</date> everything started to shift into the foothills of these mountains on one side of the valley, so we kind of moved out of the—of the—of <placeName>the paddy area</placeName> and up—up into these foothills, which were covered by really thick brush. It was very—no trees in the foothills. Big trees up in the mountains, but the foothills was this kind of impenetrable brush. And so we had a very—I just let <persName>Sgt</persName>. <persName>Elliot</persName> pretty much run the platoon, and we had a very hard day plowing through all this—all this crap.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And [chuckles]—well, actually, in the way another epiphany moment. [Chuckles.] But a real thing that I was not going to be letting—<persName>Sgt</persName>. <persName>Elliot</persName> was not going to be running the platoon.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I—you know, I—I took charge of the platoon at that time, you know, kind of raised a little hell—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—at that moment and made sure everybody was staying awake for the rest of the night. And then the next morning I had a meeting with the squad leaders and laid things on the line. And, you know, not easy for me to do because I’d never—never had done anything like that, really, before, and I—I don’t know how good a job I did, but, you know, at least got their attention.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So what were the usual types of missions that you had? What was your usual call to duty?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well—well, probably the most—I could probably divide it—three—three big things would be what—maybe what we called sweeps,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—patrols and—and ambushes. Okay, so a sweep would probably be a unit at least as big as—as a company, which would be—if it was full strength, would be around 250 men. Very seldom—I would say never was a company at full strength. Could be a battalion sweep, which would be over a thousand men. I one time—one time participated in—in I think something larger than a regimental sweep, where, you know, several thousand men were kind of moving forward along the same—along the same axis at the same time. Not that you could see—you know, you could see each other, but it was all happening at the same time.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Patrols are—patrols are more—usually were more like a—a search type of mission. So they’re sent out to—to find information, maybe find weapons caches or food caches, maybe to find enemy fighters and involve a lot of the same things as sweeps—as a sweep, so if you’re down in the paddy country, where you’re patrolling into are these villages I was telling you about.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And to get to a village, you have to go across a rice paddy, and it’s usually exposed when you do that, with no cover in the rice paddy. The village is bordered by a tree line, so it’s really easy for the enemy to dig what we called spider holes, little—little foxholes and be completely invisible there, wait until—wait until the Marines get into, like, a kill zone, very close to the edge of the village, and then open up and just cut them down. That’s how <persName>Bill Smoyer</persName> got killed.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Anyway, so if you get into the village—then as I say, if you’re doing some searching—and one really horrible part of—of what we did—where I was down in the An <placeName>Hoa</placeName> area was what’s called a free fire zone, which means—you probably know what that means, but I’ll explain it a little bit.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">The entire area was considered to be potentially enemy territory, so in order to call in air strikes, artillery, to shoot, whatever, you never had to get any kind of clearance. If we—you know, if we felt some kind of artillery or air strike was called for, we could call it in and get it, and there was no questions asked.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So what were the kinds of, like, contact that you had with the Vietnamese?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, okay, so I was in a very—very peaceful platoon. We just wanted to stay alive. And we had no—I can really say this with a great deal of confidence—we didn’t have feelings of enmity towards the Vietnamese people. We loved the kids, and we realized that what we were doing when we were cleaning these villages like this was horrible for the people.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">We hated doing that. And we felt sorry—you know, we felt sorry for the people that were—that were having this brought to them. And we—we tried to be nice to them as much as we could. We couldn’t really communicate with them because, you know, none of us spoke Vietnamese. You know, we only knew a few words, like <persName>di di mau</persName>, which is “Leave. Get outta here.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And “chop chop” was “food.” You know, we would—maybe—I don’t know—you know, <persName>beaucoup</persName>, left over from French times; that meant “a lot”. We just had a few things we knew. But, of course, there was a lot of non-verbal communication.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But—yeah. You know, we weren’t—I—I’m sure this is not true for everybody, but the tone of the platoon I would say was generally empathetic towards—towards these people that were in these villages. And that’s in spite of the fact that there were—booby traps were a horrible problem. You know, there were really bad things that—that—that could happen. But I don’t know, we just innately understood what—what a horrible situation these people were in. They were farmers who wanted—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">They were farmers who wanted to farm, and nobody was letting them do it: not us, not the <orgName>NVA</orgName>, not the <orgName>VC</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. So then that’s—you’ve gone over sweeps and patrols. Can you tell me a little bit about ambushes?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">About what?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Ambushes.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Ambushes. Okay, yeah. Ambush. Those are mainly nighttime activities, and I actually wasn’t involved on them too much myself, but as I told you somewhat earlier—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Every night—every night we would set up in some kind of a perimeter, usually a platoon-size perimeter. It might be a company-size perimeter. And part of the security of a perimeter like that is to have one or two small ambushes, probably fire team-size ambush out in front of the lines at night. So, you know, it was something where if—if there was an enemy attack at night, these guys out on the ambush would detect it before it—it got close to the lines. Again, this was not something that ever actually happened to me, but if it had happened, those guys probably wouldn’t have been in too good a position. But, on the other hand,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—you know, might have been able to start—start shooting and kind of—and then get back to our perimeter and, you know, get back safely and have—kind of saved us from a—from a bad situation. That would be the idea. You know—yeah. So that would be an ambush.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">That could be up to a platoon size. I got—we got sent out on several platoon-size ambushes. Never had any enemy actually walk through it, so never actually sprang an ambush but, you know, that’s [unintelligible] then some. You know, they’re scary. You’ve got your—you’re out there, a little island, kind of exposed and—and,  you know, could potentially be surrounded. And the whole idea is that, you know—the whole purpose is to have enemy walk into your trap and to actually start a fight. So [chuckles], anything we wanted to avoid was fights, so we didn’t particularly like going out on ambushes.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Can you just hang on one second? I have to go to the bathroom.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, of course. No problem.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Just a <orgName>sec</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">All right. Well, I guess it’s a good time to tell you about the very worst thing that—that happened to me. I’ll tell you about it—you know, some—some really bad things that happened. I was—I actually—in many ways, I had a really lucky tour. From <date>the first month</date> I was there, my platoon had no combat at all: no booby trap—I mean, there were booby traps happening around us, but, you know, nothing happened at all. And that was very lucky because I—I got to learn to be a platoon commander, and I got to build my relationship with my squad leaders and—and, you know, I got—I got—I got things going. And I—you know, I had a really good personal relationship with my squad leaders and the guys in the platoon, and there was a lot of mutual respect, so it was—that was a good thing.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">The first thing—the first bad thing that happened was a guy named <persName>Corporal Bear</persName>—we were on a patrol <date>one day</date>, and he was stopped at a rest stop. Corporal <persName>Bear</persName>, he was—his job was he carried an antitank weapon, which we didn’t use for antitanks; it would be used more against a bunker or something. But anyway, that was his job.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—tripped another booby trap. This one was a smaller one, a grenade, and he got fairly lightly wounded, but he had to get <persName>medevac’d</persName>, too.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">And when was that—was that pretty early on for you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, as I say, I don’t remember exactly. I think—I arrived in <date>early August</date>. I would say this was <date>early September</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So <date>about a month</date> in.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And it turns out two guys from my platoon were on one of those helicopters, I think maybe coming back from <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> [rest and recuperation] or maybe they’d been wounded and were coming back to the field. I can’t exactly remember. So that’s two more guys. And this is killed by—you know, in a friendly situation.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE"><date>A few days later</date>, the operation comes to a hill called Hill 100, in the foothills along one side of this valley. And a different M&amp;amp;E company, a different company in our battalion—I don’t remember which one—assaults this hill. Okay, so that would be kind of like a sweep. They—they start from the bottom of the hill. Everybody’s on line. They go up the hill. But there were a lot of enemy on top of this hill, and they got shot off the hill. There was a certain number of—of casualties. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It’s balls to the wall entirely. Have you ever seen the movie, Platoon?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Do you remember that big firefight at the very end, when they get attacked?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, I do.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay, that actually is a very good portrayal of the kind of controlled insanity—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—that’s called for if you want to survive one of those attacks.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Anyway, so we’re on this hill. And it’s the monsoon season, so we’re getting lots and lots of rain, and I had—everybody has good foxholes and everything, but it’s still very exposed, and one night I had my foxhole behind our perimeter a little bit because my job is a command job. I’m not supposed to be out on the front lines. And I had my foxhole—I had a couple of—of cartons of C-rations in the bottom of my foxhole so I wouldn’t have to sleep on the mud.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">We were very good at sleeping in terrible conditions. We had ponchos with a little synthetic blanket called a poncho liner in them, and you could roll up in those ponchos and—and sleep just as well as you would sleep in your dorm room.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I was sleeping like the dead in the bottom of my foxhole, and all of a sudden I’m woken up by a hellacious racket. And I was sleeping sound enough so that, you know, I didn’t make the mental connections instantly, but, of course, those were quickly identified as a lot of explosions, grenades and stuff, going on. And I’m lying in the bottom of my foxhole, and I had a moment of utter fear, followed by a moment of almost irresistible inclination to stay lying there in the bottom of my foxhole.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So I got—it got me out of my hole, and I ran around to all the different squad positions, and they’re not really—there must have been a lot of lead and a lot of shrapnel flying around, but I’m not too aware of that, really. I’m just, you know, concerned about—with—with what I’m doing.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">It’s okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">[Recovering his composure.] So he—he said, “Whatcha doin’ down here?” And went up to the next squad, <persName>Paul Ferrante</persName>, who was still alive. And he said, “We’re okay here.” And then I went over to <persName>Jimmy Leeks’</persName> squad, and they were in a bit more trouble, and he said—they were kind of a—his last position was kind of at the end of a little finger positions, and he said, “Oh, I’m not really too sure what’s goin’ on out there. I heard some guys were hurt, and the corpsman went out to see if he could help them. But we’re pretty low on ammunition.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So those—those two guys were casualties, and—and Taco —usually a wound we considered a lucky thing because if you—if it wasn’t bad—because if you got two wounds that required 48 hours or less of—or 48 hours or more of hospitalization, you got to leave <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And if you got three wounds—if you got three wounds of any kind, you got to leave <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. But <orgName>Taco</orgName>’s wound was bad enough so that—you know, that was a bad thing for us. And we didn’t know what was going on with [unintelligible]. That was pretty worrisome. But in a lot of ways, we got out of that one very lucky.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So that was—that was a nasty one.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So how did—</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Sorry. How did these encounters with the enemies, where you lost men that you either knew or were working towards the same goal with, how did that affect the way that you went into your next missions?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Heh! Well, the effects are—the effects were cumulative, and I’ll get to that. At the end of this battle, in a way—I mean, obviously it was terrible that eight—eight guys in the other platoon got killed, and it was very regrettable that Taco got hurt as bad as he did. But there was also, like, a—for me and I think for everybody there was a kind of a sense of exhilaration because we hadn’t—we had survived, you know, and in a way we had won the battle. It wasn’t like a victory type of thing, I wouldn’t say, but we were still alive, and, you know, we’d come through something tough, and we had made it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I’ll say it again: <persName>It’s</persName>—I’ll say it again: It’s amazing how—what a strong force that is and how soon, you know—how soon it could kick in. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">We were living normally not long after, I would say. Now, I’ll qualify that, though, by—we were up on that hill for—for <date>a few more days</date>, and we were still, like, the very most advanced position in this whole operation?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And <date>one day</date>, <date>a few days later</date>, we get an order from the battalion, and, as usual, it was my platoon that got ordered to do it, which [chuckles]—every platoon commander would probably tell you the same thing, but it seemed like—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—it was always my platoon got these dirty jobs, and that’s what the guys in my platoon said, too. So we get an order—we get an order to a patrol off of this really exposed hill, farther into the foothills into the mountains, you know? And this was terrifying to us. A <date>daytime</date> patrol.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And there’s no—and I believe this is true. There was no reason for that patrol, but there was a hell of a lot of danger. And, you know, I had had a really informal relationship with the guys in my platoon and my squad leaders and stuff, and they’re complaining like hell to me, and I’m complaining to the—to the company commander. And I don’t know, he might have said something to the battalion commander on the radio, but, you know, the orders come through: “You’re going out on that patrol.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. But in a more general way, you know, as—well, you know when I was telling you about—about the—the—the patrols and having to blow up the—the family bunkers and the <persName>hooches</persName> and everything like that?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right, yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So here I am, here we are out in—you know, doing our best, and, you know, in plenty of danger <date>every single day</date> and guys getting hurt periodically, and, you know, we’re well aware that the way—what we need to do to win the war is their hearts and minds stuff. And we also were well aware that what they’re doing while we’re operating is the exact opposite of winning hearts and minds. We are losing hearts and minds. And, you know, for me, in my leadership position and kind of maybe with my—you know, my education and my idealism—you know, my—[His voice cracks with emotion.] My—my heart is, you know, just slowly smothering, I guess would be a way to put it, you know. And I really have no purpose—I cannot see any sense or any reason for what we’re doing.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And—and why can’t—the epiphany I told you about when <persName>Bill Smoyer</persName> died, when I got that news—I had no reason for being there except keeping guys alive.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I’m doing my best at that, but, you know, that’s not working all the time—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So—</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—so I’m gradually—you know, I’m gradually—things are getting worse and worse for me. At the same time, you’ve got this resilience going, I have—I had relationships with guys—well, my—my strongest relationship was with my radio operator, [<persName>Matthew A.]</persName> “<persName>Matt” Ruden</persName>, a big, strong farm kid from <placeName>Iowa</placeName>. And, you know, he and I—I think it was the closest, strongest—you know, it’s completely different from any friendship that I’d—that I’d had up to this point, but just—just for what we meant to each other—you know, just for what being with each other meant to each other was just the strongest friendship that I’d—that I’d ever had. You know, it was really of a completely different nature.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Just because we were together, we felt a lot better about—about life, and it’s kind of a hard thing to express, but very—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—strong and very special.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So did you two sort of come to the realizations at the same time? Like, being in the villages and interacting with people, did you sort of have the same opinions about how the war was going?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Yeah, you know? One thing that was pretty clear, and that was if you look at it from the big picture, in—any combat that we were involved in, we won, you know? Just if you look at it as a battle, you know? If a platoon got ambushed coming across a rice paddy, yeah, some Marines would get killed, but the village that the fire had come from would get bombed, and, you know, in the end we would—we would be the winners of that battle. But it didn’t make any difference. You know, we weren’t accomplishing anything. We could take any piece of ground that we wanted to take, eventually, but we couldn’t control—we couldn’t control anything. You know, it was all too vast. The only places we had control was the combat base that was where the airstrip was. Everything else was just up for grabs all the time.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And if we had wanted to be winning the hearts and minds of the people, we would have had to control the countryside so they could farm and be grateful for us, you know.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">They needed to farm. And there was no way we could do that. And, you know, we would have had to have millions of—of Marines there or, you know, troops there to—to accomplish that, and, I knew that was never going to be a reality. So, you know—well, I knew, and I knew it so clearly, there was no way we were going to win this deal.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. And so you mentioned that going into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you thought that there was a purpose in being there. Would you say that the interactions that you had with Vietnamese locals, farmers in those villages—was that kind of a turning point for you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, yeah, certainly, you know, yeah. And for the reasons—and for the reasons that I’ve said. You know, instead of being able to—be able to help them, we were harming them.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I knew that wasn’t going to work. Yeah. Yup.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So were you at all aware of, like, politics—like, back-home politics about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, or as it more just your experience there?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Was I aware of back-home in politics? Yeah, I was, in a way. Yeah, I knew that—I knew that there was a lot of protesting going on. It was ’<date>68</date> was <date>the presidential election year</date>. Before I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, [President] <persName>Lyndon</persName> [<persName>B.]</persName> <persName>Johnson</persName> had bowed out of the presidential race, so there was a lot—there was a lot going on politically, a lot of protesting before I left. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I can remember my grandfather writing me and saying—he was a pretty strong Republican, but he said—he said to me in his letter, “Tell me which—which candidate you think will be best at ending the war, and that’s the one I’m going to vote for.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So, yeah, so I was aware of politics. We got most of our news from Stars and Stripes, which was the—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—the military newspaper that would come to us when helicopters would come out with resupplies and stuff, so there <orgName>wasn’t</orgName>—I don’t think there was coverage of protests in that. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So was this shifted opinion pretty universal, or was it only a few specific men who saw that the war was taking a bad turn?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I—okay. I’m going to personalize the question a little bit. One of the rare nights when we were back at An <placeName>Hoa</placeName>, our relatively safe combat base—we were back there for <date>a few days</date> to kind of regroup before we went out on another operation. And one night, a bunch of enlisted men from my platoon and I got together someplace, and people just brought whatever—brought whatever they might have in the way of—of booze, you know?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">If they had some beer or if their parents had sent them a bottle of whiskey in a CARE package or whatever, we just kind of pooled it all together and we had a little booze party there. And talked, you know? And we didn’t have to worry about being quiet or anything like that, so it was kind of like—it was a memorable time, and I think the guys who were there probably remember it to <date>this day</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">“When we get home, we’ve got to tell people about this.” And, you know, I know I didn’t do a very good job of telling people about it when I got back. You know, we mostly got focused on picking up the pieces of our lives again.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But we knew—I think a lot of us were aware—were aware that—that things weren’t going well and that it would be important to tell people.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we were not, you know—how did this boy call us? Yeah, “Lt. <persName>Jevne</persName>’s bitchin’ little heroes,” “bitchin’” meaning that we were always com- —we didn’t want to—we didn't want action. We didn’t want to fight.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But whenever anybody gave us an order to do something we thought was going to be dangerous, you know, the guys in the platoon would always complain to me. [Chuckles.] Yeah, we were, like, peaceable. We weren’t “go-get-’em, get-some, <persName>gung-ho Marines</persName>.” We just wanted to get back alive.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right, just get through.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Like, disillusionment—you know, this, you know, real grim, cynical, disillusionment with the war—I would say that we enjoyed every moment of our lives that we possibly could, playing back alley bridge or, you know, just bullshitting or whatever. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we hated what were doing. We wanted to get out. We wanted to survive. But we weren’t, like—you know, we weren’t desperate or, you know, just really negative.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So how did the change in opinion, the way that you felt so negatively—did that affect your missions at all—like, your feelings when you were actually out in the field fighting?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Ok so I’m going to recount two more really bad incidents which will bring that out.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">The next one happened on <date>November 3rd</date>, and—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><date>November</date>—sorry, is this ’<date>68</date>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE"><date>November 3rd, 1968</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right, great.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. So a new platoon commander had been assigned to our—to our company, and I remembered well the experience of being a new platoon commander. So on <date>this day</date> in the morning of <date>November 3rd</date>, <orgName>there’s</orgName>—our company had spent that night at the perimeter, one particular spot, and there was a very large village nearby that needed to be cordoned and searched, which means surrounded by security perimeter and then thoroughly searched by the Marines that were out on security duty on the perimeter.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And the other one—you know, I was overly thoughtful of the new platoon commander. I knew how hard it was to—you know, to step into a leadership position. I thought, Well, if I make noise about it, you know, it’s going to be pretty humiliating for him. And since I didn’t—you know, there wasn’t anything happening around there in the way of aircraft. I thought, Well, this is not good, but we’re just—you know, we’re just going to go into the village.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">These were the guys that were going to search the village. So I ran back to the closest squad, got on the radio and to the company headquarters said, “They bombed their village. Get the air strikes stopped.” No more planes came in. I ran over to—to where the bomb dropped. Sure enough, it had landed smack dab on the hooch where I had left—left these guys. I—I saw—I saw some blown-up bodies. I just started—you know, I didn’t see anything to start with, and then I started seeing pieces of bodies,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—whole bodies all blown up. I, you know, started identifying guys. I found a boot with a foot in it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I found a beautiful guy from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> named [<persName>Joseph E.] “Joe” Davis [Jr.</persName>]. And <date>about a month</date> to go before his tour was up. He was a grenadier, a grenade launcher. He was still alive, unconscious, breathing, an arm, his forearm bone sticking out at the elbow. I mean, I’m just—I just can’t believe it. And didn’t really know what to do, you know, for—for quite a while. It’s just me there, and <orgName>nobody’s</orgName>—nobody’s alive. There’s—there’s also a whole bunch of Vietnamese women and children all blown to hell.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And, you know, bit of a blur. What I  really remember is the gunnery sergeant from the company coming over there and kind of taking charge, calling in a helicopter. You know, <persName>Joe Davis</persName> might have been alive when he got choppered out, but he wasn’t going to make it. That was, you know, totally clear. Everybody else was dead, and most of them in pieces.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And that’s the one time, you know, I can remember where there was an interval when I really—you know, it was probably maybe—I don’t know—probably not longer than 15 minutes or a half hour, but I really wasn’t in a position to run my platoon.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know—you know, I told you a little bit about <persName>Matt</persName>, my radio operator, but [weeps] the other guys—again, it would be really hard for me to tell you who they were, what they meant to me. [Continues to weep.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, they got killed by our own—they got killed by our own jet—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—due to a mistake by another platoon commander and a mistake by me, you know.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So the fact that it was friendly fire—did that—first of all, did that happen often, and second of all, what kind of difference did that make mentally in terms of the platoon?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It happened pretty often, so—you know, I couldn’t give you any statistics or anything, but friendly fire injuries and deaths were fairly common. I also told you about the two guys in the helicopters, you know?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">The Marines and the soldiers—they’re just ordinary—ordinary human beings, but they’re operating potentially lethal equipment, all the way from their—you know, their rifles through machine guns and grenades up to, you know, <orgName>Howitzers</orgName> and fighter jets. And, you know, things can happen.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Another time—another time, that lieutenant who took over my platoon—I eventually got a slightly easier job that still kept me in the field; I became the company executive officer. But this boot lieutenant who took over my platoon was cleaning his .45 [caliber] pistol. He cleaned it. He put the magazine back in, and he let the slide go home, which he should have done after he put the magazine in, and so he let the slide go home, and fired a round into the leg of his platoon sergeant.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So—so, yeah, accidents happened quite a bit, and it’s devastating for morale.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">However, the one that I just told you about would be on the very high end both of in terms of what happened and the impact that it would have. You know, a few of the guys that got killed in that incident were very beloved in the platoon, and they only had <date>a month</date> to go before they would rotate. They were just right at the tail end of their—of their tours. They had survived so much shit.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And then got killed by a friendly air strike right at the right, right towards the end, so, yeah, I mean, I—I imagine I was the most devastated, but the other—I, other old-timers that were in the platoon. I’m telling you, we were in sad shape.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I’m still in touch with guys from my platoon, and we—we talk about it with huge—huge sadness to <date>this day</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. So that was <date>about three months</date> in, you said?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Yep.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So that’s a pretty tough sort of beginning.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Right. And so you were asking about how that affects the mission afterwards.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay, as I told you, I was a little dysfunctional for a brief period of time there, but, you know, once—once everything was taken care of there at that site, you know, it became time for the company to move out to the next—next position. And I—you know, as a leader I knew that if this—if I let this affect me too much—well, I don’t know. I guess—this is maybe a thought process, but I knew that I—that me and the whole platoon just had to get back in the saddle right away or we might get not back in the saddle at all.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So we—we moved out on point. We went to a place—where we set up that night was—you know, it was—there—we were security—we were surrounding—we made a perimeter around a weapon that you almost never saw in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. It was called a four-deuce mortar [an M2 4.2-inch mortar]. It was a big, huge mortar with a four- —a little over four-inch diameter to the tube. Very powerful, noisy weapon. And there was a whole battery of these four-deuce mortars, and they were—you know, I had all my things to think about all night long, and these mortars were firing all night long. It was one of the hardest nights I ever spent.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But I was a little bit lucky because I was already slated to go on <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> <date>a few days later</date>, so I got a bit of relief. You know, it might have been hard if I’d had to—had to stay with the platoon.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But that—R&amp;amp;R—that helped me out some.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So how long were you on <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> for, then?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, R&amp;amp;R maybe took up <date>five days</date>, <date>six days</date>, you know? Another <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> part about that I, you know went to where we get on the plane for the <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName>, and here again is [<persName>Robert</persName>] “Bob” <persName>Corey</persName>, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> ’<date>65</date>. He’s on R&amp;amp;R on the same plane. And we’re going to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>—me, to meet my parents and <persName>Bob</persName>, to meet his wife. We played cribbage all the way from—from <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> to <placeName>Honolulu</placeName> and spent a little time together on <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> there, and again on the way back, we saw each other. And <persName>Bob</persName> met—met my parents.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So, yeah, I was actually going to ask: How much did your parents—or how much did you keep in contact with your parents, and how much did you tell them about your experience?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, my parents and my family wrote me a lot and sent me all kinds of stuff, and, you know, I wrote them as often as I could. You know, I wrote nosy, good—newsy, I’m sorry—good letters and told them—you know, tried to tell them about what life was like. I tempered the scary stuff, took them out and put in a lot of reassurance about, you know, that—you know, “All this stuff is going on. I’m good at what I’m doing, and I’ll be back.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. But, you know, I definitely sheltered them, but not totally. And I think, you know, on the <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> I told them a little bit more about what—about what was going on. And it was pretty hard—pretty hard to have any kind of authentic conservation if you’re completely hiding the hardest—you know, the most important stuff that’s going on in your life. I don’t remember specifics, but mostly we had fun, but I think I told them about stuff.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I remember one interesting thing. Have you ever heard of “<persName>Donald T. L.] “Don” Ho</persName>?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">I’m not sure.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE"><persName>Don Ho</persName> was a very well-known nightclub entertainer in <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, and he was a kind of syrupy—I don’t know for some reason—anyway, we went to the <persName>Don Ho</persName> show. It was just typical for everybody, all R&amp;amp;R guys. And in his show he at one point—it might have been even the very beginning—he—he—he did some horrible patriotic thing that I just couldn’t stomach. You know, a <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> thing.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I don’t remember the details of it, but I couldn't take it, and I just got up and walked out, and my mom and dad and my uncle, who were with me—who were with them—they—they walked out with me. and we were the only ones. Everybody else was eating it up, but it was—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And then another thing that happened: You know, I told you I spent an evening with this woman that I was sweet on, and we were—we were kind of drunk in a bar somewhere, and we got to talking with a guy who—another guy, a Marine—I don’t know if he was a Marine or not, but another guy on <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And he was drunk. And it turns out that his job had something to do with—with air control, you know?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And he started saying some- —he started saying something about, “If you ever get in a situation where there’s a mistaken bombing run”—and you can imagine how that triggered me, and I just got furious in this guy in a second.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And kind of uncharacteristically for me, told him off—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—told him off. You know, it was a strange thing to have happen.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I was doing my best to have a good time, but I was [chuckles]—I was not in very good shape.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">It still really affected you, yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">All right. And how was that, after having some time off? How did it affect you?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, you know—okay, so by this time I’m one of the most experienced guys in the platoon because there’s so much attrition—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—you know, guys getting wounded, guys getting killed, guys getting sick—you know, guys leaving for one reason or another. And I’m—you know, I’m pretty convinced that I’m the only one that really knows how to—how to run this platoon. And I still have this really strong commitment to just keeping guys alive. So there’s—there’s a part of me that, you know, wants to get back to my—to my job, and, you know, there’s another part of me that—that just wants to get home to the States. So, you know, I don’t know, I just got sent back to my platoon and started—started doing the same thing again.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">They would have, you know, <date>45 days</date>, <date>a month</date> left to go.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And at that point, everybody, especially the guys themselves, but everybody else in the platoon is getting really nervous about, you know, them surviving this little bit of time they’d got left.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">For me, that took the form of doing everything I possibly could to somehow get those guys left behind in An <placeName>Hoa</placeName> when we would go out on operations—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—you know, to get them totally out of—out of the field. Or if they had to go out in the field, to have them at least be doing the safest job I could possibly have for them to do out there. Well, this actually was in huge tension with sort of the bureaucratic functioning of <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> in that context, you know, so there’s a first sergeant back in An <placeName>Hoa</placeName>, who’s in charge of getting people into the field and keeping as many people as possible out in the field, and he’s resisting all this at every step that he can.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And they’re seeing something—I’m doing something totally from the perspective of myself and the Marines in my platoon, and the people above me are seeing it from a—you know, a bigger <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> perspective.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And the tension—the tension is huge and a big—big part of my life. You know, I saw a lot of my emotional energy went into protecting these short-timers, we called them.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.  So as you got towards the end of your time there, how did you—did you also try to avoid doing certain things?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Eh, I don’t—[Laughs.] Okay, so I’m going to fast forward <date>about a month</date>, to another incident. In the three times that we were out on our amazing operation called <placeName>Meade River</placeName>, where we had gone—I’m just going to skip that. <placeName>Meade River</placeName> was a very big operation, and there were some interesting things that happened.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—and I actually—I actually loved being up there in those mountains. It was a triple canopy and some of the most beautiful forest you could possibly imagine. It just enchanted me, and I wanted—it was such a strange thing to have happen, you know, under those conditions, but—but it was the monsoon time, and we had a lot of rain, and that was hard to deal with, but we were good at that. And there was also a lot of periods when it would clear. And I don’t know how much time you’ve spent in the mountains, but when it gets sunny after—after rains, it’s so beautiful.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know? So—and there wasn’t anything really happening. We were running patrols, and there were ambushes at night and stuff like that, and nothing was happening, so it was—there were a lot of parts of it that were enjoyable.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And so there were really only two guys in this platoon with the amount of experience that I trusted completely. So we were running a patrol <date>one day</date>, which is—our job is to follow the trail that—that had been discovered through the mountains and search for base camps and stuff. And at one point in the patrol, we’re going along a creek valley, and then the trail leaves <placeName>the creek valley</placeName>, and there’s a little switchback right at the bottom there, and it starts to go climb the mountainside.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So we get on radio to the company commander and tell him this, and he says, “Okay, well, move on up the trail.” So we move on up the trail. Okay. So I’ll just tell you who these guys are. On point is a guy named <persName>Ray [W.] Hesterlee</persName>. Very sweet, baby-faced kid from—from <placeName>Georgia</placeName>. Just—you know, again, the opposite of what you would—how you would picture a Marine. Just the nicest, most thoughtful, most generous person you could—you could ever encounter. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So that gets into, you know, kind of your questions about the mission. So when the triple canopy helicopter can’t land, we’ve got a wounded guy and a dead guy to get out. And the way that happens is the helicopter comes, hovers over where we are and drops a wire harness, like a loop at the end of a wire rope, and first of all—you know, you hauled up the wounded guy that way, and then put the loop around <persName>Ray</persName> and pulled him out—up. I’m not—I’m not a religious person, but as <persName>Ray</persName> was being hauled up, you know, his—his arms were extended out to his side, and it was just—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—an inescapable <persName>Christ</persName> image. And, you know, <persName>Ray</persName> was kind of, you know, almost saintly in a <persName>Christ</persName> way.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It was just an image I still carry. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">At this point, the orders from the company commander are to continue the patrol, continue up the trail. And, you know, I’m not going to do it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There’s no point—there’s no point in going up this fucking trail. You know, the only other thing—the only thing that could possible happen is we would walk into another ambush. We’re not going to be killing anybody. It’s only us that’s going to be killed. I’m not doing it. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Again, this is a strong—strong image that I have of this—you know, here’s—here our enemy. Our enemy has just killed a guy I love. You know, I’ll tell you <persName>Emily</persName>, there was—there was no—I don’t—you know, I don’t think me or anybody else that saw this guy, that there was any—any hatred. He was in the same position that we were.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, if he had—if you could at all open your heart looking at him, all you could feel was—was sympathy.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. Well, you know. So the next morning, get—get him evacuated out there, and, you know, it came—it came to the company <orgName>LZ</orgName>, and the company commander was never any of the wiser that I hadn’t followed the—the platoon—you know, the patrol route.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And so I had—you know, a bunch of us had received a bunch of <date>Christmas</date> stuff from—from home. But I was in really sad mental—mental shape at this time, and really, you know, it’s like, Aw, I can’t do this anymore. You know, it was, like, I cannot go out on another patrol. I can’t be there when another guy gets killed for no reason.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I’m really  struggling with myself about whether or not I should just go to the company commander and say, “I refuse to serve anymore.”</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">“Let the chips fall where they may.” At the same time, it’s <date>Christmas</date> time, and we’re celebrating. That—that same resilience is there, and I’ve got this—my mom—my mom sent me a kind of a Merry Christmas—you know, a string of letters spelling out <persName>Merry Christmas</persName> that you could hang someplace?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we hung it over my foxhole, and we still have a picture of this Merry <date>Christmas</date> sign hanging over my foxhole in the jungle.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Anyway, so <date>one day</date>—one day just right at this time, a helicopter comes in with resupply, and two new lieutenants get off the helicopter. And one of them takes over my platoon, and the other one takes over another platoon. And I don’t have—all of a sudden—I still have to stay in the field, but my new job is executive officer, second in command, and also weapons platoon commander. And I don’t have to go on patrols anymore. And I’m not really—I’m not really responsible for a platoon of men. And, you know, I don’t want to go to prison, and this takes the pressure off enough for me to let go of—of what I’d been struggling with.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. And so, you know, what happened after that I think is sort of <date>two more months</date> in that job, and then it was pretty typical for Marine lieutenants to only serve about seven—six, <date>seven months</date> in the field and get some kind of a job in the rear. And I got a job—at that point, I got a job in the rear. My first one was the assistant operations officer for the battalion.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Oh.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">He was a career <orgName>Marine</orgName>. He was the highest—that’s the highest job a military man can have.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. Wow.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I replaced <persName>Pete</persName>. [Chuckles.] But anyway, I didn’t have the job for very long. I didn’t fit it in very well. I was not a pog—I was not a pog Marine; I was a field <orgName>Marine</orgName> all the way, and I—I—I only felt good doing—doing a field job. I got sent to even a more pog-y job, which was assistant operations for the regiment.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I was, like, the guy who received the reports from the field and passed them on to the operations officer, stuff like that. it was kind of—kind of a flunky job, but I was—on the other hand, I—I read every report that came in from the field, so I knew exactly what was going on, and I was also, like, a witness to the decision-making processes of the higher-ups.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I hated that job. I hated the way they thought. I hated the decisions they made. And I ended up requesting to go—go back into the field. I was going to go back to my—I think even my old platoon. And at that point, my brother, who was a lawyer, also a <orgName>Marine</orgName> but a lawyer, came to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. There was a regulation that you only had to have one brother in country at the same time, so I had a chance—chance to leave. I think I only had <date>a month</date> left in my tour.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Instead of going back to the field, I left. I left <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Got out <date>a month early</date>. I did <date>12 months</date> instead of 13.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So I guess this is a good time to move to your time after <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but just, again, I want to check in and see if you want to talk about something you either forgot about or that I didn't ask you about, just before we move on.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, there’s probably things that I might have forgotten to tell you about, but, you know, I feel like—I feel like I’ve gotten at most of it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. Great.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But we can move on, yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. So you got back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> after a year, and how—how was that experience, coming home? How were you treated differently?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, I actually had, you know, an easy homecoming. I was, I spent <date>a month</date> in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName> on the way home because, you know, I was out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but I was still in what was called <orgName>the Western Pacific Command</orgName>, so I—I—I finished my tour in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName>, and so that was kind of a defusing time. It was a real limbo time, and, you know, I had nothing—no positive memories of it, but it was just killing time. I had some—some unimportant job I was supposed to be doing, but—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—I wasn’t thinking about debriefing <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. PTSD [Post-traumatic stress disorder] had not been heard of [chuckles] at the time, or not in that form. So, you know, “back to the world” is what we called it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And it was, like, you know, carrying on and enjoying life.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So how long would you say it took for you to sort of settle back at home and start, you know, moving on from your <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, like I say, you know, I didn’t delve into my—I just—I just carried the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience under my skin and just tried to live—you know, especially in that leave period, just trying to—trying to live.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And I got a disappointment with—with my next orders. You know, I had interesting places where I wanted to be stationed, but instead I got sent down to [unintelligible] Marine Base, Camp Lejeune, and assigned to another infantry—infantry battalion that was getting ready for the job of being on board ship in the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName> [Sea] for <date>a month</date>—for <date>six months</date>. And I had to do that for a while. And, oh, that was like, you know, all the—all the <orgName>Stateside</orgName> activities that Marines and military people usually do was pretty small stuff for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> veterans. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Oh—on the ship? Sorry, on the ship that you were on?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">In <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> in general, on the ship. I was involved in a way. There was a—a black <orgName>Marine</orgName> sergeant who decided that, you know, the situation for his people in the country was such that he wasn’t going to serve anymore, and, you know, he got thrown in the brig [military prison]. And I—I used to spend time with him and other black Marines, kind of talking about things. I had a lot of black Marines under my command and did my best to, you know, relate to them. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—and eventually get themselves in trouble, you know? A lot of things were—a lot of hard situations.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And then eventually, you know, got back from the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>, and I did a job. I was working in the <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> base legal division, quite an easy job, and then eventually I—an early out came on. I should have spent <date>a few years</date> on active duty, but I think I got out maybe <date>two or three months early</date> because they were downsizing <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> a little bit, so—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know? Okay, so then I’m out of <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName>, and, again, I’m really not—it was hard being still in <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> and having to put up with <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> bullshit and, you know, the difficult positions I was in, but I wasn’t really feeling mental anguish from—from the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> stuff. You  know, I started living in the ways that I wanted to be living, and what I ended up doing: I wanted to travel. I wanted to ski. I wanted to play more hockey. And I ended up going to <placeName>Europe</placeName> by working as a hockey player-coach on hockey teams in European ski resorts. I did that for a <date>winter</date>—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Woah! [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. I did that for a winter in <placeName>Austria</placeName> and then <date>four winters</date> in <placeName>Val d’Isère</placeName>, <placeName>France</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, I was in the mountains. I was doing what I wanted to do. I was very interested. I was learning languages. I was leading a real physical life. Had lots of friends, lots of fun. And, you know, that’s how I lived. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I can’t say that I was—you know, I was having—I was having my—my mental problems and not—not really knowing exactly what they were. You know, I know <date>today</date> that—I know <date>today</date> that I had <orgName>PTSD</orgName>. Well, I—I—I went through <date>three years</date> of group therapy on <orgName>PTSD</orgName>. I know a fair amount about it. And one of the biggest affects that it can have, and I think that it did have on me, was it can slow your emotional or stall your emotional maturation process.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know? So in a lot of ways, I think in the way I related to people I was—I didn’t really grow the way that you grow and mature through the normal course of a lifetime.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So, you know, I think that probably affected things like relationships with my—you know, with my love affairs and things, and made it hard for me to, like—you know, I certainly wasn’t going to undertake anything, you know—I lost a lot of faith in political systems, the way the world runs, and I wasn’t going to step out of my—you know, I was basically going to live life for myself and my friends. You know, I wasn’t going to take on anything that would take me beyond that.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Well, I think it was there from the get-go. I think it was like a slow drip, and it took a long time—what took a long time before it affected my life to the point where I recognized that I had it—it didn’t take that long before it started to affect my life. I didn’t really know what was—what was going on, and it was in I think <date>the late ’80s</date> before I really said, Oh ok, it’s <orgName>PTSD</orgName>,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—and do something about it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So you mentioned the emotional maturity, but what other sorts of ways did it affect your life?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I’d say, you know, kind of a depression and a hopelessness. It was like I would have these periods, and increasingly as <date>the years</date> went by, of—it was like life—you know, the—the world is such a shit sandwich, not necessarily maybe life, because I’ll always—I was always having plenty of fun when I was in the mood to have fun,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—but I would get in these periods where it was, like, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, this world is so fucked up! And what’s the point? And, you know, You did things that you never should have done, and you know, in a way, you don’t deserve to live. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And sometimes I would just sort of pass <date>days</date> that way. And sometimes I would—I would—I would fantasize about going someplace where there was some kind of war going on and—and going—going—going and fighting that war,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—which was probably some sort of a death wish or something. I’m not really sure of the psychology of that, you know?</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">But I didn’t have—didn’t have flashbacks, didn’t have too much trouble sleeping. On the contrary, probably too much sleeping was more of a problem.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">You know, a lot of guilt. I made mistakes. Everybody does. Mistakes—mistakes literally cost lives. But you know, looking at it now, and having been told so by a lot of guys I served with, [He starts to weep; unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So when you started to realize that there was a problem, what did you find was the most helpful sort of resource that you had? Was it talking to other vets or doctors or—</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There was group therapy. And I’ll just give you, you know, kind of a brief history of things. At one point in <date>the middle ’80s</date>, <date>early ’80s</date>, I found myself—I had a girlfriend and had two friends who had built this sailboat, and they were starting a trip around the world, and they needed a couple of people to sail to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName> from <placeName>Washington</placeName> state, where I was living at the time.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Talked to [unintelligible] my girlfriend, and I sailed out there. We broke up, but I stayed out in <placeName>Hawaii</placeName> for <date>a year</date>, and I had a friend out there who had loaned me a house, an isolated house in a really beautiful place. And I think, you know, the things that I was just talking to you about just kind of really started to affect me in a severe way out there. But on the other hand, I was completely free to just sink into it entirely.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And at some point, towards <date>the end of that year</date>—and I really can’t tell you why—but it came to me that my next step was to go to <orgName>the University of Washington</orgName>, get a teaching certificate and become a teacher.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And, you know, the idea behind it was, Well, if anything ever is gonna change, it’s gotta change with the way people think. You know, I went into the war without knowing what the war was about, and if education was being done right, people would think—would learn what the war was about, and then we’d have better decisions about it all.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">So, you know—and that was a huge step for me. Like I say, I wasn’t going to have anything to do with anything that committed or anything that involved in, like, public life. You know, I did exactly what I planned to do: went back to school at the <orgName>U.</orgName>, became a teacher. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—what kind of questions—what kind of questions to ask him to help him keep going.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Learned a lot of, you know, things about fully feeling feelings, what intimacy is—skills, in a lot of ways, you know? Acceptance.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">One thing I can really remember is accepting the fact that whatever anybody did in any war that’s ever been fought, however horrible it was—[Adolf] <persName>Hitler</persName>, whoever you want to name—under the right circumstances, I could have done the same thing.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And even though—even though I didn’t—you know, I deserve to live. And, you know, I learned things like to look at myself in the mirror and—and say—I don’t know, it was something like, You’re loveable, fully knowing I didn’t believe it but just saying—just saying it anyway. You know.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Just facing—just facing things. I did it there for <date>three years</date>. It was a revolving group, and we’d kind of renew every 10, <date>12 weeks</date> or so. You know, a new commitment to stay with the group. People changing all the time. But the leaders stayed the same—stayed the same, and at <date>the end of three years</date>, he said, “You know, I think you’re ready to graduate from this.” </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Then—and I did. And really at that point—<orgName>PTSD</orgName> still affects me a lot, you know.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I’m very aware I have it, and, you know, <date>there’s</date>—there’s a really sad side to me, but, you know, I can—I can handle it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. Because that group gave you sort of the tools to deal with it.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. And, you know, especially since you’re gonna be talking with <persName>Juanita</persName> [<persName>F. Ramsey-Jevne</persName>], you know, it has—it has a huge effect on—on the people who are closest to me. You know, intimacy is tough. And, you know, intimacy with my parents and my family and especially intimacy with—with <persName>Juanita</persName>. It’s been—been a long—you know, an ongoing, still-in-process thing as to how to—you know, how to keep that. And I think—you know, that’s, intimacy is—is a lifelong thing, it’s always growing. But with <orgName>PTSD</orgName>—you know, I can be scared shitless of—of intimacy. It can be the scariest thing in the world. So just to live with that fear and keep it from going deeper, but it’s hard.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It’s especially hard for—for my partner.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">What was that like, going back, especially after struggling with <orgName>PTSD</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">That was maybe one of the healthiest things that I could have done. The trip was offered to my brother and me by my mom. She paid for it, and she kind of paid for it in style. So we were able to do it—you know, do it in a way where we didn’t have to pay attention to how much it cost, which meant that we—we could have drivers and interpreters and stuff like that.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we spent a certain amount of time sort of visiting historical sites and battle sites in the northern part of the old <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, which was called I <orgName>Corps</orgName>. That was kind of the first part of the trip. And then we—then we actually traveled around, mostly by motorbike, with our—with our guide/interpreter in the actual area where I was in combat.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Then visiting a lot of the places where I’d been in battles. And so it was all hugely therapeutic. You know, I knew the Vietnamese people were lovely people, and I wanted to connect with them before I ever went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> the first time, and, you know, I was aware that that was a big part of what I was going back there for. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we had one of the early digital cameras, so could take photos and show them to the people right away.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">We got a lot of laughs out of that. So, you know, like, it was  a lot of really rich contact with—with the Vietnamese people. And the countryside was beautiful. Kind of that triple canopy jungle’s all gone; all the trees have been cut. That was a disappointment, but I did get up into the mountains and had some experiences up there. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">So it was a good trip, then?</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It really just kind of, you know—it allowed me to experience <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at peace and to know that it truly is at peace. You know, the people there, whether they were involved in the war or not—most of them are too young—they’re not—they’re not hanging onto it. They’ve let it go.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">There are war memorials everywhere. They honor their people that participated, and, you know, it’s a big part of their national identity,—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—you know, American vets can—can move around over there and feel really welcomed and comfortable, and that felt good.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, that’s great.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah, okay. Well, I mean, the lasting effect is prostate cancer, which I have known that I have since <date>1999</date>, so that’s <date>16 years</date> now. Actually, my first scare came with it in <date>1994</date>, but I—I but also really I’ve been dealing with it for <date>over 20 years</date>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">I didn’t really know that when I was first diagnosed, and my mentality is such—was such at the time that I didn't want to have anything to do with the <placeName>VA</placeName> or really the government in any way.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Just didn’t trust—and so I never—I never put in for benefits; I just dealt with it, you know, through my private insurance and then eventually, when I became <date>65</date>, through <orgName>Medicare</orgName>. But I’ve had a lot of treatment—a lot of treatment. I’ve had my prostate removed. I’ve had radiation in several different forms. I still take testosterone blockage to keep my body from producing testosterone, which the prostate cancer kind of thrives on.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">It’s affected my life quite strongly. I’m still pretty healthy and pretty active, but it kind of—you know, through all that time—would have been sort of under an increasing specter of, you know, possible death from this. And, you know, obviously this affects especially my wife and my son.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And, you know, it’s at a stage now where it’s metastatic in my bones. I don’t have any particular symptoms from the prostate cancer itself, but it’s kind of threatening in that it—it—things could go very south very fast—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—and could make me really unhealthy or—or kill me. So, you know, it’s something that we live with.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And we have to—it’s a strange situation because we have to be aware of it, accept it, and yet at the same time not let it run our lives. </u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">And that’s day-to-day—I have—no, I have a really smart understanding—you know, committed, willing to go wherever life takes us, beautiful wife, and if there’s any reward to having the condition I have it’s, you know, what comes from sharing it with her.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Right. That’s great.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah. I—I—I think we should probably wrap it up, <persName>Emily</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Something nice that happened that I just kind of want to get on the tape: You know, [<persName>James E.]</persName> “<persName>Jim” Wright</persName>, who was president of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> before the present—the current president, was at reunion, and a great historian, of course, and he’s also—he’s writing a book about, you know, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> combat experiences and how it’s affected people. And I’m grateful for that. [His voice cracks with emotion.]</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">[He weeps.] You know, so it’s been where <persName>Bill Smoyer</persName> died and where <persName>Duncan</persName> [B.] Sleigh [Class of <date>1967</date>] another a guy from our—our class, not somebody I knew but he was actually in my <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> class and my Marine training class, but I—I don’t remember him. Anyway, he died, and <persName>Bill</persName> died. You know, <persName>Jim</persName>’s been back there. You know, it’s—and what you’re doing—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—you know, it means a lot to us to be remembered and—[weeps]—and to have our—our college do it.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. My, yeah, that’s—</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Yeah.  So thanks—thanks for what you’re doing, and thanks to—</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, I just wanted to—</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">—to all who are involved.</u>
      <u who="CUMMINGS">Yeah, thank you so much for speaking with us. You know, it’s reasons like that that we’re doing it, so it was really great to speak with you. I’m going to stop the recording right now.</u>
      <u who="JEVNE">Okay. </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
