<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="CHUNG"/>
        <person xml:id="JOLLY"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="JOLLY"><placeName>Virginia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><placeName>Virginia</placeName>, yes. Sorry. Awesome. Right. Mr. <persName>Jolly</persName>, thank you so much for taking your time to have this interview with me. Right. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Okay. I was born in <placeName>West Virginia</placeName>. You used the location before, and that’s where—I am a West Virginian, a native. My parents were both from southeastern <placeName>Ohio</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Great. Yeah. So before we get into kind of how you started your college years at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, I actually would like to hear just a little bit more about your childhood. And, you know, you said it was a, you know, rough terrain but it was a good place to grow up, so I just wanted to hear a little bit more about, you know, what you liked to do as a child, if you had any sibling[s]. Like, maybe talk a little bit about your elementary and middle school experience as well?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I could wander around and spend a lot of time on that.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Go on.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, high school was seven or eight miles away. It was a fairly large high school, about, I would say, 1,300 students or so, in three grades. I sort of left my little town then and joined the larger community and become involved in all sorts of high school activities. Got grades or <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> wouldn’t have welcomed me. Good grades.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Great. Now, I find it really fascinating that you were a part of Boy Scout[s] and <orgName>Eagle</orgName> Scout[s] during your childhood because I know a lot of things kind of [that] they do is very much of an outdoor activity, and it also in a way kind of prepares for you, like, kind of to be out there, and I guess even, like, in times of, like, emergencies and war, kind of, you know, you really get those trainings to prepare yourself for that, so it would be great if I can hear a little bit more about, you know, your <orgName>Boy Scout</orgName> and <orgName>Eagle Scout</orgName> experience. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, actually, <orgName>the Boy Scouts</orgName> were great training for the military, which came later, in that you were part of a group. You were aware from your parents when you were <date>11 or 12 years old</date>. You had to learn to function in this group. You had adult supervision, but it was pretty much a group of kids sorting things out for themselves. You learned about nature. You learned about, you know, First Aid, citizenship, all kinds of good, healthy things. Electricity. I had an aviation merit badge that—I’ve never flown a plane, but if I ever had an emergency, I would try to think back to what my aviation merit badge taught me about landing. I would never take off, but I’m able to land.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Great. Right. Great. Awesome. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Probably <date>the first week</date>, I was frightened because I had always been on top. Now, I was first in my high school class. I was—always got good grades. I just thought I was pretty sharp. But the people that I met were equally sharp, that—they were from different places, knew different things. Particularly, some seemed much more sophisticated than I was. If you’re from <placeName>Connecticut</placeName> and you go into a prep school, you’re a little bit ahead of, in some ways, a high school graduate out of <placeName>West Virginia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Great. And what did you study in <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and what are some different activities and organizations that you were involved in [at] <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I started out, like probably many people at the time—things were going on in society when I was in the ninth grade, tenth grade. There was <name type="event">the Cold War</name>, and there was <persName>Sputnik</persName>, and there was space exploration, and so we were all to be engineers. And so I began as an engineering student and took the necessary courses, actually through <date>my first three years</date> at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, or two and two-thirds years, something like that. Took a lot of math courses, physics, German, and the normal distributive requirement sorts of courses. I ended up, though—the first part of engineering, I understood and it was good, but at some point I went into a class <date>one day</date> and there was a board full of equations, none of which I could relate to any practical thing. And at that time my engineering grades started to go down, and I fled from it into—about the only way I could get enough credits to graduate was to combine economics and mathematics, so it was an economics major modified math, because I had already taken a lot of math courses that would count to the combined major.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I assume most everyone still at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is involved with the [<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>] Outing Club, if for no other reason than to get good rates at the [<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>] <persName>Skiway</persName>. I wasn’t a—I was a member—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—but not a major participant. For a while, I was in what was called <orgName>the Dartmouth Society of Engineers</orgName>, besides ROTC [Reserve Officers’ Training Corps], which was a major user, my activity was to be in a fraternity. I was in <placeName>Phi Kappa Psi</placeName>, which is no longer an actual fraternity on the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> campus. [It is now <orgName>Panarchy</orgName>.] But we were strong at the time.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see.  And, yeah, as you’ve just briefly mentioned, that it seems like <orgName>ROTC</orgName> has been a big part of your <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> experience, and [I] just kind of want to hear about, like, what motivated you to join <orgName>ROTC</orgName> and what was your experience like there?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I think I—you know, coming from—<placeName>West Virginia</placeName> is a state that’s, for one reason or another, known for being involved in the military. I think it probably still has one of the highest per capita participation rates in the military of the country, so growing up in that environment and seeing veterans coming back—and I can remember <name type="event">World War II</name> veterans when I was quite small and seeing <name type="event">Korean War</name> veterans, and it just seemed natural. And my brother had been in the <orgName>Army</orgName>, so it seemed natural that the military would be there somehow. You didn’t question. Sort of if called, you would go. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Yeah. I just find it really interesting that, you know, from a very young age, you were exposed to, you know, seeing many veterans coming from their big wars, so I’m just, like, wondering if you had I guess interaction with any of these veterans and, like, any kind of—I guess kind of childhood memories that you have about these veterans.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Not any specific—you know, I just remembered they had gone to war, and once in a while would tell a story or something, but it wasn’t that, you know, I had a strong, vivid experience or anything with that. I had a great uncle that I can recall who was wounded in <name type="event">World War I</name>, in <placeName>France</placeName>, and it greatly affected him. It would be what we now call <placeName>PTSD</placeName> [post-traumatic stress disorder]. I think that he was a dashing young man, from the pictures before his time in <name type="event">World War I</name>, and he was sort of a broken person after that. He had been wounded. And so I didn’t understand all that; I just knew he had been a soldier. So, again, no—I can’t recall many things. It was just men in town had been in the military. I knew that and not much more than that.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. And it’s also interesting that—because it seems like you just have a lot of exposure to, like, military and <orgName>ROTC</orgName> in general, even prior to kind of joining one yourself, so I also would like to hear a little bit about—more in detail about kind of the impressions that you had from seeing your brother in <placeName>ROTC</placeName> and in [the] <orgName>Army</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Just my brother and I were <date>ten years</date> apart, and, you know, so we were never close growing up or anything, but it was a little bit of I respected him, and I wouldn’t call it worship, but he introduced me to many things that perhaps my parents didn’t. And he would tell me things about the military. He was in the Reserves at the same time, so he went to a <orgName>Reserve</orgName> camp. And he knew the names of weapons and various military vehicles that he could pass on to me, and it was just a way of learning, I guess.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And did your brother go to any of those big wars, maybe—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><name type="event">—Vietnam War or Korean War</name>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">He was—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay.  And so—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—on active duty right after <name type="event">the Korean War</name>, so it would have been in the, oh, I think ’55 through ’57 period that he was on active duty. Never left—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Oh, okay.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—<placeName>the United States</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And what was his position and role in [the] <orgName>Army</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It was strange. He had been in <placeName>ROTC</placeName> when he was going to college and was in the Reserves at the same time.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Great. And would you say what your brother did in [the] <orgName>Army</orgName> and, like, his position and his duty kind of in a way influenced your decision in making—in your decision of—I guess your role and what you want[ed] to do in [the] <orgName>Army</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Probably not. It may have had a little bit of influence and made me be interested in the <orgName>Army</orgName> or—you know,—I’ll get off on another subject here in a little bit, but it was just something that looked like the natural course for me. It wasn’t like, Gee, I want to be just like him. There was an earlier point where I thought about going to [<orgName>the U.S. Military Academy</orgName> at] West Point or the brand-new [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Air Force Academy</orgName>. And—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I see. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So, yeah, I guess kind of talking now more in details about your <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC experience, it would be great if you can tell me a little bit about, like, kind of how often you were trained and what kind of training that you received and maybe your typical <date>daily</date> routine as an <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It varied over <date>the years</date>. There were different programs. But generally every <date>Wednesday</date> you had what was called “drill,” and that was usually on Chase Field, if you know where that is. Down beyond where the [<persName>Rupert C.]</persName> <persName>Thompson Arena</persName> is, is where we would drill. We would form up behind Alumni Gym[nasium] and march down there, and in your <date>early years</date>, you just drilled and learned all the—you know, how to turn right and left and “about face” and what to do with your M-1 [Garand] rifle, which is the rifle that we had. And so that was pretty much <date>the first year</date>. But you also had a class going on, and you’d get a grade in military science, but it was—the class was an hour or I think two hour classes a week or so, and <date>the first year</date>, it was just introduction to military. It was what the ranks are and how to recognize them and how to address an officer and go to military courtesy as much as anything else, I think. And you later picked up, you know, the military alphabet, how to say those, and you started into radio telephone communication, and gradually it increased over <date>the four years</date>, and you would get more—there was also—I wasn’t in it; my two roommates were—there was a mountain and <date>winter</date> warfare detachment at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Great.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">The biggest difference is boys versus men. You know, we were now men and what we were about was serious, because there were in <date>1961</date>, ’62 there was <name type="event">the Cold War</name>, and there was Cuban Missile Crisis, and that made it seem a little serious. But it was—coming back from summer camp, on the radio I heard about something called “<placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin</placeName>.” And <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was just a small thing that was in ’63, ’64 starting up, you might say. But this was a grown-up world versus the boys’ world, but there were certainly similarities. You had uniforms. You were outside. You had to get along in the trees.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Great.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">We had—I forgot to mention also, I believe <date>our junior year</date>, a military history course, and it was taught by <orgName>the history department</orgName> at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I forget the name of <name type="event">the gentleman—[Louis C.] “</name><persName>Lou</persName>” <persName>Morton</persName>; it seems like <persName>Morton</persName> was his name, anyway. Was a professor who taught the class.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And we had a lot of reading and lectures about various battles and strategy and tactics. You know, he went clear back to the Romans and the Carthaginians and up through <name type="event">the American Civil War</name> and <name type="event">World War II</name>, and so this was a regular <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> course, but it was mandatory for the military science students.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And anything that you kind of learned outside the military science courses, like math or engineering or economics? Like, were they kind of relevant to what you’ve learned inside military science courses in any manner, or no?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">As it turned out, you know, the job I ended up in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> certainly—I was working with computers, and so the math background when you’re out on a pile of rocks with the computer was helpful. But more than anything, just the liberal education at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was helpful because you had to deal with diverse people from all walks of life, with different motivations, and to have seen the broader world that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> introduced you to made you a better officer, I think. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. And you told me that you went to <orgName>ROTC summer</orgName> camp in your junior summer. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah. So would it be possible for you to tell me a little bit about what that experience was like, now that you are mingling with cadets from, like, other schools, like, and now you’re no longer in, like, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> setting but in a different place?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I think <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> had a reputation among all the schools that were there of being good. We had—our lead non-commissioned officer attached to the <orgName>Dartmouth ROTC</orgName> unit was <persName>Sgt</persName>. Major <persName>William</persName> [R. “Sarge”] <persName>Brown</persName>. And <persName>Sgt</persName>. <persName>Brown</persName> was a veteran of both <name type="event">the World War II</name> and going up the boot of <placeName>Italy</placeName> against the Germans, but he also was on the Yalu [River] when the Chinese came across the <persName>Yalu</persName>. As I remember the story, he became a battalion commander, which is roughly 1,000 men. He was the highest-ranking officer. He wasn’t an officer; he was a sergeant, but he was the highest-ranking person left alive. So he had all kinds of experiences, and had a great reputation. He was really a good guy, but he wouldn’t let you know it, so just his image made us have a good image also. So—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And what—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Are you there?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.] Yeah. What is the trophy about? </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">The trophy—it’s for map reading, that there were 1,600 guys in this camp,—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Ohh!</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—<orgName>ROTC</orgName> students and one of my friends from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and I got the only perfect scores on the map reading test, and I have to hear about this whenever I get lost. I’ve got a trophy.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But I sort of took pride in it, because I never beat 1,600 people before in anything, so—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right!</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">That’s just—you know, that’s the kind of thing—we also learned that in classes at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, in the military science classes of how to read a map. And I still don’t need GPS [<orgName>Global Positioning System</orgName>]. I’m fairly good at the old-fashioned way.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. So other than that reading which you did really well, apparently, I could tell, what were some other trainings that you received during the <placeName>ROTC</placeName> camp, <orgName>ROTC summer</orgName> camp, and were they really different from the previous training you received at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No, not so much. It was just more of it on a bigger scale. It’s interesting that we were still taught to fight in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. [Chuckles.] The whole—the tactics we learned at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—were you were—we had a battle line. And you had the forward edge. It was called the <orgName>FEBA</orgName>, the forward edge of the battle area. And you had the I think <orgName>IP</orgName> [initial point] or something when you cross that in an attack. And everything was geared to what the military knew. It wasn’t geared to the next war; it was geared to where they had experience, so we were pretty much trained to fight in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. You just did things on a larger scale. There were now tanks.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Right. Ooh, that sounds very intense. Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And you got different weapons. You practiced the old-fashioned bayonet and machine guns, and you fired rocket launchers. We were exposed to military aviation, even branches because we had to choose our branches by <date>our senior year</date>, and so each branch of the <orgName>Army</orgName> would have an orientation program and tell them what their branch did.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. So, yeah, I guess talking a little bit about your <orgName>ROTC</orgName> experience in your senior year, so now you have to make [a] decision on which branch you want to join and I guess kind of where you want to take away with your—on <orgName>ROTC</orgName> experience at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. So it would be great if you can tell me a little bit about that.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Okay. You had to—I’m trying to think what—you had to choose one combat branch. Combat is infantry, artillery, engineers—I think that—and maybe [<orgName>U.S. Army] Signal Corps</orgName>, but infantry, artillery—armor and engineers. You had to select one of those, and your top three choices, and if you selected—there was something you selected, you had to choose a fourth. And my first choice was armor because I had taken German, and I thought we had a lot of troops in <placeName>Germany</placeName> and, Well, if I’m in the armory, they’ll send me to <placeName>Germany</placeName> because, you know, that’s where armor goes. So that was my first choice. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Yeah, so you said your first choice was armor because you wanted to go to <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and is there any particular reason why you wanted to go to <placeName>Germany</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah, well, <persName>Elvis</persName> [<persName>A.]</persName> <persName>Presley</persName> was there, and why not join <persName>Elvis</persName>? I just had taken German and wanted to see <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and I thought I would like to see <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and it wasn’t a great—it was an inspiration in the hallway: If I’m going somewhere, I might as well go to <placeName>Germany</placeName>. And I would get to speak a little of the German I had learned at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Mmm. I see. It’s just sort of really interesting because I guess kind of your impression of <placeName>Germany</placeName> would have been formed from your previous knowledge of, like, <name type="event">World War II</name> and all that, so I just kind of find it interesting how that you were kind of attracted to that language and that country, specifically when, you know, the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> has been fighting <placeName>Germany</placeName> for such a long period—well, not too long, but, like, a considerable number of <date>years</date>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I don’t know, I think I was attracted to German more because it was at the time we were all to be engineers, and German was a good engineering language. Russian seemed to be too foreign to me. It was also a good engineering language. So that was more the attraction than any sort of a <name type="event">World War II</name> or having much knowledge of <placeName>Germany</placeName>. I had to pick German, French or Spanish, and I tried German.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Great. Yeah. So now you I guess—you have decided your branch, the branch that you would be joining, so it would be great now if I could hear a little bit about kind of the graduation ceremony and your military career shortly after graduation.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Okay. It was also in this time, I should mention—when I started <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>1961</date>, as I mentioned, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was just a—you know, you’d heard that there was something going on there, but I was a different generation than those who came to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>1966</date>. Things changed abruptly. You know, we just—I don’t know. A good many of us were in either <orgName>Army</orgName>, <orgName>Navy</orgName> or Air Force ROTC. We didn’t think about resisting anything, and the change took place. But also, as the war escalated, everyone—there was a great movement to go to graduate school.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">[Coughs.] So I sort of joined the crowd. I was commissioned. We were commissioned in the <orgName>BEMA</orgName> [Big Empty Meeting Area] I think <date>the day</date> after graduation. There was a ceremony and speaker, and maybe 25 of us became second lieutenants.		</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Great. Yeah, just I guess kind of talking a little bit more about the atmosphere, like, the general atmosphere at the time of your commencement. I just find it interesting that—you just mentioned that people kind of tend to go to graduate school as the war escalated, so it would be—I was just wondering if I can hear a little bit more in details about kind of what were some words that people were saying about the war and especially kind of within I guess the cadets, like, your peers that you met in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>. What was kind of the general sentiment and reception about the war?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I think those in ROTC,—you know, while we were not wild about the war or anything, we were of maybe a different time, and it was our obligation to go. And I didn’t—while my two roommates that I mentioned were both in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>, they were both—they also went to graduate school, but as soon as that was over, they went off to the military. They were both married. I’m sure they hated to leave their wives, but that’s what they had to do.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay, so even—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I think I was almost ready to go on active duty.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. So even up until, like, ’<date>64</date> and <date>’65</date>, like, I guess kind of the students’ attitude or a reception of war wasn’t really I guess negative or, you know, it wasn’t really an avoiding atmosphere per se. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah, it was more of an awareness of it, but it wasn’t a heated kind of thing. At least in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, it wasn’t. There may have been—if you could go to [<orgName>University of California</orgName>,] <orgName>Berkeley</orgName> or a more active campus at the time, it might have grown sooner. But it hadn’t really hit <orgName>Hanover</orgName> in a big way. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. And so was it just the common thing for a lot of students to go straight into graduate school after their undergrad programs?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It seemed, at least at the time, to be a big thing. You know, the fact that “this war will soon be over,” and while I said we weren’t protesting in our group, it was, Well, I might as well get a graduate degree here, and then I’ll go on to my military service. It was just a more of a common sense decision, not an angry decision.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Okay. Okay, now I think I understand that better. Great. So while you’re in business school in <orgName>University of Virginia</orgName>, did you get any kind of a military training or did you continue to have exposure to, like, <orgName>ROTC</orgName> and <orgName>Army</orgName> training in any sense?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No way. It was—you know, you would have to report that you were in good status or something and you were still in school and you would—the deferral wasn’t for <date>the full two years</date>; you had to update the military on it. But as long as you were still in school, you could continue to be in school. You couldn’t continue forever. It was only for <date>two years</date>. After law school, you—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">And I—okay. And I bet, like, you know, the overall atmosphere and the environment and everything kind of was very different from your experience in <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> while you were in <orgName>University of Virginia</orgName>, so what were some kind of transitions or changes that you experienced?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, there started to be—yeah, there was music I didn’t understand. You know, when I was in grad school, I was very busy. I didn’t have the fraternity house or anything, but people like <persName>Bob Dylan</persName> were appearing. You know, “What is that music? It sounds foreign, strange.” And hair was growing a little longer. Even at <orgName>the University of Virginia</orgName>, which is known as a very formal school, and you wore coats and ties and—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—you’re a Southern gentlemen, and it was starting to appear here. There was a different movement underway, a more—a little more hostile, and it was—you know, <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> was having <orgName>Haight-Ashbury</orgName>. [Transcriber’s note: He refers to the hippie counterculture movement there in <date>the ‘60s</date>, and, in <date>1967</date>, <name type="event">the Summer of Love</name>.] The climate was changing. But I was in business school, and I was working until 11 o’clock every night, and I almost didn’t notice that the change was going on because I was so involved with my work in business school.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. And so what was it like to kind of, you know, now go into business and actually have a career after your business school?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, there was a little—you know, I knew it was only—I forget the time, but I went into the <orgName>Army</orgName> in <date>January</date> of ’68, and I finished <placeName>Virginia</placeName> in <date>May</date>—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—of <date>’67</date>, so it was that short period that I worked for <orgName>IBM</orgName>. Part of that was in school in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, <orgName>IBM</orgName> school. I mentioned <orgName>Haight-Ashbury</orgName>. I now could see Haight-Ashbury. That was in its nice period. Not too bad yet. The “flower [children]” period. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. So I guess you—were you still kind of able to kind of sense I guess the transition in [the] public’s, like, general sentiment towards <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>, though?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Could I sense it? Yes, because <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> was building. It was on the news, when I got home on time to watch the news, but it was on the news regularly. You know, I knew friends who were now going. The mood in the society was, you know, going from “Let’s support our boys” to “Gee, what’s going on here?” kind of thing.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Great. So I guess the atmosphere was definitely different from the time that you were just kind of graduating from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah, I would say so. It had escalated in that period. But, again, I was in a little bit of a cocoon, working long hours and somewhat oblivious to what was going on around me. You know, I just had to get the work assignment done. I knew I was going into the <orgName>Army</orgName>, but I still had the immediate objective in front of me.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. I see. Okay. So you entered active duty in <date>January 1968</date>, so I’m just wondering if you could tell me a little bit about your military career prior to going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Okay. As you said, I had been designated to <orgName>the Ordnance Corps</orgName>, so the first thing I had to do was show up at <orgName>the Ordnance Officers</orgName> [sic; Officer] Basic Course at Aberdeen Proving Ground, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, which was the home of <orgName>the Ordnance Corps</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—ordnance officers’ basic class, you were going to go on to additional training. It was almost like advanced <orgName>ROTC summer</orgName> camp. It was a lot of the same things all over again. You had to—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—learn military procedures and how to give a platoon leader’s order or a patrol leader’s order, practiced the various formations and weapons, and, you know, you would fire for qualifying for whatever skill you had as a marksman. Many things all over again. You were reduced to—you weren’t commanding troops now, you were just a trainee once again.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And it was cold in <placeName>Aberdeen</placeName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY"><orgName>Hanover</orgName> is a very cold place, but it’s also cold right off <placeName>the Chesapeake Bay</placeName> in <placeName>Maryland</placeName> when the wind’s blowing, and it was <date>January</date>, and we were outside a lot.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. That must have been tough.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">None of which prepared us for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. [Chuckles.] Right. It must have been really different. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">That’s where I ended up. I had all kinds of <date>MOS’s</date> along the way. I think almost all of us had a secondary MOS of infantry platoon leader. That’s where all this training—we could have led an infantry unit, but I’m trying to think of what other—I’ll get back to the MOS because that’s where I ended up. That probably is the end of the story of how I got that MOS. Out of <placeName>Aberdeen</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, I think we can have an interview, if I get talking here, that could last <date>three days</date>, but it was at <placeName>Aberdeen</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—when I first ran into personal war resistance, I guess, because I said we were all graduate students and we had had jobs or had been lawyers before we went on active duty, and I went to a college mixer, hoping—well, I’m unmarried, and I don’t know anyone around here, and we’ll go to the college mixer.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Mmm. I see. Uh-huh. Right. That is actually a very compelling experience, have to say.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I also—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">You told me a little bit about—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—met a—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—the—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I met a young lady in <placeName>Baltimore</placeName> that was going to <orgName>Goucher College</orgName>, and maybe it was the time—I didn’t know where I was going, and I was lonely, but I fell very much in love, but we had different views on the military.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And we got along well, but that was a contributing factor, I think, in our breakup, that—different views. So it was now affecting me personally.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. So that’s—so were there any kind of any other incidents that you kind of felt that antiwar sentiment directly hitting you, and were there any kind of—more of, like, new stories or things that you’re reading on newspapers that is telling about the rising antiwar sentiment during <date>the year</date>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, out of <placeName>Aberdeen</placeName>, I was sent to supply and service school in <placeName>Fort Lee</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, which was almost back to where I lived in <placeName>Richmond</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. They probably weren’t going anywhere.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Yeah, it seems like—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">There was a lot of experiences walking the streets of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> that you would hear comments.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And was there any kind of special events or anything that struck you or anything that you still remember till nowadays during your time at the supply and service school at <placeName>Fort Lee</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Not—the most unusual thing that happened there is I had a—my roommate, who had been my roommate at <placeName>Aberdeen</placeName>, another lieutenant, came back to our bachelor officers quarters one night and said that he had learned that if we knew a way to get housing off post, we could move off post and have it paid for because there was a great housing shortage, and so I called my landlord from when I was a civilian and moved into the small units that they had, and so we could move off post. That’s not a great experience, but it was an unusual situation, and I almost was getting extra pay to do that, and I wasn’t making as much as I did with <orgName>IBM</orgName> but was making more than lieutenants usually do. The pay then was $330 a month for a second lieutenant.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Mmm. I see. That’s really interesting. And anything—so what were your duties at supply and service or what were trainings that you received at supply and service school? Was it very kind of different from the courses that you took at the ordnance officers—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It was different in that it covered just about any kind of supply and service thing that you could think of: graves registration, how to mark bodies and put them in bags, and how to run a cemetery. We had <date>two days</date> of that. We went to a model cemetery. Any kind of maintenance units on vehicles. Just as the name “supply and service,” it was anything to keep the troops—that if you were in <placeName>Europe</placeName> or in <placeName>Korea</placeName>, the troops that were on the front line, you kept them going. It was <orgName>the [U.S. Army] Quartermaster Corps</orgName> sent people here. They did things like laundry or food or clothing or any kind of supplies. That’s the sort of training that you received at Fort Lee. It was under what was called the <orgName>Quartermaster</orgName> branch of the <orgName>Army</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. And just before we move on, can we just kind of clarify on the timeline here? So it would be great if you can tell me, like, when you started your Ordnance Officers [sic; Officer] Basic Courses [sic; Course] and then when you moved to supply [and] service, and then when you finally arrived at <orgName>the Army Electronics Command</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I know that I started in <date>January</date> of ’68, went on active duty at <placeName>Aberdeen</placeName>, <orgName>Aberdeen Proving Ground</orgName>. I’m thinking that was about a <date>nine-week</date> course, and then I went to <persName>Fort Lee</persName>, to the supply and service school, for <date>nine more weeks</date>, I think. So that’s <date>18 weeks</date>. Does that put us in <date>June</date> or something?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Umm—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Close to it, anyway.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">That puts—<date>May</date> or <date>June</date>, yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And then that’s when I went to <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I see. Okay.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No, that was unusual. It was an installation of about 3,000 <orgName>Department of the Army</orgName> civilians and maybe 20, 25 military. The commander, who was the colonel, who was military—and then you had lieutenants and captains there. I don’t think there were any enlisted. Basically, I would have to say I did nothing. I had a job name, but you would go in, and you would talk about who won last night’s baseball game or just no one else was doing much of anything. You know, a building of 3,000 people and perhaps 300 actively doing things, so they should have gotten medals or bonuses or—you know, they were doing serious things. But the rest were counting up their sick leave. It was just sort of shocking to see how little work was being done and knowing that there was a war going on, that people were dying, and they needed batteries and radios and electronic gear that worked, and they needed it delivered in time, and it wasn’t happening at all. What was happening was the 300 people who deserved rewards and not the other 2,700, but basically none of us—we would come to work at 8:30 or 9 in the morning and leave at 11:30 for lunch and play cards. Like, five or six lieutenants would play hearts until 1:30 and go back to work and leave at 4:30.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. So it sounds a little bit—it sounds like your military experience since your active service—like, since you began your active service—it sounds a little bit different from the experience that you had back in <placeName>ROTC</placeName> at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, so just kind of wanted to ask you, like, kind of—was there any kind of changes and thoughts about military career since you started your active duty? Like, what were your feelings? Was there anything kind of that surprised you, or were there any things that were kind of similar to what you have expected from your <orgName>ROTC</orgName> experience at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, there was just—there was a war, and you had this—even though I was very bored in my job of not doing anything, you knew it was coming. You knew you were going to go, so you didn’t know—it was a great unknown. What would it be like? What were you going to end up doing, you know? Where would you be? You know, could you do your job? And it was hanging over your head. I mentioned I had a girlfriend. We were together but not together, and some pressure there. So, you know, it was in some sense a relief the day I came in. I have a desk in an office, and it was mostly civilians in the office, and I came back from one of our long breaks, and this was empty. Where did everybody go? And I went to my desk, and here was this stack of orders saying, “You’re going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.”</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And I guess it’s totally fine if you would not like to discuss a little bit further about this, but—and not to be too, I don’t know, kind of infringing upon your private life, but I just find it interesting that, you know, the sentiment towards war and, like, different opinion towards war was kind of the factor that even influenced your kind of relationship and role in romantic life. So just kind of wanted to ask you, like, what were some I guess disputes and kind of the conflicts that you had with your girlfriend about the war? Like, what were some, like, words that you guys exchanged or the opinions that you guys shared that kind of, you know, always kind of conflicted one another?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I don’t think—well, it turns out that the girl’s parents had met during <name type="event">World War II</name>. So she wasn’t totally anti-military. Her mother was a nurse in the military, and her father was a major in the <orgName>Army</orgName>, so she couldn’t totally be against lieutenants. But she was <date>three years</date> younger and a college senior, and more things were happening then in college than when I was a college senior <date>three years before</date>. We never reached the point of yelling at each other or—but it was a factor there, that we had some different political views, and I don’t know that’s what broke us up, but it was an element of it, I think. You know, we never had shouting matches over the war because I think she knew that I wasn’t looking forward to war, you know.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But I would explain, “My concept is if there are American troops there and I’m an American, and I’m a pretty good officer, I think, it’s sort of my job to go be there for it.” She thought, “Well, it’s not good, and you should take a stand.” So we had that difference.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. I see. I see. Okay. And I guess kind of also was it very different experience for you? Because it seems like at <orgName>the Army Electronics Comment Command</orgName>, you’re mostly with the civilians rather than I guess soldiers or military officers, and you did tell me a little bit about how that dynamic was like, but I just would like to hear a little bit more about how their—like, if there was any difference, how their opinions kind of differed from yours about <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> in general.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">They seemed to, you know, not—because they had jobs that depended on the military, they didn’t talk against it. They didn’t—I didn’t have many conversations with them, and if they had been against the war, they probably didn’t want to talk to an <orgName>Army</orgName> officer as though they were against the war when their job depended on it. But I didn’t run into any—you know, we young lieutenants got along well with the young ladies who worked there, so, you know, that was—didn’t find any problem there. So—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But the civilian workers—I don’t think we had any problem, and they seemed to show some respect for us.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And our—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">And what were some kind of the—mm-hm. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">We were—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">As I’ve mentioned, the group of officers, all eight or twelve of us—we hung together. We were our only—we didn’t know anyone else. We had two apartments, and all the parties had the same twelve guys, and so—and we’d go to the [New] <placeName>Jersey</placeName> shore with three or four. So we were sort of confined to ourselves. We weren’t great chick magnets at the time, because it seemed like if you were headed to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, that wasn’t somebody that a young lady should consider of high potential.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Right. So what were some I guess words or opinions that were kind of circulated or that the different officers are exchanging about the war?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You didn’t talk about it that much, because you were in the <orgName>Army</orgName>. You were an officer in the <orgName>Army</orgName>. I don’t want to fall back on <name type="event">World War II</name> and “orders are orders,” but, you know, it doesn’t make much difference to—you just got to do your job. So I don’t think we—we talked more about how <orgName>the Philadelphia Eagles</orgName> were doing in football than what happened in [the] Tet [Offensive], you know. We were, of course, very interested but didn’t exchange opinions about it.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. I see. Okay. Great.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">This is where you can start to talk—you know, I sometimes in the local newspapers here will see someone, an obituary where they have a picture of them as a 20-year-old person with their uniform on, and you read and you think, Well, a 20-year-old died. No, he’s 84. But it’s such a period of your life that you can remember more things in 24 hours than you can remember in <date>a year</date> that happened <date>ten years ago</date>. You want the humor as well [chuckles] as the—funny things happened along the way, too. I guess you can have funny things in history. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, definitely.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">So I had to go all the way back and get my second uniform, the one I was going to wear home. (I was confident.) And exchanged that. You know, it was a big mess because I had to get a bus to go to the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> base. Coming out of the restroom, I had my uniform on, and an old guy came up and said, “Excuse me, son, are you going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?” And I said, “Yes, I’m on my way.” And he said, “Well, think of the advantages.” I said, “Sir, I can’t think of many advantages.” And he said, “Well, you’ll be eligible to join the <orgName>VFW</orgName>, <orgName>the Veterans of Foreign Wars</orgName>, when you come home.” And I said, “Oh, I hadn’t thought of that. Okay, that puts me in a good mood.” </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Yeah. I bet.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">We flew from <placeName>Seattle</placeName> to <placeName>Tokyo</placeName> and then <placeName>Tokyo</placeName> on into <placeName>Cam Ranh Bay</placeName>, is where I entered the country. Now you have to wait for your assignment. And you had no idea where you were going. But at Cam Ranh Bay that night, there were flares across—I think there were jagged mountains and this white sand, and it’s an absolutely beautiful place. And I said, Well, this war isn’t too bad. It’s sort of beautiful here. But it was maybe 14 hours later when somebody came by and said, “Are you Lt. Jolly?” And they told me where I was going. I had to go from <placeName>Cam Ranh Bay</placeName>—I had to go to the airport and take a C-130, which is a cargo plane, to <orgName>Bien Hoa Air Force Base</orgName>, near <placeName>Saigon</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And you arrived in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date>January 1969</date>. Is that correct? Or early—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I believe it was, yes.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—<date>1969</date>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Early—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. Okay. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—’69.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Early ’69. Right. Early ’69. Right. Sorry. So it must have been—the war has escalated quite a bit by this point, so what was—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">That was a real live war then.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—the general atmosphere when you—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Tet had already occurred. <persName>Tet</persName>’s <date>the previous year</date>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, exactly. Right. Tet occurred <date>the previous year</date>. So what has been, like—what was the general atmosphere when you arrived in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? Like, what was the vibe that you were getting from the officers club, there for <date>several months</date> already, and, you know, I guess kind of the general—kind of the vibe that you got from the country when you landed in?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It was—no question, everyone was on a war status. You know, you saw four flares going up in the sky everywhere. You would hear artillery. You know, still—like, <date>the first week</date> I was there, we were in—it was a temporary—because the build-up had taken so long, they didn’t have quarters for officers, and we were in what was an old barracks, and it was called <placeName>the Bay of Pigs</placeName>, because it wasn’t a very good place to be. And if you remember the Cuban crisis and the Cuban invasion that failed and they landed at <placeName>the Bay of Pigs</placeName>,—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—so that’s where this name came from. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But it was about—sometime my first week I was there, I heard someone yell, “Incoming!” And “incoming” to me was something I’d heard in movies, and I heard somebody else yell, “Hit the dirt!” “Hit the dirt” is what [movie actor] <persName>John Wayne</persName> would yell. And then all of a sudden—wham! <persName>wham!—rockets</persName> started hitting. You know, I learned it was real, and I sort of stood there as—This is like a war. You know, I didn’t stand very long, but—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. I see. Yeah. I guess I’m a little bit curious about your role at the <placeName>Long Binh</placeName> depot—like, what exactly you were doing. And—so you said it’s about the computer—like, ammunition and the supply, so what exactly would be some things that or some informations that you’d be processing there?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">What we were doing? We had—at first, I was sort of running something called the document control and analysis section and that’s where the—we had Vietnamese keypunch operators. They were there in <date>the day</date>, ladies who were—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You know, we had—I like—these guys—we had to take out—we had miscellaneous duties. I had to take out patrols once every—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—week or so. And when you took out the patrol, it was nice to have people with infantry experience behind you in the patrol.They were good at this. Even though they transferred to get away from it, they had experience. Later on, I became the night shift officer in charge of the data processing installation.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Great. Yeah, just I find it really interesting that—though, like, you did have to do the patrol and were in charge of, like, more things, just like beyond your kind of information processing duty, it’s just really interesting that you actually got to kind of interact and work with the officers who had more of, like, a combat and were, like, infantry combat experience.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">They were the enlisted men who would transfer out of infantry units.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">It just sounds like—Right. Yeah, it seems like just—it sounds like you guys would have had, like, very kind of different background coming into this, so I just want to hear a little bit about what your interaction was like with them.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh. You know, it was—if you ever want to learn how to lead a group of people, you get this group of people behind you that are of different races, nationalities, persuasions, desires, objectives and give them all loaded weapons and then walk in front of them [Chuckles.] You got to learn how to deal with a lot of different people and a lot of different situations. They don’t have—you know, they weren’t all <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students. They are from the hills of <placeName>Tennessee</placeName> and ghettoes of the city. They’re Latino, <placeName>they’re</placeName>—but you got to get the job done, and the best way to do it is to be the best officer you can possibly be, and they’ll recognize that and they’ll follow you. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Great.  Yeah, and what were your kind of patrol experiences like? Yeah. So you said you had to lead patrol about once <date>every three weeks</date>. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah, something like that. Oh, the first time we went out, we were supposed to—one of our objectives was to check a gate. We were beyond the perimeter of <placeName>Long Binh</placeName>, and we were supposed to check a gate that was supposed to be locked, and so you had to go up to this gate, and we had three gun Jeeps, and they were Jeeps with 50 caliber machine guns mounted on them and four guys in each <orgName>Jeep</orgName>. And so we were going up, and as we walked up toward the gate, you could hear there was a little faint light, and you could hear a murmur of voices.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But it was good to get—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">So was it because of—right. Yeah. I bet. Was it because of a miscommunication or lack of communication between troops? Because it sounds—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I’m sure it was.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. It sounds like it was, like it could have—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Two commands didn’t talk to each other.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Uh-huh. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">That it shouldn't have happened that way. We shouldn’t be sneaking up behind them, not knowing they’re there.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Exactly. Yeah, that sounds like it could have been, like, a really, really dangerous situation, so just wanted to ask you that.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh, I’ve got another <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> story. Can I tell—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah. Any other memories about—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—you a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> story?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, I would like to hear that.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">My roommate at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, <persName>Wayne</persName> [A.] <persName>Wight</persName> [Class of <date>1965</date>], was in <orgName>the [U.S. Army] Transportation Corps</orgName>, and I found out after I had been at the Long Binh area for <date>a month or two months</date>, through his wife and my parents—found out we were a mile or so apart. And where we lived. And so I went to see him one night, and his company was away doing something, and he and just a few of the men were there, and I brought a six-pack of beer. And so he said—there was a red alert, meaning there was some kind of activity either going on or potentially going on. They said, “Well, let’s go to the bunker and take our radios and drink a beer.” And so we went—he had a command bunker that he had built, and we went into the bunker and were drinking the beer, and it came over <orgName>the Armed Forces Vietnam</orgName> radio [sic; Armed Forces Vietnam Network]—they were bringing the news, and some of the big news that evening was that <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName> had abandoned <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, that <orgName>ROTC</orgName> no longer had a place on campus. And <persName>Wayne</persName> and I looked at each other with the shared thought of: “Can we go home?” You know, we thought maybe this would let us out. But it didn’t. That was a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> story from a bunker.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. That’s, yeah. That’s really actually really interesting how that roommate was stationed very close to where you were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes. And my other roommate was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So were you able to—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—but I never got together with—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Oh.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—him. He was farther away.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. I see. Did you have any—like, after this encounter, did you have any other chances to meet this roommate at <orgName>the Transportation Corps</orgName> after, or no?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Did I see him after this time?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">The one that was in <orgName>the Transportation Corps</orgName>? Not regularly, because, you know, we went different ways, and he went home before I did. But I would see him.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">There was an officers club, and I would occasionally see him at the officers club. I saw him there. The officers club is nothing that would impress you. If you take the worst <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> fraternity house and downgrade it about three steps—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—it would equal an officers club in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. But we did have bands and music, but I would occasionally run into him there. You would go and have a beer.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. I see.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It was a particular kind of beer.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I now go into restaurants here, and there are 400 different kinds of beers, and there, you took whatever beer—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">That’s true.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—they had.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It could be <placeName>San Miguel</placeName> from the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> or just any kind of beer. You would—you just drank the beer. And it was warm. So you learned to live with that.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. I see. Right. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—in your office, so I just wanted to hear a little bit more about that as well.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh. You know, there were about 30 or 40 Vietnamese that worked at our units during <date>the day</date>, but, as I said, I went to the night, so I didn’t have a great an interaction with them after going to the night.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. And did they speak—like, do you guys interact in English or—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I learned perhaps a hundred words of Vietnamese. I still go to a Vietnamese barber, and I can tell him, you know, that my hair looks like a monkey’s tail or something, but I learned about a hundred words of Vietnamese, so I could communicate a little bit. But the <placeName>GIs</placeName> and the Vietnamese had a total pidgin language between them.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. That’s really interesting.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah, that’s almost a separate language, of how the Vietnamese and the <orgName>GIs</orgName> communicated. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. And also just kind of wondering: What were the kind of the background that these Vietnamese employers or the officers are coming from? Like, their maybe education or, like, their kind of political belief? Like, kind of their socioeconomic status? Like, if you are able to kind of, you know, notice any of that in any sense.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Of the Vietnamese that we worked with?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Some of them were—the males had been—I can think of one who was an officer in the Vietnamese army and was wounded, so he was disabled. So he came to work for the Americans at the depot. More women than men were working there because the mean were off in their army. They were just very good workers and very pleasant, and they sort of—they believed in <placeName>America</placeName>. They didn’t want to come to <placeName>America</placeName>. Said, “Well, don’t you want to move to <placeName>California</placeName>?” They said, “No, I’m Vietnamese.” But they thought <placeName>America</placeName> was a good place.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">They generally—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">That’s real interesting.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You could—you saw bad things.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You know, the Vietnamese—some Americans called them names, you know.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But I would say at least 75, 80 percent, they got along fine and they kidded a lot.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">So relatively good relationships.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Interesting. Yeah. Do you just remember any kind of conversations that you had with them that kind of—that was telling about where they were coming from or their thoughts?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Um—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Or any episode or anecdotes?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Nothing other than that kind of short conversation and that I mentioned: “Wouldn’t you like to live in <placeName>the United States</placeName> someday?” And “No, because I’m Vietnamese.” Many now live here. But that wasn’t their intent, anyway. I don’t remember having deep, serious conversations with them.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. I see. So that’s real interesting that after the war, did a lot of people who worked in your office end up living in <placeName>the United States</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I don’t know. I don’t know what happened to the people that I worked with. I have never seen any mention—it’s hard to find them, anyway. A third of the people in the country are named <persName>Nguyen</persName>, and so [chuckles] they all have the same name. [Chuckles.] But it’s like <persName>Lees</persName> in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. There are a lot of them. Or <orgName>Smiths</orgName> in <placeName>the United States</placeName>. But I have had no contact. I’m sure some of them, like the gentleman that I spoke of that was in the South Vietnamese army—I’m sure he was reeducated in some way, and he worked for the Americans, so—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, you’re coming through just fine.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But he couldn’t speak any English, not a word of English, and he was sort of a lonely man. I learned from one of the other Vietnamese that he had lost five sons in the war. He had come from <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName> in <date>1954</date>, but he had a very low job, but I heard him humming “<persName>Adeste Fideles</persName>,” the <date>Christmas</date> carol, around Christmas <date>one year</date>. And I had learned to sing that in high school Latin class, so I started singing it, and he started singing it in Latin. He had been trained by the church. He had gone to church schools. So from then on—he was much better in Latin than I was, but I could say, “All of <persName>Gaul</persName> is divided into three parts” and “I’m a farmer,” and I knew enough Latin that he and I communicated in Latin, the only use I really had for direct Latin is with him. He lit up when he could speak to an American.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. That’s really interesting. That’s really cool. Right. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No, none that I worked with. I haven’t seen—it seemed like I had either officers or enlisted. I’ve had no contact with any of those. My two college roommates—the one who was in <orgName>the Transportation Corps</orgName> and—the one I see regularly, because he lives not too far away, the one who was in <orgName>the Transportation Corps</orgName> I see at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> reunions. Saw him <date>last fall</date> when we were in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> together.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Oh. I see. Okay.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Okay. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">It sounds like it’s a really tough job because you’re a one-horse thing overnight at the place, so, yeah, please go ahead.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, I liked the job because it was quieter at night. You didn’t have colonels around. You could just do a job, and it was you and the <placeName>GIs</placeName>, and the <orgName>GIs</orgName> that we got for the computer job were mostly college dropouts. I can think of one guy who went to <orgName>the University of Minnesota</orgName> for <date>three years</date>. We had one who went to <orgName>University of South Carolina</orgName>, [<orgName>University of] Louisville</orgName>. They decided that they were having too good a time in school or school wasn’t for them, and they got drafted. But these guys were smart enough to a computer job. But they still wore their uniforms, and they went out on patrols.  But they didn’t like where they were. They didn’t like some of the things they had to do. But they did their job.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">One guy who came to our unit—there were always people who still would try to buck the military. He had gone to—the <orgName>Army</orgName> had sent him to Russian language school to learn Russian, somewhere in <placeName>California</placeName>. It seems like—not <placeName>Pasadena</placeName> but <placeName>Monterey</placeName>, I think. And he had completed the school, but at the graduation ceremony, whoever was giving the talk said that “you should be proud to die for your country,” and he stood up and said, “Well, I would die for my friends, I would die for my family, but I would never die for anything like my country.” And so they washed him out of the school—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—out of that school and put him in an infantry unit.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—he should have just kept his mouth shut, but he still went to the infantry unit, so he exchanged and came to us for extending <date>a year</date>, and then I would try to counsel him, and they were on him for not wearing a hat. In uniform, you’re supposed to wear a hat.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Oof!</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">When you’re outside. And he wouldn’t do it. And the lifers, those who were making a career, were just on him all the time. And I would say, “Just put the hat on your head,” you know. And he ended up—when I was leaving, there were charges against him for disobeying orders for that kind of stuff. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. I see. I just find it interesting that you were also kind of in charge of court-martials [sic] as well, so just wondering if there are any kind of court cases or—what were some kind of the trend that you saw in these court cases? Like, what were the most frequent reasons an infantryman or officer would be brought to court in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Never saw an officer brought in. It was only enlisted men.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And it was usually for usually really, really dumb things. Yeah. For instance, going to an area where you weren’t supposed to go. You know, there were off-limits areas. You’re not supposed to be on Tu Do Street in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, which is where the young ladies ply their trade, you know. You’re not supposed to be there, and we had guys go there and get picked up by the MPs [military police]. I was never on that kind of a situation, but most of mine were marijuana. I had one where a guy fired his weapon through the roof of a building for—you know, he got angry with somebody, and—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I forget what the charges were. I never saw a situation where anyone was innocent, because this was a low level of court-martial.They were always truly guilty. Now, like marijuana violations. They were caught with marijuana.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. I see. That’s really interesting.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">It sounds like it also can kind of be a very, I don’t know, nerve-wracking and anxious job because you’re kind of out there in the—outside in the fields at night, where you can’t really see anything. Like, you can’t really tell as well, like, as you would during [the] day when someone’s approaching, so was there any kind of, like, memorable experience that you had during your—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No, I never encountered—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—shift?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—a combat situation, particularly on the patrols. Never ran into anybody. Some patrols were lost because during Tet, I understand, <date>the previous year</date>—you know, you’re out there with three Jeeps. You’re more likely to be found than you are to find someone else. But you make a lot of noise in dying. [Chuckles.] That there are 12 of you with three machine guns, and the fact that you fight back alerts the good guys that “there’s something going on out here.” And they can react to you. So you’re out there and you stumble into something—you’re a sacrificial lamb, is what you are. But I was never the lamb that was sacrificed.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. Okay. Right. Did you have any, I guess—so any kind of urgent or any kind of patrol or, like, on-field experience that you remember till nowadays?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">What kind of experience?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">So any kind of, like, experience that you had during, like, patrol or during your night shift duty that was—that kind of sticks to you till nowadays.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You know, there are probably a thousand of them, but the people, the situation, the hours. I never, ever worked so hard on any job in my life. I would work, in effect, <date>seven days</date> a week and work at a 13-hour shift. And it was partially because I wanted to do it for the guys wearing the green uniforms, but it was also because I didn’t have anything else to do. I had to pour myself into those duties that I learned where things were in the depot. You know, I can tell stories of a supply sergeant we had. He was—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">He was really, really good. And he was a great trader that—this was on the night shift. He came in one night and said, “Lt. Jolly, can I borrow the deuce-and-a-half [2-1/2-ton cargo truck] and a couple of men for a while?” They were going to have—and he had the twinkle in his eye. I knew something was up. And I said, “Sure, Ben. You know, go ahead.” And so they were gone, and they came back, and what they had was—a deuce-and-a-half was a large <orgName>Army</orgName> truck. You’ve probably seen them on the roads in—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It’s not a dump truck but a little bit like it. And they filled the whole vehicle with <persName>Visqueen</persName>. <persName>Visqueen</persName> is [polyethylene] plastic sheeting, and there are rolls of it, and they had maybe 200 rolls of this that they brought back in a truck. And we had a building near us that they unpacked it in. The next morning, I was still there, and he called on the field phone to an engineering unit, and he said, “You know, what you guys say is right, it’s almost impossible to find this <persName>Visqueen</persName>. And I’m looking at him. He got a truck load of it. And it was maybe, I don’t know, 200 rolls or something. And he said, “Come by tomorrow morning. I think I found a way to get a couple of rolls for you.” </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I see.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—event that I thought of last night. There was a program on <orgName>PBS</orgName> about <orgName>Neil [A.]</orgName> <persName>Armstrong</persName>, and I went to the <persName>Bob</persName> Hope show. You know who <persName>Bob Hope</persName> is or was?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Mmm, no.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">An American comedian that was famous for entertaining troops all over the world. And there were about—this was at Christmas—25,000 GIs there, and they were climbing light poles, and you can still see it on <orgName>YouTube</orgName> if you look up <persName>Bob Hope</persName> at <placeName>Long Binh</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Mmm. Yeah! That must have been really touching.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And I told one of the Vietnamese—lower—we called her a peasant. The Vietnamese had a story about <persName>Hang Nga</persName>, and <persName>Hang Nga</persName> was a beautiful virgin who lived on the moon, and at least two cleaning ladies were looking at a magazine that had pictures of the Americans in it. “What is this?” And I told them, “<persName>Hoa ki di</persName>” [roughly: Americans go]—whatever “moon” is, and convinced them that the Americans had gone to the moon, and they got very angry. They started yapping and—you know—had to get the other Vietnamese to explain to them that—this was <date>a month</date> after the Americans had gone there, and they hadn’t gotten the word.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. That’s very interesting. Right. Yeah. I mean, if you have any just memorable experiences or memories that you have, whether during your duty or, you know, while you’re taking time off in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, like while you’re off your duty, like, you know, just really tell me anything. I would love to hear anything that you would like to share with us.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, it could go on for <date>days</date>, I think, that the experiences and—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You know, it—and coming home was an experience, because you couldn’t talk about it. That it was like, “Where have you been?” You know, and—and you’d go to work, and you didn’t know whether these people were anti-war, pro-war, so you just didn’t tell the stories—like I’m telling now. There was no one to talk to.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">So it’s really nice even <date>50 years later</date> or something to be able to find somebody that actually wants to listen and that you don’t bore. So it’s kind of—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—now—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—it’s more than the returning <name type="event">World War II</name> veterans, who could talk about it. And, you know, the situation I have described is I was not—people had it far, far worse than I did in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in that I had lucked into—but it still wasn’t a pleasant situation. I could have spent <date>a year</date> somewhere else that was nicer, but all in all, it was an experience I’ll never forget, and I guess I’m glad I did it.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Yeah. Yeah, I guess kind of just going back I guess to your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so you were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> from <date>early 1969 to 1970</date>. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes, pretty much most of ’69 I was there.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. Okay. So were you at the same station the whole entire year?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes. I did move around a little bit. I went on one trip back to Cam Ranh Bay to take some items there. But mostly I was the whole time on the edge of <placeName>Long Binh post</placeName>, although I did—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">And—right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I went on both a leave and R&amp;amp;R. I guess <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName> is rest and relaxation [sic; recuperation]. I went to <placeName>Singapore</placeName> for <date>five days</date> and <date>five or six days</date> in <placeName>Sydney</placeName>. And the Vietnamese experience, as well as <placeName>Singapore</placeName> and <placeName>Sydney</placeName>, infected me with a travel bug, I guess, and I’ve now probably been in 80 countries or something, because, you know, it’s like if you eat a potato chip, you can’t just eat one potato chip. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">If you’ve been to three or four countries,—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">That’s true.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—you’ve got to go to more countries because they’re all different and the cultures are different—and learn from all of them. So I haven’t been to <placeName>North Korea</placeName> yet. I’m not sure I want to go, but it’s still—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Have you?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Oh, no, I haven’t. I personally haven’t. [Chuckles.] Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But it’s something that the experience gave to me.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, yeah, definitely. Yeah, I guess actually would like—kind I hear a little bit about your R&amp;amp;R experience in <placeName>Singapore</placeName> and <placeName>Sydney</placeName>? Like, it must have been, like, very different from, you know, being in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at your station.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh, yeah, because you still—even though I said—well, I didn’t, you know, have the worse the job, you didn’t know when a rocket or a mortar would come in on your head at night, and in <placeName>Sydney</placeName> I was safe.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Exactly.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">In <placeName>Singapore</placeName> I was safe. And I went to <placeName>Singapore</placeName> with three <orgName>GIs</orgName> from our unit, enlisted men, and that usually doesn’t happen, that an officer—but they were all <date>three-year</date> college dropouts. One was a college graduate, was a salesman for <orgName>Pfizer</orgName>’s chemical company, and his <orgName>Reserve</orgName> unit was called up, so that’s how he ended up there. So it was a more mature group that I was with, that they could go along with an officer, and we’d had no problem. But it still—even then, out socially in <placeName>Singapore</placeName>, because I was the lieutenant, I got to sit in the right seat of the taxi, and I got to—you know, “What restaurant are we gonna go to?” I got to decide because I was a lieutenant. It just worked that way.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Right. And do you remember exactly, like, when you went on this <persName>R&amp;amp;R</persName>? Was it, like, maybe in the midpoint during <date>the year</date> or towards the end?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I really don’t remember. It was when—I had been there <date>six months or so before</date> the first one, anyway. I had been there quite a while. I think you build up some sort of seniority to go, that you couldn’t go your <date>first week</date>, that it took a little bit of time before you could go on the places.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. Yeah, and I guess kind of talking a little bit about kind of your position as a lieutenant, you said that during your service in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> there were just some things, some of the duties that you had to take upon kind of just processing the information because you were one of the very few rank officers around the region, so could you tell me a little bit more about that?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Of the miscellaneous duties that you had? Court-martials—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I was the—you had to teach—there were education classes that you would bring guys together, and you were under a tent or something, but every once in a while, the lieutenant—I remember I had to give a lecture on Educational Opportunities in the Army After Vietnam, for those who were staying in—everybody had to take it, but it was with—<orgName>the University of Maryland</orgName> had classes that they gave I guess around the world in <orgName>Army</orgName> posts, and so I had to talk all about those classes. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. Right. So, yeah. I know—well, if you would like to, we can go for <date>days</date> and <date>days</date>, honestly, with the interview because I can always come back to you at any time, as long as you’re available. So, yeah, just I really kind of liked that little bit of these anecdote and episodes that you had kind of in terms of, like, your interaction—like, you know, just stories about the supply sergeant or <persName>Bob Hope</persName>, so if you have anything kind of like that—you know, kind of on your, like, day-to-<date>day</date> ba- —kind of <date>daily</date> routine or maybe special occasions that you had that you would like to share with us, that would be great.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, I have, you know—I had a birthday party. The Vietnamese—even though I was on the night shift, the ladies that worked there decided to have a birthday party for me. And I still have—they were very concerned—because I was—let’s see, I’m a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> ’<date>65</date>. I would have been <date>21</date> then. So by ’68 would have been 27, 28 or something like that. At the party, one of the gifts was bride. They gave me a Vietnamese doll, which I have downstairs here, of a <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> outfit, because they were very concerned because I was so old and I didn’t have a wife yet, and so they thought this would work like a wife.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And I have notes and letters—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. I guess—right. I guess you really built a rapport with kind of local Vietnamese officers and people who worked in your office.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah. I ended up probably liking the Vietnamese as much or more than many of the Americans I saw. Not the American troops. I loved the American troops. But some of the civilians that were there. You saw some “ugly Americans” occasionally that I didn’t like that much, and I tended to bond with some of the Vietnamese. I still—I went back with my son to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> when he was 16, and it was interesting to—you know, he sort of—it became a little real as I started remembering my hundred words of Vietnamese and I could talk to people, and there was still a divide between the north and south, even if you go to <placeName>Saigon</placeName> or <placeName>Ho Chi Minh City</placeName>. You can tell the northerners and the southerners are different. And the southerners would occasionally come up to you. They were the lower workers in the hotels, and they would say, like, “The Americans weren’t so bad after all.” They said, “Americans can be pretty good. We’ve been taught that they’re not, but my mother said they liked Americans.” </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right! Yeah, I bet. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Yeah. Right. And is there—so did you also spend your <date>Christmas</date> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> as well, <date>Christmas</date> of ’69, I suppose?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes. Uh-huh, <date>Christmas</date> and <name type="event">New Year</name>’s.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. How was that like?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY"><persName>Mừng Chúa Giáng Sinh</persName>—<date>Merry Christmas</date> in Vietnamese. Pardon?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Ah. Yeah, I’m just wondering how that was like.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It was a touching moment. I’ve been asked, “What’s your best <date>Christmas</date>?” It was that, because, you know, my family doesn’t like to hear that, but it was when—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—the other <orgName>GIs</orgName> came up to you and they said, “Merry Christmas,” they meant it. I remember seeing—there used to be signs in the newspapers, like, “<date>14 shopping days</date> left till <date>Christmas</date>,” and then “<date>13 days</date> left till <date>Christmas</date>.” And I saw a <orgName>Jeep</orgName> with a sign on it that say, you know, “<date>382 days</date> left to <date>Christmas</date>,” because they weren’t observing <date>Christmas</date>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And, yeah, I guess kind of hearing about, like, what’s going on in <date>Christmas</date>, and you did briefly mention about reading the magazines about what’s going on in <placeName>the United States</placeName>, so I was just wondering how you kept in touch with your family and what’s going on in <placeName>the United States</placeName> during your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, the several areas that I think I could address. One, I have right behind me about ten tapes that—my father bought a tape recorder at—he bought one for himself and my mother, and one for me, and I took the one. We exchanged tapes for a while. And I put the tapes away when I got back, and I still haven’t listened to them, although they’re three feet away from me right now, because it’s my dad speaking to me. Me, speaking as a young lieutenant in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I remember one. I was describing what it looks like and how it’s not that different from <placeName>West Virginia</placeName>, and my dad’s just telling me what’s going on around there, and I don’t know if I could listen to that now without breaking up, but that’s one way I communicated with my parents.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It’s not like the troops in—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">And troops now are texting or sending e-mails back and forth. We didn’t have that. A letter would take quite a while. But there was no postage. You could write, “FREE” on it.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. And so also, you know, the antiwar sentiment and, you know, general public’s reception of war also changed during all your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and were you able to kind of get that as well along with I guess kind of messages from, you know, your family and your friends? Like, were you able to kind of—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Not so much—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—also kind of learn—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—from—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—about the general—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You got it a little bit from new replacements coming in	would tell you what was happening.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">When I left <orgName>IBM</orgName>, <orgName>IBM</orgName> gave me a gift subscription for <date>a year</date> to any magazine, or for <date>two years</date>, I guess, when I went into military service, so I got <orgName>TIME</orgName> magazine, and so we’d around—my <orgName>TIME</orgName> magazine was passed around. And so we’d see, you know, signs of the major war demonstrations and antiwar demonstrations, and so we really didn’t know—you know, as I had feared going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, the unknown, there was the fear of returning to <placeName>the United States</placeName>. And a little bit—I got back to—I got out of the <orgName>Army</orgName> at <orgName>Oakland Army Terminal</orgName> [<orgName>Oakland Army Base</orgName>] in <placeName>California</placeName>, and this lieutenant and I went across the street to a bar. We had some extra time before we were processed out. And there were some ladies in the bar arguing about the length of skirts.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Yeah, that’s quite a transition.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I flew home to <placeName>West Virginia</placeName>, and when I landed at <placeName>Dulles</placeName>, it was 6 degrees with snow on the ground. And after a year in <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, that was hard to take.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Right. Yeah. Actually, that kind of—that makes me curious how you felt about the general—like, the environment and climate of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, because that must have been really different from, you know, anything that you experienced in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> or in <placeName>Maryland</placeName> or—I’m not actually quite familiar with what <placeName>West Virginia</placeName> is like, but I’m assuming it was also a little bit different from there as well?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah. The human body is very adaptable, but it takes some time. I remember when I first arrived in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> in <date>January</date>, coming back after the <date>Christmas</date> break, the start of <date>winter</date> term, I’d stepped off of an airplane in <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> and thought, I’ll never be this cold again. And for <date>the first month</date> in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> I wore, you know, three jackets and—but then—you know, at <date>the end of that month</date>, I could walk out on the Green in a sweatshirt, and my body had adjusted over temperature. And <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was the same thing. When I arrived there, I was—it was this oppressive heat. You couldn’t get away from it. It was awful. And then <date>30 days later</date>, it was just perfectly fine. My body had become adjusted enough. It didn’t bother me. But it certainly took some time.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Yeah, that must have been really different. And was there any other—the Vietnamese officers and workers that you really were able to build a strong rapport with? Was there any American soldiers or officers that you also interacted pretty well or you clicked well with?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No. I had people that I knew and that I liked, but they were sort of coworkers, and you never knew—people were coming in, and people were going out, and you—I didn’t build lasting relationships that continued. You know, there were—I mentioned <persName>Ben Richardson</persName>—Sgt.—“General <persName>Ben</persName>.” I will remember forever and truly respect and admire the guy. I don’t know what happened to him. I hope it was good.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Right. And, yeah, is there any kind of I guess kind of going to back to episodes and anecdotes—you know, just kind of—before talking about your <name type="event">post-Vietnam War</name> experience, if there was anything else that you really would like to share, and really don’t worry about the time. You know, we will set a time if we need more time, so just please feel free to share any of the, yeah, your memories and stories, because we really would like to hear as much as possible.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I probably have—you know, they just don’t pop into mind. A lot of them have. You know, I even started making some notes <date>several years ago</date> and writing them down. And the problem is it never ends. I’m going to have an 800-page document out of <date>a few short months</date> of life. You never are as intense—you know, I’ve heard it compared to childbirth, and I can’t experience that, but as far as the experience, but wars last longer than childbirth, I think.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Definitely. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But I could probably look through those notes and come up with, you know, many other funny or interesting—I remember a time I almost shot a doctor, that—one of the guys in our unit—was walking through the unit, and I saw him. You know, he was in bed, and he had two blankets on top of him, and he was shivering. This is <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and I just described the weather.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.] Mmm! Right. I feel ya. [Laughter.] But, yeah, I mean, was there any kind of troublesome or kind of I guess problematic situation that you ran into during your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh, well, race was a problem in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, that—you learned things like—one of the other duties was to be the bunker line inspector, and, you know, when you went out on that bunker line at night, you had to do it; it was your job to go around and see that everything was okay and that everybody was awake, and, you know, usually it would be the smell of marijuana, but there were—you know, the blacks stuck together, and you had to be gentle with—you know, occasionally you’d give the <orgName>Black Power</orgName> salute, and you got along fine, but you had to know how to do that.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And I guess kind of just one of the questions that I just had—came to my mind is it seems like there were a lot of Vietnamese, local people working in your office, a lot of civilians. Did you have any interaction with, like, <orgName>ARVN</orgName> [pronounced <orgName>AR-vin</orgName>; <orgName>Army</orgName> of <placeName>the Republic of Vietnam</placeName>] troops or, like, <orgName>ARVN</orgName> military officers?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I didn’t have that much interaction with the ARVNs. I remember—you know, they were there, and you would see them. But I didn’t have that much interaction, although there was one unit that came in, what they called a “stand-down,” I think, and they were just there for a while. And they started playing basketball, and I went over and watched them play basketball.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Oh. Okay. Interesting. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Particularly when I first arrived in Cam Ranh,—I was talking about the <placeName>Bay</placeName> and across the jagged mountains, and I forget the name of it, it was, like, <orgName>the White Horse Division</orgName> (<orgName>9th Infantry Division</orgName>, <placeName>Republic of Korea Army</placeName>]. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, it was probably <orgName>White Horse</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But they never got attacked by the North Vietnamese, because the North Vietnamese were afraid of them. It was the story, anyway. And they were—but they did spend some time near us, and they knew all the angles. There were PXs [post exchanges] in <placeName>Long Binh post</placeName>, and supplies would come in. Like, <date>one month</date> or, you know, one time there might be a truckload of little refrigerators or a truckload with little televisions. And the rocks always had somebody stationed near the <orgName>PX</orgName> to broadcast back to all the other Korean troops, so they would come rushing in. They were united, and how do you get the supplies out of the American <orgName>PX</orgName>? So they were so well organized.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles, then laughs.] Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">The guys on our night shift found a box of—do you know what C-rations are? They’re the canned food that you eat in the field, or used to be, anyway.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Their enthusiasm went down a little bit.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. That’s funny. That’s really funny.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">You probably don’t have kimchi in Thayer Hall?</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I can get—because, actually, I really connect to that because sometimes my Korean friends would have kimchi in their refrigerator, and if you don’t store them right or if you keep them for too long, it definitely smells—it does not smell good to me, either. Just like—yeah. So—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">The Vietnamese equivalent is nuoc mam, and nuoc is—they put it on everything, and, as I understand, it’s the juice of rotten fish, that the fish ferment somehow, and it’s a smell you don’t forget. If you go into a room where there’s a group of Vietnamese eating, it is there.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Wow. <persName>Oooch</persName>. Yeah. I mean, that doesn’t sound too pleasant in such hot weather, because it sounds like it’s going to go bad really fast.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, they like it, though, so—it’s a sauce they put on things.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I’ve never really tried it.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. Oh, okay, so it’s a little bit different. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I don’t know that there were any bombs falling. It was just an alert that someone has been spotted nearby; there’s been some kind of military activity approaching our perimeter, and so they called a red alert so everybody would be—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">But there could be—the mortars and rockets that came in were most psychological weapons that if you have 20,000 people in this area and you send in three rockets, they’re all going to write home, and that kind of thing sort of—you know, the letters back home say, “Well, our sons are having rockets fall on their head. What is this war for?” </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I see. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. And were there any other times where kind of around your depot your troop or your office sensed military activity that you guys had to be alerted?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh, I’m trying to think. There were alerts off and on. I remember one night I was the duty officer for what was called <orgName>the Saigon Support Command</orgName> [sic; <orgName>U.S. Army Support Command</orgName>, <placeName>Saigon</placeName>]. And I don’t even know what it was, but it was—there were, like, 20 units attached to it. And—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I forget the story I started to tell. You were asking if there were ever other alerts? Oh, I know what I was going to tell.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Oh! Oh, no!</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">That morning, I went to the depot and was eating, and I heard these two captains talk about, you know, “Some idiot lieutenant sent us out there, and it wasn’t even an alert, and he didn’t call us back.” And I just, you know, quietly ate my breakfast and left. I was the idiot lieutenant.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles, then laughs.] I see. Wow. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No, there were a lot of things—when the war first started, the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> just pumped supplies. They sent shipload after shipload of supplies, many of which were still there in unmarked crates when we arrived, because they had so much, they didn’t know where they were going, and they couldn’t handle them, and they stacked them up in the far reaches of the depot, in a very military fashion. So if you flew over, it looked like all the crates were lined up neatly, but nobody knew what was in any of those crates because they’d been out in the weather for <date>years</date>, <date>five years or so</date>, and all the identification had washed off of them.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Right. That’s such a really interesting point. Were you able to—because this is around the time when—now, war kind of has peaked, and we’ve passed the time of <persName>Tet Offensive</persName>, so—and with the increasing kind of antiwar sentiment amongst the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> public and, you know, some kind of conflicts and the sense within the government and within the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> military now, there are just—kind of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> is slowly pulling out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And were you kind of able to sense that while you were—during your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yeah, toward the end of my time, we’d started—I mentioned the word “Vietnamization,”—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—that troops were—the number of troops went down in <date>my last months</date>. Units were being pulled out, and so it had really just started, and we didn’t know what it meant or how rapidly it was going to go or any of that, but it had begun, anyway.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Oh, okay.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">We probably—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">So do you remem- —<persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I think the general sentiment was probably the ARVNs wouldn’t be able to handle it because I think by that time, there were very few VCs [Viet Congs] left. It was all the North Vietnamese Regulars. But they were well supplied and kept coming.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And I guess—and in terms of, like, what kind of supplies you guys are receiving or supplies that the American troops were requesting in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, was there also kind of—were you also able to kind of see the Vietnamization of <persName>Nixon</persName> kind of taking into place?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">None, other than some of our equipment was being—as I mentioned, our favorite truck was being turned over. I didn’t see anything any different in the supplies coming in or going out. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Everybody thought the world would end? Well, the world briefly ended—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—in <date>1969</date> going into <date>1970</date>, that all our computers quit issuing supplies because the <orgName>Army</orgName> used a four-digit date to determine—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—time, and if <date>today</date> would be—<date>today</date> would be 5—whatever the number, the <persName>Julian</persName> date is, let’s say 5 100,—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—that falls apart when you hit zero, when you start to subtract <date>one day</date> from the other, and so for <date>about ten days</date>—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—the computers in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> no longer issued supplies. We had to just cope without them, which maybe we were a little better off. But they had to fly teams of people in from—and we had sat around at night, saying, “Well, how are they going to handle that, when we know we’re now 9/3/64 [sic], and what happens when we go over and we have the zero and the arithmetic no longer works? And which supplies, which requests are the oldest?” So it just didn’t work for <date>about ten days</date>, but nobody mentioned that in the news media, that for <date>ten days</date> we couldn’t issue supplies. But it was a preliminary of what was supposed to happen at Y2K.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Oh, so what happened in Y2K?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, nothing, because everybody was out changing computers, and so everybody was adding—you know, when it went from, you know <date>1999</date> to <date>2000</date>, now the arithmetic didn’t work, and so it was expected that all the computers would blow up and everything. You know, I went to a <name type="event">New Year’s Eve</name> party, and I thought life would be over, but the party went right on.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Laughs.] Right. So during <date>the ten days</date> of suspension of kind of supplying, you know, military supplies, was there—I guess that created a big chaos and kind of halt in a lot of maybe operations or plans or the projects that different troops throughout <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>—the different American troops throughout the <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> were carrying out.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I don’t think anybody let it do that. The practical soldiers and people—if somebody needed something, we’re still going to give it to them, you know. We were running the system, but we weren’t going to let the system get in our way, so nobody went hungry or without ammunition or anything like that. It’s just we screwed up the system, so it didn’t work for <date>the next year</date> because supplies were issues without paperwork, but nobody was going to lose a war because they didn’t have the right piece of paper.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I see. Okay. And do you remember, like, preparing supplies for any specific operations or projects during <date>the year 1969</date> that kind of was a major thing for the American troops in <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">No, not that I can think of that we were dedicated, you know—no <placeName>Normandy</placeName> invasion or just major operations within <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>. I don’t recall that the depot acted any differently. We just—we plugged away <date>every day</date> and shipped out whatever somebody needed.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Oh, okay. I see. Right. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I think I’ve run out of things, although probably as soon as we break the phone call, I will run to my wife and say, “These are seven stories I should have told <persName>Hannah</persName>,” you know, but—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—I can’t think of them right now.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Laughs.] Okay. No, that’s totally fine. I </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I’ll call you in <date>the middle of the night</date>—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">I mean, if you think of it,—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">— to tell you to turn the recorder back on.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Uh-huh. Ah. Well, unfortunately, <orgName>the Rauner Library</orgName> will have their laptop in their office and will be locked, so that—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—will be hard. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I was gonna say, unfortunately or fortunately.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. No, yeah, please let—unfortunately, or fortunately maybe. Who knows? [Laughs.] Right. Yeah, but really, please let me know if you have any, like, specific memories or experiences that you remember that you would like to share. Just shoot me an e-mail. And if you have quite a bit of that, you know, we can definitely come back to it and talk a little bit more about it.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">If something pops into my head.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">If—we had a computer repairman—this how things, you know, appear in the mind, but he was a guy in our unit, but he really didn’t work with us; he went out in the field and worked on little computers that were out in smaller units issuing supplies and doing maintenance, and he was a repairman. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Yeah. I guess it’s kind of—it’s real interesting how the questions pop up in my mind as well, because talking about the computer maintenance, it just kind of made me wonder how the whole, like, computer system and, like, the devices and electronics and equipment worked at your office because as far as I understand, there was—you know, the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, itself, was not really producing any kind of those electronic devices. You know, there were no factories or manufacturing plants in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so was it always like that—you know, American troops would be shipping things from the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> and installing there? And, you know, usually electronic devices don’t do too well with humidity and heat, so how did the maintenance of these devices work?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Those are very good questions. All of our equipment, our major equipment was produced by <orgName>IBM</orgName>. We had something called an <orgName>IBM</orgName> 7010, which is probably—your cell phone has twice the computer power in it or a hundred times more computer power than our machine that took up a whole room.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. That’s really interesting. Right. Awesome! </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, I told you it was cold when I got back. That was rough to take. But then, like, I had all these stories to tell, and, again, I wasn’t suffering from post-traumatic [stress disorder (<orgName>PTSD</orgName>)]. I hadn’t been out in the boonies and had a terrible experience, but it was an experience, anyway, and I wanted to tell people about what I had been through, and it seemed that other than maybe my parents, no one—and even my parents had trouble understanding the things and the feelings—but no one much to talk to because, you know, it wouldn’t help you in your job, and there were hard feelings that had mellowed over time. You know, at one point I thought, Well, why would I hire anyone who had not been in the military? It was a great experience. Which I still believe. But now you can’t find anyone who’s been in the military. There are very few. The college graduate type people.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Right. And what did you do, like, in terms of I guess, like, how did you spend your time right after you got back to <placeName>the United States</placeName>? Like, did you go back to school or did you get a job?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Got a job. Well, the first thing I did was the $5,000 I was talking about after I paid for <orgName>the Hotel Mark Hopkins</orgName>—I went to <placeName>Europe</placeName> for <date>30 or 40 days</date> and had a Eurail pass, and, as I mentioned, I now had been exposed to foreign cultures and travel, and so I thought I would get <placeName>Europe</placeName> out of my system and all travel out of my system if I went there for <date>30 or 40 days</date> before I came home. I had interviewed for a job in <placeName>Illinois</placeName>, and they said, “We want to hire you, but we won’t be ready for <date>about 40 days</date>,” and that was just what I wanted to hear. And so I went to <placeName>Europe</placeName> and wandered around and rode the rails of <placeName>Europe</placeName> for <date>30 or 40 days</date> before I came back to that job.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">What are some countries that—mm-hm. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah. Yeah, what are some countries that you visited while you were in <placeName>Europe</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Started in <placeName>Spain</placeName>. Went to <placeName>Italy</placeName> then to I suppose <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>, sort of made the circle in through <placeName>Belgium</placeName> and <placeName>Amsterdam</placeName> [the <placeName>Netherlands</placeName>], and then to <placeName>England</placeName>. I think that was it. I may have hit another country or two along the way, but that trip—that was the route I took.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Ah, you covered quite an extensive area. And, like, things that you’ve experienced and saw while you were traveling those countries must have come to your, like, really differently now that you had that experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Like, as compared to if you had gone straight to <placeName>Europe</placeName>, like from—without having gone to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, just right from <placeName>the United States</placeName>. I mean, I guess it’s kind of hard to—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Once you’ve walked down the streets of <placeName>Saigon</placeName> in the middle of a war-torn economy <placeName>London</placeName> doesn’t seem so unusual. You know, that you can always find food, and you understand where somebody lives. They live in a house; they don’t live in a culvert somewhere. Once you’ve been exposed to that war-torn place, anything—you can almost handle anything. It doesn’t shock you that much.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. [Chuckles.] And I guess—yeah, after your travel in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, now you came back to <placeName>the United States</placeName>, and did you start working right away, then?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes, I did. I think, you know, <date>two or three days</date> after I came back. Went to <placeName>Illinois</placeName>, which was a new place for me, to <placeName>Peoria</placeName>, <placeName>Illinois</placeName>. Still had my—you could still tell I was military. I had short hair on the sides, and I had a moustache that was proper military, because it wasn’t supposed to go down beyond the mouth. So I still looked like I was just out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I think.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Right. Uh-huh. And I assumed <placeName>Illinois</placeName> must have been a very different setting for you as well, compared to any other places that you have been.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">It’s a little different, but not actually too dif- —<placeName>West Virginia</placeName> is a little Southern and a little Midwestern, so it isn’t too different from places that I’ve been. A little flatter, I think, but people are not so dissimilar. Many of them had never heard of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, which makes them terrible, but other than that,—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.] Right. And what was your job like? So what did you do? What was your job about in <placeName>Illinois</placeName>, more in detail?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, it was I think tied not so much to my military experience but to my <orgName>IBM</orgName> experience. I was the—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—corporate headquarters of a steel company. I started as sort of the IT liaison. I did whatever they needed with computers, the corporate financial staff and planning staff and the accountants, the president’s office. I built—you know, actually <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> helped, too. We built models with—[what was] called [the] <orgName>Dartmouth Time-Sharing [System</orgName>]. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. I see. Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Through all that I didn’t talk about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I just had to work. You had to—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Okay. But you did visit—you—right. But you said you did travel to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> once again with your son, so—</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—I know you briefly mentioned about that, but I just would like to—can I hear more about that? Because that’s really interesting, that you actually, you know, went back there after, you know, your experience of war service in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Because I loved the Vietnamese people, and there’s something about—you know, I thought we would stay in one of the old hotels, but we stayed I think at an Omni [Hotel] or something, and my son said, “Well, this is the fanciest hotel I’ve ever been in.” And I went: That wasn’t the <placeName>Saigon</placeName> I wanted to show him. But when I went up on the rooftop, I took a deep breath, and I still do it with <placeName>Saigon</placeName> because it smells like <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. You can call it <placeName>Ho Chi Minh</placeName> [City], but it still smells like <placeName>Saigon</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. And you said you visited <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> with your son. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, yes. with my son, yes, who was 16 at the time.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So, yeah, right. Just kind of curious to hear a little bit more in detail about his reaction and his responses to things that he’s seeing and, you know, stories that he’s hearing from you.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, he has read my—well, I call it my story or something that I have written. He’s read it all, and there are parts of it that I wouldn’t even want to expose—you know, I may have had a girlfriend or two in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and so my son—that’s part of war, too. My wife said, “Why’d you put that in?” Well, I was a soldier, a young soldier, and if you have such encounters, tell it like it is, as they say. But he didn’t—you know, he didn’t come out and say, “good” or “bad” or anything else, but I think he now knows his father a little better. And when he was 16 he liked the—you know, we were at <placeName>Angkor Wat</placeName> in <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> when he was 16, and he was not speaking to me because he wanted to be with his friends in <placeName>Indiana</placeName>. You know, I had to say, “We’re the only two people for 30 miles that speak English, and you’re not speaking to me now, so why don’t you start talking?” It was his birthday, and he didn’t want to be with his dad in a strange country. But <date>about six or seven years ago</date>, I heard him—overheard him talking to a friend at a football game, and they were talking about what they did for their 16th birthday, and he had a smile and said, “I want to <placeName>Angkor Wat</placeName>, <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>.” And nobody else could top that. And so—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—his views have changed, and he also has now become a pretty good traveler. He’s been to a lot of places and continues to do that.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. I see. Great. What are some other places that you’ve traveled, other than <placeName>Europe</placeName> and <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, let me see, <placeName>Africa</placeName>. My wife and I are going on a cruise to <placeName>west Africa</placeName>, down the coast from <placeName>Ghana</placeName> to <placeName>Cape Town</placeName> <date>this fall</date>. We’re about ready to go on a trip to <placeName>Madagascar</placeName> and <placeName>Mauritius</placeName> and the <placeName>Seychelles</placeName>. Been to <placeName>Fiji</placeName> and <placeName>Taiwan</placeName>, all the countries of the former <placeName>Yugoslavia</placeName>, <placeName>Russia</placeName>, <placeName>South Korea</placeName>, <placeName>Taiwan</placeName>, <placeName>New Zealand</placeName>. Name a country. I think I’ve been to most of them.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I’ve been to most of them that are safe to, anyway.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Yeah, you did travel really extensively. And I actually forgot to ask you: <date>What year</date> did you travel back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? When was that?</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">He was born in ’78, and even though I told you I was a partial math major—’78 and he was 16. That makes ’94.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Yeah, okay. That’s actually the year I was born.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">We went to <placeName>Laos</placeName> and <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> and <placeName>Thailand</placeName> on the same trip.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Ah. Interesting. Okay. Great. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I, you know, somehow got in the <placeName>Midwest</placeName>. I somehow—[there] was a friend from <orgName>the University of Virginia</orgName> who had started to work at the same company in <placeName>Illinois</placeName> and had said, “Why don’t you come on out and join us?” So I did that. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>, <persName>mm-hm</persName>. Ah. I see. Great. Awesome! Right.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">I decided to—my first loyalty—I bleed green first, to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but I have a second love, and that’s <orgName>the University of Virginia</orgName> that I like, and I like my <date>two years</date> here, and so we had a chance to move to this town, and it is warmer than <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, and so we like living in a university town, which <orgName>Charlottesville</orgName> is.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Great. Awesome.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Oh, maybe one thought—</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">—you know, any kind of opinion, your thoughts, your feelings.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—that pops into my mind since—I talked of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and <orgName>ROTC</orgName>. I may have mentioned to you on our earlier phone call that some of the best officers I ever ran into were <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> graduates—that it was a combination of—you don’t go to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> unless you’re interested in the outdoors, in most cases. You like trees and you like nature and being out there, but also a liberal education you receive—it just all combines to make—if you’ve got to have military officers, if you just have to have them and if you have to have wars, I can’t think of any place that produces better officers than <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Okay. </u>
      <u who="JOLLY">—soapbox and make a speech.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right. Great.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Part of a great heritage.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG">[Chuckles.] Right. Great. Thank you so much.</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Well, I have absolutely enjoyed it, and next time you’re in <placeName>Virginia</placeName> or I’m in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> when you’re there, I’ll tell you 14 more stories, and you can tell me what you’ve heard from others.</u>
      <u who="CHUNG"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Yeah, sounds exciting. Sounds like a plan. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="JOLLY">Okay. </u>
      <u who="CHUNG">Right. Uh-huh. Thank you so much. I will just turn off the recorder right now.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
