<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="CAROTHERS"/>
        <person xml:id="KEISWETTER"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So this is <persName>Andrew Carothers</persName>. <date>Today</date> is <date>October 30th, 2015</date>. It is 10:45 a.m. I am in <persName>Rauner</persName> [<orgName>Special Collections] Library</orgName> at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName> in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>. And I’m interviewing <persName>Allen Keiswetter</persName> [pronouncing it CHAISE-wetter]. Oops, sorry. I think I might have—how do you pronounced your last name, again?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">KEY-sweater, like “keyed” and a sweater, KEY-sweater.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">KEY-sweater. All right. So I’m in <orgName>Rauner Library</orgName>, and I’m interviewing <persName>Allen Keiswetter</persName>, who is in <placeName>Arlington</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>. All right.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Just fine, thank you.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. So the plan for the interview—I’d like to start off with your—your early life. It’s going to be your childhood, your upbringing, and then we can move into your time at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and then your experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and then anything you’d like to share about your—your <name type="event">post-Vietnam</name> life, your perspectives on <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> now, looking back <date>a few years later</date> and how that experience has shaped you.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">That sounds fine. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. So to start off with, where—where were you born?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I was born in <placeName>Hastings</placeName>, <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>, but this was where my mother’s parents lived, and I grew up and spent most of my childhood in <placeName>Kansas</placeName>, in small towns: first <orgName>Alton</orgName>, which has a population of 300 people; <orgName>Woodston</orgName>, also about the same size; and in <placeName>Great Bend</placeName>, which is a thriving metropolis of 13,000.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.] All right. All right. And what year were you born in?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">In <date>1944</date>, <date>June 3rd</date>, <date>three days</date> before <name type="event">D-Day</name> [the <placeName>Normandy</placeName> landings of <name type="event">World War II</name>].</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><date>Three days</date> before <name type="event">D-Day</name>. All right. In <date>1944</date>. So what was that like, being born—I mean, I imagine, obviously you don’t remember the end of <name type="event">World War II</name>, but what was that like being born and growing up—and probably some of your first memories of your childhood was in—was during this early <name type="event">Cold War</name> period. And so as—from—as a relatively young child, do you remember anything about that <name type="event">Cold War</name> context, and what was that like?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, before we turn to <name type="event">the Cold War</name> and give you some idea, when I lived in <placeName>Alton</placeName>, a very small town and I was—what?—four or <date>five, six years old</date>, I would walk every night to my grandmother’s house and get a pail of milk, as it was a sort of a rural community, and then help with plucking chickens and gathering of eggs and planting a garden. Anyways, I was thinking about it. It was a very pleasant, almost idyllic time.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That’s funny.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I don’t have strong—strong recollections of that period. I do remember—and this is when I was in the second grade, I think? That when [<placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> leader <persName>Joseph V.] Stalin</persName> died—and I was always—I was an international relations major, and a diplomat later, but I remember—probably my earliest memory was coming to my second grade class and telling my teacher that <persName>Stalin</persName> had died, and she wondered why I would know that. [Both chuckle.] </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Nice. Well, that’s funny. I remember hearing about those—the nuclear weapons shelter drills from my parents, and both of us mentioning, “Hey, you know, we feel like hiding under your desk in the event of a nuclear attack is probably not going to be that helpful,” but I guess it provides sort of a sense of security.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I think it raises sensitivity. It made people aware that there was an enemy. I think that was probably the major purpose of it all, because [chuckles] I can’t imagine that it has much real effect.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.] No, I—I doubt it. So we’ll definitely circle back to more—more about <name type="event">the Cold War</name> and your experiences. There’s a lot that I’d like to get into. But before we get back to sort of the political side, can you tell me a little bit about your—your family and your parents? What did you do? Did you have any siblings?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes. Both of my parents grew up on farms. They were children of <name type="event">the Great Depression</name>. My father was one of nine children, and my grandmother would tell stories of wetting down <persName>gunny sacks</persName> to plug under the doors and windows to keep the dust from blowing in as <placeName>Kansas</placeName> was in the middle of <name type="event">the Dust Bowl</name>. And to <date>this day</date>, there is a family recipe called—what’s called “Depression raisin cake” because foodstuffs are made available, and flour and butter and raisins, and so my grandmother made—came up with a recipe called Depression raisin cake, which still lives on in the family as a great favorite.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Interesting. I had no idea that <placeName>Kansas</placeName> used to be one of the biggest oil-producing states in the country.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yeah. Well, <orgName>Great Bend</orgName> was the center of the industry, which is why we lived there.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Interesting. So it sounds like growing up there was really no question that you were—you were planning on going to college, that your parents really valued that. How—how else were your parents involved in your education, growing up? And were there other attitudes or perspectives that your parents had that you thought particularly influential in—in your upbringing?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes. Yeah. You mentioned the valuing of education. That’s certainly true. I think both of them had a strong curiosity, and that’s something that I certainly have, a curiosity about the outside world, just about life in general. They certainly work hard working, and that was passed on. And I suppose the most important is it was a loving and generous family, and we all liked each other, got along with each other and still do. I talk to my brother two or three times a week, even now. So I think those are the most important things.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Great. And as you—what were you involved with besides—obviously, academics were important to you. What else were you involved with, growing up in elementary, middle, high school? Were you an athlete, involved with debate or some sort of other, more sort of international relations sort of activity? What did—what did you do outside of the classroom?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes. Well, I was very much interested in the outdoors. I liked fishing. Not so much into hunting. One of my best friends was the same age I am, but he was greatly interested in herpetology, and so we collected snakes and other things. And a humorous tale: He and I went out and caught a jar full of small water snakes that we brought to his home, and his mother was the president of <orgName>the Kansas State Presbyterian Women’s Association</orgName>, and we had put the snakes into—I think in the guest bathroom.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">And then we took them out and put them in an aquarium, but that afternoon, when his mother was entertaining, a woman came screaming out of the guest bathroom because a snake had poked its head up out of the drain [chuckles]. Anyway, so small things like that.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And did you—did you often talk about international affairs and politics and history with—with your parents or your brother or friends?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, not with my parents but—well, I had two good friends, <persName>Chuck</persName> [<persName>Davis</persName>] and <persName>Bob</persName>, and <persName>Chuck</persName>’s father in particular was an intellectual mentor to me. He was the mayor of our small town. He established our library. He established a local <orgName>NPR</orgName> [<orgName>National Public Radio</orgName>] station and radio and TV, and was a prominent Republican figure. And he, I think in many ways, was my intellectual mentor, guide star at this part of my life.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That’s funny. And what was—what was <persName>Chuck</persName> dad’s name?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">His name was [<persName>Horace C.] H. C. Davis</persName>, called “Dave” Davis, and he owned a small oil drilling company, <persName>Davis Drilling</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And  he was—he was the one who was your intellectual mentor, right? Or was that <persName>Bob</persName>’s dad?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right. No, that’s H. C. And <persName>Bob</persName>’s dad was a public servant, and he was in charge of the welfare program and welfare system for <placeName>Barton County</placeName>, where we lived, which had about—I don’t know— 20,000 people.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. And so the—the <persName>Kennedy</persName> election would have been when you were a sophomore or a junior in high school? Correct?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Mmm, junior, I think.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Junior in high school. Okay. And what—what was—what was that election like? I know I’m talking with a number of people. That’s a memory that has stood out for a lot of people, you know, the <persName>Kennedy</persName> election. And so as, you know, someone who’s <date>fifteen or sixteen</date> at that time and a <persName>Kennedy</persName> fan, what was it like seeing <persName>Kennedy</persName> elected, and sort of what were your thoughts about what the <persName>Kennedy</persName> election would mean for the country moving forward?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, of course, there was the youth factor, and that was greatly appealing. And <placeName>Kansas</placeName> then was a Republican state, perhaps not quite as fanatically Republican as it is <date>today</date>, but it was always a Republican state, and so <persName>Bob</persName> and I were frequently the sole defenders or supporters of <persName>Kennedy</persName> in most discussion groups.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. Gotcha. And before we kind of move—move on a little bit, there’s one more element of your childhood that I was interested in. You touched on how you moved around a lot—well, not necessarily a lot, but lived in—lived in a few different small towns and then ended up moving to Great Bend and graduating from high school. What was moving your family around?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, my father’s employment, I guess. We lived in <placeName>Alton</placeName> and <placeName>Woodston</placeName>, where he ran filling stations. We moved to <placeName>Oklahoma City</placeName>, where we lived for <date>a couple of years</date>, and again he ran a filling station. But then, while there, he made the acquaintance of another intellectual mentor, <persName>Ed Hammond</persName>, who owned an oil fill chemical business headquartered in <placeName>Oklahoma City</placeName>, and he needed someone to open up a business in <placeName>Kansas</placeName>. And so we then moved to <placeName>Kansas</placeName> when I was about, I don’t know, seventh grade, whatever that is, 12? And then I spent the rest of my—my high school years there.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so in—in seventh grade, when you moved to <placeName>Kansas</placeName>, that was when you moved to <placeName>Great Bend</placeName>, right?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">That’s right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. And what was that experience like, moving around to a number of different cities, a number of different states, living in some very small towns, living in some bigger cities like <placeName>Oklahoma City</placeName>? What was that experience like?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, the small towns, I liked very much, and <placeName>Oklahoma City</placeName>, I did too. And I do remember, however, going to high school or to first in middle school—the last part of the sixth and <date>the beginning of the seventh</date> grade. And, you know, it’s much different when you’re in a school that has 1,000 or 2,000 students than one, the entire school has at most 40 or <date>50</date>. [Chuckles.] So that was a bit of an adjustment.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">So, it well, it had extremely good schools. It provided opportunities to go out fishing on the Ar-KAN-sas River. It’s a six- to eight-hour drive to the mountains in <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, where I spent most of my childhood vacations during this period. We still as the family go back there. So all in all, I guess it came with an appreciation that if you were willing to drive six or eight hours, you can have a very good life.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And once you—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">That’s not true, by the way.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER"><date>Today</date> that’s not true, because of the large Hispanic population.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. Okay. And so once you left Great Bend and came to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and then after <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, what was that experience like, going from a place with—I mean, granted, I believe you said earlier that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> wasn’t particularly diverse when you were there, but moving out of Great Bend, did you—did you find a lot more diversity in the other places that you were, and what was that experience like?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, let’s start with why I went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I decided that I did want to go “back east” to school, as the expression was. I ended up applying to <orgName>Dartmouth, Brown [University</orgName>] and <persName>Princeton</persName> [University], and you say, “Why these three?” Well, the answer is they’re all located in relatively small towns. I didn't think I was up to <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> and <placeName>Boston</placeName> or <placeName>Columbia</placeName> [University] and <placeName>New York City</placeName>, and these seemed to be relatively small towns, with which I thought I could cope.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">And I got a thick envelope from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, along with a large scholarship, and it was a question of what I would do. I remember talking to my parents and saying, “I want to go to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>.” And they basically said, “But why don’t you just go to <orgName>the University of Kansas</orgName>? That’s three hours from here, not sort of a <date>three-days</date>’ drive from here.” And at the end of the conversation, they said, “Sure, fine. You’ll go to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. We’re glad to support you.” And so they did.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">You said he had gone to <persName>Mount Sherman</persName>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">To <persName>Mount Herman</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">To <persName>Mount Herman</persName>. Is that a prep school?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes. It’s I believe in <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName> or <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>. I’ve forgotten. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure. Yeah. Let’s—let’s move on to—Let’s move on to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. So you arrived at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in <date>the fall of 1962</date>.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what—what was the experience like of coming from—from <placeName>Kansas</placeName> and coming from small-town <placeName>Kansas</placeName> but then arriving in small-town <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>? Were there a lot of parallels between small-town <placeName>Kansas</placeName> and small-town <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, or was it really a totally new experience?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">It was a totally new experience. <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was diverse, and certainly I went from being the top or one of the top students to struggling for <date>my first year</date> at least, my first term, in part because of the adjustment, I think, from being away from home. But it was certainly a much stronger academic challenge than I had ever had before that.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Anyway, I went to see him, a regular counseling session almost, and I would credit him with giving me one of my most important life skills, which is the ability to write well, quickly and clearly. And this has been a skill that has been very important first in my foreign service career and now, since I retired from the foreign service, in my role as a scholar at <orgName>the Middle East Institute</orgName> and as a professor at <orgName>the National War College</orgName> and <orgName>the National Defense Intelligence College</orgName> [now <orgName>National Intelligence University</orgName>] and <orgName>the University of Maryland</orgName>. So big kudos to him, although I suffered mightily. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I remember I wrote some essay on the Frost poem, “Apple Pickings” [sic; “After Apple-Picking”]. And I got it back, and he called it an original sort of interpretation, but it was not in a good sense.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">He said he had thought that this was in no way what <persName>Frost</persName> had intended, but he would ask <persName>Frost</persName> the next time he saw him. Whether this meaning—this meaning is a good—a good interpretation. And my reaction to that is, I don’t care what <persName>Frost</persName> intended. I thought that the action was valid no matter what. Anyway, <persName>Frost</persName> was important, and my class was the last class that he addressed before he died, so my favorite poet remains <persName>Frost</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Very nice.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Otherwise—go ahead.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Oh, no, no, go ahead. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, to capture the spirit of the times, if you will, I would say that campus life was jokingly—what summarized by a rivalry between <orgName>the Green Weenies</orgName> and <persName>the Big Greeners</persName>. The Green Weenies were the intellectuals, and the Big Greeners were the athletes and the frat boys, the fraternity boys in particular. And The <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—there would be chiding letters and stories.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Did they ever—did they ever find out who—who was the culprit, which side?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, it was some fraternity, although I don’t remember the name. It was a fraternity prank of some sort.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Anyway, the political environment? I guess two comments there. In the election of <date>1964</date>, <persName>Nelson [A.]</persName> <persName>Rockefeller</persName> was running, and his sort of labor base, recruiting base was <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>, because he was a graduate from there. And I and another friend—[phone rings]—let me move here—I and another friend, who—and my friend was—his name was Gene [<persName>B.] Marshall</persName> [Class of 1964]—was from <placeName>Littleton</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>. So we were assigned <placeName>Littleton</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, for the Republican primary. And he and I went out <date>every weekend</date> for <date>weeks</date> and <date>weeks</date> before the primary to talk to everybody in this town. And when the election came, guess what: <persName>Henry Cabot Lodge</persName> [Jr.] won the state by a landslide as a write-in. So—</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">But I did participate in the Young Republicans at that stage. This is not my current political views, but nonetheless, it was then.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. And while—while you were there, and especially before <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> really—really escalated, was there a lot of talk about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> or American involvement overseas, on campus? Or was it really not much of a contested topic?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, it was certainly a topic of a great deal of interest. It wasn’t a movement topic. But I do remember going to lectures about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at that time—and maybe it still exists; I don’t know. Seniors had to take something called <name type="event">the Great Issues</name> course. And I believe it was evry night—excuse me, every <date>Monday</date> evening. We would have some outside lecturer, who—a diplomat, a politician, you know, a well-known academic or commentator or journalist, people who were nationally-known names.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Gotcha. And speaking of—of politics, one thing that I noticed was that you were a big <persName>Kennedy</persName> fan back at home, and then at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> you were involved with the Young Republicans and were—were campaigning for <persName>Rockefeller</persName>. Did your—did your political beliefs change at some point in there? Had you previously identified more as a Democrat and then moved over to more of—of a Republican? What was the evolution of your political beliefs like in high school and college?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, the difference between <persName>Kennedy</persName> and <persName>Nelson Rockefeller</persName>—not all that much [both chuckle] because there was a liberal wing of <orgName>the Republican Party</orgName>. I think when I was in <placeName>Kansas</placeName>, you know, there was a little bit of the spirit of rebellion, but I knew for sure that I didn’t share the beliefs of, say, my uncle, who told me that he would vote for <persName>Fidel Castro</persName> if he ran on the Republican ticket, so—[Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That makes sense.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Correct.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And there were a few—a few major political events that—that happened in there, so one—one event that I want to touch on is the—the <persName>Kennedy</persName> assassination.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">People that—people that I’ve talked to who lived through that event have compared it almost to 9/11 in terms of people remembering where they were—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Sure.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—when it happened. And what—what was that—what was your reaction to that, and what was the general campus reaction to the <persName>Kennedy</persName> assassination?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well shock was the reaction, of course. The country’s reaction as well. As to how I heard about it, I was coming back from class to <persName>Cohen Hall</persName>, and there was someone—one of my suite mates in <persName>Cohen</persName> came running out, and he was on the way to class, and he shouted at me as he ran by and stuck out his fist. “<persName>Kennedy</persName> has been killed!” And what I did is—he hit me in the stomach—is collapsed on the sidewalk. [Chuckles.] Anyway, I do remember it because of the pain as well as the psychological shock. And I can’t remember exactly what happened on campus after that, but I’m sure it was sort of the standard grieving process.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">But, nonetheless, there was a great sensitivity on campus to the Cuban missile episode, something which we all followed closely. And that particular memory lives—lives on.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And another—another important event, and particularly one that relates to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that occurred while you were at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, was the <placeName>Tonkin Gulf</placeName> incident [sic; <placeName>Gulf of Tonkin</placeName> incident] and then, <date>a few days later</date>, <placeName>the Tonkin Gulf Resolution</placeName> [sic; <placeName>Gulf of Tonkin</placeName> Resolution]. And what were—what were your thoughts on that, and what was the general campus attitude towards really the start of—not the start of  <placeName>U.S.</placeName> involvement in <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> but really the start of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, by this time, these resolutions and these events have been so impressive and on my part with other memories and study and so on and so forth that I can’t really sort of isolate out exactly what it was at that time. However, the—the campus was clearly anti war, clearly anti [President <persName>Lyndon B.] Johnson</persName>. And I’m sure that the reaction was critical.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That makes sense.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Tell me a little bit about that. How did you end up working for <persName>Bob Dole</persName>, and what was that experience like, being in the heart of politics in [<placeName>Washington</placeName>,] <placeName>D.C.</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, this is indeed a long time ago. <persName>Bob Dole</persName> was from  Russell, <placeName>Kansas</placeName>, which is not far from <placeName>Great Bend</placeName>, where I grew up, and my friend, <persName>H. C. Davis</persName>, was friends with <persName>Bob Dole</persName>, and my father had also met him. So I applied for an internship there and was accepted. It was outside the college auspices, but I did participate in the college programs in <placeName>Washington</placeName> for the interns from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> who were there for <date>the summer</date>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">And so the only part of my speech that survived is the question in the beginning. [Chuckles.] I think that was very important, that you have to know your person that you’re writing for if you’re writing a speech, and the context of the audience. [Chuckles.] It was a learning experience for me.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I was not particularly surprised when they divorced.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">All right. Wow! [Chuckles.] And so it sounds like you had—judging from what I’ve heard from friends who have interned in <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, it sounds like you had a lot more contact with Congressman <persName>Dole</persName> than certainly interns do now. And then was that internship that you had—was that unusual amount of contact with <persName>Dole</persName>, or was that fairly par for the course?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I think I probably had more contact than the other interns, but still, you know, there may have been three or four interns. There were not tens and dozens as there are now sometimes. And besides, it’s just like if we’re from <placeName>Virginia</placeName> and we want to see the <placeName>Capitol</placeName> and we wanna get a special pass, it’s very hard to get one from our congressman or senator. But if it’s my brother visiting from <placeName>Kansas</placeName>, he can contact his senator or congressman, and [chuckles] there are not so many Kansans that request them. You know, the demand is much less, and he can arrange it right away. So it’s partly just the laws of supply and demand.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And did working for <orgName>Dole</orgName> and spending <date>the summer</date> in D.C.—did that have an impact on your—your political beliefs and particularly your—your sentiments about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I don’t remember having any particular affect on my sentiments about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I can’t even recall at this point what <persName>Dole</persName> believed about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. But it had a larger impact. It was my first chance to see <placeName>D.C.</placeName> I sort of—I liked it immediately. It sort of set the stage for where I live now and for much of my career. And in that way, it—it was sort of a tidbit, a tasting of a life that I like very much.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. Got it. And so after that internship, you—you came back, and you returned to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and graduated in <date>’66</date>. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">That’s right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what did you do after you graduated? What was your first job?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, let me finish up my college career, if I could, please, <persName>Andrew</persName>. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER"><date>The last year</date>, I wrote my senior thesis. As an international relations major. We had to write a senior thesis. Normally, seniors didn’t do that. I don’t know what the practice is now. But I wrote it on European relations. It was particularly about the prospects of the British entry into the <orgName>EU</orgName> [<orgName>European Union</orgName>], and the point about this was that I was at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and my course collective centered on European affairs.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><placeName>Ho-ho</placeName>!</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Anyway, this shows the type of experience it was there. I lived with an Italian—a German and a Brit, an Englishman for <date>a year</date>. And <persName>Richard [A.]</persName> <persName>Hitchman</persName>, the Englishman and I, have remained in close touch since and see each other <date>every few years</date>, and they come here, or we go there.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I realized that even if I joined <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>, which is what I did, I would be going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> because all entering <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers—and even more true for single male <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers—went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So I decided if I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I would prefer to go as a diplomat than as a draftee. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. Got it.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Italian.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Italian. What was that experience like, and how did that affect you?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Okay. Well, <orgName>Bologna</orgName> was in many ways a wonderful experience because we took the opportunity to travel. There were school-sponsored trips. There were two of them, each one about I think <date>a week to two weeks</date> long, where we hit the major European capitals. The first time I saw <placeName>Paris</placeName> was on a European trip. We went to <placeName>Paris</placeName> and <placeName>Brussels</placeName> and <placeName>Luxembourg</placeName>. And then privately we managed to see much of <placeName>Italy</placeName>: <placeName>Rome</placeName> and so on. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Wow</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">While there, I did get to know well <persName>Richard Hitchman</persName>, and his father was a senior official in the British government, a senior civil servant. He first headed <orgName>the National Public Health Service</orgName> [sic; <orgName>National Health Service</orgName>], and then he headed <orgName>the British Atomic Energy Commission</orgName> [sic; <orgName>United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority</orgName>]. And I remember that one time—I guess it was on the way home to <persName>Bologna</persName>—I stayed with <persName>Richard</persName> and his family, and his mother was <placeName>America</placeName>, and his father was obviously British. And both of them Oxbridgians.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure. And did—did being in <placeName>Europe</placeName> in that international exposure and being in close proximity to people who were coming from political systems all over the world—did that—did that change your—your political beliefs at all? Like, did that—I know you mentioned that you eventually, you know, came to oppose the war in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Did that experience in <placeName>Italy</placeName> factor into that?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I think it did because by this time the Europeans were largely against <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I guess I would say that I was—I think as I recall it, I was at the beginning sort of had an academic approach to it; that is, of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Wanted to know more about it, wanted to read, wanted to learn. Maybe because the academic world was almost solidly anti <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I was opposed to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I just wasn’t fervently so.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes, it was. It actually was in <placeName>Rosslyn</placeName> [<placeName>Virginia</placeName>], which is just across the <placeName>Potomac</placeName> [River], but was in the <placeName>D.C.</placeName> area. And we were the largest <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> class ever admitted, the 79th class, and I can’t remember how many there were, but in the nature of 40 or 50. And it was because they were—<orgName>the State Department</orgName> was hiring <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, frankly. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">And so, you know, this struck some of us that here—you know, it’s sort of like, “Other than that, Mrs. <persName>Lincoln</persName>, how was the play?” You know, why exclude the most important issue? But this was well respected. I mean, nobody asked him about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I remember being impressed by him but being disappointed that <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName> would exclude that.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And do you know if—if they found that an effective mechanism to—to communicate their dissent and if that dissent had—had any impact, or was it—did it seem more of a way to give people an outlet to express that dissent without, say, going to the media?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, the answer is both, because it certainly provided a means of venting, and <date>each year</date>, there is an award for dissent in <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>, and there are many good examples over <date>the decades</date> since then to where policy has been changed as a result of dissent. So, yes, it has been effective, but it was, I suspect, initially an idea meant to allow venting.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">No, there were a few women, but not—</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">—not too many. I—I—I can’t give you any specific numbers, but, you know, maybe there were four or five women.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. And did all of you have a sense that you would be going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">No, I think only the single young men or the young men married without children. I think we all went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. And what was—what was the background of the other <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers in your class? Were they largely, you know, people like you who—you know, <placeName>East Coast</placeName> educated, had some graduate school experience, or was there—or was it a diverse group?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I would have to reflect on this for a moment. First of all, we came from all over <placeName>the United States</placeName>. I think it’s true to say that they were all well educated, maybe not at <orgName>the Ivy League</orgName> or at <orgName>Stanford</orgName> [University] or [<orgName>the University of California</orgName>,] <orgName>Berkeley</orgName>, although many were. But, you know, I would say the—the best schools across <placeName>the United States</placeName>: <placeName>Wisconsin</placeName> and <placeName>Chicago</placeName> and so on and so forth.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And in terms of people’s political attitudes and particularly their thoughts on <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, was there a lot of continuity within the class or was there some legitimate disagreement among <orgName>FSO</orgName> among what the American role in—in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> should be?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I don't recall any strong, highly opinionated discussions at this point. I do a bit later, but not in the <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> class. I think for many of us it was an acceptance, a learning experience, the idea that whatever opinions we have now, we were about to have a real experience to find out what it’s all about. At least that was my attitude, and I think that was a common one.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">What? I’m sorry. What? Go ahead please. I didn’t understand the question.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Okay. I was just saying let’s move—let’s move into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And you arrived—you arrived in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> shortly after the Tet Offensive. I believe you—you arrived in <date>April</date>? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right. Correct. For me—</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, for me it was a very traumatic arrival because I had left <placeName>Washington</placeName> and flown to <placeName>Kansas</placeName> to see my family and then flown to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, and while I was in <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, I learned that President <persName>Johnson</persName> was withdrawing from the election or the candidacy to be reelected, principally because it seemed certain that he couldn’t get the nomination. And I had this feeling that, well, things are changing at home, and I haven’t even left the borders of the country yet.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And you—you noted earlier that you realized that you were probably going to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and decided you’d—okay, you’d rather go as a diplomat than in the military. And then you arrive in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and encounter a real sense of danger as a <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officer there.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes. Right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Did you expect to feel that threatened and that—that in danger in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> when you were thinking about being a diplomat and especially as you were going through your—your training, or did it feel much more dangerous than you imagined it would?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I would say I did feel a sense of danger, but it wasn’t a constant feeling of danger. They were isolated incidents when I felt in danger. Certainly, the entry was one of them. I as in the Chiêu Hồi Program [a large, expensive psychological (PSYOP) campaign of <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>]. And we can come back to that in some detail. But in this capacity, I traveled quite a bit, and I remember going to a place called <placeName>Ninh Binh Province</placeName>, which is in the [<placeName>Red River] Delta</placeName>, and I went out with a group called <orgName>Armed Propaganda Teams</orgName>, which are defectors that had left <placeName>the Viet Cong</placeName> or <orgName>the North Vietnamese Army</orgName>, but usually <placeName>the Viet Cong</placeName>. And they would go out to recruit other defectors.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what was it like being as a—now, you were in your mid-20s at this point, right?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes, yes.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Being someone—you know, a young man in his mid-20s and having to confront these very real issues of life and death and knowing that a lot of people who went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> weren’t going to come back and knowing that there was a possibility that that could be you as well?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, you know, I didn’t have sort of existential paralysis. That didn’t happen to me. It was a fairly intellectual question to me, meaning I always realized it could happen, and certainly there had been brushes with danger. But it led me to read books like Is God Dead? And to sort of think about these things.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And—go ahead.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, why don’t you ask me another question? I lost my spontaneous stories at this point.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure, sure. So within CORDS there was a variety of different programs, and how did you end up working specifically for Chiêu Hồi? Were you assigned? Were you able to preference this specific program?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, the answer was when I got there, we were sort of—we were assigned—but there was an interview process, and there was a man named <persName>Ogden Williams</persName>, who headed <orgName>the Chiêu Hồi </orgName>program, and I had an interview with him. We immediately liked each other, so I didn’t go on to the second choice; I just accepted and I was on my way.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what was—so you—you arrive in—outside of <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, and then you—<date>you’re first</date> stationed in Can Tho. Correct?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">That’s right. Correct.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So Can <orgName>Tho</orgName> is down—down in the <placeName>Delta</placeName>,—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—an area that—at some point it had had a lot of Viet Cong activity. I know that there was a lot in the <placeName>Delta</placeName>. I don’t—I don’t know particularly about Can <orgName>Tho</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, yes, it was not prime—most of the fighting happened north—around <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and through the north, but there were, in <orgName>the IV Corps</orgName>, considerable activity, as evidenced by my experience in <placeName>Ninh Binh</placeName> when I was there. But it was—it was more like asymmetric activity—you know, snipers, this sort of thing, rather than mass assault forces. That being said, I lived in a hotel there, and any given night you could go up on the roof and you could see the airplanes firing the tracer fire all around, on all sides, so there was quite a bit of action.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And you mentioned that on any given night you would go up to the roof of the hotel and see tracer fire. So in your—your <date>daily</date> life in Can Tho, did it feel like you were in a combat environment, or did it feel like you were largely removed from a lot of the violence that was going on?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">It seemed more removed, and I did not move around the city wondering whether I was going to get home. So it—there was not—there was during Tet, fighting in Can <orgName>Tho</orgName>, and certainly in <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName>, but the city had been pacified.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what was that environment like? You know, the leaders would talk a lot about pacification and about South Vietnamese villages being pacified. It sounds like that was not the experience that you necessarily had, where you were in an area where, okay, the major city is pacified, but a couple of times that you’d go out of Can Tho, it sounds like you ran into situations that suggest that the area was not pacified.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I think that’s exactly true. And since—there had been publications of a lot of documents to suggest that even the pacification was a false sense because the Viet Cong had so heavily penetrated <orgName>the Vietnamese Army</orgName>, <orgName>the South Vietnamese Army</orgName>, the South Vietnamese security forces generally, the government. So while I did have a sense of security in my daily life, and, you’re right, when I traveled out of the city, there was a greater exposure to danger, I think probably the reality is that there was just a lot, that I didn’t know, couldn’t appreciate—no American knew, and probably much—many of the people I knew had Viet Cong sympathies.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And did coming to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and despite the rhetoric coming from leaders about pacification, discovering that a lot of that was not true, did that have any impact on morale of American both <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers and enlisted men and other—other people in the military? Did that impact American morale in the region? Did you—did you see any of that?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, not during my time. It did a little later, in ’74, when the evacuations occurred and all of that, when it became—when all of this infiltration became apparent, and many <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers who were there at that time really did heroic deeds to get out Vietnamese who were their friends and with whom they had worked. And I knew some of those. My friend <persName>Ogden Williams</persName> was among them. And he went back, and he was what I would describe “a man of many ladies”—[both chuckle]—so he sort of brought back to <placeName>the United States</placeName> the families with whom he had been closely associated.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And I would love to hear about some of those, and especially some of the characters that you were around, too. You <persName>mentioned—[A</persName> tone sounds again; there are missing words here; 1:44:42] who sounds like a [tone; missing words; 1:44:47]—who sounds like a very—a very interesting man. And what—what was it like working for him, and just—was—was that sort of a common figure, like the foreigner who had come to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and do a little bit more than just interact on a professional level with people</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes. Well, [tone; missing words; 1:45:16] was the son of a British diplomat, and when <name type="event">World War II</name> broke out, his family was assigned to <placeName>Russia</placeName>, and they couldn’t get—to <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, and they couldn't get out via <placeName>Europe</placeName>, so they took a train across <placeName>Russia</placeName>, <placeName>Vladivostok</placeName> and a boat to <placeName>Australia</placeName>, and that’s how he became an Australian.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Wow. And what were those medals—what were those awards for?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Oh, it was just for heroic service to the Vietnamese people and the cause of saving <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> from, you know, the communists.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. Were they awarded for particular instances, or was it more just—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">No.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—as a commentary on your career there?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes, I think it was a commentary on my career.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. And what—it sounds like you had a lot of interactions with the Vietnamese and others—others did, too, you know, with some people. All of you interacted with them professionally; some people, on a romantic level; some, on a personal level. What were—were largely the interactions like between the Americans and the other—the other Westerners there and the Vietnamese people, both your <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> counterparts and also just Vietnamese civilians in general?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I think my interactions were all I think quite positive except for those who were trying to shoot me, I guess. [Both chuckle.] For example, in <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName> I lived in an estate—that’s not the word I want, but I can’t think of it at the moment—but in a large house with about a half a dozen other Americans. And all around the outside were small Vietnamese shops. And so I could walk out the door in the morning, and there would-at the pho I could have breakfast, if I wanted to, and I frequently did that. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">All right! And what do you think the—the Vietnamese attitudes were towards the Americans? Were they equally positive?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, the appeared to be positive, but you got to keep in mind we lost the war, and evidence suggests heavy infiltration, but I know—I can jump ahead. I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—when was it? I guess <date>seven years ago</date>. And, you know, there’s no rancor. Part of that is generational change, but there is no rancor. People were extremely welcome—welcoming, I should say. And generally Vietnamese and Americans like each other.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That’s—that’s—that’s interesting to me, seeing—you know, given the history. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Is that—is that surprising to you as—as well, or—or is—or has there always been sort of a positive relationship? You  know, you’d think that a number of people in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> would not look favorably upon <placeName>the United States</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Look, I have several explanations. One is when I was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <orgName>the Foreign Service</orgName>, the people were in essence paid to like me, and when I was there as a tourist, I was paying them to like me. [Both chuckle.] So there is that difference of context. But if you go back historically, you go to <placeName>Hồ Chí Minh</placeName>. He tried hard to develop relations with the Americans. He wrote several letters to various presidents. But the decision was made we had to support the French; we couldn’t support the independence movement.  And so there was a certain admiration, underlying admiration for <placeName>America</placeName> and the principles for which we have stood, and I think this carries over, to some extent.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I would love to circle back to that. I have a couple more questions about—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Sure.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><persName>—Chiêu Hồi.</persName> So what was the dynamic like between the military people and the Foreign Service people, the <orgName>USAID</orgName> people, from—well, I’m not sure, actually, how—how much the <orgName>USAID</orgName> was involved in Chiêu Hồi, but I’ve heard it more broadly about CORDS. It was kind of this jumble of people from—from all over various government posts. So what was the dynamic like within Chiêu Hồi?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, first of all, we did have, <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> people. We did have AID [<orgName>U.S. Agency for International Development</orgName>] people, and we had Filipinos, obviously Australians and some others. We all got along quite well. There was not a problem there. And I think there may have been some problems in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, where there were larger gatherings and, you know, there were factions that feel that they weren’t getting their just treatment or something like that. But out in the corps and in the provinces, no problem. At least, I didn't find a problem.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. And now—that was the—the relationship was cooperative and productive, both within various people from the American side and then also with—with your South Vietnamese counterparts and—and other—other groups as well?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yeah. Yes. It was—it was cooperative, and I guess it was dysfunctional—it may have been dysfunctional cooperation [chuckles], I guess.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">But the different question is to whether it was effective.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That’s actually my—my next—my next question, is: Do you believe that the Chiêu Hồi program was successful? And kind of especially this—this policy of sending defectors who—the majority of whom did not defect, because they were big believers in sort of the South Vietnamese cause—sending them back to go to try to recruit more defectors. Did this program seem successful or—or no?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, it certainly was successful statistically because it took fighters off the battlefield, and I don’t know what the statistic was or how many thousands it took off the battlefield, but it did do so. But how permanent, is another question, because it was fairly easy to re-defect. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yeah. Yeah. And you briefly touched on <persName>Nixon</persName> earlier, and <persName>Nixon</persName> was obviously elected while you were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And at the time, what—what was your—your thought on <persName>Nixon</persName>’s election? Earlier, you had said that you weren’t a big fan of <orgName>LBJ</orgName> earlier, so was—was that a—in your mind, was that—was that a good change? You know, looking at it at the time, were you pleased to see that change, and also just in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> what was the sentiment around <orgName>LBJ</orgName> going out and <persName>Nixon</persName> coming in?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Okay. Well, personally I voted for <persName>Humphrey</persName>. And as I reflect on it, there were not many others who supported <persName>Humphrey</persName> among my colleagues. [Chuckles.] Most of them were for <persName>Nixon</persName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And you were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> for <date>almost year</date> after <persName>Nixon</persName> was inaugurated in <date>January of 1969</date>. Did you see the impact of <persName>Nixon</persName>’s policy on your experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes, absolutely, because suddenly it was no longer how [unintelligible], but the question was, “We’re cutting, and so here’s the support you’re not going to get.” So yes, I did.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And in terms of your ability in <persName>Chiêu Hồi</persName> to go out and effectively run your program and continue to take fighters off of the battlefield, did <persName>Nixon</persName>’s policy of starting to, you know, try to decrease involvement and removing a lot of funding and support—did that—was that detrimental to your—to your program?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, yeah. I think for me personally—just a minute. [Talking to someone else] Goodbye.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Got it. And looking back now, what are—what are your thoughts on <persName>Nixon</persName>’s <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> policy?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Hmm. Well, I think he did a decent job. He got us out of there, since I think it was a mistake to go in there in the first place, at least in this very large, overwhelming way, and so I guess I always admired his policy and the negotiations that <persName>Kissinger</persName> did to get us out of there. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so speaking of—speaking of getting out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you leave <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date>October of 1969</date>, correct?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yeah, <date>October 3rd</date>, to be exact.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><date>October 3rd, 1969</date>. And—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I was there for <date>18 months and three days</date></u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS"><date>Eighteen months and three days</date>. And after <date>those 18 months and three days</date>, what came next? What did you do after <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I came back, and at this time I still thought I wanted to be a Europeanist, so I came back, and I went to work in <orgName>the Department of State</orgName>, on European affairs in <orgName>the Bureau of Intelligence and Research</orgName>. And I followed French and Belgian affairs, sort of from something that was a hot topic to something that wasn’t.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And I know you were—you mentioned that you were still opposed to the war, and actually wrote—what was it a letter along with a couple of other <orgName>Foreign Service</orgName> officers in opposition to certain elements of <persName>Nixon</persName>’s policy?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, yes. This regards the incursion into <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>. And I thought this was a mistake. I had just been back in <placeName>the United States</placeName>, I don’t know, <date>a few months</date>, <date>a few weeks</date>, and I went out on a lunch break to walk around the building, where I was accosted by someone who asked me to sign a petition saying that the incursion into <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> was a mistake. And I did so, and before <date>the end of the day</date>, there were headlines that said, “<orgName>Foreign Service Officers</orgName> Oppose <persName>Nixon</persName>’s Cambodia Policy.” </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yeah. And while, you know, you didn’t get fired from your job for signing this petition, were there repercussions?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I don’t think so. You never know for sure. And <date>sometime later</date>, a good friend of mine was in personnel, and he found these materials in my file, and he said, “I’ll fix the problem for you.” I think he just took them out.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">All right! [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Oh, yes.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So what is the story there?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I had been back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and I was living with some friends near Dupont Circle in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, and <orgName>Dupont Circle</orgName> at that time was the rallying point for the protests. And I remember going there on two occasions in particular: once, thinking, as you hear very broad slogans, “No, no, I won’t go” and so on and so forth,” thinking, You know, the situation is much more complex than that and thinking, you know, there are many more shades of gray and so on and so forth.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That’s wild. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I wanted to sort of say that when I was flying back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and I was thinking about, What does all this mean?—I mentioned <persName>Robert Frost</persName> earlier. And he has written a poem called “Into My Own,” and one of the lines, a couple of lines are that “They would not find me changed from him they knew— Only more sure of all I thought was true.” It seems a little arrogant to say that this stage (or maybe at that stage), but I did feel that. I fell into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I had had a chance to observe it first hand. I still thought it was a mistake, but it was a much more complicated mistake than I thought it was. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yes, I can imagine.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, I guess I identified as part of the government, and I—to some extent, as well as having some sympathy with the protesters, and well, I guess I drew personal lessons. I would not want to join protesters who were inclined to violence or to attract attack, and I have to say, later in my life I’ve been involved with other social movements. We have a GLBT [gay, lesbian, bisexual, transgender] son, a transgender son, so I’ve been very active in gay rights things. So it’s not social movements in general but certainly those that have a violent tinge—it has a whole different set of issues that you have to think very carefully about them.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And so it sounds like you’re a little bit—I don’t want to put words in your mouth, but are you—are you conflicted on the---the antiwar movement? Because obviously it’s—it’s a—you know, just like the experience in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, the antiwar movement is—is complicated, and it sounds like you sympathized with some but with others, you know, when it comes to sort of the more violent elements of it, you’re in opposition.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I think basically <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was a mistake, and I—I guess I intellectually appreciate that it was the antiwar movement that produced, in large part, the changes. But, on the other hand, I’m not quite a law-and-order person, but I have an appreciation that these are very complex problems. I’m sort of rambling here because I’m not quite sure what I’m saying. But the point is, I personally did not feel comfortable being involved with violent and riotous behavior.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">That certainly makes sense. I don’t think I would be, either.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Sure.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So you spent your career in international relations.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">And what experience or what impact do you think <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> had on—on you? What lasting impact?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, first, I learned first hand about war. And secondly, I learned first hand about the military. And it engendered certain ideas also about the whole concept of the use of force. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Oh, speaking of <placeName>the Middle East</placeName>, do you see lessons from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> as being relevant to current <placeName>Middle East</placeName> policy?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">That’s a good question, and it’s something that <orgName>I’m</orgName> now thinking about, not exactly in those terms, but what is the utility of the so-called military [phone rings] instrument. Just a moment, please.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure. It’s probably somebody asking me, giving me a free trip to <placeName>Caribbean</placeName> or something or other. Anyway. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">And in <placeName>Syria</placeName> we neither invaded nor occupied, and it was a costly disaster.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Maybe that’s just circumstances. A prudent policy is to be on the sidelines and try to nudge things in the right direction. So—I’ve just written a piece called “<placeName>The Middle East</placeName> and the <date>2016</date> [Presidential] Elections,” and what I hope will happen is we will have sort of a grand strategy discussion of the use of the military instrument in <placeName>U.S.</placeName> foreign policy but particularly <placeName>the Middle East</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yes, it was.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, first of all, my wife and I—we both felt sincerely welcomed. We visited schools, and children would sing songs to welcome us. And Vietnamese cuisine has already, of course, intruded deeply into American table, and so that, of course, was good. But most—there were two—really three startling things, or observations.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Fortunately. And then, secondly, there was the misconception of <persName>Johnson</persName> that somehow we would defeat <placeName>China</placeName> and its ambitions in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And I think that’s, would be hard to support.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Well, thank you for giving me your—your thoughts on that. And is there—are there any other topics, like, that you would—that you—that you would like to cover or any elements of your story that you feel like were missing?</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Not about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I thought I might provide a little side light as to how I became an <placeName>Arabist</placeName> after <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and then being a Europeanist.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Sure.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, this happened because <persName>Henry Kissinger</persName> at this point was secretary of state, and he came up with the policy of globalization, which had an entirely different meaning than what we think of <date>today</date>. And here, it was a technical term that means that if you had two tours in one area, you should have a tour outside of that so you can develop at least two specialties. </u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Very interesting. Well, if there’s a region in the world that’s a particularly interesting one to study, the—<placeName>the Middle East</placeName> is certainly up there.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yeah. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I’m actually reading—reading a book right now. I don’t know if you know it. It’s called <placeName>Lawrence</placeName> in <placeName>Arabia</placeName> [:War, Deceit, Imperial Folly and the Making of the Modern <placeName>Middle East</placeName>].</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Oh, I loved it! I just loved it. I thought it’s one of the best books that’s been written recently.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I’m making my way through. I’m probably 150 pages into it at this point, and it’s fascinating. I love it. I don’t get as much opportunity to just, you know, sit down with a good book and read as I would like, but it’s—it’s—maybe after I finish it, I can—I can give you a call and [chuckles]—and hear your thoughts on it.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Sure. Yeah. Well, I thought it was excellent, and I have read quite a bit about [British soldier <persName>T. E.] Lawrence</persName> and the [Seven] Pillars of Wisdom and so on. I recently watched [the movie] <persName>Lawrence</persName> of <placeName>Arabia</placeName> again. When you consider that he was a short man, and blond and not particularly athletic, to see him portrayed as a six-foot-three or –four blond person who is athletic—should we say, the body, the stereotype isn’t right, but the film was good. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Well, a little <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> magic.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes, exactly. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, good. I will be coming to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for the 50th reunion in <date>June</date>, but I suspect you’ll be gone then. But let’s do remain in touch. I’d like to hear—well, for example, do <orgName>the Green Weenies</orgName> and the Big Greeners still exist in some sort of form?</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I—I would say it’s probably not quite as—as clear cut as it was,—</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">I see.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">—as it was in <date>your day</date>, but a little bit.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Well, you have—you have women to—to mediate this image a little bit. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Yes,  yes. [Laughs.] I imagine, certainly from that regard, it’s—it’s a very different place than it used to be. </u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Yes, exactly. So anyway—and I know liquor is a problem, and the college is doing quite a bit to change the—the culture, but do you think that’s effective?</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I think—I think in some regards it is. I think it’s probably not quite as effective as the college would like, but I think it’s certainly more effective than doing nothing.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Right.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">So—yeah, I think—I think [<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> President <persName>Philip J.] Hanlon</persName> [Class of <date>1977</date>] is doing a lot.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Okay. Well, thanks for your time, and I look forward to the results, and I hope that it isn’t completely inarticulate.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">I—I—I think it’ll be great.</u>
      <u who="KEISWETTER">Okay. <persName>Goodbye</persName>. Thank you very much.</u>
      <u who="CAROTHERS">Bye. Thanks have a good one. </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
