<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="PEARL"/>
        <person xml:id="MEYERCORD"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="PEARL"><date>Today</date> is <date>February 27th, 2016</date>. I am <persName>Josh Pearl</persName> conducting an interview for <orgName>the Dartmouth Vietnam Project</orgName>. Today I’m interviewing [<persName>Kenneth F.]</persName> “<persName>Ken” Meyercord</persName> [pronouncing it MAY-er-cord]. The interview is being conducted by phone from <persName>Rauner</persName> [<orgName>Special Collections] Library</orgName>, <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, and <persName>Ken</persName> is on his phone in <placeName>Reston</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">That’s correct, except it’s MY-er-cord.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">MY-er-cord. Sorry about that. And, <persName>Ken</persName>, can you tell me where and when you were born?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">The year I was born?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah, when and where.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">When and where. <date>June 15th, 1944</date>, in <placeName>Madison</placeName>, <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about your childhood?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I spent <date>my first ten years</date> in <placeName>Madison</placeName>, which back then was a lovely little town, sort of like <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, I’ve always wanted to get back to. Never have. I mean get back to the same ambiance. Then we moved down to <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and I lived there through high school, then went off to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. And that really led to <placeName>Texas</placeName> again, I have some? family down there.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">All right. And can you tell me about your family?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah. I’m one of seven: five boys and two girls. My father went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, Class of <date>’27</date>. My mother was from <placeName>Texas</placeName>. And three of my brothers went to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> as well, Class of—let’s see, <persName>David</persName> [<persName>K. Meyercord</persName>] was Class of ’69; [<persName>Andrew N.]</persName> “<persName>Andy</persName>,” Class of ’71; and <persName>Philip</persName> [L.] would be Class of <date>’72</date>, though he dropped out after a year or two.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah, talk about your family.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, yeah. When I was eight—that’s what occasioned—I moved down to <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">You want to know my current family?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah, sure.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Okay. Well, that’s a long story. I don’t know whether you read my book, Draft-Dodging Odyssey.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">I did read your memoir.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Good. Then you know that I met my wife in <placeName>Beirut</placeName> [<placeName>Lebanon</placeName>] when I was on my odyssey, and we came back to the <placeName>States</placeName> in <date>1975</date>, having lived in <placeName>Algeria</placeName> for <date>a year and a half</date> after <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>, where our two kids, <persName>Khaldun</persName> [Meyercord] and <persName>Nadia</persName> [<persName>Meyercord</persName>] were born. And we lived in <placeName>Texas</placeName> briefly, then moved up to the <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, area, where we have been living ever since. Our kids are now grown up. One is teaching in <placeName>Florida</placeName>, and we’re not really sure where the other one is.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about your parents’ occupations, what they did in <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName> and then I guess in <placeName>Texas</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">You mean <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL"><placeName>New Jersey</placeName> </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD"><placeName>Jersey</placeName>, yeah. My dad worked for <orgName>Western Electric</orgName>. He was a classic <date>1950s</date> commuter, taking the [Erie] Lackawanna Railroad [now Erie Lackawanna Railway] into <placeName>Manhattan</placeName> <date>every day</date>. And my mother was a housewife, you can imagine, with seven kids, though she did have a career initially as a writer and editor in her own right. Had a piece, a fiction piece, published in The Saturday Evening Post, which those of your generation only read about in your history book, but it was, along with <orgName>LIFE</orgName> magazine, one of the two most popular <date>weekly</date> periodicals in the country back then.</u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And can you tell me more about the neighborhoods you grew up in?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, like I say, <persName>Madison</persName>, <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>, was a classic little town. We lived in a big old house with a big old porch and lots of places for kids to have adventures: woods and a big yard and that sort of thing, and walked to school, knew the people in the neighborhood, unlike [chuckles] some of the suburbs we’ve lived in since.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Excuse me?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—life growing up as a child—can you tell me about growing up in <name type="event">the Cold War</name>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">[Chuckles.] Well, my first current event memory—and I think it’s a memory and not just something I heard about—was the end of <name type="event">the Korean War</name> in <date>1953</date>. I can’t think of anything prior to that. And, of course [laughs], you—your generation has probably seen film footage of how we would have air raid drills every once in a while in school, where we all got under our desks. Supposedly that would protect us from atomic attack from <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">What else about <name type="event">the Cold War</name>?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Do you remember anything—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I was not—I was not a political type. I didn’t follow—I didn’t read TIME mag- —what was it back then—were—<orgName>Newsweek</orgName> and TIME, yeah, I guess, were what people read back there. Of course, a couple of people got <orgName>The New York Times</orgName> on <date>Sundays</date>, and we’d all line up for a chance not to read the political news but to see the bra ads. Pretty tame stuff by <date>today</date>’s standards, but that was pretty exciting for us. It was all guys up there.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Do you know anything about—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I think	I was not unusual in not—not really being attuned to what was going on in the world as far as typical <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> guy back in <date>’66</date>. I was surprised in <date>just a couple of years</date> after I graduated, the school became much more politically active. [<placeName>Alabama</placeName> Governor] George [C.] Wallace [Jr.] was kicked off campus or something.</u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Which was later. So—all right. Interest in and involvement in current events was really low start. Well [chuckles], there was one thing that came up. Senior year, I applied for a <orgName>Fulbright</orgName> scholarship (of the <orgName>Fulbright</orgName> U.S. Student Program], and I remember at the interview, the last question, “And how do you plan on fulfilling your military obligation? You guys have heard of the draft.” And that’s how they put it back then: “fulfilling your military obligation,” <date>two years</date>. And I said, “I don’t if can help it,” being very naïve and simply expressing what was the common through around the dorm, at least with the crowd I hung out with. And I didn’t get the scholarship, strangely enough, despite one of the interviewees telling me how impressed the were with me. It never occurred to me who provides the <orgName>Fulbright</orgName> scholarship, which of course is the <placeName>United States</placeName> government, which probably didn’t look favorably at my answer to that last question.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me about—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Where are we getting?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">I was hoping we could go back to <placeName>Texas</placeName> and you can tell me about going to high school in <placeName>Texas</placeName> and how that was.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah. Okay. [Laughs.] Wow! That’s a—okay, you wanted to know about <name type="event">the Cold War</name>. Like I say, I’m trying to think of how it—other than crawling under our desks a couple of times a year—I’m trying to think of how <name type="event">the Cold War</name>—what happened to it before—in that late period. Well, the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Marines invaded <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> in <date>1958</date>, because there was a commotion in the Arab world, which of course was blamed on <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me more about the racial makeup or I guess the racial politics of your neighborhood in <placeName>Dallas</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, yeah, sure, yeah. It was a hoity-toity neighborhood, nice suburban homes, and homes in <placeName>Dallas</placeName>—boy, they’re really nice, and not expensive still. I was just down there <date>a couple of weeks ago</date>, and it’s just a pleasure to drive around north <placeName>Dallas</placeName> and see these beautiful homes and compare it to the home prices up here in the <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, area.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">[No audible response.]</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So can you talk about him?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Not even at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. [Laughs.] No, definitely not in high school, and only vaguely at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">No, and I wasn’t—you know, by <date>late ’64</date>, there were even from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, certainly from <orgName>the Ivy League</orgName>, going down to <placeName>Mississippi</placeName> and <placeName>Alabama</placeName>, trying to register blacks to vote, and occasionally getting killed doing it, but not me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So how did you come to end up at school at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? Why <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">My dad went there. Well, my older siblings, of which there are three—I’m in the middle—had all gone to <orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName> right there in <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, just a few miles from our house, so I assumed I was headed there, till my mother suggestion I apply to my dad’s alma mater. <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> hadn’t really figured much in my existence up till then. Occasionally, my mother would get visits from my father’s classmates who were passing through town on business, but we never visited <persName>Hanover</persName> even—I don’t remember—even when we lived in <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>. So it was—it was not really something in my mind or something I had much experience with. But I’m glad she recommended it.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So can you tell me about your—your <date>first year</date> on campus, as a freshman?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah. Okay. A typical freshman year, I guess. I hear you don’t wear beanies anymore. You know, freshmen had to wear beanies, and they’d get pulled off our heads by the upperclassmen. And there must have been some—some sort of events, maybe competitions with the sophomores or something, though I don’t remember them. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me how campus compared to—to <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, the student body?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, like I said—I had probably—what would it be? Well, my high school was <date>only three years</date>, yet there were 2,000 students in it, so it was certainly different for me, coming from a public school, than for those guys coming from a prep school, I’m sure. But let’s see, the all-boy aspect, or bad aspect was not that different [chuckles] for me, except I didn’t date much in high school. It was different because you didn’t have any girls around. But I wasn’t into dating, anyway, well, at that time. That didn’t matter too much.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me about social life on campus?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I didn’t do much socializing, myself. I was studying hard, got some very good grades. And there was intramural sports. I probably played with that for advanced course math. You know, I suppose it’s the same <date>today</date>, that you can’t join a fraternity <date>till sophomore year</date>. I didn’t have a date—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you join any clubs at all?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Did I do what?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Join any clubs or fraternities?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Oh, no. God, no! I don’t know whether we were even allowed in fraternity parties back then. Like I say, you couldn’t be in a fraternity until <date>sophomore year</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So, I guess, what <date>about your years</date> as an upperclassman?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I eventually joined <orgName>Kappa Sigma</orgName> [now <orgName>Chi Gamma Epsilon</orgName>], what was called <orgName>Kappa Sigma</orgName> back then, right there on <orgName>Fraternity Row</orgName> [on Webster Avenue in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>] my junior year. I didn’t—<placeName>didn’t</placeName> rush <date>sophomore year</date>. I was so unsociable, that didn’t really appeal to me, but a couple of guys right across the hall that I respected a lot at <placeName>North Mass</placeName> joined <orgName>Kappa Sigma</orgName>, so I did join a fraternity junior year, but I never got—you know, I went to the parties and whatnot, but  I wasn’t a big part of the fraternity scene.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Were you part of <orgName>ROTC [Reserve Officers’</orgName> Training Corps] at all?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Was I what?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Part of <placeName>ROTC</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">No. I was aware it existed, I guess, but I can’t think of anybody I knew who was actually in it. Maybe a guy named [<persName>William B.]</persName> “Bill” Hayden [Class of 1966], who eventually became an admiral in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, commanded a nuclear aircraft carrier. I can’t [chuckles] think of anyone else who was—and I really don’t know what <orgName>ROTC</orgName> was like at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> back then. In fact, I can’t say for sure we had it, but I’m pretty sure we did.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Was there any ever discussion of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> on campus while you were there?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">No, no, the whole <date>four years</date> I was there—I’m sure there must have been some disc- —we all know what the discussion was: How are you going to get out of the draft, pretty much. But as far as talking about what the war was all about and where <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was and stuff like that, I just don’t remember. There must have been some, but I can’t remember that we paid any attention to it other than trying to figure out what we were going to do with regard to the draft.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what did you think you were going to do about the draft?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I didn’t—I was going to—I went to <orgName>the Stanford Business School</orgName> [sic; <orgName>Stanford Graduate School of Business</orgName>] after <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so I still had my student deferment, so I hadn’t really thought about it. I knew I had <date>at least two years</date> of deferment. Back then, you could get married and have a kid and get out of the draft, which some of my classmates did. I don’t mean to say they did that to avoid the draft, not like [former Vice President <persName>Richard Bruce</persName>] “<persName>Dick</persName>” <persName>Cheney</persName>. But that did qualify you for a deferment.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, I was applying to go to <placeName>Australia</placeName> and [chuckles]—typical of how dedicated I was and can be to things, it wasn’t that there was some particular—I wanted to pursue study in history, particularly economic history, and some Australian university had something of remote interest, but I just wanted to go to <placeName>Australia</placeName>, basically. But that didn’t happen. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about attending <orgName>Stanford</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, that was—that was a transition. Once again, I picked <orgName>Stanford</orgName> just because I thought I’d like to live on <placeName>the West Coast</placeName> for a little while. I mean, obviously it’s a good school. I probably could have gotten into <orgName>Harvard Business School</orgName>, but I just wanted a change of coast. And also I had a friend out there, who I lived with, a friend from <placeName>Dallas</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you--</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, so it was all [banging noise] it ended up with my, and with my draft deferment ending, all of a sudden I had to think about what I was going--how I was going to fulfill my military obligation.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you become more politically active or involved while at <orgName>Stanford</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">No, no, I was an observer. That’s sort of the story of my life. I’m an observer, not a participant or an activist. No, I didn’t—I didn’t get involved in the demonstrations, the antiwar stuff <persName>or—[Laughs</persName>.] There weren’t too many people in the business school who who were into that in <date>1966</date>, at least that I was aware of.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So what did you think of the demonstrations and activism that you saw?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I don’t remember even seeing any. There must have been some on the <orgName>Stanford</orgName> campus, but I was living up at the hills. And, you know, pretty much all I saw on the campus was the business school and that was it, and then back up into the hills and--and--I can’t think of anything. Like I say, I was aware of <persName>David Harris</persName>, but the whole--other than the drug scene, which the guys I was living with were into, I don’t--I don’t remember anything.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, like I say—well, I was in the top third of my class, but my grades went down in the course of <date>a year</date>, to the <date>three-quarters</date>, and so I think they may have offered me a partial scholarship or something, but, like I say, I sort of lost interest in business school, and business, I guess. I don’t know, it was sort of a stupid decision.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what prompted you to drop out, I guess, then? What did you decide to do? What did you think you were going to do afterwards?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Maybe one of the things that prompted me to drop out: I knew my--the guy I was living with, a rich guy from <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, was--had gotten married <date>that summer</date>, and he decided that he and his wife would drive <orgName>the Pan-American Highway</orgName> all the way from <placeName>Dallas</placeName> down—not to <placeName>Punta Arenas</placeName> [<placeName>Chile</placeName>] but down in <placeName>Chile</placeName>, anyway. And he invited me to come along, the newlywed. Strange, but we knew each other. We’d all lived together in <placeName>Stanford</placeName>, so I guess it wasn’t that unusual.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So can you tell me about traveling to <placeName>South America</placeName> with your friend?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Oh, I wrote a whole book about it, as you know.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">It was great. We experienced—my buddy and his wife would—money is no object. [Chuckles.] We were driving a <orgName>Chevrolet</orgName> station wagon that he had had an iron plate put on the bottom of to protect us from the bumps in the road. I mean [chuckles], it was totally inappropriate to once you got past <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, as far as the conditions of the roads [laughs] you were driving on. It just lowered the car instead of protected the engine.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So I guess when did you start learning about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, in <placeName>South America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, yeah. You know, here, I was going to face the draft in <date>a couple of months</date>, and I—I mention in my book that on the way out of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, we stopped at <orgName>the University of Texas</orgName>. Had a party there. A young lady—some young lady asked me what I thought of beautiful, and I said, “Viet-what?” because [chuckles] that’s about as far as I’d gotten in my—I was being facetious, of course, but I really hadn’t gotten into the issue, even—even at that point. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yes.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Okay. Yeah, I guess if you’re on this project, you probably would be. Anyway, that was small time compared to what was happening in <placeName>Latin America</placeName>. And these kids—they knew their history, and they knew what we were up to down there. I don’t think—and actually there’s an interesting sidelight: You know that when—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what did you think of these new ideas and what these student activists and demonstrators were doing?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">No, I’ve always had an open mind, I think. I like to think so. So a lot of—I know—actually, now that I think about it, when I went to <placeName>Brazil</placeName> in <date>1961</date>, <date>the summer</date> of ’61, I was one of three American kids in this little town in southern <placeName>Brazil</placeName>. And I guess the Brazilians, the young people that we hung out with gave us an earful, too, but I was mostly interested in the young ladies, so I wasn’t paying much attention. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Fifty-four.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD"><date>Fifty-six</date>, fifty-four. You probably know that. And ending up with the same allies, the affluent bourgeoisie and whatnot as—as the French had used or had used to maintain their colonial rule. And the same enemy. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">There was this poor—very poor country fighting off the strongest military power the world had ever seen, by any means possible—to believe they were all brainwashed by the communists really how they were fighting for their country. If Americans knew that, they probably fighting with them instead of against them.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about <persName>Maria Innes</persName> that you met in <placeName>South America</placeName> and some of the stuff you learned from her?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">What?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">In your book you mentioned a woman named <persName>Maria Innes</persName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Oh, yeah, <persName>Maria Innes</persName>. When I got to <placeName>Rio</placeName>, I got a job within <date>a couple of days</date>, teaching English at a bi-national center down there. These are all over the world. Some of them were set up by the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> government; some of them were just private. This one I think was part of <orgName>USIS</orgName>, which no longer exists, <orgName>United States Information Service</orgName>. And they would set up these bi-national centers of basically libraries and other things in major cities around the world. And so I was teaching English there, and she was one of my students. You had regular university classes, and English was a complement to that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what did you believe—what did you come to believe that the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>’s role should have been in these countries?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, it should have been what we say it is [chuckles]—you know, <orgName>USAID</orgName> [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Agency for International Development. There was one guy I remember well, counselor to the president, <persName>Eugene</persName> [V.] Rostow. I think it was <persName>Eugene</persName>. There were two brothers, <persName>Eugene</persName> and <persName>Walt</persName> [W.], one of them [<persName>Walt W.]</persName> who wrote a book called The Stages of Economic Growth[: A Non-Communist Manifesto], in which he postulated the stages that every country goes through and that the Third World countries would go through as they progressed towards an American lifestyle and living standard. It was bullshit. [Laughs.] [Both chuckle.] It was such simplistic—but it was best-seller, and, you know, <orgName>the World Bank</orgName> was repeating. What’s <orgName>the World Bank</orgName> there for except to end poverty in our time?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what did your family think about—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">True <date>today</date>. Hasn’t changed.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What was that?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Excuse me?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">I interrupted you when you said the last stuff.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, I said it’s true <date>today</date>. Our policy hasn’t changed.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what did your family think about you traveling across <placeName>South America</placeName>, not notifying your draft board?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, that’s—that’s an interesting question. My mother died <date>the summer</date> before I went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, entered <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so I had four brothers and two sisters and an aunt as my immediate family in <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, and my oldest—my next youngest—next oldest brother [chuckles]—first youngest brother was at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> by the time I—I went abroad. And he eventually actually dropped out I think his junior year and went in the <orgName>Army</orgName>, did his service in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and then went back to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and graduated.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you know that you’d be indicted, or did you think that it would just go away after a while?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Oh, no. I assumed it was serious stuff. And I by that time—when I left <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, I would say I had committed—you know, I definitely—while I was in <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, I had committed to not being drafted, not going into the—not serving. I’d like to say it was some idealistic stand, even patriotic I like to say that it was that I was taking, but it was certainly—fortunately, history has absolved me, in a sense, in that as things worked out, I think a lot of people came to que- —not only question but condemn what we were doing in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. You know, draft evasion is not a good charge to have against you. I’m not worried about the cowardice angle. I don’t know if it took much character to let yourself be drafted, and until you got in combat, you didn’t realize, Hey, this stuff is really serious. But a lot of people, I think—I didn’t even think about—I don’t think I thought about that aspect much, myself.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">What?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">When you were at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, you didn’t want to serve in the military. You didn’t want to do the draft. So why didn’t you want to serve at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">At <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, I didn’t think about it much, because I had my 2-S, and I didn’t know what the war was all about. No, I didn’t—I didn’t really give much—well, I gave some thought to it out at <orgName>Stanford</orgName> because out there they were so active about it, but I hadn’t—I really hadn’t—when I left the country in <date>November 1967</date>, I had not decided that I would not serve in the military, by any means. I would just—I figured I had <date>a couple of months</date> and that this traveling was a rare opportunity with my friend, and so I was going to do that, and I’d make—make that decision later on.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">And I did make that decision in <date>the eight months</date> I spent in <placeName>Rio</placeName>, somewhere along the line there, when I was drafted and was in big trouble if I didn’t go home immediately. I decided I wasn’t going to—and, of course, by then—what are we talking? We’re talking about ’68. You know, by then, it looks like the war couldn’t go on much longer. It had gone on for—well, depending on when you say the starting gun went off, but <date>at least three years</date>, <date>four years</date>. Massive demonstrations against the war. We were [unintelligible] the Tet Offensive did not convince anyone that the end was in sight.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what did you think of your brother serving in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I was concerned about that. I’m not surprised. Well, let’s talk about my next brother, <persName>David</persName>, because he’s the type of guy that responds to the call of duty and is very conventional in his outlook and his knowledge. I was a little surprised that he dropped out of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> to go into the military, and I still don’t understand what that was all about. But I’m not surprised he served. I knew he would serve well. But, you know, I thought, What is not only my family but everybody else going to think if one of my brothers is killed in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> while I’m gallivanting around the world?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What about your brother <persName>Andy</persName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">At least physically they were all right. My brother <persName>Andy</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Asked?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yes, about <persName>Andy</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, he got a deferment. I’m not sure what the basis of the deferment was. I think it was [chuckles]—you know, you [chuckles]—not everybody, but a lot of us, including myself, were trying to finagle the draft. I had one—my brother-in-law’s brother, who was a star athlete in college—when he went in for his physical for the draft, he—he ate a bunch of chocolate the night before so his blood sugar was—it looked like he was diabetic, and that got him a 4-F. There were [chuckles]—I forget what the basis of <persName>Andy</persName>’s deferment, but he managed not to be drafted, and he just went to law school and got married. Maybe the marriage helped him out. I don’t know.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what prompted you to continue traveling after <placeName>South America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I decided that I loved it, I was learning a hell of a lot, it was a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity, and if I wasn’t—I knew going back to the <placeName>States</placeName> was out of the question, if I really was intent on not serving in the military. And I had—just had the opportunity and had the interest, so I just continued. I decided in <placeName>Brazil</placeName>, I’d go around the world, which I eventually do. Not quite the way I planned it, but pretty close.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Going back, can you tell me why you originally went to—to <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> from <placeName>South America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">How I got from <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> to <placeName>South America</placeName>, back to <placeName>South America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">No, no, why did you originally—why did you originally go to <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> as your first stop after—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, like I say, in <placeName>Beirut</placeName>—I worked there for <date>eight months</date>, and I decided I wanted to go around the world, so I got on a boat to <placeName>Spain</placeName> and from <placeName>Spain</placeName> hitchhiked across <placeName>North Africa</placeName> to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, [Chuckles.] I was so out of it! Like I say, I was headed for <placeName>Israel</placeName>. I figured I had enough money to get to <placeName>Israel</placeName>, and I could—I now found out that it wasn’t very hard to get a job, at least teaching English, anywheres in the world, so I didn’t worry too much about employment. I figured I’d get by all right.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what were you teaching at the university?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I didn’t teach at the university at that time. I did when I first was there. I got a job teaching English at another one of these bi-national centers.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Like I say, they’re all over the world, okay? [Chuckles.] If you had a college degree and were a native English speaker, you could get a job there. And because I had a college degree from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, which people were impressed with, I would get to teach the highest level courses, which were basically like using the textbook from your junior year in high school American literature course or something like that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I headed off across <placeName>North Afr-</placeName> —across <placeName>South Asia</placeName>, <placeName>Turkey</placeName> and <placeName>Iran</placeName>, under the shah, <placeName>Kuwait</placeName>, <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> before king at that time and where hashish was sold by the government. [Laughs.] It was legal in Afghani- —I still wasn’t—I never have done—I mean, obviously I’ve smoked marijuana. Everybody did back then. I never inhaled. Maybe that’s why I didn’t get addicted to it or have much of a positive experience of it. I was drinking. I forget when I started to drink. And even—I learned to smoke when I was about 25 in <placeName>Turkey</placeName>, where the cigarettes are extremely mild. That was one of the biggest mistakes in my life, never picking up a cigarette. Drink, I don’t mind so much, or think was a mistake.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">No.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD"><persName>L-e-h-r-e-r</persName>? And when he retired from the satire, political satire business, they asked him why, and he said, “Well, political satire ended <date>the day</date> that the Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to <persName>Henry Kissinger</persName>.” Which is a pretty good line. [Chuckles.] And very accurate. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">So, yes, why don’t you—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">So anyway, so I stopped at all these places: <placeName>Japan</placeName>, <placeName>Hong Kong</placeName>, <placeName>Taiwan</placeName> on my way to [chuckles]—it was interesting: When I got to Can- —when—there was a layover in <placeName>Vancouver</placeName>, and I called home! It was ten cents back then [chuckles] to make a pay telephone call. And I called home, talked to my aunt in <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, but I couldn’t—fortunately, there was—I couldn’t book my flight that would stop in <placeName>the United States</placeName> [chuckles], so I was going from <placeName>Canada</placeName> to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, nonstop. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">So I guess—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Excuse me?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">I was going to ask how you felt about touring <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> while in reality you should have been touring <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> next door, I guess.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, yeah! Well, let’s see, my brother just—I think my brother—I’m not sure whether my brother—I don’t think my brother <persName>David</persName> had gotten there yet. That would have been—so I didn’t—I didn’t really think too much of it, except by then I was, you know, very interesting in what was going on over there, so I was glad I was at least able to get as close as <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>. But I don’t remember anything political in <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> at that time. It was <date>just a year</date> before we started our—our secret bombing.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And then you said you went to <placeName>Vancouver</placeName>. Did you ever consider doing landed immigrant status, like many other draft evaders did?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">No, no, I never did consider that. I never did consider that, probably because I had a typical American attitude of <placeName>Canada</placeName> as the Great White North. [Laughs.] And even though I enjoyed the Great White North in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, somehow <placeName>Toronto</placeName> just couldn’t compare with <placeName>Rio de Janeiro</placeName> and <placeName>Brazil</placeName> and—I mean <placeName>Beirut</placeName> and places like that. I didn’t see any reason why I should—because once I had my passport, I’d rather be traveling than stuck in <placeName>Canada</placeName>. So I never even considered that.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">So did you plan to continue traveling until the war had ended?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So let’s go back to <placeName>Colombia</placeName>. What type of work were you doing there for your friend’s dad?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">The father of my friend, who at this time, interestingly enough, was a <placeName>United States</placeName> congressman, and he’s hiring a draft dodger to be—to help his son-in-law out. His son-in-law was the president of this company and was living down there. His wife I’d known since grade school, the sister of my friend from <placeName>Dallas</placeName>. And I was supposedly—the idea—those who know, after <date>a year</date> or two I would take over as president of this comp- — or directing this company, and they’d go back to the <placeName>States</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Good.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah. So I go back to <placeName>Beirut</placeName>, and I get in the master’s degree program in history. Like I say, <placeName>Beirut</placeName> was a wonderful city—the university is accredited by <placeName>New York State</placeName>. Founded by Presbyterian missionaries back in the 19- —1860s, just around the time of <name type="event">our Civil War</name>, and had become the predominant educational institution in the entire <placeName>Middle East</placeName>. That is the local universities—what’s the Muslim university in <placeName>Cairo</placeName>? I can’t believe I’ve forgotten the name of it. But, you know, they were teaching the Quran [chuckles] for a while. <persName>AUB</persName> was speaking science and stuff like that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me about your activism in <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>? I know that you got involved in the embassy in some protests.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, that was—yeah, that was when I went back. There was something about—let me think. No, yeah. Well, when [chuckles]—I got back there in <date>September of 1970</date>, and at that time, [the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Congress</orgName> was debating—and by then I was—ever since I visited <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, I was a proponent of the Palestinian cause because what else could you be when you understood—I mean, if you [chuckles]—it’s a little hard for Americans even <date>today</date> to—to have a good conception of what really is going on over there, but, you know, these people are getting pushed off the land, half a million refugees fleeing to other countries and whatnot.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you ever get involved in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> activism while abroad?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I’m sure we had little—we must have done things. You know, most of the Middle Easterners didn’t—that wasn’t they’re going to get out for. I don’t know, there weren’t enough Americans to—to demonstrate or anything. It was mostly just hanging out and, I don’t know, writing maybe articles or something. We didn’t have the Internet so we could get something distributed world wide back then, as it is <date>today</date>. I don’t really remember protests. There just weren’t enough of us to do that. And, you know, the Arabs were busy protesting <placeName>Palestine</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what did you do in <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> once—you know, you’re graduating. I guess your student visa expired, and you didn’t have a passport.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">In <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>? Well, that’s what I say. When I was released from jail because of the notoriety—when my picture—when my story appeared in the newspaper, the prime minister of <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> actually got me released because it looked bad. He didn’t look like he’s just doing this for <placeName>the United States</placeName>, following the orders of <placeName>the United States</placeName>, because what I faced was that’s what would happen—you know, I stayed in jail in <placeName>Lebanon</placeName> or they went me back to <placeName>the United States</placeName>, and they couldn’t do that—they couldn’t—well, I supposed they could have forced me. They could have shot me and dumped me in the river. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">So can you tell me about going to <placeName>Algeria</placeName> and starting your teaching career there?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Excuse me? Oh, could I tell you about it? Well [chuckles], they [chuckles]—oh, boy! Okay. By now I’m married, and my wife is <date>eight months</date> pregnant, my wife of <date>ten months or so</date>. And we land in <placeName>Algeria</placeName>, in <placeName>Algiers</placeName>, middle of the night, and I don’t have a passport. You know, I have this piece of paper from the Algerian ambassador in <placeName>Beirut</placeName>. And Immigration [chuckles] ends up taking us to the local jail, not putting us in jail. My and my <date>eight months</date> pregnant wife, and me not speaking French, or Arabic, she speaking Arabic, and they, not speaking English, so this poor wife, who [chuckles]—I don’t know how she did it—was having to do the translating between the Algerian officials, government officials, security and me. They hadn’t been expecting me, apparently, [chuckles], and they didn’t know quite what to do with me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">—ought to resolve this legal situation I’m in. And that’s why when—when the war officially ended with the collapse of the South Vietnamese government in—you’ve seen the pictures and the people flying off the embassy roof out to ships, American ships in the—off the coast. I figured—and, you know, there was so much—not opposition but just disgust with the whole <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience amongst the American public. I was betting that the courts would be lenient on me if I came back, and I had to get this resolved some way. It couldn't—I didn’t want to—I can’t have this hanging over my head all my life.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did your family, like, come back to you—come back with you to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Oh, my wife and the kids, yeah. Yeah. Sure. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">It was sort of a interesting—you don’t realize how difficult it is for people to get in <placeName>the United States</placeName>. We always—you know, when traveling in <placeName>Iran</placeName>, we would always make fun about how hard it was to get visas to these Third World countries, but it’s the same trying to get into <placeName>the United States</placeName>. I mean, to get my wife a visa proved rather problematic because she was coming as the wife of an American citi- —I’m not sure what kind of visa she came on, now that I think about it. I think it was a permanent residency visa. But they could have easily denied her a visa. They didn’t.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what did you think in <date>1973</date> when you heard that the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> had left <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I thought it was long overdue, but—yeah, I thought it was long overdue, but I guess I—why didn’t I come home at that time? I guess because we were still deeply involved, even if our troops weren’t there, not on a mass scale like it had been. But it was really the fall of the South Vietnamese government that was the seminal event or the life-changing event, or the official end of the war. We were still—I mean, we bombed—we were, like I say, carpet bombing <placeName>Haiphong</placeName> and <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> into <date>1973</date>. It was <date>Christmas 1972</date>, so even though our troops were not there, we were still actively involved.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well [chuckles], you either—I think it’s a binary thing. You’re either an internationalist or a nationalist. In other words, you either accept that the world is divided up into these nation states—and, you know, we all recognize that it hasn’t always been nation states; it’s been empires and monarchies and tribes and all sorts of different entities, city states, that people have recognized themselves as citizens of. And, you know, <date>today</date> and for <date>the last couple of hundred years</date>, it’s been the nation state that has been the political entity that has been recognized by people and by the various nation states as the—as an appropriate political entity for people to—to be citizens of and—and have duties towards and be loyal towards.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So did you see yourself as an American citizen while you were abroad?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I can’t help but—you know, this is the world we live in. You’re a citizen of a country or—I was pretty close not to [be] a citizen of any country in terms of my legal status, since I didn’t have a passport, but I am—yeah, I’m forced to be a citizen of a country or—you don’t want to live like a stateless Palestinian. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">And, you know, it’s—it’s a knotty question, obviously, but who do I owe loyalties to? Who do I have duties to? Lately it’s to <placeName>the United States</placeName>. My mind is [banging noise] not—my loyalty to <placeName>the United States</placeName> is in fact [banging noise] owing to policy, which is for all mankind, but I—our leaders are almost fiduciary—have an almost fiduciary responsibility to promote the interests of the American people, not the people of the world.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And when you came back to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, how was your transition and your wife’s transition and your children’s transition back to American culture and American event?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Oh, the kids were just half a year and a year and a half, so there wasn’t any tradition other than my son getting confused because he knew he was born in <placeName>Africa</placeName> and he wondered why he wasn’t black.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Was there any ill will towards you for not serving, or—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, it was interesting. There was ill will, but I can remember my brother-in-law’s brother-in-law, who was a minister, praising me personally, you know, in a conversation for having taken the stand I did. And there were—certainly, you know, in the antiwar crowd, it was sort of heroic status to have resisted the draft. Just with that crowd. I’m not suggesting it was a prevailing opinion in <placeName>the United States</placeName>. But there were enough people who—there were certainly plenty to condemn my actions, in my own family, even.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yes, so—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">It would come up with regard to that. You know—but I don’t—in the end—you know, after <date>six months or so</date>, <date>a year</date> in <placeName>Dallas</placeName>, I moved up to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, hoping to get a job in international affairs, because that was now my passion. And I did. At an international center sort of affiliated to [sic] the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> government. And I don’t know whether they knew my history, other than what they saw on my résumé, which didn’t mention why I was abroad for so long. But I was able to work there for <date>three years</date>. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what type of career did you end up—what kind of job did you end up working in?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, I should have said I wouldn’t be hired by corporate <placeName>America</placeName> to work overseas. I ended up doing computer stuff for a megacorporation. Actually, my wife got a job as a translator on a big project for <placeName>Saudi Arabia</placeName>, a computer project. And through her, I got a job teaching English to some Saudi trainees coming over, who were going to learn programming and would be maintaining the system, theoretically, once it had been implemented. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">No.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">It was the company which broke AT&amp;amp;T’s monopoly on long distance telephone calls. Started out of <placeName>St. Louis</placeName>, and they just wanted to be able to talk to their truckers between <placeName>St. Louis</placeName> and <placeName>Chicago</placeName>, and AT&amp;amp;T said, “No, you can’t do this. You’re violating our monopoly.” They took it to court. They won. And they became—you know, they were the predecessor of <orgName>Sprint</orgName> [Corporation]—they became <orgName>WorldCom</orgName>. I don’t know what they’re called <date>today</date>. But they were the first, and they were very successful as a long distance company. And that’s what they were called back when I worked for them, <orgName>MCI</orgName>, which I don’t even know what it stands for <date>today</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, that’s—I had [chuckles]—some people are surprised that I could remember such details after—<date>what?—40 years</date>, but in fact, I just—<date>the first year or two</date> after I was back in <placeName>the United States</placeName>, before I found a job and when I really didn’t know what type of job I was looking for, I thought, Gee, my story’s pretty interesting. I think I’ll write it up. So I wrote up a rough draft, not nearly complete, and very rough at that time, <date>just a year</date> or two after I came back to <placeName>the United States</placeName> and then never did anything with it. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">What are some of the responses you got from your book?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Well, there are two reviews out there [laughs] on <orgName>Amazon</orgName>. One guy, who I don’t know who he is, gave it a favorable review. He ends by saying, “It’s a good book, but it could have been a great book.” And I think he’s exactly right. I regret that I didn’t spend a little more time on some of the chapters, polish it up a bit, think a little deeper about some things, express myself better. But I think it’s a good book.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">You know, it’s an easy read. And not that long. But, you know, they [chuckles]—I’m sure—they’re saying they haven’t finished it so that they don’t have to comment on it, because I’m a weird guy. And I know that a lot of people would agree with something I’m saying on one page and think, Yeah, yeah, right on, kid. Tell it as it is. And the next page, I’d say something that would piss them off. [Laughs.] Because I don’t—I don’t exactly fit in the right hole for anybody. I’m not this heroic, war-resisting guy, and I’m not a conservative neocon, either. You know—for instance—I think I say in that book—I’m pretty sure I do—and just a sort of little encapsulation of—of my political beliefs is that I find conservatives ignorant but honest and liberals world wide—world wise but sleazy. Who’s gonna [chuckles]—who’s gonna like that remark [laughs]? Neither the conservatives nor the liberals. </u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">People love it there.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I’m not doing anything in that regard. That’s a facetious remark, but [chuckles] I wouldn’t complain if it did happen. But I was tickled that see—and you could imagine what this would be like for a Chinese, you know? She’s a very—not—she’s very friendly towards <placeName>the United States</placeName>, so I’m not thinking, you know, they were on the other side in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, though they were. That was not her—she just found it an interesting story, I think. It’s hard to say how much they know about the whole <placeName>Palestine</placeName> and <placeName>Middle East</placeName> or something, not to mention <placeName>Latin America</placeName>. So hopefully they find it interesting, something they haven’t read about.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I mean, they don’t—you know, someone who’s disloyal to <placeName>the United States</placeName>—that doesn’t bother them a bit.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And I guess one of my last questions is what did you think of the 1978—Carter’s pardon?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, <persName>Carter</persName>’s thing. You know, that’s one of the things I left out of my book! By that time—and I had been acquitted, so I didn’t even—I didn’t follow <persName>Carter</persName>’s amnesty, and his was a real amnesty. He just said, you know, “Stop prosecuting people. Let them out of prison,” whatever. But I—because it didn’t apply to me, I forgot all about it. I had to put it in the second edition so people, like you, who were aware of it [chuckles] would know what my—why I didn’t mention it or why it wasn’t a big deal for me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I don’t know whether there were big celebrations as these people’s cases got dropped or they came out of prison or what happened domestically when he did that, or what the response of the country was. I’m sure <placeName>Dallas</placeName>—they hated him—well, they already hated him, so [laughs] this would have been just the icing on the cake. But I don’t know what the response in the country was, because I was so out of touch. My contact with <placeName>the United States</placeName> was <orgName>the International Herald Tribune</orgName> [now <orgName>International New York Times</orgName>]. And I didn’t read that—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">You went back to <placeName>Algeria</placeName> in <date>1978</date>?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">Yeah, I did. I did briefly, on a business trip of sorts because we had all this—like I say, one of the things about countries that are Third World countries that are trying to be real countries is they put restrictions on capital outflow. You can’t just change your domestic money into dollars and take it out of the country. So I had all this money in <placeName>Algeria</placeName> that I couldn’t get out of the country, so I went back. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah. 	At this point, what was that?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I haven’t been back since. I haven’t been to <placeName>Algeria</placeName> since.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">At this point, I’m ready to just about wrap up the interview. Do you have anything else to add?</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">[Sighs.] No, I—I have all sorts of questions about your generation, but that would not be appropriate for this—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Oh, yeah, we can—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">—interview.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">We can talk once I—once I end the interview.</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">I’m interested to see how—I mean, I know you’re just one person, but it would be interesting, your perspective on the whole <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience,—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah. Well,—</u>
      <u who="MEYERCORD">—how your generation see it.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah. Well, on behalf of <orgName>the Dartmouth Vietnam Project</orgName> and myself, we’d like to thank you, <persName>Ken</persName>, for your time helping us with the project.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
