<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="MANNES"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="MANNES">It is <date>August 20th, 2015</date>. My name is <persName>David [J.] Mannes</persName>, and I’m here with Mr. <persName>Denis</persName> [pronounced DEN-iss] [R.] O’Neill, on a phone interview for the Dartmouth Vietnam Project.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Nice to meet you, too.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. So I want to start this interview actually a little bit before your beginning. I wanted to start by talking a little bit about your parents. Let’s start with their names and where they’re from?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah, just a brief history, yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">And what <date>year</date> was that?</u>
      <u who="MANNES"><date>Nineteen forty-eight</date>, okay. So you—so you were born in <placeName>Bridgeport</placeName>, grew up in <placeName>Westport</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Can you tell me about your—a little bit about the neighborhood you grew up in, your childhood?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Which sports—which sports did you play?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">I’m sorry. You said you played sports all the way up through your school, so which sports specifically?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And you mentioned that this was such, like, an idyllic, I think was your word, childhood, living in this neighborhood. And you also mentioned that it’s the time, the end of <persName>Eisenhower</persName>, which you said was, like, the golden time for <placeName>America</placeName>. But this is also one of the most intense periods of <name type="event">the Cold War</name> that you grew up in. This is <persName>McCarthyism</persName> [named after Sen. <persName>Joseph R. McCarthy</persName>]. There’s <name type="event">the Korean War</name>. Did that affect you at all?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And is that because politics wasn’t big in your home or it’s just because you were young, or it was just—just in general?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And, again—then that’s when we’re reaching <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, because <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> started, of course, back, I don’t know, at the end of <name type="event">World War II</name>, pretty much. So when did you first hear about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? Because it really built up after <name type="event">World War II</name>, even before you were born.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So, yeah. So that was—that would have been when you were just entering high school. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Let’s see, that—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And so, again, you said politics was big in your home, so when <persName>JFK</persName> was assassinated, that must have been—that must have been quite a—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So would you say—so you said that in your house, your father’s friends were very against the war, at least very nervous about it. Were other people not?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. So how about yourself? Because you are—you are in high school. <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> is gradually creeping up. It’s building up. And you’re getting to the age where you would be—you would be old enough to be in the [U.S.] Army. You’re getting towards—you’re getting towards <date>the age of 18</date>. So did that concern you at all? Like, you getting older and the war still getting bigger?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. So let’s—I guess let’s get into <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, then. So you said your father was Class of ’31 at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. Your father has friends that went to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> with him, <persName>Ted Geisel</persName> being maybe one of the foremost of them. So what really went into your decision to go there?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And were you recruited as well to play hockey, or was that something—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—you decided to—</u>
      <u who="MANNES"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">And so once you got to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, was it everything—in your freshman year, this is, was it everything you expected? Like, what were your first—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—impress- —it was? Okay.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So it wasn’t much of an adjustment, is what you’re saying.</u>
      <u who="MANNES"><date>The first winter</date>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. So can you talk to me a bit about academics your <date>freshman year</date>? What did you decide to study, or what did you think you wanted to study when you came in?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And so as a—or I’ll say in general, what was the campus climate like in relation to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> your <date>first year</date>? You took—you said you were a government major. I don’t know how many government classes you took, maybe, <date>that year</date>, but did you discuss that in your government classes?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Were people vocal on campus?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And so <persName>Billy</persName> was, it sounds like, was really that wake-up call for you. Was—were there multiple cases of this throughout the rest of <date>the year</date>? Did—were there more so-to-speak? </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And so did the protests, themselves, people standing around, like, the <persName>Green</persName> or <persName>Parkhurst</persName> [Hall]—did that protest presence start in <date>your sophomore year</date>?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">After these people started—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And so—I’m actually going to take just a step back to <date>the year before</date>, but can you tell me a little bit about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, your experience at <placeName>Heorot</placeName>? Starting maybe in pledge term. You don’t have to tell me what exactly you did then. I’m sure [chuckles] you don’t want to. But just a little bit about the culture.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. And so—and then this—one of the so-called “Magnificent Seven”—I can’t remember if you said her name. She—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And so this brings up to ’<date>68</date>, when all the—so to speak all hell breaks loose and there’s a lot of stuff going on. <persName>RFK</persName> is assassinated, <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> [Jr.] is assassinated, the Democrat [sic Democratic] National Convention happens I think in <date>the beginning of the year</date>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">The Tet Offensive.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So what is the campus climate like now in regards to the stuff that’s happening domestically and towards <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? We can start with domestically maybe. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. So you brought up a lot of points that I want to actually go back and touch on a lot of them. I also found it interesting, first of all, that you brought up <persName>Nixon</persName> and then the politicians lying, because <persName>Nixon</persName> came into office with the—with the platform that we were getting out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and then, under <persName>Nixon</persName>, we had the highest troop deployment in the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> era. And it’s stuff like that, where it sounds like it upset a lot of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students. So I was wondering: How did—how did you guys get your information? If they are lying to you and the reporters—or the photographers are the ones bringing back the—the—truth, so to speak, how did you guys get your information about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and then how do you disseminate it on campus?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And you briefly—you briefly mentioned that there was the whole antiwar music movement happening. <placeName>Woodstock</placeName> is, of course, <date>the next year</date>, but can you elaborate on that a little bit?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So I’m just going to give a quick recap. So there’s the antiwar music going around campus. There’s <orgName>the National Guard</orgName>, the police coming in to break up things, like protests that might be happening. There’s the politicians lying. There’s this sort of life-or-death, like, thought going on campus about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. What did you guys do for fun during this time? [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">That’s interesting that you say the fraternity is kind of your escape from what’s happening, but it’s also the area where you sit down and talk about the war that’s happening.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And then in—so moving on, <date>later that year</date>, so towards the end of your <name type="event">junior year</name>, ’69 is <persName>Parkhurst</persName>. That’s correct?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">The takeover.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And so could you—what—what were you doing around this time? Were you involved or—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So you said—I’m going to go back and discuss kind of a different being, because you discussed it a lot in there. You started out by saying there were all these students that took over <persName>Parkhurst</persName>. Did they represent the general <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> atmosphere? Were these students representative of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Did you ever consider—did you ever consider joining <orgName>SDS</orgName> or one of these movements like that?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. And what was the reaction to this after, let’s say, by students, alumni, the faculty, the administration?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. And the students that were standing outside—what was their—what were the students’ reactions?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Were they—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">No.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And you guys weren’t—you weren’t concerned at all that—you said that they showed up in, like, the full gear and everything, with the dogs and riot police. You weren’t concerned that this would actually turn to violence at any point, were you?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. Because, yeah, the <placeName>Kent State</placeName> shootings would happen the next—<date>the following year</date>, but it sounds like <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> wasn’t—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So you—before <persName>Parkhurst</persName>, you said, it was kind of like a balloon or a volcano, you know, steadily building up, building up, and then it exploded at <orgName>Parkhurst</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And then after, what was—what was left? Did it–did it deflate? Did it calm down, or did is just start to build up again?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">I believe it was <date>the end of April</date>.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Okay. So I guess the lottery is where I want to go next, because you’re going into your senior year. This is the end of your <date>four-year</date> <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> experience when you kind of are leaning to be who you want to be and deciding what you want to do later in life. And then here comes the draft, which is pretty much the opposite. It’s having other people telling you what to do. So can you talk to me about the beginning of the draft and the lottery? When did this first come into your head, let’s start, that this might actually happen?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yes.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So with—with your draft—your lottery number, can you go through your thoughts from, like, when you first got it until after you got exempt from the draft?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Especially—especially—you didn’t have a very, very low number, and you didn’t have a very, very high number—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—so you were kind of caught in the middle.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. I mean, you said in the beginning of your senior <date>year</date> you were staring down the barrel of, like, the end of your <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> experience, and in the future—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—you literally could be staring down the barrel of a—of a gun, so to speak. I thought that was an interesting irony—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—and other symbolism.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">So graduation. You’re graduating, and you find out either later that day or in <date>the next few days</date> that you’re not going to be going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. What kind of feeling does that give you? Like, what’s your outlook on life now that this isn’t hanging over your head, that you have a future that you can control?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">At where? I’m sorry.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Oh, <orgName>Boston University</orgName>. Okay.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And so what—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Laughs.] Exactly. And so with your writing career—how did that develop? Because I know you—I know you did writing, you did some screenplay.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">I see. And so you graduated at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. You left on this—this experience on the—the—I’m sorry, the name of the ship was the <orgName>Mobil</orgName>? </u>
      <u who="MANNES"><orgName>SS Mobil Fuel</orgName>. I’m sorry. And you went off to <placeName>Europe</placeName>. Were you still following <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> during this time?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">All right. Okay. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">And so is this is a story that you have—did you think about this story a lot over <date>the years</date>, or was this something that you really had to come back to and think about and meet up with people to, as you said in the beginning, to kind of triangulate what actually happened?</u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Right. </u>
      <u who="MANNES">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="MANNES">Yeah. Well, thank you. It was—it was a great story. It was a great memoir, and it’s been a great experience. If you don’t have anything to add, I—</u>
      <u who="MANNES">—think I’d like to conclude it.</u>
      <u who="MANNES">That’s correct.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
