<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="BURACK"/>
        <person xml:id="PEASE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="BURACK">Hi. My name is <persName>Emily Burack</persName>. I am sitting in <orgName>Rauner Special Collections Library</orgName> in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, on <date>Monday, February 15th, 2016</date>, at 10 in the morning. I am speaking with <persName>Don</persName> [C.] <persName>Pease</persName> [III], who is at his home in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, <placeName>Canada</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Good morning.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Let’s get started. Let’s start at the beginning. Where were you born, and when?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I was born in <date>February of 1944</date> in <placeName>Burlington</placeName>, <placeName>Iowa</placeName>, which is on <placeName>the Mississippi River</placeName>, just about 80 miles up river from <placeName>Hannibal</placeName>, <placeName>Missouri</placeName>, which is the setting for <persName>Huck Finn</persName> [The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn], <persName>Tom Sawyer</persName> [The Adventures of Tom Sawyer] and all of that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What did your parents do, and what were their names?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. My father was <persName>Don [Pease]</persName> Jr. I’m actually the third. And my father ran the family business, which he had taken over and managed once my grandfather, also named <persName>Don [Pease]</persName>, had died. The family business was a small business, too. He was a beer distributor, a middle man, an intermediary between—between the breweries that he represented and the taverns. And, grocery stores, occasionally.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Gotcha. What was it like growing up with three siblings?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, well, in the postwar, which is, of course, when I had come to consciousness, and during <date>the ’50s</date>, it was very much a—popularly described—I mean, there was certainly a sense of anything is possible. The <placeName>U.S.</placeName> was in quite a commanding position in the world and actually experienced a great deal of prosperity during those times from the end of the war until at least the <orgName>mid-’60s</orgName> or well beyond.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Definitely [both chuckle] a different world <date>today</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. I always think, certainly from the perspective of living outside of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, that there’s an amazingly quick fear trigger in the broad populace in the States. Very easy to crank that up and get people to do—it’s of course relevant to the war—to do quite extraordinary and dangerous and very often horrific things out of fear. That seems throughout American history to have been—the populace has been conditioned to have quite a—quite a quick trigger on that sort of thing. So there was nuclear war ominous, hanging over, but that was so—and we had—you probably heard it—the air raid drills regularly—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—at the school. You would take cover and have the illusion that you could protect yourself from radioactivity by hiding under a desk or a table and all that sort of thing. [Both chuckle.] So that was there, and certainly <name type="event">the Cold War</name> was very much on when I came to awareness and consciousness, social consciousness. So that was that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It certainly would have felt that way. There were very few black people who lived in my hometown. There was de facto segregation in housing and great discrimination in, um, jobs, so for them—but they were a very tiny minority, so the prevailing atmosphere was we can do everything. We are free, and the world is a hospitable place.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. How much older was your older sibling than you?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. My oldest sister, <persName>Diane [Pease</persName>], was <date>two and a quarter years</date> older than I, and then following after me: one brother, who was <date>five years</date> younger than I am, and my youngest brother is <date>nine years</date> younger.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So did you and <persName>Diane</persName> go to school together? Or she would walk with you to school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Did I and <persName>Diane</persName> go to school together?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes. She would have accompanied me. That’s an interesting point. She was very nurturing.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So my oldest granddaughter, who’s now four, and a big sister, herself, I tell her my sister <persName>Diane</persName> taught me just about everything I knew—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—in <date>the early years</date>, so, yes, she was attentive. But my memories are walking alone or with a kindergarten friend.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, she certainly would have been a sheltering presence. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Did you play sports, growing up?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes, sports were always a very big deal. Some of my very early memories were playing what they called the tackles. Tackle football, with the older neighborhood boys. And I was three or four or five, so I was certainly brought up to be—to like that sort of thing and be athletic and show bravery and spunk. And I recall getting a lot of praise for doing that with older kids.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">He was an important figure in local social landscape and my life as well. But in any event, they were both athletes, and I had good coordination now and all of the things. You need a lot of encouragement. So sports were a very big deal, yes. And all through school I played whatever sport was on <date>that season</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Did you play sports in high school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I’m sorry, did I play?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Any organized sports in high school? Like, for the school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes. Right on through school. We had organized sports. We had organized basketball of a sort even in elementary school, and it meant starting in junior high, which ran I think through nine. There were organized sports, tackle football with equipment, basketball, and, you know, the seventh grade and eighth grade team makes and the varsity, so I played on all of those things. But I was a decent athlete. I was supposed to be in the varsity [unintelligible] starting [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, that was a very big part of my identity.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, what, did you like high school, or did you like school, or more of your teams or—what was it like?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, I always liked school. I liked [unintelligible]. And junior high. It was—we had a <date>weekly</date> newspaper in grades eight and nine. In ninth grade I was the editor of that local, mimeographed school newspaper. And so I was involved in that and various school government. The usual profile of—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> student they were looking for back in <date>those days</date>. [Both chuckle.] Broad experience over all sorts of things. I understand it’s not nearly as rigid <date>these days</date>. You think—you might even be looking for an accomplishment or strong interest and involvement in one field, rather than requiring that, a little dab here and there of everything. But—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—that was certainly the standard, the profile that they were looking for at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> back then, and so it may [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So what drew you to, sorry, I didn’t mean to interrupt you.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Sorry. I fitted into that model, so—yes.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So what drew you to apply to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, or what put <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> on your radar in high school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. What put <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> on my radar? It was the fact that [<persName>Robert L.] “Bob” Blackman</persName>, who was a very successful, quite brilliant coach of the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> football team, sent out letters to I guess most high schools in the country [both chuckle], to football coaches, asking if they had any student athletes who would fit that profile of school and a decent athlete and that sort of thing, and my—my football coach gave <persName>Bob Blackman</persName> my name.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and all of the outdoors, <orgName>the Outing Clubs</orgName> [reference to <orgName>the Dartmouth Outing Club</orgName>] and the orientation to the outdoor was huge, in my estimation. I was very much keen on doing outdoor things as much as one could in that environment. So the thought of being in <placeName>New England</placeName>, woods and the mountains and water that actually ran clear rather than muddy, like the <placeName>Mississippi</placeName> [both chuckle] and many tributary rivers or creeks or anything.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So you came to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> as a football athlete?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. Back then—No, there were no tied athletic scholarships allowed.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I didn’t even have to go out for the football team to maintain my—my scholarship,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, I see.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the general aid package. So, no, it wasn’t dependent on it, but the reason I heard, along with other states [state schools], of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was by football and the recruitment letter, all that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So you graduated high school in <date>1962</date>? Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, that’s right.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">How did you feel upon graduation? Were you excited to leave <placeName>Iowa</placeName> and go up to <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>? Were you nervous?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, quite excited. I felt that I had had a successful time in high school. I was of course engaged in, looking back on it, what seems like a lot of striving, which I love, and pushing myself through high school to do all of the things—the school newspaper as well. I was playing in sports and student government and all that sort of stuff. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I thought it was within my capabilities, and I was quite exciting. Yes, looking forward.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So you get—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I was not disappointed.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So when you get to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>the fall of 1962</date>, did you go on <date>a first year</date> trip? What was your first impression of this school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, I— I was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Did it meet your expectations?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes, absolutely. I wouldn’t have missed the freshman trip for anything.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Most members of my class, which was around—slightly over 800, I believe—most members of the class have gone on it—I don’t know if that’s still the case.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It still is, yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. And at that time, they broke us up into groups of five freshmen, and a leader—an upperclassman would be the leader, and we would hike for I think it was <date>two, three days</date> before we all gathered at Moosilauke [Ravine Lodge]. I certainly remember all the—the other four members of that little freshman hiking group. I’m still in touch with just one of them, but, yeah, that was a terrific way to start.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So freshman fall. Did you join anything, or did you go out for the football team? </u>
      <u who="PEASE">I did go out—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What were you first actions?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Both chuckle.] I did go out for the football team. There were massive numbers of people. I was one of eleven left ends in <date>the first days</date> [both chuckle] of football. And then it was a wonderful practice at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. Anybody who went out for the team was on the team. The focus was on participation. Of course, they wanted to win, and <persName>Blackman</persName> has <date>an undefeated season</date> and won several Ivy League titles, et cetera, so they were successful. But the policy was if you wanted to be on a team, you could be.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the first team. Second team, I guess it was. But anyway, I enjoyed that and learned that at just under six-three, six-two-and-a-half or so, and weighing 150 pounds, even in the Ivy League I was not college football material. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So I just concentrated on track, indoor and outdoor track in <date>the winter</date> and <date>the spring seasons</date> my freshman and then <date>my sophomore years</date>. And quite enjoyed that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So you were just on the football team your freshman fall.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Just for <date>that first year</date>, right. Then <date>winter</date> and spring track. And <date>the second year</date>, I just stayed with track only. I played—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I see.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—in various things like that, but sports were less of a focus but still part of my life.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What was your first impression of classes? Did you find it harder than high school? What were you interested in studying at the time?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I remember—well, I was quite—I am quite glad, in retrospect at that time—I don’t know what the situation is now— There were distributed requirements, so you had to take so many courses in science, in science, and arts. You had to have a foreign language. Unfortunately, you could take an exam in a foreign language of your choosing as an entering freshman and pass out of it. I was not a good enough student of Spanish and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—did not pass out of it, so I had the good fortune to be in quite a small, wonderful beginning Spanish class with a professor by the name of <placeName>Francisco</placeName> Goto[sic, <placeName>Ugarte</placeName>] from <placeName>Spain</placeName>, although he identified as Basque. And, yes, he was a fantastic teacher, and I instantly changed my attitude toward Spanish and very much enjoyed it and excelled and ended up majoring in Spanish. So that was one of the three courses I took in my first term of <date>freshman year</date> that was very enjoyable.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—I had: two A’s and an A-plus, so I felt I was capable of handing this—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—environment fairly comfortably.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Were you living with a roommate, or did you have your own room?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I had one of the least expensive rooms, and so I had two roommates. It was quite a nice room, with a fireplace and everything in Richardson Hall.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But, yes, there were three of us, but it was—basically it was two and in a long hallway, enough room for—yes, it was quite nice, and I was very pleased that we had a fireplace and it was spacious, too, with the long hallway and it was quite nice, and I was very pleased that we had a fireplace which [faced towards] birch fireplace wood, so I couldn’t have been happier.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.] That’s good to hear.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I’m sorry, I didn’t catch the last one.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry. What was the rest of your freshman year like? Did it continue on this very positive streak?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Yes, it did. The big event, <date>just a month</date> or so into the term, was the Cuban Missile Crisis—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— and it caught our attention, and I distinctly remember reading in The [New York] Times—we got <orgName>The Times</orgName> delivered to our door every day, and reading in <orgName>The Times</orgName> at one point in the crisis—there was an article with illustrations and a map, with American missile sites near the borders of <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> and central <placeName>Europe</placeName> and in <placeName>Turkey</placeName>, certainly within 90 miles as to the west side. And I remember thinking, Gee, we can be on their border, but they can’t be on ours. Is that fair? [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So that was sort of the first questioning, more or less. It was just a questioning of the explicit questioning of the basic ideas of the geopolitics and the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> role in the world and all of that. So, yeah, I was aware. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[unintelligible] the level of activism <date>these days</date> [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So would you describe the—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[unintelligible] the <date>’50s</date>, running into the actual chronological ’<date>60s</date>. It was still that—that kind of quiet and self-satisfaction. The country did not feel immediately, hugely threatened, which seems incredibly in light of <name type="event">the Cuban Missile Crisis</name> and the fact that [President <persName>John F.] Kennedy</persName>, reportedly by <persName>Arthur [M.] Schlesinger [Jr.</persName>], and other aides felt at the time that by putting up the blockade, he was thinking there was a two out of three chance that it would lead to nuclear holocaust. And he was looking to do that. [Chuckles.] It seems quite—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— [unintelligible] to me right now.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> was still so supreme that at least I didn’t get a huge sense of immediate threat. There were seen as a country and kind of American individuals we could do pretty well anything we wanted to do, and what that would mean was of course inherently, intrinsically be a good thing because we were Americans and Americans did good things.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So would you mark—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[unintelligible] active but there were underlying things and questions here, but the overall feeling was quite comfortable.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So would you mark <name type="event">the Cuban Missile Crisis</name> as your kind of first sort of questioning of American action?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. As I look back on it, there are things in my childhood, one thing especially to do with <name type="event">the Korean War</name>, but they were never really formulated as questions. Oh, yes, <orgName>the Cuban Missile Crisis</orgName> and [unintelligible] surrounding that [unintelligible] come close to—that sort of first wave.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">There were other—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—underlying factors in my upbringing, in my life until then that would have caused skepticism. I think I was open to see and thinking [unintelligible] eventually [unintelligible] things that conditioned me to be open to that perspective. But it certainly wasn’t at a terribly conscious level at that point. If there were problems—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Can you speak—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—they could be fixed through will and energy, and hopes were abundant that all good things would come of that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Could you speak further on what you just mentioned about <name type="event">the Korean War</name>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes, as far as that. Growing up, we lived, <date>the first seven years</date> of my life, next door to a family called <persName>Morrison</persName>. They had three sons. They were all mechanics. They were older. They were adult sons, or late teenagers when I was quite small, and they lived immediately next door. All three sons I believe still lived at home.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">And he and his brothers always rescued our red cocker spaniel, which was determined, as much as possible,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—to pick a fight with the big black Doberman Pinscher across the street. The <persName>Morrison</persName> boys would always save <persName>Mickey</persName>, our dog’s life by getting the Doberman Pinscher off.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So anyway, they—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And when <name type="event">the Korean War</name> came along, he was drafted, I believe, into the military in <placeName>Korea</placeName> and was captured by the Chinese and became a prisoner of war, and it was a big issue during the war. I remember the newspapers, and seeing the coverage and all, that a number of the American POWs became labeled turncoats because they said things in captivity that were against what the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> was doing, et cetera. And <persName>Dick Morrison</persName> was one of those. So he was labeled publicly, I don’t know, by the government, but certainly by popular opinion and what was in the newspapers. As a traitor and a turncoat.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—cheap paper. Anyway, there was a big picture of them being led to the electric chair, and I was not terribly old, but nine or ten or whatever, but I remember that picture very vividly, and I remember feeling, That’s really cruel. It just seemed so cold-blooded and so terrible. [Chuckles.] They were just a couple.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">who had kids—I think their boys were about my age. Anyway, that [unintelligible], learning that things are done officially and by the government are not necessarily right, and they’re not necessarily moral, and they’re not necessarily a good thing to do.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It had been led, back in <date>the mid-19th century</date>, uniformly by [unintelligible]. Most of the professionals [unintelligible] that had been led by people educated in, by men who were professionals, professional class who actually came from university and colleges or at least part of that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—of thinking. And it really [made me feel there are just kind of childhood that made me more comfortable, [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I [unintelligible] anyway. I finished [unintelligible]. I [unintelligible]. Coming from the <placeName>Midwest</placeName> at that time, especially from my family’s structured life, where I was physically not— I was not [unintelligible]. Very few people were thinking about what happened in <date>the years</date> where I [unintelligible]. [Both chuckle.] I think there were maybe an innocence and certainly a lack of [unintelligible] that meant I would be quite sensitive to and reactive to the country not living up to the ideals its fathers as recited <date>every day</date> with the Pledge of Allegiance, that kind of thing. I think I was right to feel much more easily betrayed than if I had grown up elsewhere and had a more informal worldly view.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">To? I’m sorry, I didn’t quite catch—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry, the microphone is kind of shoddy. No, about the Cuban Missile Crisis. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, the Cuban Missile Crisis.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Do you remember people being concerned? Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. There certainly wasn’t—I don’t remember any meetings or any teach-ins. In the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> and certainly in <placeName>Europe</placeName> and in <placeName>England</placeName> there was the anti-nuclear movement. I was not aware of any presence of that anti-nuclear war movement on the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> campus. It might have been there, but I wasn’t aware of it. So there was nothing that was an organized discussion about the matter. I certainly talked about it with roommates and with friends, but it wasn’t an immense—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—impact. It was certainly a tense time, but, no, there wasn’t a whole lot of follow-up or putting it into political, intellectual—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—perspective. Nothing that was organized that I was involved in or aware about.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">And then if you flash forward [sic] a year and you have <persName>Kennedy</persName>’s assassination,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">—what was the reaction of that on campus? Or your reaction in particular.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, that was an immense, and classes were cancelled, although we were coming—<date>November 23rd</date>—we were coming up to the end of the term and the beginning of events, and not—not too far off from then. And I don’t remember exactly how many days classes were cancelled, but things stopped, and people were taking it in. And then the assassination by [<persName>Jack] Ruby of [Lee Harvey] Oswald</persName> and all the stuff was just—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—hard to digest. “Just unbelievable.” Or “Can’t happen here” “but it is” sorts of feelings. But there was enough school pressure at the end of the term that people did get back to—to their <date>daily</date> activities fairly quickly. It was a huge shock, of course, and many of us, myself included, had—had been very much awakened to active idealism by <persName>Kennedy</persName>’s eloquence in his inaugural—inauguration speech and speeches before that and speeches during his presidency, although I remember before he was assassinated, in <date>that year</date> between <name type="event">the Cuban Missile Crisis</name> and the—and the <date>November</date> ’63 assassination, I remember being—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So I remember being upset at both <persName>Kennedys</persName> for not using the power at their command to—to protect black people, to advance desegregation. But for me, <persName>Kennedy</persName> was—was quite a hero, embodied lots of ideals, and so it was a real shock, yes.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Just speaking on the civil rights thing,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—do you think your church and its kind of long history of activism—you carried with you to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? Did you seek out groups like that on campus in <date>your first year</date> there?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I’m sorry. I didn’t understand about “long history.”</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Of your church back home in <placeName>Iowa</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, my church. Yes, okay. Sorry, I missed the words—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I’m sorry. The microphone is very—the microphone on this is very wonky. I apologize.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it’s my hearing as well, although I do have my hearing aids on and telephone.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But so—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So I—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the history of [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—was just asking, with the history of your church and kind of the role it played in your hometown, did you seek out a similar group on campus, maybe another Christian group or a student activist group in relation to civil rights or—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I was [unintelligible] there in <date>the first two years</date> at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. I was aware of the <orgName>DCU</orgName>, <orgName>the Dartmouth Christian Union</orgName>, and any activism, even in terms of education, that was happening, came out of—almost always came out of the <orgName>DCU</orgName>. So I was certainly interested. I attended a few talks and programs focused on civil rights.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, very much so. And things were going well, and the one jarring thing about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> at that time was that it was male only, and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—it would be with town and all of that. It was just a dysfunctional social situation [chuckles],—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—where you would either travel to or freshman or <date>sophomore years</date>, young women bused in from—from women’s colleges for <date>the weekend</date>, and that whole dating situation, et cetera. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I was a ghost. That’s what they called a person who didn’t participate in <date>those days</date>. But—so there was that social activity. And I actually had met a young woman from <orgName>Colby [College</orgName>], and we had a relationship starting in <date>the winter of my sophomore year</date>, so that was—that was a very good thing. And my life was more normal socially that way, as much as it can be in an all-male environment.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. [Chuckles.] Yeah. So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So thing were going along.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So then, if I remember correctly from when we were speaking <date>this summer</date>, in fall of <date>1964</date> you went to study abroad in <placeName>Spain</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes. I actually went in <date>late July</date>, <date>early August</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, <date>late July</date>. Excuse me.</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><date>Five, six weeks early</date>, before we all had to be there. There was a group of eight students and a professor, <persName>Robert</persName> [<persName>H.] Russell</persName>, and his wife. That was the <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> contingent in <placeName>Salamanca</placeName>, <placeName>Spain</placeName>, that fall. So, yes, I had <date>a month</date> on my own, wandering around a bit in <placeName>Paris</placeName> and then hitchhiking through <placeName>Spain</placeName>, which was a great experience. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—remember two things struck me. Of course, they’re highlighted in retrospect. But I remember at the time I was struck by certainly the <persName>Johnson</persName> campaign, which was heavily portraying <persName>Goldwater</persName> as a warmonger. That made a big impression on me, and I was concerned about who would win the election and that I really wanted <persName>Johnson</persName> to win, just because things would be safe and peaceful.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—And trying to follow it. But at that point, ground troops of any number in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> wasn’t an issue, and even though <persName>Johnson</persName> had a plan  for a backup during that election campaign, he was not letting on he had planned a massive expansion, et cetera. He was going to be the one who was pursuing war. Well, I mean, against <persName>Goldwater</persName> on that basis [chuckles], so—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So studying abroad there, did you ever feel fear—feel the same fear that you were talking to these Basque and these Protestants—that they felt?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, I felt I wore that invisible American cloak, so nothing bad—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—could happen to me. There was a certain—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—empowerment there, where—it was not just in that age, where it’s quite common for people to feel immortal—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—but to be quite indifferent to what’s happening. But being American at that point certainly gave one an extra added feeling that nothing bad could happen to one, even civilians, of course. So, no, I don’t remember feeling fear. I remember—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Um—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—feeling that on behalf of the people who did feel fear and were subjugated. And I talked to some workers as well. And, of course, outside of the official fascist syndicates, there was no real organized unions or anything to—to protect themselves, so that aspect was—was there as well.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">I wish I—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Do you remem- —</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—had been more politically conscious with this thing. Of course, <persName>Franco</persName>’s big slogan when I was there in ’64 was [unintelligible] <date>25 years</date> of peace. It was <date>25 years</date> since ’39, since the end of <name type="event">the Spanish Civil War</name>, in which there had been, of course, in many ways, a run-up to, a precursor, a dress rehearsal for <name type="event">World War II</name>. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I wish I had been more aware, and I would have sought out people and been able to speak more knowledgeably. I was trying to educate myself but did not have a good understanding of it.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So when you got back from <placeName>Spain</placeName>, did you take this kind of upset and shock over the regime there, and did you translate that into actions when you were back on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I did. I was back on cam- —I think shock was probably—a world view, shock, was probably—that’s probably a fair description. Uncharacteristically, once I was back on campus, I didn’t attend my classes. I’d never done that. I wasn’t doing my work. I was just up in the Tower Room. Alternately, reading escapist literature and trying to educate myself about what’s happening in the world, to make sense of all of this.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—inform me, but [unintelligible] the draft [unintelligible]. I was not taking it in. So anyway, I did leave, stayed with a friend at <orgName>Harvard</orgName> for <date>a couple of weeks</date>, I guess, and then on to <placeName>New York</placeName> and there on my own for <date>three or four weeks</date>, during which time <persName>Malcolm X</persName> was assassinated in <placeName>Harlem</placeName> [<placeName>New York City</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>]. And I was staying at the Y[MCA], and [<orgName>Robert] Sargent</orgName> [“Sarge”] <persName>Shriver</persName>, who was a relative of the <persName>Kennedys</persName>, was coming through—the first of—the beginnings of <orgName>Johnson’s War on Poverty</orgName> effort, and <persName>Shriver</persName>, as the head of <orgName>VISTA</orgName>, <orgName>Volunteers in Service to America</orgName> [now <orgName>AmeriCorps VISTA</orgName>], the domestic <orgName>Peace Corp.</orgName></u>
      <u who="BURACK">Wow.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—fortuitous. Fortuitous and very interesting and influential. As <orgName>VISTA</orgName> volunteers we could help with the farmworkers union [<orgName>Mexican-American National Farmworkers Union</orgName>] on our own time, which was sort of a strange concept [chuckles], but anyway,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—we had permission to do that. But, of course, we could not be more official due to [unintelligible] great, great opposition from the establishment, from the large farmers and [unintelligible]. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—fellow <orgName>VISTA</orgName> volunteers in part, was a young woman, <persName>Lucy Norman</persName>, who was a <orgName>Quaker</orgName>. [unintelligible] known her, and their peace testimony pacifism, opposition to war, and activism in civil rights matters. And the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> community that she was a part of there in <placeName>California</placeName> that was also a significant influence.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So just to—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] by ‘65—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—a lot—yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the war was picking up, and even in terms of civil rights were certainly coming much more to a crunch, so [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes. So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">There were all sorts of things going on. And at one point there was an official with <name type="event">the War on Poverty</name>, who was also a professor of social work at [<orgName>University of California</orgName>,] <orgName>Berkeley</orgName>. He took myself and a guy [unintelligible]. He took us to his class in <placeName>Berkeley</placeName>, just to speak about the type of organizing, the things that were going on.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And the literature that I picked up just then—it was a day trip, we didn’t stay overnight, to <placeName>Berkeley</placeName> was very [chuckles]—was very influential in helping me put some things together S that was just—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So just to—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Before—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Dropped out. Ended up in <placeName>VISTA</placeName>. And on to <placeName>California</placeName>, which was a hotbed for all sorts of political movements. Yeah, those were all major influences.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.] You said you— just keep going. When you were in <placeName>New York</placeName>, and <persName>Sargent Shriver</persName> was at your Y, how did he convince you to join <orgName>VISTA</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, I didn’t need much—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Or what was his pitch?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— huge convincing—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, you didn’t need much convincing. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—as I applied for what it was. And, you know, there are all these problems, and I have some abilities and energy and interest and idealism, and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, it was a good fit. Didn’t take much convincing at all. [Chuckles.] I was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] something.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. So when you get out to <placeName>California</placeName> and you, like, meet <persName>César Chavez</persName> on your first day, what’s your impression of all that?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, just that it was wonderful stuff, and I was trying to catch up on the background, the history, the technique and all of this. It was a steep learning curve for me because I hadn’t been—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—immediately involved in political movements. I was very interested, was very sympathetic, had done things on the periphery but had never been centrally involved, let alone an organizer, so, yes, it was a steep learning curve, and I was very motivated, and it was—it was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">And—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—interesting—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Just—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and exciting and extremely worthwhile.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">If you could just explain to me what <orgName>VISTA</orgName> volunteers did in <placeName>California</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, it was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I’m not too aware of their—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—very wide open. What we were doing in the south, in <placeName>Parlier</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>—there was—Parlier-organized [unintelligible], an area outside of that jurisdiction on the edge of it but in an unorganized municipality called The <placeName>Colonia</placeName> or <placeName>La Colonia</placeName>, where the farmworkers lived. And the politics beyond <name type="event">the War on Poverty</name> being brought to <persName>Parlier</persName> were—was that <orgName>the Catholic Church</orgName>, which was traditionally well embedded, of course, in Mexican-American farmworkers—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—was under great challenge by evangelical Protestants. And Father <persName>Collin</persName>, the local priest, who spent most of his career in <placeName>Latin America</placeName> and was brought in to <placeName>California</placeName> to fight this battle with the prostitutes [chuckles]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">He was able to make an application on behalf of the community, which was legitimate—they were a large part of the community—to <orgName>VISTA</orgName> volunteers, to help in <placeName>La Colonia</placeName> to get a water system, to provide educational opportunities, just a vast array of meetings, and we were there to do whatever we could—it wasn’t well defined—working with the local community. But in fact the local community, was represented by Father <persName>Collin</persName>, and his intention was shore up <orgName>the Catholic Church</orgName> against the—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— new development we progressed very quickly and distanced ourselves [chuckles], but nonetheless, <persName>Lucy</persName> was quite involved with—with setting up <date>summer</date> camp program and after-school programs, and she had a number of volunteers come for <date>the summer</date>, nursing and university students, who helped with that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—activity, but there was some violence and people who [unintelligible], so there I was, at <date>the age of 21</date>, trying to [laughs]—trying to help deal with—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— the guys who were <date>a few years</date> younger than I was and from a different culture. Anyway, we made some progress, nothing spectacular, but some progress on both fronts. And the community—not while I was there, but eventually it got—it took over the water system and became incorporated and [unintelligible]. On the side, I was of course very interested in the farmworkers’ unionization and organization, [unintelligible] was necessary to point out wages and working conditions, which were quite terrible, with long hours and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— uh so, yeah, a maelstrom of—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah! It seems like it. [Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes it was most—[unintelligible]. I was vaguely aware, but, yes, that was certainly the real introduction—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—to that way of thinking that approached that history. And it was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Um,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—influential.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Did you—so I know when you were back on—at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> campus—and we can talk about this in a bit—but you worked with the Quakers on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes. And my wife, whom I met at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>summer</date> school in <date>1966</date>, when they were first allowing women be in <date>summer</date> school—it wasn’t <date>the first year</date>, the second or third, somewhere in there. Anyway, <persName>Carol-Anne</persName> [Riese] became and still is my wife, was coming from a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> background, herself. She—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—is not herself a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> at all [chuckles], but she went to a private boarding school on <orgName>the Main Line</orgName> in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, and they were let out of the grounds only on certain occasions, one of which was <date>Sunday</date> morning they could leave, on their own, and walk to church. And it happened that <orgName>the Friends Meeting House</orgName> was the furthest away, so the longest walk she could—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Unintelligible, laughs].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">She started going to the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> meeting and became quite—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I see.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—enthusiastic about it, and then when she was at <orgName>UCLA</orgName> [<orgName>University of California</orgName>, <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>], she actually helped, with one of the founders of the new <orgName>Quaker</orgName> museum [unintelligible] and all that. So she had the beginnings of a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> background, and we met in my first class back at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. Once I left and returned my draft card and eventually made my way back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>June</date> of ’66, to finish up my degree, and my class was graduating in <date>June</date> of ’66, and I got there in time to see some of my friends when they to say “hey” and to work after graduation, which was a bit—[laugh], and the reunion—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—unusual activity, but anyway, I was back. My first class was introduction to [unintelligible]. There were only two of us in the class, myself and [unintelligible], and <date>the first day</date>, we went to lunch and we had a nice lunch, and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and became quite involved [unintelligible] and got the next [unintelligible] of my introduction to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I started off—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.] Very good note.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. [Both chuckle.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Just to go back to <orgName>VISTA</orgName>, and then we’ll talk more about the rest of your time at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, you said that Father <persName>Collin</persName> was the one that brought in the <orgName>VISTA</orgName> volunteers into this district. So how involved do you see religion in these activist movements?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Ah.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Or not activist movement, in <name type="event">the War on Poverty</name>, the role of the church in <name type="event">the War on Poverty</name>—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">—is my question.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The church—from my understanding—I don’t have a broad knowledge of it, but my understanding is that local groups would often have some religious component, and, you know, I don’t think that was explicit that the church, itself, could bring in a—be the actual contractor to sign an agreement—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—on <name type="event">the War of Poverty</name>. It was community groups associated with the church and Father <persName>Collin</persName>? 1:13:50] was at the—at the—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But it was fairly common that interest groups would be involved in some way.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Gotcha.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—it wasn’t always the case, by any means, but it was fairly common. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">And so what did it—I mean, I’m trying to formulate this question. Are you—do you sign up for <orgName>VISTA</orgName> for a specific amount of time, or you were just ready to leave that spring?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, for <date>a year</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">For <date>a year</date>, so—I actually left shortly before my year was up. It was <date>January</date>, I guess it would have been <date>a couple of months</date> before my [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I came to the point that <date>winter</date> of ’65-’66, where I just was—really, I was upset about the war, knew I had to deal with the draft in some way, at some point in the near future. And I just became so horrified by the whole thing that I ended up returning my draft card fairly publicly and making an issue of it. I would—if I had it to do over, of course I would do it with much more consideration for my poor parents, who were—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—hit with this pretty much out of the blue. And I was quite fortunate that the editor of my hometown newspaper, an ex-Marine who simply had no love of war and was a <orgName>Democratic Party</orgName> activist—and by that point in <date>early January ’66</date>, he was quite strongly antiwar, so he was upset when I returned the draft card, this hugely public, with a letter explaining the actions, and I sent a copy to him. And he gave my action and my situation front-page coverage for quite a while, from an antiwar slant. So he was quite complimentary to me and my background, and the take he had on it was an all-American boy, you know, went through high school, was horrified by what the country was doing. So—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—if the local editor had been of a different political outlook, I could still be quite [chuckles]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—nailed. Yes. And it would have been even tougher on my parents. I think it made it considerably easier for them, although it wasn’t easy for them, given that he was giving a very positive coverage and saying this was a good thing and society should take notice, somebody who was so embedded, so involved in [unintelligible] to the structure and the ideals of dissolution. We should break up and look at what’s going on here. So with that setting of it,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—they protected –I’ve never experienced hostility directly towards me in my hometown at that time. I went back, and I took my draft card—I went back to my home for all of that. The only—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So what are the—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, an interesting little quirk back to childhood neighbors and activities. I had mentioned that when I was small, I got a lot of praise from the local older kids in the neighborhood for doing—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—game and playing tackle football and other sports. Well, that came back [chuckles] to—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—bite me and only hostile letter that I saw in the local newspaper was from one of the youngest about—He was about my age, and his older brothers were given to, when we were little, praising me for being tough and brave and game, and using that as a stick with which to shame him.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—about [unintelligible]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">but that was the only visit of real hostility—went back to a childhood experience and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Anyway, I was quite fortunate in having the support of the local newspaper—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—in that it was presented [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So can you just talk me through the process of returning your draft card? What kind of spurred you into that action? Was it more press coverage of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? Was it leaving VISTA? Kind of what brought you to that act?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">You know, as I say, I think I really had to deal with the draft at some point. I likely—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—could have gone back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and had an exemption for the time there, but it was going to have to be dealt with. And I was quite taken by what was happening in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. There was a buildup in troops. There was, of course, much more emphasis on— It was personal inasmuch as—I’ve mentioned that there were student nurses who had come for <date>the summer</date> to <orgName>VISTA</orgName> to work, helping with <date>summer</date> daycare programs. And there was a boyfriend who was a Marine and being shipped off to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> came to visit and stayed with me while he was visiting his girlfriend, before he shipped out to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So that was the summer of—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Wow.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—’67, during that huge buildup. The fact that I knew him and he was going off and he was going to be killing and possibly be killed, himself. I mean, that was very difficult to me. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—way. But I remember meeting in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> [unintelligible] <date>every day</date> and I was still in <placeName>California</placeName>, and they gave quite prominent coverage to what <orgName>Senators Church</orgName> and <persName>Morse</persName> were saying. That was certainly influential, that there were people in the establishment who felt compelled to speak out. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Anyway, that’s the background.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Once I returned my draft card, and left <orgName>VISTA</orgName> and was in <placeName>Iowa</placeName>, and I was in my hometown, in <placeName>Burlington</placeName>, for a good number of <date>weeks</date>. Probably, like, <date>six weeks</date> I was in <placeName>Iowa City</placeName>, which was—is where <orgName>the University of Iowa</orgName> is, and I was staying with a high school friend and started a relationship with a young woman from my high school as well during that period in <date>the spring</date>, before I developed—before I returned to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So I was engaged in trying to persuade friends of my views on <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, to get them to join me in not going into the <orgName>Army</orgName>, et cetera. I was singularly unsuccessful in convincing any of them.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But I’m glad I had direct contact with them. And the person I was staying with, <persName>John Cloyd</persName>, a friend from high school, that was in a university seventy-five miles away from my hometown. I stayed with <persName>John</persName>. And he ended up going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and having one of the most—and surviving, having one of the most dangerous jobs. He ran sniffer dogs outside the wire at night, looking for Viet Cong snipers. There was a very high mortality rate in that job, but he came back alive and not injured physically. I’m very glad that we are able to maintain our friendship while he was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And subsequently he and his wife came to see us in <placeName>Canada</placeName> right after he got back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date>1968</date>. So it was a very—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—immediate [unintelligible] in terms of—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—having friends who were going off to [unintelligible], all that sort of thing, centered around my hometown, was very visceral—those were important experiences that I’ve had—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Unintelligible] for that time. I was very glad to get back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>June</date> of ’66.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah. So I was just about to ask—so you get back on campus.</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">And you’re in this <name type="event">New Testament</name> religion class, where you meet <persName>Carol-Anne</persName>. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I wanted to know if <persName>Jesus</persName> really was a pacifist—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and had similar interests. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Did you find out?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Laughs.] You can find what you wish to find in the Bible.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">That’s very true.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I certainly was convinced then and still on the whole that the account given is a pacifist one, but it was not exclusively so. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I think it’s strongly enough leaning towards pacifism, though, that it’s—it’s quite startling that Christianity can be used for military crusades. I found that quite out of step with the actual texts and early traditions. Anyway, that’s another discussion.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">You are taking religion courses. Is that right?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes, I am. I’m studying history and religion here at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Right.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It’s a very cool department. I’ve been a fan of all the classes I’ve taken thus far.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So were you taking other classes or just this one?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, I took another class. It was a big seminar class called <orgName>The Guards of Modern Self-Consciousness</orgName>, through literature, when called “How human beings came to be aware of self and society”, et cetera. A broad topic. Interesting. All the students other than myself, however, were still in high school or had just graduated and were taking a summer course. Anyway,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—my main contact with people <date>that summer</date> was <persName>Carol</persName>—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and our relationship developing.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Go on?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Did you like—did you like being back on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes, I did. Very much.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And <persName>Richard—Richard [P.]</persName> <persName>Unsworth</persName> was the dean of the [<persName>William Jewett] Tucker Foundation</persName> at that time. And he was friends with prominent pacifists, the leader of the pacifist movement in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, called <persName>A. J. Muste</persName>. Anyway, I had been to see <persName>Richard Unsworth</persName> as the head of <orgName>the Tucker Foundation</orgName>, and, of course—to see [unintelligible] the head of <orgName>the Dartmouth Christian Union</orgName>, the Rev. George [H.] Kalbfleisch. I got in touch with them immediately when I was back on campus. I knew that they—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—were like me, antiwar. They were certainly involved with the civil rights movement. And they were personally very, very supportive, so I tried to organize something during—in <date>summer</date> school to deal with the war. It was a pretty sleepy time on campus. There weren’t many—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—students. There were interesting things. There was the <orgName>ABC</orgName> program, A Better Chance, which was taking largely black, and a few white kids, I guess, kids from inner cities and giving them pre-university courses and training in preparation for university. One of my many—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—<date>summer</date> jobs <date>that summer</date> was—was a bit of tutoring and just being at a session study hall with those students. So that was interesting. But politically, certainly in terms of antiwar events, there was not anything going on, so we just would, with money from <orgName>the Tucker Foundation</orgName> and <persName>Richard Unsworth</persName>’s help, we got [unintelligible]. She wasn’t available [unintelligible]—Johnson from <orgName>the American Friends Service Committee</orgName>, a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> social action—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—committee, and he came. The <orgName>Quakers</orgName> had written a very dissected, sort of moderate, sort of a political book against the war on [sic] <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And he was the author of that book. And he came and spoke to [unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What was his name? Sorry.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—on campus, which we held at the old—the old math building. And I suppose there were maybe—oh, I don’t know, 30 to 50 people there for that. But that’s the only thing we did in the way of antiwar stuff in <date>that summer</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry, what was the name of the man who wrote that book and came to speak?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I forget his first name, but his last name was <persName>Johnson</persName>. And he had—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—written a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> small booklet on—on the war in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">And very effective in [unintelligible] churches and amongst respectable [chuckles], pretty well mainstream people. In fact, in my hometown, after I had returned my draft card, it was quite interesting. And it became a big public event. People came out of the woodwork, out of the woods, all sorts of peaceniks, who had been in my hometown, who had been my teachers—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—contacted me and said they had long contributed to <orgName>the Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors</orgName>. They long committed to the <orgName>Quaker</orgName>—<orgName>the American Friends Service</orgName> committee. They were a member of this peace group and that. They didn’t ever feel confident enough to be open about it in our little [chuckles] closed society.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So they did contact me, and there were possibly peace churches, like Mennonites, ministers who contacted me, even a Baptist minister who had been active in the civil rights movement and was a pacifist himself, personally, even though the church was not. He contacted me. It was quite amazing.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—he wrote booklet against <name type="event">the War</name> on [sic] <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in the winter of ’66, because many people in town asked if he possibly could. So that—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Wow.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— that was [unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—that—that booklet, and the author of it. It’s the same guy who we happened to—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] speak to in <date>the summer</date>. So there were some nice connections there. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So it seems like—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It was a very interesting process. I was amazed at just how many left-leaning, pro-peace sentiments on what activist on backgrounds, there was also a guy who had worked—scientists who had worked on the <placeName>Manhattan</placeName> Project developing—developing the atomic bomb, who was very regretful of that, had retreated back to her [sic] hometown and was just working as a scientist at the local foundry. He lived a block and a half away from my home in <placeName>Burlington</placeName>. He contacted me to tell me about his anti-nuclear war and other activism, so I was—I got a new perspective on my own town—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—by going—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It seems like you had—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—south. Yeah. Very, very interesting.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It seems like you had quite the outpouring of support.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It was. It was quite wonderful. I was very fortunate. Not everyone—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—opposing the war had such support. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><persName>Dean Seymour</persName> was very personally supportive to me and very helpful in many ways, even though in the fall of—no, I guess it was <date>the spring of ’67</date>, so <date>the next spring</date>, there was the annual <orgName>ROTC [Reserve Officer Training Corps</orgName>] <date>march</date>/formation ceremony out on the football field. And by that time, there was an established antiwar movement led by <persName>Jonathan Mirsky</persName>, a professor of Chinese.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Wow!</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—of them—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—between us, this small group of peaceniks singing “We Shall Overcome” [chuckles] and the equally innocent, I must say, <orgName>ROTC</orgName> students. So there was a good bit of upset and arguing about the fact that the state troopers were called </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—was contrary to what <persName>Mirsky</persName> had been promised. So we actually had a march on the administrative building. The name escapes me. I don’t know why I can’t remember the name of—where the president and the deans offices—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><orgName>Parkhurst [Hall</orgName>]?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Pardon?</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Parkhurst</persName>. <persName>Parkhurst</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, that’s right. So we—we had a demonstration there and a small—actually, a small sit-in, a small occupation that only lasted, like, an hour or two at the most—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and it was quite peaceful. But that was interesting to me. I had a very good relationship with—with <persName>Dean Seymour</persName> before that and after that. But his role in the power structure was of course to do what he did, all of it very—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—interesting. But I never felt personally attacked or, or scorned or anything, but supported, actually. Very fortunate.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So after <date>summer</date> session ends and more students come back on campus, did the antiwar movement become more organized?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It did, and I think it was in <date>September</date> I got to know a student by the name of <persName>Mike Mikelson</persName> from the [unintelligible]. Anyway, somewhere in there. From the Class of ’67, so he was going into his senior year. Turned out he had gone to a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> school. His father had been a screenwriter who was banned during the blacklist, anti-communist hysteria blacklist in <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>, and he can do writing as well. So that was <persName>Mike</persName>’s background. He came from political [unintelligible]. His family had gone to a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> school. So we both were interested in doing something about the war, so <persName>Mike</persName> suggested that we have a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> style silent vigil on the Green.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—main pathway running from <orgName>Dartmouth Hall</orgName> to <placeName>Thayer</placeName> [Dining Room, now Class of <date>1953</date> Commons] at the Main Street side. Facing the administration building. We were right there on—on that would be the <placeName>North</placeName> side of that pathway, just standing for hours in silent vigil in <date>the first few days</date>. I think it was just once a week, I’m not sure if it was on <date>Wednesdays</date>. Anyways, we started that out. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">Mmm?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— activists. There were actually—one of the guys was a theology— professor of theology. And he had a printing press, and we’d go down to have a shot at printing press.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So he had this—articles and booklets, antiwar literature. And he set up a table right next to where our [chuckles]—our vigil was. Within <date>the first few weeks</date> he did that. <persName>Tommy Jackson</persName>, “T. J.”, was his name. He worked at the computer center. In any event, then some professors who were antiwar joined us, and a few other students. But it was quite small and pretty calm for the first—probably for that first term in the fall of—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—six- —there were many other things going on.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So the rest of <date>the year</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Pard’ me. Hmm?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I’m assuming you didn’t have the—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—standing on the <orgName>Green</orgName>—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. I’m sorry.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—during <date>the winter</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I seem to have lost you.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, no worries.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Are you there?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Can you hear me now? Hello?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Just barely. Just one second. How about if we take a few minutes’ break?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">And I’ll call you back in five minutes?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay. That’s good. I need to—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Hello? Okay.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Unintelligible]. Okay. Talk to you soon.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. All right. Sounds good. All right. Bye.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Hello, this is still <persName>Emily Burack</persName>. It is still <date>Monday</date>, February 15th, 2016. It is now 11:50 a.m., and I am speaking with <persName>Don Pease</persName>, who is in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, <placeName>Canada</placeName>, right now. We just took a brief break, and now we’re back.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">And the sound is better. Okay, so we were just speaking about the <date>weekly</date> silent vigils on the <orgName>Green</orgName> in the fall of ‘66</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, the fall of <date>’66</date>. But it built gradually, and we had the literature table, and I tried to stay abreast and stay in touch with the national antiwar efforts. The main thing was building up to a large march in <date>April</date> of ’67 in <placeName>New York City</placeName>,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—accommodating a speech at—in front of the <orgName>U.N.</orgName> [<orgName>United Nations</orgName>] by <persName>Martin Luther King</persName>, who was in ’67 increasingly taking a very expressive antiwar stance, so—and there was a buildup to that. There were various things. And the focus, as far as I was concerned, was the vigil. There were teach-ins, as I recall, and I think before I returned in <date>June</date> of ’66 there had been some things that spring. They did not carry into the <date>summer</date> school session, but there had been activities, and some of that kept on.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And there was a growing anti-war movement. The war was quite serious, quite bloody, quite horrific, and so there was more and more focus upon it. And, of course, it was part of the immediate future for all the students, with the draft.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And the issue—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—of conscription was an issue we could not avoid.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So this march in <date>April</date> of ’67—did you go down to <placeName>New York</placeName> for it?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes. And by that time, <persName>Carol-Anne</persName> had left <orgName>UCLA</orgName>, <date>just a few months</date> before graduating. I think it was probably <date>February</date> of <date>’67</date>. She was to graduate in <date>June</date>. She left, because we didn’t know—I should say, what had happened after I returned—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—my draft card was that I did go straight onto my parents, by my parents and by actually a lawyer who was a member of <orgName>the local draft board</orgName>. I was persuaded by them to formally [unintelligible] take back the card and apply for conscientious objector status, so that was what was going on from <date>the spring of ’66</date> right on through and probably ends in <date>’67</date>. My application was being investigated by the <orgName>FBI</orgName>. They sent the <orgName>FBI</orgName> out to talk to people everywhere, so I have a 19-page, single-spaced typed—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, my gosh!</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—<orgName>FBI</orgName> summary report—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—of people they talked to in my hometown and <placeName>California</placeName>, et cetera, et cetera, and up at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. In any event, there were appeal levels after I was eventually turned down, but—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What did you apply on the basis on?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the application was in process at that time. The conscientious objector application was in process for <date>that year and a half</date> or more.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What did you give your reason as, your reason for conscientious objector status?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Well, I didn’t come from a traditional peace church. It’s not <orgName>Mennonite Brethren [Church</orgName>] or <orgName>Quaker</orgName>—you know, a matter of faith, never—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible]. But I set out my view of things, not explicitly Christian religion but certainly some of the aspects of it. And the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> philosophy was certainly very—very strong. I don’t remember everything in the long—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—application. I certainly [unintelligible] how much [unintelligible] justice from my church. It’s very much encouraged. Didn’t have a strong doctrine other than [unintelligible] think for yourself, and in the <date>Sunday</date> school, my normal experience from fifth grades was that we were very strongly encouraged to think for ourselves, [unintelligible] critical of the issues of <date>the day</date>, so that certainly [unintelligible] aware of things. But in the context of—of doing good and—in any event, I just presented that, and it was not accepted—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—in any event. There was no real reason. That they should.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and in terms of those who refused to go into the <orgName>Army</orgName> and stayed in the country and went to jail, the sentences very much varied, depending on where you were in this country.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">They could go from <date>the full five years</date> and ten thousand [dollars] in the <placeName>South</placeName>, hardline areas to too much left in more traditionally antiwar areas. So the draft, in addition to coercing people to kill, was terribly, terribly inequitable in its impact on people and its [unintelligible] according to class, and race, and all the usual things.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">All the usual things.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So going back to <date>the spring of ’67</date>, your CO application is denied at this point.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">My CO application was pending.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, it was still pending. And <persName>Carol</persName> had come back?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">In <date>the spring of ’67</date>, did you say?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah. Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes, leading up to the march in <placeName>New York</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, so <persName>Carol</persName> had left <orgName>UCLA</orgName> <date>just a few months</date> before graduating because we didn’t know—I could be—the decision could have come down at any time, in which case the process of trial and going to jail, which was the only thing I was contemplating at the time,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—but [unintelligible], and <persName>Carol</persName> wanted to have as much—we both wanted to have as much time together as possible, and she was willing to not have.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So we were together then and were planning to get married, which we did in <date>June</date>, at <orgName>the Quaker Meeting House on Rope Ferry Road</orgName> [in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>]. But she had an interesting experience, coming from a wealthy, privileged background. Her parents were not supportive of her leaving—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible], just before graduating. And so she had no financial support. She was working, for the first time having a job, and she was working as a waitress [unintelligible] The Green Lantern—The Green something on Main Street. And [chuckles] she said she had a class experience for the first time. The <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students who were coming there would treat her very badly, had very condescending [unintelligible], until they found out she had been a university student—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and her boyfriend was a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> student. That was night and <date>day</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So she said. [Laughs.] [unintelligible]. We were—she, of course, had a separate room from—we lived in separate rooming house type situations.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Until we were married. I don’t think anyone would have rented to us, a non-married couple at that time.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I’m not sure. It just certainly wasn’t—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—on the—on the horizon at that time. So, yes, we were respectively together, and we—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—went, you know, to the <date>March</date> on <placeName>Washington</placeName> together,</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—along with other friends, who were—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. We’ll get to the <date>March</date> on <placeName>Washington</placeName>. I want to hear about the march in <placeName>New York</placeName>,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—when <orgName>MLK</orgName> spoke.	 Did you see—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I’m sorry?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">In <date>that spring</date>, before you were married, I think, you went down to <placeName>New York</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, that’s right. That was before we were married in <date>June</date>. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><date>June</date>. So what was that like?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, that was quite the immense gathering. And it was a very—a very joyful demonstration inasmuch as there were groups of high school students who were dancing and marching and shouting and having a good time in their opposition, and it was quite an immense <date>march</date>. Part of it assembled in <placeName>the Sheep Meadow</placeName> in <placeName>Central Park</placeName>, which is a huge area.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And it was—it was pretty well just completely packed with people waiting to line up for the march, and the march went on forever and ever. It was certainly the largest gathering and formal event of any kind of the opposition that I’d ever been involved in. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">Wow. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We stayed, I believe the first night—yes, we stayed with a fraternity brother who recently [unintelligible; 1:53:09] and he was working in Bedford-Stuyvesant, [a low-income neighborhood] in <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>. And we stayed in his apartment that night, <persName>Carol</persName> and I and some other friends who also were members of the U and were down for the antiwar march. We stayed there. So we stayed in a ghetto the first night.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Hmm!</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—a man by the name of [<persName>William H.] Schuman</persName>. So they had a penthouse on <placeName>Central Park East</placeName>. Huge. They weren’t there. Their daughter wasn’t there, but she had arranged for us to be able to [laughs] stay there.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—for one night immediately before the march. So we just went up from the ghetto to the luxurious, immense penthouse, with all sorts of original paintings and things I was not terribly familiar with as being in one’s residence. Anyway,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—we left from there. Went directly out to <placeName>Central Park</placeName>, to the demonstration.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—we stayed in suburban <placeName>New York</placeName>. And, of course, the contrasts and the attitudes amongst them all was—immense contrasts.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Very interesting perspectives to—to get in—in three or four nights such a range of poverty to wealth and the large middle class. What struck us about <placeName>Long Island</placeName> was the fear that was pervasive, the fear of crime. People were generally antiwar, and certainly the parents of her good friend, where we were staying, were strongly antiwar.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—of being white-white. Anyway, so the level of fear in suburbia really struck us as extraordinary, given what was the actual level of threat. But that was a terribly interesting experience.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">They were trying to dominate everything. But <persName>Chomsky</persName> actually got to speak, and he is immensely impressive with the scholarship. His level of—level voice and level-headed outrage was just like a factual basis that he had established his conclusions and hearing him made quite a bit impression on me. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—your responsibility. Anyway, that was all coming together, bonding at that time. And it was a terrible situation. It was an awful war with a result of the destruction, but in terms of social movement and intellectual activity and inquiry, it was a very alive, intense time, of course.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">At the same time, personal future via conscription, volunteer [unintelligible] very seriously.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">I went to <date>summer</date> school again. I was trying to get all my credits as quickly—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—as possible, and I worked at a variety [sic] of jobs, and we lived in a nice apartment. Finally got to live together at—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yay!</u>
      <u who="PEASE">— at number [unintelligible], quite near the street, alleyway that runs alongside <orgName>the Dartmouth Bookstore</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So anyway, we were there for <date>the summer</date> and were married, as I say, at <orgName>the Quaker Meeting House</orgName>. And Professor <persName>Robin</persName> [<persName>J.] Scroggs</persName>, who had conducted <name type="event">the New Testament</name> seminar in which we met—he attended and spoke at our wedding. In a <orgName>Quaker</orgName> ceremony where people being married, married one another. It’s legally signed by the clerk of <orgName>the Friends Meeting</orgName>, but there is nobody officiating as such. It’s the usual silent meeting, and at some point the people being married stand up and say their vows to one another in front of everyone, and then they sit down, and if anyone feels called upon to speak, then they stand up and do so.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—in <date>the fall</date> of <date>’67</date>. As I say, quite a wonderfully supportive environment, [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah, it sounds great.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. I think I had an appeal-level hearing <date>that summer</date>, for which I went back to <placeName>Iowa</placeName> that was, and it was still pending. That’s all.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">So certainly from <date>the fall</date>, <date>the previous fall</date> of <date>’66</date>, right on through, the antiwar movement and the antiwar activities had continued to build a good deal at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and I was very much involved with them, and <persName>Carol</persName> was as well. In fact, <date>the summer of 1967</date>, <date>the summer</date> we were married, was called <name type="event">Vietnam Summer</name>, and it was a nationwide project to help students spend <date>the summer</date> doing antiwar organizing wherever they happened to live, and a bunch of people had organized <name type="event">Vietnam Summer</name> at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and we were—we were very much a part of that. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And the war was still expanding in terms of American bombing and American troops on the ground and free fire films and all sorts of horrendous things. And the movement was much, much larger on—on the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> campus by the fall of <date>’67</date> so that our—our vigils were—one center point for activities, and the literature was given out there, and people would I guess fairly—I guess in <date>the year</date> prior to that thing going on, people would occasionally stop and want to talk or would challenge or whatever, and then one of us would leave the line and—and things were silent and go speak with them and have literature. So it was quite active constantly, trying to organize, spreading the word. And it was in fact building considerably.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—so we had a lot of people at the vigil, to the point where I believe it had to be that fall, pro-war people took umbrage and organized a counter-demonstration, lining up on the other side of the pathway. They announced this, called it, and so it became the standoff. I haven’t—I didn’t save the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> accounts of it or whatever, but I’m sure it’s there.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It does exist, yeah. I have read it. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, okay. What date is it that it took place?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I don’t have it in front of me, but it was that fall.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The memory is not completely shot.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I remember going up to my old haunt in the Tower Room at Baker Library [<orgName>Fisher Ames Baker Memorial Library</orgName>, now <persName>Baker-Berry Library</persName>] and looking down on a demonstration, and I don’t know if there was a photo. I think there was from it in The <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. But it was quite striking, the lines of people facing one another across—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—many, many pathways on the <orgName>Green</orgName>. They were immense, It turned out to be several thousand people taking pretty well over the entire Green, with the antiwar people in slight majority—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah, I actually—I just looked back in my notes. It was <date>the spring of ’67</date>, too. It says there was roughly a thousand people on the Green.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, it was <date>the spring</date>, not the fall.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Then the counter-demonstration took place.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes, and I think it continued into <date>the fall</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And roughly a thousand, not thousands. Okay.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah, roughly a thousand.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Still, still, that’s many—that’s so many people!</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It says—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It was large, and it was interesting, and certainly the dialogue was—was engaged, so—[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It said—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It wasn’t just shouting at one another.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">No.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">There was some of that, I gather, but my experience was mostly people would talk and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—sometimes it could be heated, but there was—there was engagement, anyway.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah. The article says the peace students had the majority. I don’t know if you remember, a slight—a slight majority. [Chuckles.] Well, anyway, so that fall—did you participate in any more demonstrations like the one in <placeName>New York</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes, the big—the biggest demonstration was called the <date>March</date> on <placeName>Washington</placeName>,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—which was over I think <date>October 21st</date>, if I’m not mistaken—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and was a march from the Mall, from the Lincoln Memorial and—assembling there and going a long ways back towards—from the Lincoln Memorial back towards the Washington Monument, assembling to march past the—to the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> and, to the extent possible, surround the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>. That was the massive demonstration of—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">How did you hear about it?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, it was the focus of the antiwar movement, a national movement, and I and others were in touch with that. We tried to coordinate with them with certainly literature. <persName>Cornell</persName> [University] was one of the places were this literature was published, and they were very well organized, so I was in fairly close touch with people at <orgName>Cornell</orgName>. And it just was a focus of the antiwar—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—network. Because this massive effort to have this huge thing, demonstration, including civil disobedience at the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> that fall. So that was a major focus of what we were doing, and quite a number of us went down.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So when you went down, how long were you there for? What was the march like?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was <date>several days</date>. I know that the night before, my friend <persName>Paul</persName> [<persName>S.] Stetzer [Jr.</persName>, Class of <date>1967</date>], who is my good friend to <date>this day</date>. <persName>Paul Stetzer</persName>, he was a fellow member of DU. And he was in touch with a DU member who had graduated and lived in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, and his parents had a big home and we were welcome to stay there, so a large group of us stayed there. He was one of the—I think he was the only—the guy who hosted us. I think he was the only black student in DU at the time I was there. I—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Just to clarify,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[unintelligible] black students on campus was not large, but he—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Do you—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—hosted us. They—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">DU is <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Hmm? He was a—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry. Sorry to interrupt you. Just to clarify, DU is <orgName>Dartmouth Christian Union</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, I’m sorry,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—DU is <orgName>Delta Upsilon</orgName>,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, okay. [Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—a fraternity.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, okay. Oh, okay. Just—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I just got confused. Okay.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The other is <orgName>DCU</orgName>.  Yes, no, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, okay.</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><orgName>Delta Upsilon</orgName>. It later became <persName>Foley House</persName>, I think—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—after ’67. I wasn’t active with it, so I don’t know.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">No.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry. I just wanted to clarify that.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[unintelligible] <persName>Foley House</persName> disaffiliated because of racial policies by the national fraternity. That’s all.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But at that time,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Sorry. I just wanted to clarify that.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So you stayed—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, Yes.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">There was definitely <orgName>Dartmouth Christian Union</orgName> was the center for all antiwar and civil rights activities, so there were many, many people from <orgName>DCU</orgName>, who affiliated one way or another with <orgName>DCU</orgName>, who came down on the march. We didn’t hire a bus. Everybody made his or her way there on their own, but there was quite a—quite a group.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. So you were staying with a DU brother, or an alumni [sic; alumnus].</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">And did he participate with you guys in the march <date>the next day</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I don’t—I don’t remember about that. I mainly remember his  mother being very warm and hospitable. I don’t know if <persName>Mike</persName> was even there.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That’s—that’s unclear. But certainly there were—in <placeName>New York</placeName> there had been very large contingents of—of people from <placeName>Harlem</placeName>, black students from <placeName>Harlem</placeName> high schools and other areas, so there was a large contingent from <placeName>New York</placeName>. And certainly there were good numbers of African-Americans at <date>the March</date> on <placeName>Washington</placeName>, including—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—prominent civil rights groups [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. And it was led by—the very first line, once we started marching towards the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> from the Lincoln Memorial—the front line was <persName>Benjamin [M.] Spock</persName> and—what’s his name? <persName>William Sloane Coffin [Jr.</persName>], a prominent minister from <orgName>Yale</orgName>. <persName>Norman Mailer</persName> and <persName>Noam Chomsky</persName> and a bunch of other prominent people clearly led the demonstration, and they led off with the people willing to and determined to commit civil disobedience and be arrested at the Pentagon.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And I was of that persuasion. I wasn’t anywhere near the front in that group. [Chuckles.] But the people I was with were also quite looking to be involved in civil disobedience and were prepared for that, [unintelligible]. And a friend of mine, <persName>Paul [W.] Beach [Jr.</persName>] from the Class of 1967—he eventually ended up going to jail rather than go into the <orgName>Army</orgName> and organize. He was with me, and we were arrested together at that demonstration at the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What do you—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We only spent 12 hours in jail, and they were prepared for a large—I think there were security jails in the area, so they had prepared to deal with several thousand people. I think it was just over a thousand who were—who were arrested.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—didn’t get a chance to [unintelligible], unfortunately. But they were around. And I [unintelligible] a guy by the name of [<orgName>Napthtali</orgName>] “Tuli” <placeName>Kupferberg</placeName>, who was a prominent member of the antiwar, civil rights, aging hippie band called The <persName>Fugs</persName>, F-u-g-s, out of the Village [<placeName>Greenwich Village</placeName>, <placeName>New York City</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>]. He was in our—our group. I was mainly thrilled that he was there. So anyway—[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It wasn’t a harsh prison experience by any means, and we were only there for 12 hours.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So when you went to the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>, you all sat down as a means of civil disobedience?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Those of us who were—who were—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">You and <persName>Paul</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—engaging.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not anyone, by any means. <persName>Carol-Anne</persName>—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Uh,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—wasn’t comfortable for that, but she was providing—but she could do <orgName>First Aid</orgName>, helping people. There were some people who were a bit injured and such, but that wasn’t common. So people decided what they wanted to do.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And there were—there were various contingents, of course, of this massive crowd. I don’t know what the official count was, but it was certainly well over 100,000 both in <placeName>New York</placeName> and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—at the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>. And there was a wide variety of—of contingents, of groupings with different approaches, different points of view, different actions they were willing to take. There were people such as [Beat poet <persName>I.] Allen Ginsberg</persName>, who had—oh, he was also in the front line with <persName>Chomsky</persName> and Spock, et cetera—<persName>Ginsberg</persName>, who was leading a group who were going to chant “om” and levitate the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> by the power of spiritual power. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh! [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So there was that approach. And then there were people who, I’m convinced, had to be agent provocateurs—in other words, hired by the government or [unintelligible], to do provocative actions. There were some who were actually trying to physically assault and get into doors and things. Quite far out. Just a very few of them. And then there was a large group of people who, following the civil rights movement tactics, were quite willing and prepared to engage in civil—nonviolent civil disobedience. That was the vast, pervading approach. But there were—there were fringe groups in there doing other things.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So how long were you at the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> before you were arrested?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, pretty well—between being I guess that’s called the Mall, between the <orgName>Lincoln</orgName> and <orgName>the Washington Memorials</orgName>—it was <date>all day</date>, from early in the morning—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—until it was well after dark, [unintelligible], so it got dark relatively early, but it was <date>a long day</date> there, and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—overnight. We were released the following morning. But despite being, you know, quite a team and intellectually stimulating interest in a brief, brief 12-hour jail experience, the fact that it had jail had some impact on me.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">When you were taken in, were you, like, questioned or you were just put in this room with the 50 other or so?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We were on a paddy wagon, and then we were processed. We were not questioned, no.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—I was [unintelligible] within <date>a few weeks</date> of being back [unintelligible] a couple of <orgName>FBI</orgName> agents. And they wanted to know my intentions and my views and if I could tell them about any identifying marks on my body. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, wow! [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Laughs.] So anyway, yes, they came to <persName>Scroggs</persName>’ house that we were fortunate enough to be occupying at that time. Came to interview me about my intentions. But—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Do you—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—at that point, I had returned my draft card again.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">In <date>that fall</date>, building up to—well, from—from <date>April</date> of <date>’67</date>, the big antiwar demo in <placeName>New York</placeName>, there was a movement to return draft cards. There was some burning draft cards. I remember witnessing the burning of draft cards during <date>April</date> [unintelligible] <placeName>New York</placeName>. And certainly in <date>the fall</date>, leading up to the <date>march</date> on the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> and after that [unintelligible] there was a strong movement to try to organize a mass civil disobedience, not cooperating with the draft. So as part of that, I did return my draft card again that—that fall.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And I think the reason for the <orgName>FBI</orgName> interviewing me was both the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> arrest and the returning of the draft card.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">How did you react when the <orgName>FBI</orgName> showed up at your door?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I’d had previous contact with the <orgName>FBI</orgName> because of my CO application, so it wasn’t hugely scary. It was—you know, I was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—I was [unintelligible], I think. But I don’t remember other—other reactions. I have had them, but—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—they haven’t stayed with me.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.] So nothing too significant.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So when you returned—so you were released 12 hours after your arrest.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">And did you go straight back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I came back, and—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">What were your next steps, kind of?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—then—from then until we actually left—on <date>December 10th</date> we left the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> to come to <placeName>Canada</placeName>, so after that march, I hadn’t fully made up my mind about what we were doing or were going to do, whether I was going to continue to plan to go to jail or—<placeName>Canada</placeName> became an option that I was thinking about after we were married. It was the idea of my going to jail was—was very difficult for my mother to accept and for <persName>Carol-Anne</persName> as well. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Those were the options that I considered, so that’s the decision we made. And we left from <placeName>Chicago</placeName>. We actually went back to the <placeName>Midwest</placeName> and to <placeName>Erie</placeName> [<placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>], where <persName>Carol</persName>’s parents lived, and we went—we flew from <placeName>Chicago</placeName> to <placeName>Toronto</placeName> on <date>December 10th, 1967</date>. That’s <date>the day</date> that we always in our family celebrate as a personal <name type="event">Canada Day</name>,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The national holiday is <date>July first</date>, called <name type="event">Canada Day</name>, but we have—have our <persName>Pease</persName> family <placeName>Canada</placeName> Day on <date>December 10th</date>, <date>the anniversary of the day</date> we came to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. We have always always felt that was very good decision, in terms of the quality of our lives and for raising our children and just for being in [unintelligible.] Very glad to have the chance—have had the chance to be Canadians.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But that was quite a big decision, of course, to change course like that. And I still have some mixed feelings about not having followed the pure path of going to jail. My friend <persName>Paul—Paul—Beach</persName> is his last name; remember, the Class of <date>’67</date>. He was with me at the <date>March</date> on <placeName>Washington</placeName>. We were arrested together there. He’s still quite a close, good good friend.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—Vietnamese G.I. in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And I think he was in some jeopardy actually, as well. So they kept him in the States. Kept him at Fort Benning I think <placeName>Georgia</placeName>. And he became of the journalists—he became one of the editors of the large antiwar newspaper on the campus and quite openly organized against the war. By that point, the late 69, basically—it was low-level, a lot of unwillingness to fight, and the <orgName>Army</orgName> at that point had to just tolerate the open antiwar activity because to suppress it would have been—allowed it to grow even faster, so—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and organize against the war [unintelligible]. <persName>Dick Olson</persName> did that, and terrifically effective. He went on to a career with the <orgName>UAW</orgName> [<orgName>United Auto Workers Union</orgName>] communications department and stayed in handling civil rights matters</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">That certainly was the most effective thing to do, and I think my friend <persName>Paul Beach</persName> had intended to do that, but instead in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> it became time for him to take a symbolic step across the line and step forward after induction [unintelligible.] He found that he just could not do it. And much to his surprise, ended up in jail from that point on. [Chuckles.] He was tired of trial. So he ended up getting out in <date>three and a half years</date> sentence and served —</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Wow.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—two and a half of other. So I certainly know the impact of that jail experience upon him.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And from a personal point of view, I made the right decision for myself, for <persName>Carol</persName> [unintelligible] to come to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. It wasn’t the most effective antiwar decision I could have made, nor the purest decision I could have done, but—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">It was the right thing for you.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Chuckles.] Yeah. I am satisfied with—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible]. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So when you got to <placeName>Canada</placeName>, what were your next steps in settling down there?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Well, it was quite—quite a startling change. Nineteen- —</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—sixty-seven, <date>a centennial year</date>, [unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Hmm.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] Canadian confederation <date>’67</date> in my [unintelligible] there were world expositions, several expositions of <date>that year</date>, in conjunction with the centennial. And it was a huge outpouring of self-confidence and energy and pride in <placeName>Canada</placeName>, so we came out at very much a high point [unintelligible] English-Canadian identity, and [unintelligible] regarding the [unintelligible] energy. And we were struck, outcasts, actually.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We stood for liberal government, liberal part of the <placeName>Canada</placeName> forms of government of <placeName>Canada</placeName> in <date>1967</date>, <persName>Lester [B.] Pearson</persName>, who was the Nobel Peace Prize winner for his actions over <placeName>the Suez Canal</placeName> at the time of the <placeName>Suez</placeName> crisis. He was prime minister. And <persName>Pierre Elliott Trudeau</persName>, a cabinet minister and minister of justice. And they were [unintelligible] that we could not [unintelligible] could be said [chuckles]—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—the position in <placeName>North America</placeName>, not only about the war—and they were quite openly welcoming draft dodgers and even deserters of that time, [unintelligible]. And they were talking about some political social issues, liberalizations as well. <persName>Trudeau</persName> especially, with the minister of justice and the following liberal party [unintelligible]. </u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.] </u>
      <u who="PEASE">[Unintelligible] realities compared to what was happening in the <placeName>States</placeName> in <date>1968</date>. So we came in <date>December</date> of <date>’67</date>, and <date>February</date> of <date>’68</date> was the Tet Offensive, the uprising which saw the South Vietnamese [unintelligible]. <persName>The Viet Cong</persName> [in <orgName>the National Liberation Front</orgName> [<orgName>NLF</orgName>] of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> being on the ground of <orgName>the U.S. Embassy</orgName>. And [unintelligible] announces an uprising that set the tone for the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> having to get out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> from that time forward. There was that <date>February</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and students. And so there was a growing antiwar movement. And <persName>Lyndon Johnson</persName> had to vow he would not seek reelection. The assassination of <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> and then of <persName>Robert Kennedy</persName> within the sight of the convention [unintelligible] after [unintelligible] African-American community—[unintelligible] come out and there could not have been a greater contrast to what was happening [unintelligible] in <placeName>Canada</placeName> and [unintelligible]. So it was not—our heads were spinning from sorting everything out, so—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] country [unintelligible] country and what was happening in <placeName>Canada</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] not only in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> but in <placeName>Canada</placeName> and away and unable to go back and impact on my family. All of those things [unintelligible] active in too short of a time.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah. So in terms of that, how were you feeling about maybe not being able to return to <placeName>America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, I was certainly quite focused, even though I was living in <placeName>Canada</placeName>, and being involved in the Canadian-centered activities to a good extent—attention and [unintelligible]. I thought—I was still very, very caught up in and very focused on what was happening in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, especially with regard to the war, but everything else. It was a time of immense tumult and cultural changes, as all of the political [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I was fortunate in the sense that many of the people in the political movements I was involved in here in <placeName>Canada</placeName>—and I was in those movements, it just happened I was the only American in those groups. There were people by [unintelligible] who were becoming strongly national. They were very concerned about a security position in <placeName>Canada</placeName> relative to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> And they would let me know when I was far too focused, centered on the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> and not paying attention to where I lived now. So that was—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—they were gentle about it, in a good Canadian way.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But they let me know that I really should learn about <placeName>Canada</placeName> and think about being here, and to a certain extent we [unintelligible] to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> the reality for Canadians is you always have to be extremely aware of what’s happening in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> because—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—it’s going to affect you very, very much. But I’ve grown since and tried a moderate [chuckles], of course keeping our  Canadian stereotype. A moderate—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—was taking hold and was—was beneficial, and that—that was certainly helpful to me, to encourage me to get my bearing here and—while still being incredibly interested in what was happening in the <placeName>States</placeName>, to build my life here.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Anyway, during that <date>eight-year</date> period when I did not go back, my family was very good. They came to visit. But both grandmothers died. I couldn’t go to their funerals. So <orgName>FBI</orgName> agents attended both [chuckles] of them.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That’s pretty obvious. There were those things that I got cut off, but that also gave me the opportunity to focus on <placeName>Canada</placeName> and to become integrated here and to see myself and <persName>Carol</persName> as well. I’m very much inclined to say we see ourselves as new Canadian. And, of course, having time to be interested, if not wholly focused on—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—what was happening [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So you settled into life in <placeName>Canada</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We settled in,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—quite well.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—yes. I stopped striving. In a sense, I had a period of—of what must have been <date>15 years</date>—no, it’s <date>nine years</date>—I should get my chronology straight. I worked at a clerical job at <orgName>the National Library of Canada</orgName>, [now part of <orgName>Library and Archives Canada</orgName>], a librarian type of job, and was politically active but did not personally try to establish myself in a profession or anything like that until I decided to go to law school in <date>’76</date>, so it was just short of <date>nine years</date> from coming to <placeName>Canada</placeName> [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible]. A lot of that application came from—in <date>the spring of 1970</date>, so <date>two and a half years</date> after we came, I became very ill with Crohn’s disease, which is an inflammatory around the intestines. And really had to take it particularly easy and work 30 hours rather than 40 a week, et cetera, et cetera, for <date>a number of years</date> after that. And then I had another diagnosis, multiple sclerosis, in <date>the later ’70s</date>, in the middle of law school [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Which turned out to be false. I was undiagnosed after <date>20 years</date>. But anyway, a bunch of health concerns as well as being sort of stunned, I would think. I’m certainly not starting along on the path I would have if there hadn’t been a war and turnover in our lives [unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">So that was a period of taking stock and of relative quiescence except for the illnesses. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So you went to law school. Did you enjoy it?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, I enjoyed it.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">How long were you there? [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><date>Three years</date>, until the early part of my last—my <date>third year</date>. I got the symptoms of what was then diagnosed was MS. It turned out to be inflammatory arthritis, not rheumatoid but something like that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Anyway, that caused another pause, so, because I had these two major health problems, I—I didn’t finish my fourth, <date>the following year</date>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That was another reason. I thought I had two major—<orgName>Crohn’s</orgName> and multiple sclerosis, so I did not fully pursue the legal profession. I did not go and article and do <date>the five years</date> of—of junior slavery to get a position, get established.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.] </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But [unintelligible] legal skills, legal training as a staff member at the public service employee union, dealing with human rights and a lot of disability and immigration and general legal matters. So it was good decision to go to law school—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—I was able to put it to use, [unintelligible], so that was very good. But there wasn’t a significant period when I wasn’t pursuing anything at all like that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. So you worked as—for this public service employee union for the rest of your working career?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, for the—yes, for <date>the last 18, 19 years</date> of my working career, and that was very satisfying because it was a progressive union so that—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—I’m in charge of things like disability rights, we were one of the large unions in the country, and we were the leading union fighting that battle on the union front. And, of course, [unintelligible] moved along quite rapidly there, for [unintelligible] more rapidly in <placeName>Canada</placeName>, so that—that was successful in <date>ten years</date>. And eventually [unintelligible]. So on that front—that was a very nice time to be able to be a small part of that, and within our duty to do [unintelligible] a part of that. We had some significant victories. Nothing earth shattering, but they all added to the buildup of [unintelligible]. So that was very satisfying to be a part of. </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] opportunity so I’m glad I was able to be part of that.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">So as sort of one last question I have for you: How do you view your years at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and <date>your years</date> as someone that was very involved in the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> antiwar movement? How do you view that as a lasting impact on kind of your life in <placeName>Canada</placeName> following—like, what do you view as the biggest impact of <date>those years</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Of my experiences at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> on my life in <placeName>Canada</placeName>, my adult life?</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah, and your experiences in activism.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Very crucial. Certainly having the opportunity to go to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and to be successful at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> helped my self-confidence in—one second. I’m getting interference.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Oh, okay.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Just—I’ll put the phone down for one second.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay.  </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Hello, <persName>Emily</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Hi. I’m still here. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">My hearing aid is acting up. I don’t know—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—if you can hear all the beeps, but they were going crazy.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">No. Oh, no! I—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">They seem to have calmed down now. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Good to hear. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">You were asking me about how <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> had an impact on my adult life in <placeName>Canada</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Yes, and the impact of your activist <date>years</date>. Or your activism, yes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> certainly set the pattern, the interests and activities I had and developed at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, certainly outdoors activities: hiking and canoeing, all those sorts of wonderful <placeName>North Woods</placeName> things. Where better place could one be but in <placeName>Canada</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—for pursuing even further? And to be in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>. We eventually, after <date>a few years</date>, moved from <placeName>London</placeName> to <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, the capital. And <placeName>Ottawa</placeName> is beautifully situated on the edge of the wilderness. You know, you go 20 minutes and you’re in a national park, which has—it’s very good at an illusion of wilderness,—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and there’s actual wilderness, which goes on and on and on, not far beyond that. So living in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, you have great access to anything outdoors like that. It’s the confluence of three rivers, a canal so water—so anyway, outdoors <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. The interest that I had when I came to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and was able to greatly develop at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, even more so, certainly, in <placeName>Canada</placeName>. And our family has done lots of wilderness canoeing. We still do it as a family activity, as much as I’m able. We rearrange things so I can still participate. That’s a great joy.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—on such things, so it—it set the table and reinforced—I find it reinforced and developed tendencies I had when I came there, some of them quiet, and some with varied tendencies, but the social justice issue orientation was there. I just needed a means for its expression.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I’m not sure the exact—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—of family income—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">—criteria.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">I do know that about half of the student body is on financial aid now, and it’s need-blind [admissions], so—which is pretty neat.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. So those have improved greatly. And when I have walked around—</u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—and watched people relating and going to <persName>Thayer</persName> and listened to people talk, it’s a vastly better place than it was [chuckles] in—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible]. And I’m happy for that. That doesn’t mean that my experience was bad. It could have been even better. [Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="BURACK"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">But that was—I was quite thankful to have gone to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and for that, personally, I always found it a very supportive community. It was like being in opposition and the war movement. <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was not—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—[unintelligible] at all.</u>
      <u who="BURACK">Well, that’s good.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. No, not for the—not for the interview. No, that’s—</u>
      <u who="BURACK">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That’s fine. I’m all talked out. Thank you for—for being interested.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
