<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="PEASE"/>
        <person xml:id="PEARL"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="PEARL">This is <persName>Joshua Pearl</persName> with the Dartmouth Vietnam Project interviewing <persName>Carol-Anne Pease</persName>. It is currently <date>August 12th, 2015</date>, at around two o’clock. I’m sitting in the <orgName>Rauner</orgName> [Special Collections] Library on campus at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName> in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, and I’m interviewing <persName>Carol</persName> by phone, and she is sitting in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, <placeName>Canada</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, that’s right.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So, <persName>Carol</persName>, can you start out and tell us when and where you were born?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes. I was born <date>July 14th, 1945</date>, in <placeName>New York City</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about your childhood?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Sure. We moved from <placeName>New York</placeName> when I was four, and we lived in <placeName>Roslyn Heights</placeName>, <placeName>Long Island</placeName>, until I was <date>11</date>, and I would say those were really wonderful <date>years</date> for me. I was very happy there. I had lots of friends. I loved school. It was just a lovely time. It was a great place. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And was there any specific reason why you moved from <placeName>New York City</placeName> to <placeName>Roslyn Heights</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, that was—my parents decided to do that. My father worked in <placeName>New York City</placeName>, as many people did at that time, and I was an only child, but they felt that suburban life would be better for a child than city life, that I would have more scope and, you know, it just would be a more child-friendly environment. So I think that’s basically why they moved there.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what neighborhood did you live in in <placeName>New York City</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, it was in <placeName>Manhattan</placeName>. I don’t know exactly where. I just know it was somewhere in sort of the main <placeName>Manhattan</placeName> area, near what was called <orgName>the Lying-In Hospital</orgName>, which is where I was born. I don’t know if it still exists. [Transcriber’s note: It was a maternity hospital called <orgName>the Society for the Lying-In Hospital</orgName> in <placeName>the Stuyvesant Square</placeName> neighborhood of <placeName>Manhattan</placeName>. Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Society_for_the_Lying-In_Hospital ]</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And could you tell me about school and <placeName>Roslyn</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, it was—you know, there were—at that point, they distinguished—I hope they don’t now, but what they called the smart kids, the average kids and the slower kids, and there were three different classes. Everyone was kind of aware of that. I was in the smart kid class, and a lot of kids in the average kid class did really well later, so it’s not—you know, I wouldn’t say it was definitive, but certainly there was a lot of—it was a kind of power and prestige within the school. I found it—you know, I found it very interesting. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what was your favorite subject in school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I guess, mmm—I guess all the way along it was kind of English. You know, reading—I loved reading, and I was always very interested in English.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you mentioned that you moved to a very Jewish neighborhood and that you weren’t Jewish. Was there any reason why you think you moved to that specific neighborhood rather than a different neighborhood?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I guess—I think it was just a growing neighborhood. I don’t think my parents had any, like, particular reason. You know what I mean? Like, I think it’s just that that was where, you know, there were houses there. It was very pretty, and, you know, they just—they just thought that was great. I mean, they were not—they were prejudiced about most things, but they were not prejudiced about Jewish people, so that wouldn’t have been a problem for them either way. But I don’t think it was a specific plan. You know what I mean? I think it just happened.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And can you tell me about your family life, growing up?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, my parents—my father was from <placeName>Denmark</placeName>. He came from <placeName>Denmark</placeName> when he was <date>21 years old</date>. He had been very—come from a very wealthy, educated background. His dad had been a doctor. But he felt that <placeName>Denmark</placeName> was too limited. He wanted—he loved the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> And he was very much keen on the American dream and on doing what you wanted to do and being who you wanted to be. That’s what it meant to him. So when he was <date>21</date>, he decided to move to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> And all his life, he just remained super happy to be in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> He was quite—as I said, pretty right wing and pretty authoritarian, but he had humor, he had elegance, he was quite aristocratic.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what <date>year</date> did—going back a bit, what <date>year</date> did your father immigrate to <placeName>America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, let’s see. He was <date>21</date>, and he was born in <date>1899</date>, so I guess that would be—yeah—yeah, that would have been <date>1920</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you mentioned how your mother was an artist, a dancer, an actress. What was your father’s occupation? What did he do?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">He was a businessman. He started as an office boy in a small company, and he ended up being the president of that company, so he was an executive in a small company, but he ended up as a CEO.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And do you remember what the company did?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. The name of it was <orgName>Robeson Process Company</orgName>, R-o-b-e-s-o-n Process Company. It provided chemicals for making paper. And he was allied with <orgName>Hammermill Paper Company</orgName>, which was in <placeName>Erie</placeName>, <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>. That was their main customer, and I think they ended up—he ended up blending his company with <orgName>Hammermill</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you mentioned earlier about how your parents would discriminate, how your father was conservative and authoritarian. How did that play into family life?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, he certainly—he certainly was very set in his ways. [Chuckles.] And, you know, everything was very scheduled. Everything was very organized—you know, eating at the same time, doing things at the same time. You know, everything was just along a very set agenda. I think—I guess when I was—my experience, when I lived in <placeName>New York City</placeName>—we lived in a big apartment building, and there the cleaners were all black. And I remember I used to go down to be with the cleaners, you know, in the basement, and I had lots of fun with them. I dressed up in their shoes and all this. So my experience with black people was always very positive.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What was his political stance compared to your political stance? You said you had a lot of differences in thought.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. Well, he certainly was very active in <orgName>the Republican Party</orgName>, which is probably much [chuckles] like it is <date>today</date>. That sounds just crazy. Anyway, yeah, he was big in <orgName>the Republican Party</orgName>, a big fundraiser and known for that. He was a member of <orgName>the John Birch Society</orgName>, which—I don’t think that exists anymore, but that was a very right-wing organization in the <date>’50s</date> and <date>’60s</date> in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> So he, you <placeName>know,—certainly</placeName> <date>today</date> he would definitely be, like, the far right of Republicans.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">And I just need—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—what was your stance?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, my stance—I guess I would be more—I guess what at that time, what would be called <date>today</date> a liberal Democrat. You know what I mean? Like, I probably—I wouldn’t have been—until I went into university, I was sort of with intellectual politics, and I that would have been—yeah, that would have been, like, <date>today</date> what you’d call a liberal Democrat.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did you start developing these views by the time you were 11? What brought you this path?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It’s just my father would make comments—you know, negative comments about black people and say that they shouldn’t get the vote; they’re just out of the trees and, you know, all these things. And my ex- —it just offended me. I guess that’s why I became, and part why I became a social worker. I’m very oriented to—I just was always oriented to equality and fairness. And I don’t know why, but it just was something very important to me, and I just couldn’t accept—you know, it just wasn’t my experience. I didn’t feel that way about Black people, and I felt that I just—I just would argue with him starting about that, starting about Blacks and Mexicans. And, you know, we would argue about—sort of from a human point of view, and then as I got older it would be more a political perspective. You know, when I was younger, it was just more defending people that I felt he was putting down.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you have any friends that were minorities: blacks or Latinos?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I actually really didn’t. I didn’t really—I mean, I just didn’t meet them until actually I went to <orgName>UCLA</orgName> [<orgName>University of California</orgName>, Los Angeles]—I went to university. It wasn’t experience except—you know, it really wasn’t friends; it was just I guess my experience with the ladies at the—you know, in the apartment. And just [unintelligible] and what I read and so on, I guess.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And your mother, you said, was a dancer and an actress. How did she affect your life growing up? Because we already saw how your father—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—affected you a bit. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, she was very—kind of a mix. Because of her illness, being very paranoid and depressed, there was a lot of—I tended to be more of a mother to her than she was to me, looking after her, making sure she was okay, and she started drinking. She drank a lot. I was more a caretaker of her. But she had a fantastic sense of humor. She was just very, very funny. And I really enjoyed the humor. Like, every so often she’d just have this—you know, she’d just be very witty and very lively when she was in a good mood. And I appreciated that. I liked that when she was that way. And that did draw me to her.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you said you lived in <placeName>Roslyn</placeName> until <date>about 11 years old</date>, correct?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And where did you live after that?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">My parents—we moved to <placeName>Erie</placeName>, <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>, which is just right on the lake. That is where the <orgName>Hammermill Paper Company</orgName> was, and so my father—his company just became a part of <orgName>Hammermill</orgName>, and so we moved there when he became president of the company, of <orgName>the Robeson Process Company</orgName>, not of <orgName>Hammermill</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what did you notice—did you notice any big differences or changes between life in <placeName>Roslyn</placeName> compared to <placeName>Erie</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yeah. Yeah, that was hugely different, hugely different. It was a small town, and very class oriented. Basically a working-class town. And I had—I didn’t realize this, but, you know, my father was associated with a company, you know, that was quite a big employer in the town, and so he was very well known. You know, he had a fair amount of power. This was something I just wasn’t aware of at all. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">So I guess I should ask what type of class makeup was it in <placeName>Roslyn</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, <persName>Roslyn</persName> would be upper middle class. Yeah, everybody was upper middle class.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So you didn’t feel left out at <placeName>Roslyn</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. No.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. I also should ask you what was your maiden name?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, <persName>Riis</persName> [pronounced REESE]. I e-mailed you that, I think. It’s R-i-i-s. It’s quite a common Danish last name. It’s spelled R-i-i-s but pronounced <persName>REESE</persName>, like R-E-E-S-E.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And jumping back to <placeName>Erie</placeName>, so you didn’t enjoy school that much.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">But did you have any friends at all?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I had, like, one or two. No, I didn’t—it’s not like I had nobody, but just one or two friends. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you still experience the same type of freedoms that you had in <placeName>Roslyn</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, not as much because it was a small town. My mother started to become more and more paranoid. She was more and more worried about, you know, the town and did people like me and did people like her and would things—you know, what would happen, so she was more, you know, controlling of me. You know what I mean. Like, she didn’t want me to do anything, and she was careful that I got home at a certain time and all that kind of stuff. So it was more limited for me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Although I still liked to ride bikes and do stuff, but—yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what happened after eighth grade?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I was sent to—I went to a boarding school, a girls’ boarding school in <orgName>the Philadelphia Main Line</orgName>. It was called <orgName>The Baldwin School</orgName>, and it still exists but in a different form. It was in <placeName>Bryn Mawr</placeName>, <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And do you want to tell me about life at <orgName>The Baldwin School</orgName>, and maybe why you were sent to <orgName>The Baldwin School</orgName> rather than continue at public school at <placeName>Erie</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, my mother told me later, not at the time, but that—[Laughs.] This is going to sound very strange. But that she thought I would be better in an all-girls school until I was old enough to handle any kind of involvement with boys, any kind of sexuality. So she had found her downfall had been sexuality, and she had been married when she was 16 and then was divorced when she was 20, and then when she married my father, everything was great, but she felt that I should just be kept from all that until I was old enough.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you experience the same limitations that you had in <placeName>Erie</placeName> with the students in public school there?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, no, not in the sense that—I mean, this was a very upper-class school. But what—the separation there I think was more—like, I wasn’t in any way bullied or mistreated or you know, not at all. I was just more irrelevant because I became more—like, at that point, I was getting very involved in—I was getting very involved in social issues. I was doing volunteer social work. Like, I worked with disabled people. I worked with the <placeName>Quakers</placeName> in the slums of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>. I was doing more political things, and that separated me quite a bit from the other people in the school.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And do you believe that the school was upset with <persName>Kennedy</persName> because he was Catholic or because of his politics?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Both. I think primarily politics, but both. I have to say both. It was a very—it was quite a religious school. You know, like, we had to go to church every <date>Sunday</date>, and we had prayers twice a week and, you know, so it was a Protestant—traditional Protestant. I mean, they weren’t evangelical or anything. They were just more like Presbyterians, you know. Like, they did have an association with that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you grow up in a religious household at all?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. My father was a militant atheist, and my mother was quite—kind of this sort of mythical—like, she—she—kind of—she would have been like a New Age person, except it wasn’t New Age then, just kind of in another world. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But not religious. Not religious. But it’s interesting: I became associated with the <placeName>Quakers</placeName> in boarding school, and the reason was a very practical one. We had to go to church every <date>Sunday</date>, and we were not allowed to be off campus otherwise. Like, we could walk to church, go to church and come back. Otherwise, we had to stay in, you know, in the school, and we had to study or, you know, be prayerful or whatever. We couldn’t go out.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay.  And did the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> movement spur your social activism and outreach, or did it just aid it? Were you already engaged in volunteering?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I would say it aided it. It aided it. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what types of projects were you doing in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> while in high school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay. Well, what they had is called a work camp. They would—<date>every weekend</date>—I didn’t go <date>every weekend</date>; I went maybe once a month. They had students go—people who lived in the slum area and wished painting or sort of help with their apartments, students would volunteer their time and do that with them. They would work together. So it was more kind of home—you know, fixing up homes. And so I did that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. Did you feel that your work was making a difference in the community at the time?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I felt—well, my work—I felt—I felt it did make some difference, certainly at least to the individuals we worked with. You know, I had contact with them for a long time afterwards. And it seemed to have given them a sense of encouragement and a sense of—just a sense that they could—there was some hope in their lives. So I think it did make some difference. I think it was small. You know, I think it was incremental. I don’t think it was a huge sea change, but I think it was some small steps, and I think that overall I guess I would say philosophically I just believe things are going to take small steps.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And at the time, the civil rights movement is going on, and how did that play into your social work and into your life in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> in high school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Which, you mean doing the work? </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah, civil rights movement.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, certainly I—it was kind of interesting because at the end, the very end of school, a number of people had said they admired the fact that I was a strong individual and that I hadn’t gone along with the crowd in the school. But I didn’t actually know that at the time. I just—you know, I just thought I made people uncomfortable. But I did—at the end—when we were seniors, we were able to speak about a topic of interest, and I chose to speak about inclusion and exclusion and how cliquishness is a loss both to the people who are part of a clique and those that aren’t. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And give that view, and you told me earlier how your mother later told you that it was for sexual reasons—</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—that you were enrolled in the school, but did you want to go to <orgName>The Baldwin School</orgName>? Did you want to go to a boarding school that was all girls?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, not at all. I fought, and I tried very hard to switch. I enlisted teachers and people—I didn’t want to go to a boarding school, but I wasn’t thrilled with <placeName>Erie</placeName>, so I would accept the boarding school, but I really wanted to go to a mixed school. I really wanted to go to a school that had boys as well, and I argued for that from day one, but my mother was just set in that. And I didn’t know why until much later. But she said, “No, it’s got to be all girls, and that’s what Daddy wants, and,  you know, we have to do what he says” and all that kind of stuff, so—although I think that was more her than him. But I certainly would have much preferred to be in a mixed school. The boarding, I wouldn’t have argued so much because, as I said, I wasn’t thrilled with <placeName>Erie</placeName>, so I was willing to be in another place. But I just didn’t want to be with all girls.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you said how it was a very strong academic school. Can you explain that a little more?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it’s very—well, 100 percent of the students went to university—I should say college. I guess in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> it’s called college. But very—but they had very fixed standards. It was very hard to get into academically. It was very demanding. Actually, I found that school more academically demanding than <orgName>UCLA</orgName> [chuckles], in some ways, because they had very high academic standards. Lots of writing, lots of—you know, very difficult exams. You know, it was just—I guess basically, in the way of a prep school, which you probably heard of, for guys, I guess this was sort of a female prep school, with all the good and bad of that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what was your favorite subjects in high school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">In high school? Actually, there were three subjects I really, really liked. I always loved English because I love reading and, you know, I love writing. But I also really liked Latin because it was logical. I know it’s a dead language, but I really enjoyed it. Clarity and logic. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you also said how girls were taken much more seriously at the school, so can you maybe talk about the social life at the school and student leadership and student organizations or activities?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. There were certainly lots. There were many, many, many clubs, for a whole lot of different reasons, and definitely, of course, all the leaders would have been female because it was all-girl. There was a lot of admiration put on people who were physically capable in terms of sports. So it just—there was just the attitude that women could be what they wanted to be, that women were equal to men and women were worth investing your intellectual and emotional energy into. And I’m not sure in a regular high school—although I didn’t go to one, so I don’t really know—how in <date>those days</date>—you know, I don’t know if that’s comparable. I think women took a more passive role. Here, women were on all the leadership things. They set up all sorts of groups. They were, you know, quite active in many, many ways. So I think that was a positive.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what groups, athletics were you involved in?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, well, I loved tennis. I played tennis, and also I did some soccer, and I was in a—they were called a group, a religious planning committee. It was a group that was interested in learning about varying religions. And I guess, you know, those were—drama. I was in drama, too. I was in some of the school plays. So it was mainly, I guess, drama and religion and then the tennis a lot but also soccer.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what did you do in this religious group? Because you said that the school is primarily white Protestant.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was more looking at—just studying different religions, and it was set up by students, so it was students that sort of wanted to look at things differently, students who at least wanted to learn about other religions. We didn’t go as far as Muslim, unfortunately. But at least varying sex and just varying ideas and trying to, you know, look at what’s similar and different, you know, among Christian and Jewish—I’m sorry, Protestant, Catholic and Jewish. We didn’t go much further than that. Agnostics and atheists. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what was social life on campus? What would you do on <date>the weekends</date>? I’m assuming there were no classes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. Well, we basically had to be on campus. I guess it was very—we had study hall. We had to attend a study hall <date>Saturday</date> mornings, sometimes <date>Saturday</date> evenings. Occasionally we’d have a movie. Occasionally there would be a mixer, which was, like, you know, guys from a prep school would come and there’d be a dance. But they were very strict, with chaperones everywhere and rulers everywhere to make sure you weren’t too close. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you mentioned how you’d go to—you started going to that <orgName>Quaker Meeting House</orgName> because it was far away and you could get time out of school.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Right, yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you—how limited do you feel your freedom was compared to <placeName>Erie</placeName> and <placeName>Roslyn</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, that was kind of interesting. Well, <persName>Roslyn</persName>—oh, yeah, <persName>Roslyn</persName> was just 100 percent freedom. <placeName>Erie</placeName> was probably about 40 percent freedom. And I would say the school was maybe 10 percent freedom.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you accept that limitation, or did you break any of the rules or try to do any other type of work-arounds?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, I broke rules. I didn’t—I wasn’t—I’m not a very—personally, I'm not—although I don’t have huge respect for authority, I’m not, like, a mover and shaker and, you know, a real leader. I’m just a more—I’m a quieter person, so I didn’t—I wasn’t, like, a huge discipline problem or anything like that. I would just—oh, you know, if I—when I would go—I was allowed to visit a friend for <date>a weekend</date>, but her mother was supposed to take me to the bus station, take me back and do all these things, and I just never paid attention to that kind of stuff. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And was that a common attitude at the school among other students?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I think there was some in that—certainly at the end, you know, when people were writing in my yearbook, a lot of people said that they appreciated the fact that I was a strong individual, that I didn’t go along with the crowd, so I guess there was a certain awareness, at least that ideologically I was different. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But I wasn’t painted like a hell-raiser or a problem person or—nothing like that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So what was your senior year, looking towards the future—what were you thinking? What type of options did you want to take after you finished high school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I know—yeah, there was just no question that Id go to univer- —I’d go to col- —well, college, university, whatever, post-secondary education. And my decision—I wanted to go to <orgName>UCLA</orgName>, and basically that was because I didn’t want to be in the <placeName>East</placeName>. I saw the <placeName>East</placeName>—which isn’t fair, but us being much more restricted and sort of hidebound and upper class and, you know,—and I thought <placeName>California</placeName> was freedom. <placeName>California</placeName> was just, you know, a big, big school where you could—you weren’t—where nobody knew you, where people weren’t watching you. You know, like, a huge school in <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName> just seemed to me to be absolute freedom. So my interest was strictly to go to <orgName>UCLA</orgName>, and that was where I wanted to go, and that’s where I got—that’s where I applied, and that’s where I went.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what gave you these ideas that <placeName>California</placeName> was just a great place of freedom?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I guess <placeName>California</placeName>, at least then—I don’t know if it still does—just has an image of being, you know, kind of progressive, and certainly we heard a little bit about <placeName>Berkeley</placeName> at that time, which was really a hotbed of, you know, political activity. And it just—it still I think has some of that. I know here in <placeName>Canada</placeName>, <placeName>Vancouver</placeName> has that same image, that somehow it just seems like a more open place, I guess, because of the weather, because a lot of people go there from other places, seeking their fortune or whatever they’re seeking. It just seems a place where you’re not limited to the past, that it’s a future-oriented place. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what did <orgName>The Baldwin School</orgName> and other students and even your parents think about you wanting to go to college so far away?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, my parents—they weren’t thrilled, but at least I was going to college. [Laughs.] The other students felt it was a waste. They felt that I should be going—certainly my aunt and a lot of the students—they thought I should be going to one of the Seven <placeName>Sis[ters]—you</placeName> know, <orgName>Vassar</orgName> [College], <persName>Radcliffe</persName> [College, now <orgName>Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study</orgName>], whatever, whatever, that I should—because I was among the top of the class, and they thought this was just an academic waste to go to <orgName>UCLA</orgName>. But I never had one second interest in going to one of those schools because I just thought—fairly or not; I don’t think that was necessarily fair—but as an extension of all the limitations that I had in high school. I just wanted to be in a totally different context. I certainly didn’t want to be in an all-girls school. I didn’t want to be in a small school. And I wanted to be in a very diverse school. And that to me is what <orgName>UCLA</orgName> was.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And you said your parents were just happy that you’re going to college.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Is there any reason why?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, they didn’t—I mean, they—they knew that I was not sort of a traditional person, and I think they wanted to keep me under as much control as possible, and if I was attending school, at least that was, you know, what was expected of me in that background and that class and stuff. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">They weren’t 100 percent su- —you know, they thought—my mother I know was always concerned about, you know, my interest in social work and all my involvement. She still—she did find it difficult when that’s what I did because she saw those people that I worked with as being just scruffles. You know, she never understood why I was interested in working with the type of people I was. So I think she found me a bit of a—a confusing daughter because I wasn’t—you know, I was just kind of interested in social work. I was interested in political stuff. And she had been, you know, really a party girl and an artist, so it just seemed very different.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you do anything memorable <date>between your senior year</date> of high school and enrolling at <orgName>UCLA</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, not really, no. I worked at a camp for disabled kids, basically. That’s it.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And I guess I should ask how did you spend the rest of your <date>summers</date> at <orgName>The Baldwin School</orgName> and when you were in <placeName>Erie</placeName> and <placeName>Roslyn</placeName>? Any special during <date>those summers</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Basically—basically [chuckles], we belonged to a country club, and I played tennis 24/7. I just played tennis all the time. My father did not want me to work. He felt that would compromise his position. He did not have a daughter who needed to earn money, so neither parent wanted me to work at all. And volunteer work—again, they were not—they didn’t want that. So I basically—I just—as I say, I put a lot of energy into tennis, I played a lot of tennis. That was it.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So then how did you manage to work at this disabled <date>summer</date> camp?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, they figured, “Okay, she’s going to <orgName>UCLA</orgName>, she’s gonna be far away.” This was more palatable. You know what I mean. Like, this was something they could relate to more than any kind of political work or—yeah. And they weren’t—they would see disabled people as the worthy problem people as opposed to people on welfare or street people or whatever, who would be the unworthy.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So you arrive at <orgName>UCLA</orgName> in <date>the fall of 1963</date>. Is that correct?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, that’s right.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So tell me about your first reactions to college life and the <placeName>West</placeName> that you imagined to be this big, free zone.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it actually totally overwhelmed me. I mean, I had not even been allowed to be out at night. [Chuckles.] You know, I mean, you know, it was just completely—it was just such a scope of freedom, whereas I had—you know, I’d been lucky if I had an hour outside a day at boarding school. And the kids, you <persName>know,—they</persName> were very lovely people. They were really very kind, lovely people. But their experiences were just totally, you know, different than mine. They’d had a free adolescence, they’d had—and I was very shy and, you know, had very limited experience, so I just found it kind of—just mind boggling. It was like—you know, I just kind of—it was just, like, apples and oranges for me. Again, I was—like, I admired it, but it was so different than anything I’d ever done before that I just found it overwhelming. At first.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did it meet your expectations about what you would expect to find in <placeName>California</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It—well, it did. It did in that there really was no external—you know, nobody was bossing me around, telling me I had to do this or that or—I was completely free to do what I wanted, so in that sense, yes. But I think I didn’t meet my own expectations in that I was much shyer and more hesitant than I thought I would have been. I thought I would be free and I would just be this <placeName>California</placeName> girl, and—but in fact, I—you know, <date>those years</date> had made quite shy and hesitant, and I didn’t have the confidence, so it was, like, I wasn’t what I expected in that context, although the context was what I expected. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Why did you think that you were shy?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Why?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I was always—I was actually—I’m on the quiet part of— Anyway, I used to be on the quiet side. I was a quiet person. I certainly am an introvert. Definitely. And I need space and time to myself. I do—in the sense that introvert-extrovert is not—it’s not actually related to shyness, but it’s just more needing—a lot of stimulation is overwhelming to me. I’m the type of person who needs time to herself, time to be, time to process things. And I find I love being with people, but it’s exhausting, too, and I find I need down time. So in that sense, being an introvert in what is a very extroverted society—I mean, <placeName>L.A.</placeName> is really out there. So there was just that—I would say more—I would define it more now as being an introvert than being shy, but at the time, I thought of it as being shy because I was hesitant. I didn’t have the confidence. I was very awkward with boys. I had no idea—you know, I had had no—very little experience.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did your upbringing in a wealthy family—was that another social barrier like it was in <placeName>Erie</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not as much. You know, it was a mix. I mean, <orgName>UCLA</orgName> was much more—was not a upper-class school, so people came from—but people came from all different backgrounds, and it wasn’t as obvious—you know, I was by myself. I wasn’t with my family. People didn’t really know about my background, and I didn’t talk about it a lot. So I think most people just kind of presumed I was sort of—many of the students there were kind of lower middle class, and I could fit in with that. It wasn’t really a—you know, it wasn’t really a problem, I don’t think. I don’t think the class thing was a problem there.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What type of classes did you start taking?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Actually, I majored in sociology because I knew that I wanted to be a social worker, as I said. You know, that had been kind of my career direction from the start. And sociology, although it—[Chuckles.] It can be the practice of talking about the obvious in the most obtuse way. Still, you know, it addressed some of the—you know, the broader issues.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how did your social work continue in a new location in <placeName>California</placeName>? How did that continue?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. Well, you know, I did a few things. I was very active in starting a <orgName>Quaker Meeting</orgName> in the area. I did do some social—you know, I did do a bit of volunteer work, again in some of the poor areas in <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>, and some of the work—I—but I studied a lot, too. I studied very hard in school.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about—you said you started <orgName>the Quaker Meetings</orgName>? So you were the founder and leader?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, not the leader, not at all. I was just one of five or six people that began it. It’s called the Westwood Friends Meeting. They’re a group of people who were interested to start their own meeting, and so I heard about them, and we worked to get it set up, and that did happen. And I think it’s still going. I’m not sure, but I think so.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And can you tell me about some of the activities that you did with the <placeName>Quakers</placeName> in <placeName>California</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">With the <placeName>Quakers</placeName>. Well, again, it was a lot—there would be sort of more social worker-y things. You know, like helping poor people, helping them in practical ways. Certainly—again, it was a pacifist group, so there were certainly people who felt very strongly against <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>. And that started to be a focus at that time.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So when did you first hear about <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, that—you know, it got to be a bigger deal at those times, particularly after <persName>Kennedy</persName> was killed. And it just became more and more a part of what the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> was doing, and it became, as I’m sure you know, quite controversial, particularly on university campuses. There was a lot of consciousness raising, educative activities on all the campuses against the war. And I was getting—you know, I would—I got to be a part of that. I got to be interested in that and doing that. We had vigils. We had silent vigils. I went to demonstrations against the war, and I started to get active in that, that aspect.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And when and why did you start getting active in these type of uh, not-yet protests?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">It probably would have been <date>my second year</date>. I guess that would have been I guess ’64. Well, <persName>Kennedy</persName>’s death was quite powerful. And I think it just seems to have started—I think the crisis—I think what really happened—because there was a draft (which I know there isn’t now)—that people had to face the aspect of what personal choice were they going to make. Were they going to fight or not? So it was very immediate.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you spoke how when you were in high school you were very excited when <persName>Kennedy</persName> was elected. How does his assassination personally affect you?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The assassination with?</u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Kennedy</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Sorry, I didn’t quite hear your question.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">You’ve spoken how when you were in high school you were very excited that <persName>Kennedy</persName> was elected. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes. Oh, yeah, yeah. Oh, how did it affect? Well, as I said, I had seen him, probably wrongly, but as a real catalyst for change. I felt the fact he’s gotten elected meant that the country was behind, you know, racial equality, was behind, you know, progressive politics, and it just seemed hopeful. He seemed to typify a certain vision. As I said, I think vision is very important, rather than just an upset. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And were you involved in any civil rights activities on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I certainly spoke about it. I certainly—there wasn’t a lot—you still—it seemed—the focus was really on the war at that time, not on the civil rights stuff, although that was understood to be very important, but the war was really where I got involved, although I seem to have an interest in civil rights, but I can’t say I went—you know, that I did anything in particular with the civil rights movement other than be sympathetic.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So can you tell me about some of the antiwar activities that you participated in?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, certainly there were—there was a vigil, a silent vigil that we had once a week, people as protest against the war handing out leaflets, going in neighborhoods, you know, handing out leaflets trying to raise awareness of the nature of the war. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And were you ever involved in any of the violence—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—with the police? No?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, no. And that’s because—well, I don’t believe in—I mean, I’m a strong pacifist, and I don’t believe in violence. But also I also was not—I just didn’t—I would not put—I did not put myself in a position where I would be arrested or beaten up. You know, I just—I just did not do that. I just avoided it.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not that that’s good or bad. I don’t know. But I did. I can’t say I was on the front lines, you know, yelling and getting beaten up. That didn’t happen. I would help people who had been, and I would try to—again, the more social worker role, where you’d bandage people who had been hurt or, you know, you’d sort of comfort people or take them another place [sic] or whatever, but I was not on the front line there, getting—being the recipient of violence. And I certainly would have never been a perpetrator of violence.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did the <orgName>UCLA</orgName> administration and other students react to these protests and activities that you were involved in?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, the students—by and large, there was—I mean, <orgName>UCLA</orgName> was known as—it was called “the little red schoolhouse” (which is ridiculous), but it was certainly a liberal campus, and I think on the whole the students were sympathetic. They may not have all wanted to be part of a demonstration, but it wasn’t—you know, it was certainly, by and large, acceptable. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you feel like the protests were making a difference, that you were making a difference in the movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I felt that in terms of consciousness raising, I felt that—I felt it made some difference. I felt at least it was not—things were not going unquestioned. You know, I don’t think that’s enough. I don’t think that in itself would have been, you know, enough to change everything. I think actually what turned <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> around—I think there were two things that changed it, that stopped <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>. And I think one was essentially that the Vietnamese people just fought so fiercely and so bravely. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Anyway.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And I guess this is a more general question now, but how was this when it’s in the context of the larger <name type="event">Cold War</name>? How did that affect your life?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The larger <name type="event">Cold War</name>. Okay.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Certainly, in high school, there was the Cuban missile crisis, and I remember we had nuclear war drills, which were, unlike fire drills, absolutely silent and just—people were just terrified. Like, it was just a very frightening experience to go through that and to think, well, you know, two-thirds of a chance that the world would be blown up. Not that I thought of that’s how [unintelligible], I guess, but that was—that had a lot of impact on people.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Growing up, did you ever believe that nuclear [pronouncing it NEW-cue-ler] war was actually a reality or a possible?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Yes. In fact, it was interesting: I had neighbors. I was very close to them, and a lot of people were actually building nuclear war rooms. You know what I mean. Like, a place in their basement or whatever, a place where they thought, you know, if there is a nuclear war, they would have—I don’t know how they thought this would happen, but, you know, that they would have supplies and they would be able to make it in a nuclear war. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you mentioned how your father was conservative. How did his thoughts about <name type="event">the Cold War</name> affect your thinking about it?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, he certainly was anti-communist. Very much pro-<placeName>U.S.</placeName>, of course, in every—in every way. Although I didn’t agree so much with the anti-communism, I certainly was always in favor of free speech and democracy. Those are things he actually—he did believe in that, you know, and did—he didn’t act like it [chuckles] necessarily, but it was a belief. So he would, you know, always talk about, well, you know, democracy is important. It’s important that people can speak what they think and do what they want and, you know. So in that way, I—you know, that was kind of a connection between him and me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—no, actually, let’s go back to communism. You mentioned earlier the economics of communism.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Economics. No, I was saying I think <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> had a lot more to do with economics than ideology.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But I—certainly the ideology is what was discussed. You know what I mean. That was always—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">—a justification for the war. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And why did you believe that it had to do more with economics than ideology?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, why did I think—well, because when I looked at actually how realistic is it that the Viet Cong is going to be landing on the shore of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, which is what <persName>Johnson</persName> was saying [chuckles]—“They want what we have, and they’re gunna get it.”—this tiny little country, just rich in resources—it made absolutely no sense, but they were going to somehow take over the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> ideologically or in practical terms that made sense that the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> wanted something they—the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> actually wanted something they had, which is Soviet forces in the—you know, I don’t think it had a whole lot to do with actual fear that the whole—everything was going to go communist because they disputed the ideology. They didn’t—they wanted access to the markets.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And you said how your parents were too thrilled about you being involved in social work, but how did they react and what did they think about your <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name> work?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">The <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name>? Interestingly, they were not as upset about that. They thought it would pass. You know what I mean. I think they just thought it was a youthful rebellion that would pass. But they weren’t threatened by it. And it didn’t—I was not actually—I mean, I wasn’t going to jail. I wasn’t refusing the draft. You know, there was no practical impact for me, so I think that it bothered them a lot less. They kind of accepted it with bemused tolerance, I guess I should say.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did that feeling last throughout your experience at <orgName>UCLA</orgName>? Or did it ever change?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, it didn’t change, no.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And when did you decide to come to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for a <date>summer</date> term?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh. Well, that was kind of interesting. It, again, was kind <orgName>of—[Chuckles</orgName>.] I just didn’t feel like going to <placeName>Erie</placeName> for <date>the summer</date>, and my uncle had actually graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. He had gone—yeah, he majored in business there. And he was very keen on <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and so I’d heard about it from him. And I thought it was kind of interesting because I think—I think that was <date>the first summer</date> that women were allowed in. I’m not positive. But at least one of <date>the first summers</date>. And I was kind of interested in the idea that, Oh, this will be different because it hasn’t had women before, and, you know, it’s in a beautiful area—you know, nature. It is in a beautiful—it’s beautiful there. I’d always seen pictures of it, and my uncle had always talked about how wonderful it was.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And why do you think your parents, especially your mother, would be okay with the idea of you going to an all-male school for <date>the summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, she knew that of course girls—[Chuckles.] I think at that point she kind of thought, well, you know, I’m <date>20 years old</date>. There’s not much—you know what I mean. Like, it was mainly high school that she was worried about.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Once I got to university, that kind of stuff faded a bit because she wasn’t worried about it.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And can you tell me about how you felt about going to an all-boys school?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I saw it as a challenge. I thought it would be interesting because there won’t be many women, and you know, I just thought of it as, well, in a way, kind of the opposite of <placeName>Baldwin</placeName>, but I was just curious about it, and I thought I—you know, I’d like to see sort of the reverse of <persName>Baldwin</persName> and see what that’s like now that I’m older and in a different position of awareness. Yeah. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did you find the atmosphere on campus once you got there?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, at that time, the school—I went—I was in two classes. They were just tiny. As I say, I was in a religion class, where I met <persName>Don</persName> [C.] <persName>Pease</persName> [III, Class of <date>1966</date>]. The two of us were the only students, and the professor, [<persName>Robin] Scroggs</persName>, was the one who ended up officiating at our ceremony. But then the other was a class in Latin, and there were three students. So the classes were just tiny.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So can you tell me some of the activities or social life at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> when you were there for <date>the summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was more—yeah, that’s when I met <persName>Don</persName>, so it was a very intense relationship, so most of what I did was, you know, just—nature activities with him. You know what I mean. Like, camping and being outside and getting to know some of—a few of his friends were there. Not as many as during <date>the year</date>, but—so it was just more hanging out with his friends and doing some—you know, some nature things. And the war—you know, there was awareness of the war, but it—people were starting to get involved, but it just wasn’t as intense as later. When I came back, it was pretty intense.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how were the academics at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> compared to <orgName>UCLA</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was—I felt it was—that’s an interesting question—because, you know, <orgName>UCLA</orgName> was, like, 200 kids in every class. In terms of—it’s just everything was huge there. At <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, in <date>the summer</date>, you know, courses were particularly small. So I would say I felt academically—I didn’t see a strong difference. So certainly there was—obviously much more involvement with professor-student. You know what I mean. There was much more personal involvement  between the professors and the students. That is, you could—you know, professors were much more accessible. And I certainly liked that. That was certainly a difference. And it was accentuated, of course, in <date>the summer</date> because the classes were so small. But that’s something I still think is excellent about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, that they have an opportunity—yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me about some of the relationships you developed with your professors during that time?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, actually, Professor <persName>Scroggs</persName>, who was the religion professor, did become a friend of both <persName>Don</persName>’s and mine. And I think probably to his regret, but he very kindly—he was on sabbatical the following fall, <date>the fall</date> of <date>’67</date>, and he let us stay in his house and look after his house and his car while he was away. So that was obviously a lot of trust on his part, and we were—just chaotic and—I don’t think we did a very good job with the house, I realize now, but there was a lot of trust and respect that he had and that I appreciated. He was certainly accessible personally, and, you know, academically and, you know, he was a great guy. I really appreciated him.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And when did you begin dating <persName>Don</persName>, that <date>summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Let’s see, we met—well, we—[Chuckles.] I think we met on <date>June 26th</date>, and he thinks we met on <date>June 27th</date>, but anyway, we started dating right away.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And why did you decide to start dating <persName>Don</persName>, I guess? Can you tell me about it a little bit?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Why did I decide to—well, I guess I would say about <persName>Don</persName> at that time—and it’s still true—he—it certainly started out as a huge hero worship type of thing. I mean, he was a strong force—you know, what there was in the <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name> stuff was starting to heat up. He was a strong force at least in ideology and commitment against the war. He was a strong pacifist.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">And that drew me to him. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And were there any <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name> protests or activities on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I don’t—I honestly—that, I was trying to think about, and I—if it was, it was, it was muted. You know, I don’t—I  just—I remember—I think things started to ramp up in <date>the fall of that year</date>, in my memory. Now, I wasn’t there. I was gone for <date>the fall</date>. I was back in <date>January</date>. But I think a lot of it started that fall, after <date>the summer</date>. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">But maybe I’m just not remembering—maybe I was just caught up in the relationship and I wasn’t involved in the antiwar stuff then. I don’t know.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how does it—were there any other women on campus, or were you one of the very few?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I was one of the very few. It was mostly male. Yeah. Certainly that was more obvious when I came back in <date>January</date> of ’67, that there were very few women around. In <date>the summer</date> there would be more because it was a bit integrated and also because it was freer you know, people had their girlfriends. It was just a more open atmosphere in <date>the summer</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, much— yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how was the transition from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> back to <orgName>UCLA</orgName> after <date>the summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I—you know, I certainly—I certainly enjoy- —you know, I was happy to be back at <orgName>UCLA</orgName> in terms of the school. It was familiar to me, and I was taking courses I liked. But I missed <persName>Don</persName> very much. And actually the reason I left—you know, it was in <date>my senior year</date>. He said he had determined, decided that he was going to go to prison to protest <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>. And we thought that would be soon. So the reason I left <orgName>UCLA</orgName> and came to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—working—was really to be with him before he went to prison.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And so you went back to school for <orgName>UCLA</orgName>, and then you decided your last term to come to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yup. Well, I quit school. Yeah, I quit <orgName>UCLA</orgName>, and I borrowed money from somebody and got the money to fly to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. I figured I had never worked before. As I said, my parents were not wanting me to work. So I never had a job. I had never done anything but be in school, but I felt, Well [laughs]—I guess I’m an optimist. I figured, well, I could find something and I’d be okay, and the main thing is that I wanted to be with <persName>Don</persName> before—for the time before he went into prison for what probably would have been <date>five years</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you see <persName>Don</persName> between the time of going back to <orgName>UCLA</orgName> and then the time you visited him?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I visited—I visited there. I visited <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> at <date>Thanksgiving</date>, and then at <date>Christmas</date> I visited him at his home in <placeName>Iowa</placeName> for a little while. So I’d see him before he left.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What did your parents think of <persName>Don</persName> when they first—when you first were dating?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">What did they think of them? Well, it’s interesting. My father, you know, was totally negative, just feeling he was a ne’er-do-well, he was never going to be a success, he wasn’t ambitious enough, he was, you know, just not a—you know, he wasn’t going to be a hard-driving, successful businessman, obviously. So my father, you know, disapproved and never really liked him.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did you think <persName>Don</persName>’s parents reacted to you?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, his—I think—well, his mom liked me very much. I think his parents was a little nervous because they’re from <placeName>Iowa</placeName>, and I was from the <placeName>East</placeName>, and that—you know, that there are a lot of negative feelings about the <placeName>East</placeName> in <placeName>Iowa</placeName>. And also his dad knew I was a <orgName>Quaker</orgName>, and, you know, he was afraid I was going to be a bad influence—you know what I mean—politically, that I would encourage him to do more of the stuff that his dad didn’t want him to do. So I think he wasn’t outrightly hostile, but I think he was uncomfortable. His mom just liked me right away, and we got along really well.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">And his brother and sister liked me. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So going back a little bit, I guess—I forgot to ask this—but how did your family react to you joining the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> movement in high school and then in college?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That was—you know, they were okay—as I say, my father was a militant atheist, but he had nothing particularly against <placeName>Quakers</placeName>. And my mother—because it was sort of a non-traditional religion—was fine with it. That didn’t bother her at all.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So then <date>the winter of 1967</date>, you went to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>,—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, right. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you officially drop out of school at that point?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Yep, I just quit, yeah. I dropped out of school, and just went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> with borrowed money [chuckles] and got there. Yep.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you think that you would ever return to <orgName>UCLA</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. No. Well, I thought I might if <persName>Don</persName> ended up in prison anywhere in that area, but I was thinking he’d probably end up in prison somewhere in the <placeName>Midwest</placeName>, so I thought I would probably never be back. Yeah. I didn’t—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">—expect to come back. But I always knew—I figured I would figure university, or college, but I didn’t know when or where, but I knew that I would. I mean, because I did—I really wanted to be a social worker. I didn’t just want to just end the college career. But the priority then was to be with him before he went to prison.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how did your family react to you dropped out of school—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">My father—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—and going to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yeah. Well, my father didn’t speak to me until I re-enrolled in university <date>a year and a half later</date> up in <placeName>Canada</placeName>. He didn’t speak to me at all. He didn’t come to the wedding. He refused to let me in the house. He just had nothing whatsoever to do with me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And when you went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>January 1967</date>, did you know that you would marry <persName>Don</persName> yet?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes, we had talked about getting married. Yep.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how was the atmosphere of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in <date>January of 1967</date> compared to at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>the summer of 1966</date> or even—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, certainly it was much more strongly male. And also there was a lot more activity in the antiwar movement that I was aware of. It was primarily male work, but I got a job at the Baker Library, at the front desk, and those people were very friendly—very friendly females, and so that was comfortable.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Specifically in the general antiwar movement—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—or at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I think certainly at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and I actually think in general. I mean, I remember there was a question about what would the woman’s role be in the antiwar movement, and there was a general comment that, “Well, they can say yes to the men who say no to the draft.” I mean, that’s hardly an activist view. You know what I mean. Like, it’s a very adjunct view. And I think that certainly some of the—some of the leaders definitely of the antiwar movement in general and in specific were quite dismissive of women.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah. I think—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And were you involved in any women’s rights movements during your time at university, either at <orgName>UCLA</orgName> or <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. No.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Is there any reason as to why?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I guess—I wasn’t—there weren’t a whole lot of them then, and I think I just—I kind of—because I had sort of this mix, you know, having been at <placeName>Baldwin</placeName> and having been a varying places—I always somehow—and also I think being an only child, actually—I just had a sense that I thought, you know, women were equal. I was equal. I just assumed I was equal. And I felt that people who didn’t accept that were wrong, and eventually they would come around. I mean, it’s kind of—I don’t know. There was just sort of a—I don’t know. I didn’t feel aggrieved by it. I just sort of—I guess in a way, I just dismissed it as something that’ll fade because it’s so obviously untrue, which is stupid. I mean, obviously women have had to fight for huge things, and I’ve become much more aware of that. I was much more aware of that when we moved to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. I got very involved in women’s rights things here. But I didn’t—I didn’t in the <placeName>US</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how did you find your treatment on campus at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in <date>the winter</date> compared to your treatment at <orgName>UCLA</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, I certainly think there was—it was certainly more dismissive at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. <orgName>UCLA</orgName>—there—you know, there appeared to be no difference, but certainly at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> it was more dismissive. It was more kind of patting me on the head and, “Oh, it’s nice. Your Don’s—you’re a lovely support to <persName>Don</persName>.” And “That’s very nice.” And, you know, “He’s the leader.” And, you know, “You have a great relationship because he’s wonderful and you know it.” You know, it was just more of a—you know, kind of a condescension.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you were one of the few women on campus at the time. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Were there any other women apart from the library, I guess, that you knew of, that you were friends with?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I knew a few nurses at Hopkins Center [sic] or wherever it is—not Hopkins Center, the—yeah. I knew a few nurses at the health sciences. And I knew a few women—I worked—I initially worked as a waitress for <date>a couple months</date>, and I knew women from that. But those would be the only women I really knew. And there was one, a female—<persName>Jonathan Mirsky</persName>—I don’t—you probably will get his name or somebody will. He was quite active in the antiwar movement. He had a wife, <persName>Rhona</persName>, who was around. She was a faculty wife, but she also taught. And then Professor [<persName>Henry W.] Ehrmann</persName>, a German professor, had a wife who also taught. So there were a couple faculty wives. Then I knew a couple nurses, and then a few people from the waitressing job, as far as females.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And were you still involved with social work and <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name> protests while at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Yeah, yeah. Not so much social work. I was more—I did—I was more in the antiwar protests. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Was there any reason why less social work?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, just because it became—the antiwar thing became just a huge time and emotional focus. It just—I—it just became a kind of a focus of life. I mean, that’s what <persName>Don</persName> and I talked about. That’s what we did all the time. That’s what all our friends did. That was it. You know what I mean. And the other faded a bit, until I came to <placeName>Canada</placeName>, when that resurfaced.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what role did you play in the <placeName>Dartmouth Vietnam</placeName> protests and movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I didn’t—you know, it wasn’t a big role. You know, I certainly attended—you know, I would go. I wasn’t a leader by any means. And, you know, I certainly would hand out leaflets. I would be talking to people. Whatever job I was in, I would be telling people about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and so on. But I wouldn’t say I was a huge presence. You know what I mean. Like, <persName>Don</persName> was a real presence, and I’m sure people will find that out when they’re interviewing him. But I was there, I was very sympathetic, and it was something that I had been involved in before. It wasn’t just something I took on because of him.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what differences did you see between the <orgName>UCLA</orgName> movement that you were involved in and the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> one now?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, certainly <orgName>UCLA</orgName> included women. No question. You know what I mean. That was—just because, you know, it’s a mixed campus, and it was kind of a freer society, so certainly the difference was, you know, in how women were seen. I don’t think the goals—you know what I mean. I don’t think the antiwar goals—I don’t think the practices were different. I just think there was a difference in how women were treated, though.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Were you actually not allowed to attend certain events at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> or any social activities?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, no. No, no, nothing like that. No, no. No, nobody ever tried to stop me going or doing anything. It was just—it was just condescending. You know what I mean. “Oh, it’s nice that you came, but where is <persName>Don</persName>?” You know what I mean. That kind of—do you know what I mean? </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Like, I didn’t have any weight, myself, although nobody wished to—nobody dissuaded me or didn’t want me except that men were the key and the women could be around if they wanted.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you ever want to be a leader in the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> movements?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, no, I didn’t. I have to say I didn’t. I certainly wanted people to take me more seriously, but I didn’t—I didn’t—you know, I didn’t particularly want to be a leader.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. What did you think of <persName>Don</persName>’s friends at the time?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, they were good guys. There was a mix. Some were more sexist than others; some were not at all. I certainly saw them as dedicated people. I did see some of them as pretty clearly sexist.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So then how did—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">John [G.] Spritzler [Class of <date>1968</date>], who is on your website, is one who definitely was not. He was—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Not what?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">He stood out strongly as being non-sexist.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So was there growing movement at the time for more acceptance of women on campus if not coeducation?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">There was—well, there was—not so much coeducation. No, I don’t think that was part of—but certainly among the women that I talked to—you know, they were not happy with the way they were treated, but it wasn’t, like,—it wasn’t, like, a movement or a group; it was kind of personal awareness. And we were connecting with each other and talking about how we all were having similar experiences. So I guess that was an early start. I think a lot of women’s movements started like that—you know, individual women connecting and then realizing what a broad issue it was. And then it became—moved into more action. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah. And did you ever create any formal support networks with other women or groups?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I did. I did in <placeName>Canada</placeName> a lot, but not here—not there in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, no.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what type of protests were occurring on campus when you were there?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, they had the silent vigil. Basically had demonstrations. Again, that is kind of vague in my mind because everything was so all over the place, but I know that there was the silent vigil. I think it started in the fall of—I think it started in <date>the fall</date> of <date>’66</date>. And then there were protests over <placeName>ROTC</placeName> and, you know, there were a number of protests—I wasn’t in the forefront of those things, but I certainly attended when I was there. A lot of it happened after we left, actually. We left in <date>September</date> ’<date>67</date>. We came to <placeName>Canada</placeName> in <date>December 10th</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Were you involved with any local <orgName>Quaker</orgName> movements?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Well, I did attend a local <orgName>Quaker Meeting</orgName>, and we were married at that meeting, and they were involved in, you know, sort of—certainly ideologically they were involved, and I attended the meetings regularly. I knew those people well. And they were quite a source of support, personal support to me.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And when did you get married?</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><date>June 10th, 1967</date>. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And were classes still occurring then?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Hmm. I don’t actually know. I think—I think it may have been over. I’m not actually sure. I don’t know. I think yes, because—well, there were a lot of people around. There certainly were a lot of people that came to the wedding, who would have been, you know, <persName>Don</persName>’s friends and so on.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And was there any sense of urgency to get married now in <date>June</date> other than wait? Was <persName>Don</persName>’s—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, in the sense that—yes, in that I had wanted it to be very clear that I supported him in every way, and I supported his going to prison and that I didn’t want—I wanted us to be married when he went to prison. That was important to me. So in that sense, there was urgency, yeah, yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And when did you think he would go to prison?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, we thought—we didn’t really know. We thought it could be anytime from <date>the fall</date> to <date>the early winter</date>, after <date>late ’60s</date>, yeah, yeah. Because, of course, it would have been his local draft board in <placeName>Iowa</placeName> that would have made those decisions, so—not anything to do with <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> at all.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">This is <persName>Joshua Pearl</persName> with the Dartmouth Vietnam Project interviewing <persName>Carol-Anne Pease</persName>. <date>Today</date> is <date>August 28th, 2015</date>. We are interviewing by phone. I am sitting in <orgName>Rauner Library</orgName> at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName> in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, and <persName>Carol</persName> is at <orgName>Carleton University</orgName> in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, <placeName>Canada</placeName>. Is that correct, <persName>Carol</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That’s right.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">All right, so when we last did our interview, at least part one, we left off with you getting married. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you tell me about that?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes.  We were—we were—actually, we were married <date>June 10th, 1967</date>, and we were married on the grounds of <orgName>the Hanover Quaker Meeting</orgName>, what’s called <orgName>the Hanover Friends Meeting</orgName>. We had gotten involved with that meeting, both of us, and it was a meeting under their auspices, I guess. So it was an outside wedding. And, like all <orgName>Quaker</orgName> weddings, there’s no actual person such as a priest or a minister who officiates. You marry, yourself. That is, you say the vows to yourselves, and people listen, and then there’s meditation, and people speak who want to. But there does have to be somebody who signs the license or whatever, the official papers. And we had asked Professor <persName>Robin Scroggs</persName>, who was the professor in whose class we met, to do that. And he was a minister, of a different denomination, but he was a minister and had the credentials to sign marriage licenses, so he was our official-unofficial officiator.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And when did you decide to get married?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">When did we decide to get married? Well, actually, we had decided quite soon—as I said, I’d left university and went to—you know, came to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in <date>the winter of that year</date>, and we were—you know, we basically—I would say really by <date>Thanksgiving</date> of—we met in <date>June</date> of <date>’66</date>. By <date>Thanksgiving</date> of <date>’66</date>, we knew we would get married. And then we got married that following <date>June</date> of ’67. So basically we didn’t know each other a great deal when we decided to get married.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you ever get engaged first?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, there wasn’t, like, an official engagement ring or anything—no, it was just, like, we talked and we knew we were going to get married, and we would get married—it was open— We didn’t really know—so much of that time, you know, we didn’t know when <persName>Don</persName> was going to be drafted. We didn’t know when he was going to go to prison. So there was a lot of uncertainty about timelines. So we just—basically we knew we would get married, and we were just—felt we would choose the time that worked out according to just everything else that was happening in our lives.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And who came to the wedding? Did your families come?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, <persName>Don</persName>’s family did, his mom and dad and grandmother, and his brother and sister. He had another brother who was not able to come because of work commitments, but he was very supportive.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. What happened after the wedding?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, we had a very short honeymoon at Happy Hill Cabin. I don’t know if it’s still there, in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, but we were there for <date>a couple days</date>. And joined by a raccoon that chewed on the—that chewed on the wood overnight and another raccoon that ate our corn that was in the stream. [Chuckles.]  So, you know, it was a very quick sort of honeymoon, just a bit of time together, and then we came back. And, as I say, I was working and <persName>Don</persName> was taking class then, so we were back at—back at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> after that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So you stayed because <persName>Don</persName> was still taking classes?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. Yeah, yeah. So we figured we would—you know, until he was finished—yeah, he was still—yeah, he was still—he had been—he had been classified 1-A [Selective Service System classification; available for unrestricted military service] because he had left school, and going back didn’t change that, so he was still on the schedule to be drafted, even though he was attending school. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what was your job in the library?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I worked at the reception desk, at the circulation desk at the library. So I would check out books and—yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And was there any reason that you didn’t take classes <date>this summer</date> like you have <date>last summer</date> at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I was basically not in a school frame of mind. Like, I was working, and we were doing things—you know, some things for the war, and I guess I just—I didn’t know how long or how short we would have—you know, when he was going to go to prison, when we were going to have to move, et cetera. So I just wasn’t in a—I guess I should say a scholarly frame of mind, or I just wasn’t able to focus on that type of thing. It was easier just to go to work and then do some of the political work.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what type of political and protest work was going on in <date>the summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, there was quite a bit. It was called <name type="event">Vietnam Summer</name>. People—people were certainly doing consciousness raising. There was the silent vigils. We had a lot of speakers come in. And so even though it wasn’t busy in the summer—there weren’t as many students—people who were involved found it a time that they—you know, that they could put time into it, and so there was a lot—a lot of that work at that time.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did <date>this summer</date> compare to <date>the summer</date> of <date>’66</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, the summer of ’66—you know, <persName>Don</persName> and I had basically—you know, we had met then, and some of the work was starting, but there was a lot more political work <date>the second summer</date>. And I think also <date>the first summer</date>, we were very caught up in the beginnings of our relationship. And now, not that we weren’t caught up in the relationship, but we were more settled. We knew we were together. We knew we were married. And so we basically—our attention went more to the—to the political work.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how did your life change once you were married on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">How did it change? I don’t think it really changed objectively. Subjectively, I felt more—more secure, I guess because there weren’t a whole lot of women on campus, and certainly in the political movement, women at that point were certainly seen as—not just at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> but in other places—were seen as adjuncts, basically as the women who say yes to the men who say no to the draft. That was the term. So it was basically you were a support, but you didn’t have your own individual identity very much, either within the movement or particularly on campus. I mean, all our friends were <persName>Don</persName>’s friends, and they became my friends too, but I had left my friends when I left school, and my dad wasn’t speaking to me, so I was quite on my own there, so the fact of marriage made me feel more—that I had more of an official role, kind of. But I don’t think that—I don’t think that really affected other people so much. I just think that was in my own awareness. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did your role change during <date>the summer</date>, either because you were married or because there were just less students on campus?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I became more—a big more active. I was more active in trying to find women, you know, to get involved in this, and I think there were a few more women on campus, I guess because they were attending the <date>summer</date> school, and some of them had been active in their own schools or in their own cities, and they were interested. So we actually had a bit of a more female presence in <date>the summer</date> than during <date>the year</date>, in the actions. And I was involved in that.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And were you a leader at this point, at least among the women?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I wouldn’t call myself a leader. I suppose informally, just because I’d been there—you know, they were new there and whatever, but, yeah, I guess I—you know, I reached out to them. I guess in a sense I was, in a way. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And can you describe more of the type of activism you would do?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was—a lot of it was, you know, going from house to house in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, talking to people about the war. We had several speakers come in and, you know, organize talks. We had some connection with some of the profs who were bringing things up in their classes. And I guess—yeah, I guess that was—at that point, there wasn’t much—I think <date>the next summer</date> was <date>the summer</date> that was super active, but we were not—we had already left by then. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what were some of the reactions you were getting from people when you went door to door in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> or from the other activities you did?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, people—certainly, door to door in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>—people were polite. I didn’t have a whole lot of super negative responses, but I wouldn’t say people were, you know, all that interested. I would say it was sort of lukewarm politeness mostly. Some people—occasionally we would run into somebody who was quite interested. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you feel that you were making a difference during <date>the summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I did. I did. I felt that we were all, as a group, moving to—you know, making people more aware of the situation, giving people information that helped them look at it differently. And I felt we were—I felt effective. I felt we were effective. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And I guess looking back to <date>last year</date>, in <date>the summer</date> of <date>’66</date>, could you see how much progress you had made?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I think there was a much more solid base of people and more people, and people were more determined. Yes. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And can you tell me about your living situation for <date>this summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Okay. Yeah, in <date>the summer</date> we rented an apartment on School Street, a little apartment which was near the university, and we were there. And then in <date>the fall</date>, Professor <persName>Scroggs</persName>, whom I’ve mentioned before, very kindly offered us his house. He was on sabbatical that year, and he offered us to stay in his house and look after the house and his cat, so we had a house in the fall—and the use of his car as well, which was super kind of him, very nice of him. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did professors fit into the protest movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, there were some that were pretty active. Professor <persName>Jonathan Mirsky</persName>—you probably will have heard of him; I don’t know. But he was quite active. You know, he spoke, he wrote articles, he would often have the students over and talk to them, as a professor of Chinese. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what was the administration’s reaction at this time to the protests?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I guess for me—you know, I sort of saw them as—they were kind of—I think they were not happy. They were skeptical. But I didn’t see them as hugely negative. I think they just sort of thought it was nothing, that [it] was short lived and wasn’t going to last and—just a little bit a condescension, more than threat or fear.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And how was the social scene on campus at the time?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, our whole thing was with people who were against the war, so what we did is—you know, we did a lot of things together. I mean, there were some things we would do in nature and—you know, walks—it’s such a beautiful area. But much of our time was, you know, doing these political things and talking about political things, meeting together and talking about those things. </u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Is there anything else noteworthy that happened <date>that summer</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not—not that I—not that I recall, no.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. So then what happened that fall?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, in the fall there was—there was a big demonstration, the march on the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>, which was <date>October 21st</date>, I think. There were many, many, many people that came from across the country, and we went there. It was—I forget the numbers, but it was certainly a significant number of people.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what type of violence did you see against these women?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">These would be—one woman I know right in front of me went up to a <orgName>National Guard</orgName>, and she handed him a flower, and he just hit her—he took his rifle butt and just hit her across the face, and she fell, and she had a cut and was bleeding. And so she stepped back, and I was—you know, I bandaged her and was helping her. But a lot of yelling, a lot of swearing. There were certainly some physical altercations of people who did not threaten at all physically, who were not in any way being physically threatened.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what was your role in all of this?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Basically social worker role. I was not—I in no way have ever wanted to or was willing to be arrested or to get involved in jail, so I—I felt that the best role for me and the one I was most comfortable with was as a comfort and help. I helped people who were injured. I was, you know, emotionally supportive to people. I did stand in the group, but I did not—I was not in the front lines and did not make myself available to the—to <orgName>the National Guard</orgName> or to anyone who would be arresting people.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So you were never injured?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, not at all.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what happened once the violence heated up?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, basically people started lying down. We were ordered to leave, and people—the first groups of people started to lie down and not move. So it was I want to say passive resistance; it was not a fight. It was clear they were disagreeing but not being actively aggressive. So what happened then is <orgName>the National Guard</orgName> started to drag people off and arrest them. And I guess others, you know, stepped  back. They remained there but not in the immediate line of fire type of thing, and there were—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what did you do during this?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I had stepped back with a number of people that I knew. <persName>Don</persName> did get arrested. But a number of people in our group also stepped back. It varied. There were some who—who allowed themselves to be arrested and some that did not.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what did you think was going to happen to <persName>Don</persName> when he was arrested, and the rest of the group?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I felt they would go to prison briefly. I didn’t think it would be a very long—I didn’t fear—I was somewhat afraid that they might be injured physically, which they were not. But I guess I had the feeling that they would be kind of heroes of the resistance—you know, the fact that so many people were arrested and so many people felt so strongly about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that these people would be a huge consciousness raising to the country, that there would be a sense that there were so many people who felt this way and so many people who were willing to go to prison for it that people would start to question the war more.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did this consciousness raising happen after the mass arrests?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, as I say—surprisingly—although it was quite a huge thing, it didn’t have a great deal of play in the press, and it didn’t seem to have a great deal of impact, at least from what we could see. I think we were—having mainly been middle-class kids, who were used to having—to being taken seriously and being respected on a wide range of areas—if we had been poor kids, maybe we wouldn’t have been surprised. [Chuckles.] But we were just surprised at actually how little impact—many people hadn’t heard about it. Many people weren’t interested. So that was a bit of a reality check that we had at that time. It was surprising to us that it had—it apparently had not very much impact.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you said that you went to this—it was in <date>October</date>, so what were you doing for the rest of the fall term, <date>between August and October</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, when we left. Well, we went back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. <persName>Don</persName> was actually given—you know, he was—he was drafted and did not—did not appear, so, you know, he was technically—you know, could have been arrested any time. So in <date>November</date> we left <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and we went to—we lived in <placeName>Boston</placeName> for <date>three weeks</date>. We just got a tiny apartment there, and we got jobs there for <date>a few weeks</date> until we could get the money and the plans to go to <placeName>Canada</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what was your reaction to <persName>Don</persName>’s decision to go to <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, initially I was very, very surprised because from the time—literally the day I’d met him until then, the plan had been that he would go to prison, and I had committed to him on that basis. But I have to say I felt full of I guess a sense of relief and a sense of guilt over feeling relief, but just relief because it meant that we would be together and, you know, he would not be in prison. So, I mean, I was happy to know that. So over all, after initial surprise, I was quite happy and supportive.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And was <placeName>Canada</placeName> the only option, or was there options to go to other countries and other places?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, we could have got- —there were other countries that people went to, but I guess we were thinking, because it was English, it was very close, that was what we—that’s what we thought. We had never really thought of other countries, knowing that some people did go to other countries, but we—we were interested in <placeName>Canada</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And at this point, what did you know about <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Pardon?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What did you know about <placeName>Canada</placeName> before arriving?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, as I say, this is very embarrassing, but we had been to <placeName>Montreal</placeName> for the [1967 International and <orgName>Universal] Expo</orgName> that summer of <date>’67</date>, so I knew there were big cities. I knew there was <placeName>Toronto</placeName> and <placeName>Vancouver</placeName>, but I honestly thought <placeName>Canada</placeName> other than that was like the frontier of the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, that basically everybody lived in igloos or log cabins and that people went by dogsled and it was <date>winter</date> all the time. I don’t know how I squared that with the fact that it had been summer in <placeName>Montreal</placeName> when we visited, but anyway—so my image was of, you know, a <date>1800s</date> place. I thought it was—we were going—I was very excited. I thought it would be really challenging and interesting to be in a place that was so different than the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> [chuckles] or anywhere that I had been, because I had been to <placeName>Europe</placeName>. So ignorance, tremendous ignorance, but also a lot of enthusiasm.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And politically did you know anything about <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Nothing. I knew they had a prime minister, and I knew at that time it was [<persName>Lester B.] Pearson</persName>, but that was about it, just that they had a prime minister.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So before arriving, what did you envision you and <persName>Don</persName>’s lives would be like in <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I guess it wasn’t very thought out—you know, it was really—you know, it was mainly focused on being able to leave, but I envisioned it as being basically like a pioneer—you know, like the early pioneers in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, having a life as a pioneer.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Living off that level. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you know that you would be staying in <placeName>Canada</placeName> permanently—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes, yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—or was this a temporary plan?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, we decided this was going to be a definite—a permanent move. We knew that from the start, that if we moved, we would stay. We would commit our lives to there. Yeah. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So I actually want to go back a bit to the [<date>May 1970] March</date> on <placeName>Washington</placeName>. Were there any faculty members that had gone with you?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not that I remember. There may have been, but I don’t actually remember. I don’t remember anybody in particular. I don’t—I’m not sure if <persName>Professor Mirsky</persName> went. Professor <persName>Ehrmann</persName> did not go. So I’m just not clear.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Other people would remember, I’m sure. I just don’t remember.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what was the administration’s and the campus’ reaction when there were <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> being arrested?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, again, I think that they were not happy, but, again, I don’t know how seriously they took it. You know, I mean, I just got the impression they thought these are kind of a few crazies who were going to settle down. I didn’t get the feeling there was a super—you know, people were super upset. But then, again, I was kind of saved from that because—I mean, when I came back to my job, people had said, “Well, you know, I don’t think it’s gonna do any good, but it was good you did it,” so I didn’t face any difficulty within my job, and that was what I was most aware of, I guess.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did the wider protest movement at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> react to this? Make them feel empowered or weaker because—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I think they felt—well, I think they felt—yeah. I think actually it was an encouragement to them over all. I think despite the fact that, you know, it didn’t have the impact people expected, it had been a step. It had been a significant step for people because for many people—you know, they had never been arrested or they’d never come face to face with such a broad group. So I think it had, in a sense, an invigorating—I think in general it made people more determined to keep going rather than less.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. But did anyone come to the same conclusion that you and <persName>Don</persName> did, that it wasn’t worth it at this point to be arrested for draft dodging or anything like that?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not that I know of. Most of the people we knew—well, there was a range of what people did. The people that we knew—most of them were actually planning to—well, some of them were—some of them were going to go—a few of them were going to go—nobody else was really planning to go to prison. There were a few that hoped that they could get deferrals. There were a few that were going to go in the [U.S.] <orgName>Army</orgName> and organize. There was one, actually, <placeName>Paul Beach</placeName>, who was intending to go to prison and did do so. But <persName>Don</persName> was really the only one other than <persName>Paul</persName> who had thought of that as a plan, so I don’t think—yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you tell anyone that this was your plan?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">What, to go—you mean to go to <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yes.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Or to go to—to go to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. We did talk—because, again, we were nervous about it being something that a lot of people knew about because <persName>Don</persName> could have been arrested for refusing the draft, so we did tell <persName>Professor Ehrmann</persName> and his wife. They helped us. They were very kind. Of course, because they had left <placeName>Germany</placeName> under threat from the Nazis, their experience of immigrating was far more incredibly dangerous and scary than ours. But in motions toward our move were the same as they had had in their move, so they were very agitated and very hyper about it, so that I guess affected us. In fact, I don’t think objectively it was anywhere near what they had to face. But they saw it—they saw it that way.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah, I’m still here.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, sorry. I think you kind of faded. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Can you hear—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I can.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what was some of the advice that you were given from Professor <persName>Ehrmann</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, he had said, “Don’t let anyone know you’re leaving. Get your tickets under an assumed name.” We didn’t do that because we figured if we’re going to be applying for citizen- — for immigra- —for—you know, to be landed immigrants, we had to come in under the right name. We had to have all our ID under our right names. So we didn’t do that, but he was just saying, you know, “Don’t let anybody know where you are” and, you know, “Get to the airport clandestinely,” and—you know, it was all very—it was like a spy kind of a game to us, in a sense. But anyway, that was he was telling us, to be super cautious and to be very—very underground.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you tell your family or any of your friends that you were leaving?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. No, we told them afterwards, of course, but not—not at the time. We did go to say goodbye. They didn’t know it was  goodbye. But, I mean, we visited everybody. We visited <persName>Don</persName>’s family. We visited my mother. But we didn’t say, “<persName>Goodbye</persName>, we’re going to <placeName>Canada</placeName>.” We just said—you know, “We just want to see you because we hadn’t seen you.” And in fact we were seeing them because we didn’t know, you know, when we would see them again or if we would ever be able to come back or what would happen. So nobody knew until we—we were here.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Except for Professor <persName>Erhmann</persName>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">How did the protest movement react once they found out you had fled to <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We had fled—I have no idea, actually. [Chuckles.] I really don’t know. I guess, you know—just for me, I just made the move and was getting focused on <placeName>Canada</placeName> and doing things here, and we stayed in touch—I think people were supportive. I certainly didn’t feel there was any negative. There was kind of mixed feeling in <persName>Don</persName>’s hometown because he was very high-profile there. His protest was very high-profile there, and so I think there was more criticism there, but I didn’t feel there was much from the—at least that I was aware of, from the—from the protest—because I think they thought—they respected whatever choices anybody would  make.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. Can you describe the process of actually going to <placeName>Canada</placeName>? How’d you raise the money for the tickets and the move?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes. Well, we—I had—when I was a teenager, my father—my father and his—my father is from <placeName>Denmark</placeName>. He came to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> when he was <date>21</date>. And his sister had been very beautiful and had a number of husbands and then had killed herself. And I heard, when I was about 14, that her first husband had gone to my aunt’s grave and had chiseled out her third husband’s name and put his name on the grave. And the family, of course, in <placeName>Denmark</placeName>—they’re very high-profile friends of the king and all this, so they were horrified and aghast, super embarrassed. But to me, being <date>14</date>, it was very romantic, and it was, like, <persName>Heathcliff</persName> [a character in <persName>Emily Brontë’s</persName> <placeName>Wuthering Heights</placeName>] and <persName>Catherine</persName> [<persName>Earnshaw</persName>, a character in <persName>Emily Brontë’s</persName> <placeName>Wuthering Heights</placeName>], and I was—you know, just—so I thought it was such a beautiful thing to do that I started writing him, and we started corresponding. </u>
      <u who="PEARL"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And can you tell me about your lives after you left <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> but before you were in <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Our lives. Well, basically we just had a tiny, tiny—we rented a tiny little basement apartment in a rough area of <placeName>Boston</placeName>. I forget the name of it, but anyway, it was a really redneck area. And I got a job at <orgName>Filene’s Basement</orgName>, and <persName>Don</persName> was working at a factory. I don’t remember what it was. And it was just for <date>a few weeks</date>. But we were very low key—like, you know, we—we didn’t really explain why were left. We were just saying, “Well, we want to have some time together before <persName>Don</persName> goes to prison.” You know, this was just done very hastily and quickly, but we were—it was kind of very tense. It was very fri- —in time, we were very scared about not being able to get out or what would happen. Would people find out? And so it was like—yeah, we were kind of in hiding, in a way, I guess you could say. It was just for <date>a few weeks</date>. It wasn’t very long. But it was stressful.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what were your parents’ reactions when they—did they ever find out about the jewelry?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yes. [Laughs.] Yes. Both my parents were furious about the jewelry, just saying, you know, “It’s ridiculous” and, you know—but they were—especially my dad—they were really angry about the jewelry. But my mother was certainly happy that we went to <placeName>Canada</placeName> as opposed to <persName>Don</persName> going to jail. And my father, when I started speaking to him again, was actually—supported going to <placeName>Canada</placeName> as well, so—and <persName>Don</persName>’s family really supported going to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. So actually the families were very supportive of the move to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. Really all of them. There wasn’t a problem in terms of families at all.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Why were your friends in <placeName>California</placeName> negative about the move?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, because a lot of them were very <persName>pro-Vietnam</persName>, or some of them were <persName>pro-Vietnam</persName> and some were apolitical but they felt it was a cowardly thing to do.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you ever keep in contact with them through <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in the protest movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Keep in touch? Sorry. I didn’t quite hear.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you keep in touch with your friends in the protest movement at <orgName>UCLA</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, yeah. Yeah, we certainly—well, I didn’t—the friends in <placeName>L.A.</placeName> just wouldn’t have anything more to do with me, but we did—we did keep in touch, of course, with many friends at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, and we’re still friends with many of them <date>today</date>. So they’ve all gone different routes in terms of the war, but definitely we are friends with a lot of them <date>today</date>. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what date did you actually move to <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE"><date>December 10th, 1967</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And can you describe life in <placeName>Canada</placeName> once you arrived?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I was quite surprised that it was definitely not the frontier. It was very much a country—I don’t mean like the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, but it was a country with the sort of level of amenities that the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> had. We were very, very—and still are <date>today</date>—very grateful to <placeName>Canada</placeName> for taking us in and very much in sync and happy with sort of Canadian culture, which—well, it’s changed recently with the prime minister we have, but prior to that, it was a very—a commun- —there was so much more a sense of community, so much as more a sense of helping people, so much—it wasn’t so individualistic and self-absorbed. It was far less aggressive.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you know that you would be accepted by <placeName>Canada</placeName> when you tried to immigrate there? Did you know that you would get immigration status?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We hoped we would, but we certainly weren’t—you know, we didn’t think we would for sure. Like, we very much hoped so. But we were amazed. It was done the moment, like, we got there. We talked to the immigration officer, and he gave us status right away. And we didn’t expect it would be that quick. So that was—we didn’t—we were hoping we’d get in. We were certainly amazed it was so quick. Yeah.,</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And once you’re enrolled in <orgName>Western University</orgName> in <placeName>London</placeName>, did you complete your degree in sociology?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No, I switched to English because I didn’t have—I’d had more—I had too many—I had too many courses in sociology to be able to take enough courses at Western to say I’d been there [chuckles], so I had to switch, so I went into English, and I graduated in English at <orgName>University of Western Ontario</orgName> <date>a year and a half later</date>. It took <date>a year and a half</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And when did <persName>Don</persName> graduate?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, they kind of—he basically finished—that was <date>the summer</date> of <date>’67</date>, and they kind of—he never went to graduation or anything, but they considered him graduated at that point.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">Kind of. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what did you do after you graduated? What did you do in <placeName>London</placeName>? Did you stay around?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes. We—I—I graduated in—let me think, it would have been—we got there in ’67—’69, yeah. Yes, I graduated in <date>the summer</date> of ’69, and I got a job at <orgName>the Children’s Aid Society</orgName> in <placeName>London</placeName>, which is a child welfare organization, child protection—you know, abused and neglected children, working with them, trying to work with their parenting and making sure children were safe.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And were you still involved in the antiwar movement at all in <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, yes. There were groups in <placeName>London</placeName>. <orgName>The Student Christian Movement</orgName>, it was called, that we got involved with [unintelligible], and we again made very many good friends there and have remained so to <date>this day</date>. They were—they were, again, doing much of the same thing, although  maybe not as fiercely because there wasn’t the draft here, but there were people, you know, raising consciousness, and there were, you know, speeches, and we were—pamphlets, and we went to demonstrations here, antiwar demonstrations.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">So what social work role did you do in the movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was more like I was—you know, I would help people come into the country. I would, you know, get—in terms of counseling, in terms of finding resources, that kind of stuff. I did that with people. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And were you still involved in the <orgName>Quaker</orgName> movement in <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, we—we did, yes. We went—there was a <orgName>Quaker Meeting</orgName> in <placeName>London</placeName>, and there was a <orgName>Quaker Meeting</orgName> in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName> when we moved to <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, and we—I call myself kind of a free-range <orgName>Quaker</orgName>. I don’t always go, but I feel very close to it. So we kind of come and go, but we’re—you know, we’re a part of it. We’re certainly a part of it. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And when did you move to <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That would have been in—let me think, the <date>summer</date>—yeah, the summer of ’70. Yeah, in <date>July of 1970</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And why did you decide to move to <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, <placeName>Ottawa</placeName> is the capital, and it’s a bilingual city, and we had visited it, and it was very—we found it very beautiful. There are lovely bike paths. It’s very close to real wilderness in <placeName>Quebec</placeName>. And it just seemed very—kind of more—far more cosmopolitan and kind of interesting than <placeName>London</placeName>, which was a quieter place, and a smaller place. And we just—we thought it would be exciting to be in the capital and to be exposed to French and to be in such a beautiful place. And so close to wilderness. Actually, southern <placeName>Ontario</placeName> is not that close to real wilderness area, and we missed that after—you know, I guess, basically having been in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> and—so, yeah, that’s why we moved here.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what type of work did you start doing in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Again, I went again to <orgName>the Ottawa Children’s Aid</orgName>, doing the same thing, working with families and children in terms of abuse and neglect. And <persName>Don</persName> got a job with <orgName>the National Library [</orgName>of <placeName>Canada</placeName>, now part of <orgName>Library and Archives</orgName> Canada]—you know, yeah, the federal library. And he worked there until <date>1979</date>. He went—he went back to school and got a law degree.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And did you still stay involved in any protest movements in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, and we made friends. And because it was more immediate, there were—there were more—we got more involved—it was probably a bit broader because it was more—being the capital, of course, there’s a lot going on, and there are a lot of political things, but at that point, we started to get more inv- —or I certainly got more involved with the women’s movement and with some of that stuff, certainly some immediate Canadian issues. So we were getting more and more focused on <placeName>Canada</placeName>, but we still were—certainly there were a lot of antiwar people, and we were—you know, we were—we were involved in demonstrations and speaking out about the war, too.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And what type of women’s movements did you get involved in, and what was your role?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, it was—it started out as I guess basically consciousness—consciousness raising groups. Women who had been involved in political movement, either the antiwar movement or the civil rights movement or whatever had—I guess had had the experience of being politically active but not us being taken terribly seriously. So there was just—in progressive women, there was kind of a thought: What’s going on about women? You know, are women—why are we treated this way, and are there things that can be done for women, and should we be speaking about the women as a group that need to come—you know, some of the same empowerment and support that we’ve been giving others.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you believe that you had—that you were successful in those movements? In raising—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, in the women—I certainly think—well, over all, I certainly think that the women’s movement had a huge impact on society. I guess I would say what I feel most about the antiwar and the women’s movement—I think that there was kind of a critical mass of progressive thinking, progressive awareness, of consciousness. And I’m glad to have been part of that. I see myself as a very tiny part of it, but I think every part adds up—you know, that everyone—you know, it grows, and it becomes bigger and bigger the more people join it and the more people are aware and the more people think about things, so I’m think in a very, very modest way I was part of a move- —a progressive movement and of changes in people’s thoughts. Again, very modest. But I feel I was a part of a group that really had an impact on society. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what other political movements did you get involved in?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">What others?</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Yeah, you said that—you said earlier that you were involved in some—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Oh, in terms of that—</u>
      <u who="PEARL">—Canadian—</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, there were things—you know, there are, I guess, issues with <placeName>Quebec</placeName>. We, you know, certainly supported <placeName>Quebec</placeName> staying in <placeName>Canada</placeName>. There were certainly some questions about equal—well, this was the women’s movement, but equal pay for equal work. We got involved in some of that. Some of the union organizing for people and jobs and—so it was more—I guess more domestic, if you want to call it that. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did you feel getting involved in these Canadian movements, given that <date>just a few years earlier</date> you were an American in <placeName>America</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I actually made the switch very quickly. And actually this is something that my father said [chuckles], which was  interesting. My grandfather, who—he was a physician, and he was actually born in <placeName>Iceland</placeName>, and he left <placeName>Iceland</placeName> to go to <placeName>Denmark</placeName> because he had been in protests against the monarchy in <placeName>Iceland</placeName>. So he had moved countries for political reasons.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you feel that way about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, about being alienated?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, to an extent. I certainly don’t think women—you know, at that point, women certainly were not at that time, you know, fully respected and well treated. I’m delighted it’s a mixed school now. I think it’s far better, and I think it’s a huge step forward, although I know it’s controversial among some of the alumni.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And when did you become citizens of <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I became a citizen in <date>’76</date>. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">And were you allowed to keep your American citizenship?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. At that time, we both—we both renounced our American citizenship. Yeah. Now they’ve changed the law. Yeah, we—well, we had to—you had to be one or the other at that point, and we both were feeling strongly we wanted to be fully Canadian.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And what were your thoughts in <date>1973</date> when the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> decided to withdraw from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">That—I was very, very happy about that. I was very grateful and very, very happy. That was—that was a wonderful time. We were really happy. That very exciting moment.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Did you see that as the end of the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> problem and the protest movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, not so much the protest movement. We did see it as the end of the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> problem. Yeah. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">What do you mean by not the end of the protest movement?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I guess at that point we were aware that there were many things that needed to be changed within varying countries. We felt it was important to—to push for positive change, that, you know, it wasn’t just okay, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> is over and then everything’s wonderful. There were underlying factors that created the involvement in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>: the economic, you know, and certainly racism and poverty and—you know, there were a lot of—maybe it isn’t a protest movement in the same sense, but it was certainly important that there be social change. It wasn’t a feeling that just because there’s no longer <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, everything’s fine. It was a feeling that this was great, but we wanted to work for other kinds of social change as well.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you continue in any movements for social change?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I think for me—by and large—although, as I say, I’ll attend demonstrations now. I sign petitions. You know, I certainly am very active in electoral politics here. But I think my main thrust has actually been the more—social change and the more immediate in terms of counseling and trying to make <orgName>people’s</orgName>—working to help people’s individuals lives and to lessen suffering as much as I can in that way, rather than, I guess, a broader—broader action, although I’m sympathetic to the broader action.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And then in <date>1975</date>, when <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> fell, what were your thoughts?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Now, that was—I just felt—just felt very sad about all the huge waste of life and all the—just—just the whole—the whole—ah!—the destruction and misery of that war. It just—it just was a very—feeling of sadness.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you ever think that it could have come to that, or in <date>1973</date> did you think the conflict would be over soon?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I guess—yeah, I think—I think I thought, yeah, that I would just—yeah, somehow—that the conflict would be over soon, yeah. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And so where were you in your life with <persName>Don</persName> at this point? Had you considered starting a family eventually in <placeName>Canada</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">We had. We had. We actually had our first son in <date>1980</date>. We were—<persName>Don</persName> had had a lot of physical illnesses from <date>a couple of years</date> on from when we had come to <placeName>Canada</placeName>, and so there as a lot of focus on that, on his health. And I guess—you know, we have been focusing a lot on his health, but we were thinking more and more about having children, and actually he was diagnosed wrongly. It turns out not to be the case. But he was diagnosed with having MS, multiple sclerosis, so both of us decided we did not want to just wait around for him to get sicker and sicker. We decided we wanted to make kind of a leap into the positive and a leap into the future, and that’s when we decided to have our first child. And we had him in <date>June of 1980</date>.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And 1987—1979, President [<persName>James E. “Jimmy”]</persName> <persName>Carter</persName> pardoned the draft dodgers. Was there any thought to go back to <placeName>America</placeName> at that point?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">No. We were happy that we were able to visit, you know, but—because, you know, <persName>Don</persName> still had a family there. But we had no thoughts of moving back. We—we were totally integrated and involved in <placeName>Canada</placeName>. It just wouldn’t have—our home was here, and our identity was here, and most people didn’t even know we came from the <placeName>U.S.</placeName></u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you go back to <placeName>America</placeName> any time before <date>1979</date> without <persName>Don</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yes, I did. Yeah, I went a couple of times. He had a grandmother who was ill and died, and, you know, I went back a couple of times when his mom died. A number of people in his family died. I went back for funerals primarily, I guess, because he couldn’t go.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">His family came here to visit, of course. He saw them and so on. I just mean as far as going back there. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And so how did your lives continue in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName> from <date>1980s onwards</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I guess that we had a wonderful boy in <date>1980</date>, and we had another wonderful boy in <date>’83</date>. And I had gone back to school in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName> and gotten a master’s degree in social work, and so I continued with—I worked with <orgName>Children’s Aid</orgName>, and then I did some trauma work, and then in <date>September 11th</date>, 2001—I’ll never forget <date>that day</date>; that was my first day here at <placeName>Carleton</placeName>, working as a counselor.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And in the first interview, we talked about your relationship with your mother and your father. How did that influence your role as a mother to your children?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, that’s interesting. That’s very interesting. I hesitated to have children for a long time because I felt I wouldn’t necessarily be a good mom because I hadn’t had great mothering. But I have to say I think I’ve been a really good mom. It was certainly the happiest and the best thing I’ve ever done. Like, I don’t mean to sound—anyway, I just love being a mom. I love my kids. It’s been the happiest, most wonderful experience ever. That doesn’t mean it’s so for everybody or that everybody should have children or whatever. But for me it was just incredibly wonderful.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And did you continue any of your social activism or protesting from <date>1980s onwards</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, we go to demonstr- —I go to demonstrations. Lately [chuckles] there’ve been a lot of demonstrations against our prime minister [<persName>Stephen Harper</persName>], who is very, very, very right wing, so I—you know, I’ve gone to some of those. There’ve been—many of his policies have really been outrageous. And, you know, I’ve attended demonstrations there. I’ve certainly signed a lot of petitions. And I guess more recently there’s some stuff with the lion in <placeName>Africa</placeName> [referring to the killing of <persName>Cecil the lion</persName> on <date>July 1, 2015</date> by <orgName>Walter Power</orgName>, an American big-game trophy hunter. Source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killing_of_Cecil_the_lion ]. So I get involved in some animal stuff.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And so what were your thoughts in <date>1989, 1990</date>, when <name type="event">the Cold War</name> ended?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Well, I guess—yeah. I mean, I was glad—you know, glad that that happened. I always thought some of that was—I don’t know, it just seemed unnecessary to me. It just seemed—I don’t know, I just seemed like a no-win situation. So I’m—you know, I was glad that there was some hope that there would be [sighs] working together in some ways, so, yes, that was a good thing for me. Yeah. Yeah. </u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. </u>
      <u who="PEASE">I’d never really believed it was as bad as a lot of people thought.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">And how did you view <placeName>Canada</placeName>’s role in international affairs and the world throughout the time, at least in <date>the ’80s</date> and <date>the ’90s</date>?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, in <date>the ‘80s</date> and <date>’90s</date>, I really agreed—you know, I really liked their peacekeeper role. I liked the view of trying to remain a neutral and to try to be, you know, I felt, you know, an influence for peace and for mediation and stuff. Yeah, I certainly liked that, when that was the case. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And you mentioned briefly <date>9/11</date>. Would you like to talk about your thoughts on that?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Yeah, I guess that was—I guess I would say it certainly was scary, and nobody knew here—well, anywhere, but I mean here in <placeName>Ottawa</placeName> what was going to happen. Anybody working anywhere near <orgName>the American Embassy</orgName> just left work <date>that day</date>. Because I was working with a lot of international students, they were terrified about what this was going to mean. They thought <placeName>Canada</placeName> was so stable, and now what’s going to happen? Is it going to spread to <placeName>Canada</placeName>? Is there going to be a huge world war? It was a huge amount of fear.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Uh-huh. And oftentimes I’ve heard people compare <placeName>America</placeName>’s wars in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>, <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> as “the new <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.” Given that you’re part of the protest movement, do you see that as an accurate comparison, or what are your thoughts on that?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">I would say it’s—well, I would say it’s—I would certainly say, you know, the war between the Sunni and—yes, I think that many of these are internal conflicts, but the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> gets involved. It just makes things worse, which I think is—in that sense it’s, yeah, it’s just like—it’s like—I mean, <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> has a history of just incredible internal conflicts, and it’s not going to be resolved by an external power trying to force them into something, so, yeah, I would say it’s similar. It’s similar to the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in that regard.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. And do you have any other final thoughts before we start winding down and eventually end the interview?</u>
      <u who="PEASE">Not really. It’s—it’s interesting, you know, to think of <date>those days</date> and those times and the choices that people make and the choices that we made. You know, I think over all I certainly am very happy we’re in the place we’re in. I’m sorry the place the world is in [chuckles], but I’m happy for the place I’m in. That’s what I’d say, I guess.</u>
      <u who="PEARL">Okay. That’s great. At this point, I’m going to end the interview.</u>
      <u who="PEASE">All right.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
