<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="ROGERS"/>
        <person xml:id="LI"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="LI">This is <persName>Ellen</persName> [P.] <persName>Li</persName> in <orgName>Rauner Special Collections Library</orgName>. It is <date>August 19th, 2015</date>, around 3 p.m., and I’m speaking with Mr. [<persName>Jeffrey L.]</persName> “<persName>Jeff” Rogers</persName>, who is calling from <placeName>Portland</placeName>, <placeName>Oregon</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">First, thank you very much for doing this interview. I was born in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, <date>July 26, 1944</date>, and my father’s name was <persName>William P. Rogers</persName>. The P stands for <orgName>Pierce</orgName>, <persName>William Pierce Rogers</persName>. And my mother’s name was <persName>Adele Langston Rogers</persName>. My middle name is <persName>Langston</persName>.</u>
      <u who="LI">Great. And so you grew up in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName></u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Actually, my <date>first 18 months</date>, we moved five different places around <placeName>the East Coast</placeName>, as my mother followed my father, who was in training in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Navy</orgName> for eventual deployment in <placeName>the Pacific [Ocean</placeName>] in <name type="event">World War II</name>. So we moved around, and <date>the first five years</date> of my life we moved quite a bit. From <date>age five</date>, we moved to <placeName>Bethesda</placeName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, just outside <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName> That’s where I grew up the rest of my young <date>years</date>, and my parents lived in that house for <date>60 more years</date>.</u>
      <u who="LI">And so how did you like growing up in <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, right outside of <placeName>D.C.</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I liked it a great deal. It was, of course, a much smaller place then. I used to ride my bicycle by myself when I was—I don't know, what?—10 <date>years old</date> or something, all around <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, which would be harder to do <date>these days</date> with the traffic and developments. </u>
      <u who="LI">And did you have siblings?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I did. I do. I have three siblings. I have an older sister, <persName>Dale</persName> [<persName>Rogers Marshall</persName>], who is <date>seven years old</date> than me; an older brother, [<persName>Anthony W.]</persName> “<persName>Tony</persName>,” who is <date>four years older</date>; and a younger brother, [<persName>Douglas L.]</persName> “<persName>Doug</persName>,” who is <date>two years</date> younger.</u>
      <u who="LI">And so where did you go to school?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I went to elementary school through sixth grade at <orgName>Bethesda Elementary [School</orgName>], a public school about a mile from our house. I used to walk to that with my younger brother, <persName>Doug</persName>. And then in seventh grade I transferred to <orgName>Sidwell Friends School</orgName> in—just across <placeName>the District of Columbia</placeName> line in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, and completed the rest of my—I completed my junior high and high school years at Sidwell Friends.</u>
      <u who="LI">And what was that transition like? I assume <persName>Sidwell Friends</persName> was a private institution, correct?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, <persName>Sidwell Friends</persName> was a private institution. It’s a <orgName>Quaker  </orgName>school. Quite a few government officials and other people who are able to afford it send their children to <persName>Sidwell</persName>. It was a tough transition for me because I was the only one in my elementary school class who went to <persName>Sidwell</persName>. I didn’t know anybody there. I happened to have a very poor math teacher. Although <persName>Sidwell Friends</persName> is an excellent school, the math teacher I had in seventh grade was a terror. Used to throw chalk and erasers at kids. So I actually refused to go to school for a while. </u>
      <u who="LI">Wow. So in terms of the—the cultural differences between the schools, did you notice any changes when you went from, you know, <orgName>Bethesda Elementary</orgName> to <persName>Sidwell Friends</persName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes. Of course, it’s—it’s a little tough to compare them in the sense that I was in an elementary school at <placeName>Bethesda</placeName> and then middle school and high school, so there was going to be cultural differences of a sort, age differences, just because of the age of the students. </u>
      <u who="LI">So in this calmer environment that you’ve described, you know, what was it like growing up in an era where <placeName>America</placeName>’s recovering from <name type="event">the Second World War</name> and there are increasing tensions with <name type="event">the Cold War</name> and <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName>? Did you—were you aware of everything that was going on globally?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Oh, yes, for a number of reasons. <persName>Sidwell</persName> certainly placed an emphasis on being aware. My dad ended up in government, in prominent positions, starting in <date>the late 1940s</date>, when I was <date>about five years old</date>. That’s why we moved to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName> And he and Mother were very attuned to current events and what was going on in the world.</u>
      <u who="LI">And in terms of <date>daily</date> life—I mean, as a child trying to just grow up and go through all the—the normal things in school, high school, what was the perception of those fears that you talked about among your peers? Was it—did people believe that there was genuinely imminent danger? Were you in—you know, in constant—constant fear?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, I wouldn’t say we were in constant fear. I mean, as—as teenagers we were pretty focused on our own flies and girls or boys, as the case might be and all that sort of thing. But we observed a lot of fear, especially in our parents. I remember very distinctly when the Cuban Missile Crisis occurred <date>a few years later</date>. My parents were more scared than I’d ever seen them. And that was the culmination of a number of <date>years</date> where most of our parents—other students in school—most of our parents were [noise] [unintelligible] those fears, and that was visible to us.</u>
      <u who="LI">So going back to your father working in the government obviously during this very tense period, what was that like? What was your household dynamic like? Did you talk about the current events of the time?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Oh, yeah. Growing up in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, with a father who was in government a number of ways meant that we talked a whole lot about current events and politics, and the dinner table conversations—in <date>those days</date>, we ate dinner as a family ritual every night. The dinner table conversations were almost always about current events and politics, with some sports thrown in for those of us who enjoyed sports.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah, I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, <persName>Dad</persName> was an old-time Republican, which you hardly see anymore [chuckles wryly], and was a progressive Republican, as was my mother and so held views consistent with the progressive <orgName>Republican Party</orgName> at that time, which included the concern about international affairs and safety. You know, <persName>Dad</persName>’s career was pretty fascinating, actually. I’ll go through that at whatever point you want to in this interview. But it played a very big role. He was—he became a colleague of and then a friend of <persName>Richard</persName> [<persName>M.] Nixon</persName> in <date>the late ‘40s</date> and became deputy attorney general in <date>the early ‘50s</date> and attorney general in <date>the late ’50s</date>, under [<persName>Dwight D.] Eisenhower</persName>. </u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And I guess did that make you more interested in government in general?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, no doubt about it. As I mentioned, It was just the way things were. Like every kid, when they grow up I think they assume for quite a while that their world is the normal world, and it is for them. And that world of politics, government, current events, prominent people, parents starting to appear on <orgName>TIME</orgName> magazine covers and on TV and all that stuff—that’s just kind of the way it was. But the result was it was very much in our minds, my siblings’ and I—as well as, of course, my mother and father.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. I’m sure that was quite exciting as well.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Exciting, but at that age you don’t really know much. You don’t know better. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, in retrospect I think, Wow!, you know. But—and—and we knew it was exciting at the time, but it wasn’t the kind of excitement that you would have looking at it from the outside. It turns out, obviously, all these people were just like normal people, and some of them had strengths and weaknesses. When you get to know <persName>Nixon</persName> a little bit by playing touch football with him, as we did—well, he wasn’t a very good touch football player [chuckles], but—</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">You know, you have a different view of somebody like him than you do if you’re reading about somebody from a distance or watching them just on TV.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah. So I guess what was it like, for example, playing touch football with <persName>Nixon</persName> and having that sort of—obviously, you said that it felt normal, but I’m sure you were aware when you went to school that not everyone, you know, did that as a weekend activity. So how did that kind of play out in terms of your social life, or comparing your own experiences to those of your peers?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">These are great questions, by the way.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I guess that question could be answered at a couple different levels. I mean, on the—on the purely personal level, leaving aside <persName>Dad</persName>’s role—if on a purely personal level, there was some sense of guilt, I suppose, that I was at a place like <persName>Sidwell Friends</persName>, which was a pretty expensive school to go to and extremely high quality, and just on the inside of <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, and not far away—and actually when my sister started at <placeName>Sidwell</placeName> <date>seven years</date> before me, <persName>Sidwell</persName> was still segregated, and she worked hard to convince the administration to desegregate, and they eventually did. But to have a school like that desegregated, you know, when we were going to school there, was pretty shameful and pretty bizarre.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">And there were separate water fountains around the city, and back of the bus and all of that stuff. And so in contrast between our, quote, “privilege” and the situations that many others, mostly notably African-Americans, found themselves in was—was stark and distressing. And so that was at a personal level.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">So that made it a lot easier to see it from both sides because from both sides—for me, both sides were consistent. Both sides—</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—wanted to advance things, so that made it a lot better than it might have been at that level, although, again, at the personal level it was—it was kind of crazy to see. My kids now just marvel at the fact that it was like that <date>only a few decades ago</date>, you know.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah, I think all of us definitely do. It just seems to foreign.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, it seems so foreign, and we’ve come so far in some ways, but, of course, we have a long ways to go [chuckles]—</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—to prevent return, recently,—</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—<date>this past year</date> or two.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah, definitely.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It demystified these people. In other words, it dispelled the sense that these are superhuman people. It dispelled any sense of—for the most part, of a saw of awe. I mean, if “awe” means kind of reflex admiration, these are superhuman people, it certainly dispelled that, no matter who they were, including my dad, whose career I greatly respected. You know, I saw his flaws. [Chuckles.] I saw his weaknesses, and I saw that, too. I saw <persName>Nixon</persName>. <persName>Nixon</persName> couldn’t throw a football, you know? I mean, he was pretty awkward.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">And so you see people as humans that way, and with all the human struggles and issues they’re dealing with. At the same time, in addition to dispelling the sense of awe, I did develop a sense of admiration because those are hard jobs. I mean, nowadays the anti-government—something that is so distressing and is looked on as if there’s something inherently flawed with people in government. Well, what I saw and I’ve seen throughout my career because I’ve served in government quite a bit, obviously not in those kind of prominent positions, but what I saw and have continued to see is that there are an extraordinary number of really hard-working, dedicated people in government.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And does that mean that you held those officials to a higher standard or you just more understood the difficulty of the things they were grappling with and that they were, you know, human?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Back then, you mean?</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, I wasn’t really holding them in any—you know, I was in no position to hold them to a standard particularly, because I was growing up. I mean, I—I just—I learned a lot about them. I learned a lot about the good and the bad side of politics. I learned—what I said about admiring those who do it well, which I think it’s a large number of them, and, at the same time, recognizing how transitory it is. And <persName>Dad</persName> was quite good about recognizing that people were treating him with such obsequiousness, not because they necessarily thought he was a wonderful human being—some of them did—but they were doing it because he held government office, and when he would be out of government office, people would drop him just as quickly. And that wasn’t because it was <persName>Dad</persName>; it was just people in general.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I developed an interest in science early on and decided I wanted to be a doctor. In retrospect, I think there was an element of rebellion, what I considered and sometimes jokingly call “wippie” rebellion. </u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">My father was a lawyer. My mother went to law school and graduated but never practiced. Eventually both of my brothers became lawyers. My wife—both of my wives [chuckles], my kids later on, et cetera. I grew up in a lawyer family completely, and I tried to set another path to become a doctor, which we will get to, I suppose. It turned out not to go that way, but that’s where I focused in high school, was in science, thinking that I would be a doctor, but thinking that I would follow my own path.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. So what was kind of the decision, then, to go to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? What were you looking for in a college when you were thinking about moving on from <orgName>Sidwell Friends</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I guess I was just looking for a very top-quality college. It was sort of expected in my family that you would go to college and you’d probably go to an Ivy League school. All four of us, my siblings and I all went, I mean between us we’ve gone to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, <orgName>Harvard</orgName> [University], <orgName>Yale</orgName> [University], <orgName>Cornell</orgName> [University], <persName>Princeton</persName> [University] and so forth. So I was in somewhat of a closed universe in that sense, so I applied [to] mostly the Ivy League schools. I applied to <orgName>Yale</orgName>, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and <orgName>Colgate</orgName> [University]. <orgName>Colgate</orgName> had been where my dad had gone. Got into all three of them.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I loved the relative smallness of it, the focus on undergraduate studies and, you know, all the things that people talk about about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. It just struck me. It was one of those times in my life where it just plain felt right, and it’s hard sometimes to articulate the reason. I was just drawn to it.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah, definitely. And so when you eventually made the decision to come to campus, what was—what was the climate like back then?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Old. “You guys don’t know nothin’ these days”.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I think there’s far less snow. I mean, it was—it was a wonderful climate, I’m sure much like <date>today</date> but probably with greater extremes, at least on the cold side. You know, the fall is absolutely gorgeous. I’m sure it still is. I haven’t been there for <date>a few years</date>, but one of the things that I missed when I moved west to <placeName>Portland</placeName>, <placeName>Oregon</placeName>, was the <placeName>New England</placeName> falls, the colors, you know. It’s hard to beat that. So the falls were—fall was spectacular when I first got there.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—was pretty yucky for a while, as everything melted and thawed. And then in <date>summer</date>, I wasn’t—I didn’t stay there in <date>the summers</date>, but to the extent I was around at the beginning and the end of them, it was beautiful too. A little bit buggy at times, I think, but I loved the climate. It was extreme enough that it felt kind of rugged but—but rugged in a country way rather than like being trapped in a big city in big snowstorms.</u>
      <u who="LI">Did you—was one of your goals to get away from a city after growing up so close to one?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, not—not explicitly. I had grown up, like, in the outdoors. My mother, especially, was an outdoors person, and we used to go on hikes with birdwatchers, which was not cool when we were in high school, but—</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—did it secretely. And I was athletic. Played all—got letters in all the sports at high school. I was recruited by [<persName>Robert L.] “Bob” Blackman</persName>, who was <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>’s football coach then, but I didn’t want to play football. It was just too bruising a sport, and I’m glad I didn’t. But I played intramurals, which I loved except when I coached our fraternity intramural football team to an “unfeated” season; “unfeated” meaning we lost every game.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">We were <orgName>un</orgName>-undefeated, and so called “Coach” by my fraternity mates, and they still call me Coach, having lost every game <date>that year</date>. </u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And what was—what was, you know, mainstream culture like when you got here? What was the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> mainstream?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">What was the cultural environment?</u>
      <u who="LI">Yes.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Not—not as rugged and alcohol laden as the image had it. I always thought, anecdotally, from what I observed, that there was more drinking at some of the other schools than at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but it was—you know, the image is sort of a hard-partying school but also—and which I think was exaggerated—but also as an extremely high-quality college with a real emphasis on undergraduates, as I’ve mentioned, and a lot of enthusiasm. And there really was a lot of enthusiasm for the school. People liked being there. Not everybody. Some—some left fairly early because it was one of those places, if you didn’t like being way out there, if you didn’t like the <date>winters</date>, you really didn’t like them. But if you did, you loved it. So I had a sense that most people were happy there. Most people studied hard but also were able to relax and play. I felt like there was a lot of attention to student welfare.</u>
      <u who="LI">And, you know, being so aware of current events when you were at home, did that carry over when you came to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes. Not quite in the same way. I no longer had every meal consisting of a political discussing with somebody as I did in all of our dinners at home. However, a lot of the students there were, of course, smart, aware, tuned in to what was going on, so there was that awareness. And, of course, we had some—some huge events during my time there, including the [President <persName>John F.]</persName> <persName>Kennedy</persName> assassination. And those kinds of things brought great attention, obviously, on the part of the students.</u>
      <u who="LI">Were there many—you mentioned, you know, not much <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>-related activity on campus yet, but in terms of the civil rights movement, did you find that there were a lot of protests, or what was the reaction like on campus?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I don’t remember very much. I mean, I guess I would say there was a drawback to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> in the sense that its isolation, relatively isolation, especially in <date>those days</date>, tended to I think lessen the—the amount of passion or the demonstrations—I mean, you demonstrated on Main Street or the Dartmouth Green, and this wasn’t going to get the same amount of attention as if you demonstrated in <placeName>Boston</placeName> or at the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> or something. So there was probably a little sense of this whole detachment, being in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="ROGERS">And so I would say that—that—that was a weakness of—of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. It was not that people didn’t care, but it wasn’t the throbbing concern that it was becoming in other places.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. </u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Oh, yeah. I was in organic chemistry class. I can pretty much see myself with the beakers and stuff and pretty much picture exactly where I was standing in the lab, and heard it by word of mouth and immediately closed things up and went back to the fraternity house and watched television straight for 48 hours or something like that, with just a little bit of sleep.</u>
      <u who="LI">And what was your initial reaction?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Devastation. Disbelief. Nothing like that had happened. I  mean, that was the first of a series of world-shattering events over <date>the next decade</date> or so, but that was the first one that just was kind of—completely threw you off your bearings. Like, It cannot be happened. That can’t be real. And a sense of real grief and some sort of confusion. Fear but not fear for physical safety but just a fear for what that meant for the country.</u>
      <u who="LI">Hmm. And do you—sorry. I was just wondering. Did you—speaking to your father about that, with him, so involved in the American government at that time?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, I did. I can’t remember any specific thing that was said. I mean, there was just this shared sense of the sorrow. And he and Mother certainly felt that, too. I mean, <persName>Bobby Kennedy</persName> had replaced <persName>Dad</persName> as attorney general, and <persName>Dad</persName> had sort of mixed views of <persName>Bobby Kennedy</persName>. Especially in <date>those days</date> it was a mixed bag. I mean, later he sorted out his own life a little bit and his own beliefs, and so—but in <date>those days</date>, the <orgName>Kennedys</orgName> were very complex. I guess they were always complex and still were. And my parents had kind of a complex view of them.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It was just shock and profound disbelief beyond words. I mean, <placeName>America</placeName> had come out of <name type="event">World War II</name>, seemingly invincible and starting to make progress on civil rights. Things are pretty stable. The <date>’50s</date>, although there was a great deal of turmoil under the surface and a great deal of bias and discrimination and anti-gay and all the things that we’ve been struggling with ever since—although that was all brewing under the surface, on the surface the ‘50s were very calm, very sort of like the best of times for many people, not for everybody but for many people. And—and to have <persName>Kennedy</persName> assassinated was like—all of that was just blown apart—</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—and sort of started—you know, began <date>the next decade</date> of real turmoil.</u>
      <u who="LI">Could you speak about that turmoil a bit, especially since some of it overlapped with your—your time in college?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah. Well, of course, a summary of things include the <persName>Kennedy</persName> assassination, <persName>Bobby Kennedy</persName> assassination, <persName>Martin Luther King</persName> [Jr.,], <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, [<name type="event">the] Watergate</name> [scandal] a little bit later. Those were the big ones, I guess, and I may be missing some.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] Definitely action packed.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It’s so hard to say. It was so gradual, which is part of the problem, of how we got into the darn thing.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="ROGERS">You know, it was kind of—under the radar for a while there. I guess—I guess to some extent <placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin thing [Gulf of Tonkin Resolution] and</placeName>, even more so, when the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Marines landed at <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, ended up being eventually—when the Marines landed in <date>the spring of 1965</date>. I mean, that’s when it really became a bigger reality for most of us. But it had been building up for so long that it was, you know, like—like grass growing outside, you know? You don’t pay attention to it day by day, but if you let it go, eventually it gets pretty darn tall. And that’s the kind of thing that was happening there.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And so in those—you know, the latter half of your <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> experience, what were you—were you still focused on pursuing the medical route?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah. Yes, I was pre-med. Like you, I had a dual major. Half of it was history. Like you, I was a history major, but my other half, unlike you, in computer science I was pre-med basically, so I was a history major. I never quite know why because I had never really taken completely to history, but I think part of it was <persName>Harvey LeSure</persName>, the fellow I mentioned, w was my mentor—my tutor and then was a major reason I went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—he was a history teacher in <orgName>Sidwell Friends</orgName>. And I think the fact that he was a history teacher led me to declare as a history major but also pre-med.</u>
      <u who="LI">And obviously pre-med is so demanding in terms of the course load, and then you also had this history major. Did you feel like you were able to take advantage of the sort of liberal arts approach that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> still stands for <date>today</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, very much so, but maybe not quite as much as I would have if I had not put so much emphasis on—on pre-med. But, yeah, I think going—yes, I took advantage of it being a liberal arts school, and I think that was extremely valuable for me. I took a pretty wide range of courses. And having also focused on history, that helped broaden my experiences.</u>
      <u who="LI">So what were your favorite classes, for example, when you were here?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah. I did tend to like science classes. I liked biology quite a bit. I liked chemistry fairly well. I think the science classes. But some of the political science stuff, too, that I enjoyed. Unlike some people, I don’t have particular classes that stand out in my mind quite as much; it’s more an amalgam or a sense that this was a really good education, with a lot of caring professors. But, again, I’ve mentioned <persName>Harvey LeSure</persName>, my high school tutor and mentor, a number of times. I didn’t end up having anybody like that at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> so much, surprisingly. But I consider that I got an extremely good education.</u>
      <u who="LI">And you mentioned that you felt as though your education was broadened. Just in a sense of the scope of classes that you were taking, or was there another way in which you felt that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> had expanded your awareness or knowledge?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Certainly in the scope of classes, yes. But also just the atmosphere. I mean, although we had a good time there, people worked hard, and the professors were top quality. And, you know, going to school with students from all over the country and from a wider range of demographic and economic backgrounds than I had at <orgName>Sidwell Friends</orgName>—that was part of the broadening experience as well, I think.</u>
      <u who="LI">Were your views challenged? Or did they change by those interactions with different sorts of people?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Not in any dramatic way that I can identify. I think at the time, I sort of considered myself somewhere in the progressive Republican category. I mean, I’ve later become a Democrat all the way down the line and probably pretty radical in ways, but in those days I was sort of in a fairly middle-of-the-road kind of approach, both politically and socially. So, you know, there wasn’t any great turn at that stage. There was later in my life, but not at that stage so much. It was a—it was a pretty—it was a pretty solid and pleasant broadening experience, but it was not—it’s not an abrupt shift, by any means, in my perspectives about things.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And so I guess approaching—you say you got into <orgName>Harvard Medical School</orgName>. Did you go there immediately after <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, I did. I did my senior year at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, by the way, as a Senior Fellow—they still have Senior Fellowships, is that right?—</u>
      <u who="LI">I believe so, yes.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—where a relatively small number of high-achieving seniors get to be <orgName>Senior Fellows</orgName>, which means they don’t have any course requirements whatsoever. There was nothing I needed to take in my senior year. However, I needed to write some kind of a project, and I kind of wasted my senior year (one of the things I do regret) by dreaming up some kind of project called something like Readings from Three <name type="event">Great Periods of History</name>—Great Readings from <date>Three Periods of History</date>. I don’t even remember the name of it, exactly,—</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—which shows how—how sloppily I did the thing. So I didn’t do myself a service, really, in <date>senior year</date>. But I did take a variety of additional courses, and I did still focus on getting into medical school. And I got into medical school. I went directly there. My dad actually tried to convince me to apply for <orgName>a Rhodes Scholarship</orgName>, and I might have had some chance at it, in <date>those days</date>, anyway, but I didn’t want to. I just wanted to go on to medical school, because that had been such a big part of my aim, my identity. So I got accepted to several schools and decided to go straight to <orgName>Harvard</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="LI">And you mentioned your father tried to I guess dissuade you from going to medical school. Were your parents, in the end, supportive of that—of that choice?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No. Actually, I probably gave a misimpression there. No, he did not try to dissuade me from going to medical school. I mean, I think he puzzled as to why I was going to medical school, because, as I have mentioned, the whole family was lawyers, and this would be a big departure from <persName>Rogers</persName> and [unintelligible]. But he was proud. I mean, you know, it’s hard to—I guess it’s hard to be too critical of someone going to <orgName>Harvard Medical School</orgName>, so—</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—he—they were supportive, but <persName>Dad</persName> thought that I could take <date>a year</date> off or so and get a <orgName>Rhodes Scholarship</orgName>. For some reason, being a <orgName>Rhodes Scholar</orgName> gives you, like, a lifelong label.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It’s one of the few things where if you talk about somebody and you—you always proceed it by saying he or she was a Rhodes Scholar. It’s like a kind of coronation. Normally I don’t care about those things, but it’s one area that I regret a little bit not having applied for so I could get that automatic label, of the smart person the rest of my life, but it really hasn’t gotten in my way at all [chuckles] not to have it.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Laugh].</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Anyway, I said no to Dad. “I’m not going to apply. I’m going to <orgName>Harvard medical School</orgName>.” And he said, “Great. That’s fine.” They both—they both were supportive of it, and that’s where I headed after my senior year.</u>
      <u who="LI">And what was that transition like?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Terrible. I’ve looked back on it a lot and never been able to sort it out entirely. The end result is that after completing <date>a year</date>, I dropped out of medical school. I don’t know all the reasons, but I went from idyllic <placeName>Hanover</placeName> and <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> to a really part of <placeName>Boston</placeName> where <orgName>the Harvard Medical School</orgName> is—it’s not in <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>; it’s across the river, in a less pleasant part of <placeName>Boston</placeName>, with extremely smart people, whom I liked, and I worked just incredibly hard. And two-thirds of the way through <date>my first year</date>, I was doing fine. I got honors grades, and I was doing fine. But I got mono, mononucleosis, a pretty severe case of it and left school in the spring of <date>my freshman year</date> at <orgName>Harvard Medical School</orgName> and went home to my parents’ house to recuperate. </u>
      <u who="LI">And what about it? You said you lost interest in medicine. Can you articulate why, or is that still just one of the unknowns?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, it’s a little bit of the unknowns, but I have sort of standard answers that—that are at least part of the truth. I started thinking that medicine would be too confining for me in the sense that, although there are plenty of exceptions—people in public health and so forth—to a large extent, many doctors spend their life in a hospital or in an office with not too much exposure outside and not too much involvement in the community, for good reasons. But unfortunately, for instance, there are relatively few doctors in public positions. There are relatively few doctors in <orgName>Congress</orgName>. There are relatively few doctors in most community organizations. That’s because they’re working so damn hard and because they’re so devoted to what they do and it’s so consuming.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And so when you did return home, what were you thinking at that point in terms of, you know, your next steps?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, you know, the thing that was the obvious thing looming on the horizon was I had given up my student deferment, and this was at a time when <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> was raging. The fall of <date>’67</date>. You know [the] Tet [Offensive] was early in <date>1968</date>. The protests were increasing. But at the same time, the draft, which was still in place, before the lottery had started <date>a few years later</date>—the draft was obviously at the forefront for me because I was not subject to being drafted into the [U.S.] <orgName>Army</orgName> and being sent out on—out into the <persName>bush</persName> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and in <orgName>Army</orgName> infantry grunt.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">So I had to figure out what the heck was I going to do, given this new reality and the fact that I was feeling completely disoriented and didn’t have a sense of identity anymore, and it was a very—very tough <date>six months or so</date>.</u>
      <u who="LI">At that point, did you believe in the war?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No. I—I was not an active protester. First of all, again, I was just so absorbed in my own angst and staying out of it still physically and all those things, but I was not an active protester, but as I remember writing before I went over there, I used the phrase “stupid war.” I think it kind of sounds like [unintelligible]. I don’t know if it’s right to [unintelligible]. This kind of “stupid war.” It just didn't make sense to me even then. But I’ll just say I was not out marching with protesting.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And so in thinking that it was a stupid war, I mean, obviously you eventually went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but what did you think about the draft or the possibility of serving there?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I was terrified. You know, very few—I don’t know what the statistics are. You probably have them—how many people from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> ended up in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but I imagine it’s a relatively small number compared to the number who graduated in <date>those years</date>. And if that’s correct—I assume that’s correct, right? You know, it’s a relatively small number.</u>
      <u who="LI">I would assume so. I don’t actually have the statistics, though.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, none of my fraternity mates and my other close friends went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I was one of the few. And I could have avoided it easily in a number of ways. Staying in medical school was the first one. When I dropped out medical school, I went to see a counselor for a while because my whole world had been turned upside down, and he offered to right me a bogus deferment, based on anxiety or whatever, and I said no. I said, “I am capable of serving, and I’m not going to accept the bogus deferment.” And I’ve always been glad that I didn’t do that, and sort of proud that I didn’t do that.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And in terms of considering whether or not to be exempt from the draft, did you feel a sense of obligation to be on the same plane as every other American of your age at that point?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, if I understand your question. Yes, I didn’t—that’s the reason I turned down that offer of a medical deferment. Yeah, if that’s what you mean. Yeah, I—I didn’t want to use my privileged background in a—in a non-genuine way.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">You know, I felt some sense of obligation. If others were doing this, why should I not do this? But I don’t want to glamorize that too much. I was not somebody that said, “I’m going to join the Marines to show I can do it” or because other people are—you know. Took a middle course. I mean, I didn’t actively try to avoid my obligation, but I tried to direct my service in a way that was less—less dangerous.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And what was the family reaction to deciding to go into <orgName>the Officer Candidate School</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">My dad, who had been a <orgName>Navy</orgName> officer in <name type="event">World War II</name>, on the aircraft carrier in the <placeName>Pacific</placeName>, was hit by kamikazes and so forth—my dad was proud of me, pleased. I think Mother was proud and scared. My siblings were kind of puzzled that anybody in our family would—any of the four of us, the three siblings and I—were puzzled that I would be willing to go into the military when I had a way to avoid it.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And do you think that your dad’s—did your dad’s service influence that decision at all?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, I think it did. You know, I was proud of him. He didn’t talk very much about it, like most war veterans. He rarely talked about his service. He didn't know much about it except  kind of some of the more sanitized recollections. But, yeah, I’m quite sure that it had some effect on how I felt about the <orgName>Navy</orgName> and my decision to go that route rather than some of the other possible routes I might have taken.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And when you joined, what was that process like?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Really tough. I was still feeling really disoriented and still physically kind of weakened, very anxious. I got orders to go to <orgName>Officer Candidate School</orgName> they said that in <placeName>Newport</placeName>, <placeName>Rhode Island</placeName>, for <date>four moths</date>. I drove there, and I remember that as an extremely scary and unpleasant trip. You know, I was going into a completely new world, and—you know, again, from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and then <orgName>Harvard Medical School</orgName> to marching in formation and getting your head shaved and doing all that stuff you do in the first training in the military.</u>
      <u who="LI">Do you—it sounds like you went from, you know, such a mindset of uncertainty and then going into this environment where you were instructed what to do, you know, <date>all day</date>, <date>every day</date>. Do you think that was helpful in any way or even more disrupting?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">That’s another fascinating question. I’ve actually never thought about it. I think—I think at some level it was helpful, and I’ve never thought of it quite that way. Not having to make decisions anymore [chuckles], for the most part. You know, just being told what to do. I suppose that you lose some of the challenges, not in a very pleasant way,—</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—but in a way that maybe helped me get through it. Once you’re in the military, you’re in. You don’t just say, “I’m sorry, I think I’m gonna leave now.” [Both chuckle softly.] There may be ways out, but they’re not very pleasant. But—so, yeah, good question. And I might add that to my personal narrative as I think about it.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] Feel free.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="LI">And can you describe for me what your regimen was like, the <date>daily</date> activities and, you know, what that training process felt like?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, it was a mixture of sort of typical military vigor, you know, with a lot of marching in formation and a lot of making sure your uniform is completely the way it should be: everything is in position. And being forced to stand at attention till you felt like you were going to faint. So there was—oh, and cleaning—you know, cleaning toilets with toothbrushes and all those kinds of things. There was sort of that—kind of standard military size, certainly not as rigorous as in the Marines or in <orgName>the Army Rangers</orgName> or SEALs [<orgName>U.S. Navy’s</orgName> Sea, <orgName>Air</orgName>, Land teams] or something like that, but—but enough to be really pretty unpleasant and demeaning in one way; but, of course, there’s a reason for it: just to make you into part of a machine designed to conduct war.</u>
      <u who="LI">In terms of the interesting parts, what was most exciting?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Navigation for me was the most exciting. I guess they identified me as having some abilities in that regard, so I was kind of pointed towards doing some additional work after <orgName>OCS</orgName> in the navigation area and eventually became a navigator on a ship, among other duties. So that was probably the most interesting part.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And what was the communication like? You know, you’re obviously going through such an intense and singular experience in the sense that it’s, I imagine, so different from what your friends from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> were doing, for example, so how much interaction did you have with either friends from home or people outside, and, you know, what was it like being in this very surreal bubble?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah. It was surreal. It’s interesting you used that word because “surreal” is the term that I use most often when I talk about that whole period of my life, especially actually, <date>the year</date> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, surreal in every sense. But fortunately, not only family was really supportive and I was in close contact with them, but a number of my <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> friends were. My <persName>Dartmouth</persName> friends ended up—were then and have ended up being the closest friends I’ve kept from any of my past schools. I mean, closer than <persName>Sidwell Friends</persName> friends or my medical school friends or eventually my <orgName>Yale Law School</orgName> friends. My <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> friends, I think, partly because I loved <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> so much, but with my classmates—we kept in touch. </u>
      <u who="LI">And when you were there, did you ever question your decision to join?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, not given the alternatives.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I mean, I questioned, How in the world did I get here?</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Most people do when they’re in war. Wait a minute, this wasn’t the way things were supposed to be. I was supposed to be in <date>my third year</date> of medical school by now. Here I am. I’m floating around in little <orgName>Navy</orgName> boats with little funny hats, with the possibility of going to a war on the horizon. What’s goin’ on here?</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And what kinds of people did you meet there and interact with there? How did they compare to all of your other experiences, either growing up, at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> or at <orgName>Harvard Medical School</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">A somewhat more wide-ranging group. To get into <orgName>OCS</orgName>, you had to be a college graduate, so—so it wasn’t like this was a wildly different group of people, as actually was true when I got to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I was with a much wider range of—people with a wider range of backgrounds. But at <orgName>OCS</orgName>, it was like a wider range of college graduates. I mean, it was sort of a minor change from what I’d been in before, but, you know, again, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and <orgName>Harvard Medical School</orgName> and <orgName>Sidwell Friends</orgName>—they’re sort of the elite or snobby or whatever word you want to use, but a slice of Americana. And <orgName>OCS</orgName> guys were—and it was all guys—were from a wider range of schools: more state universities and lesser-known schools, so it was a somewhat bigger range of personalities and education and probably just brains than I had been used to, but not dramatically so.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And did you engage in open conversations about views on the war, or was that kind of, you know, taboo, in a sense?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It wasn’t—I don’t know that it was taboo, but it wasn’t really discussed. I mean, I think everybody—I know everybody was uncertain about where they were going to go, and we didn’t find out until about the third—almost the beginning of <date>the fourth month</date> of the <date>four-month</date> program, so you didn’t know where you were going to go, and everybody, of course, had <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in the back of their minds, although interestingly, not very much of us in my regiment, so-called regiment, ended up being sent to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Actually, just two, me and one other guy.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And can you tell me about that—finding out where you were going to go?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, I got a letter from <orgName>the Office of Naval Personnel</orgName>, I think it was, that basically said, “You’re going to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> for <date>a year</date>, on a hospital ship.” And I had no idea what that meant, but I knew it wasn’t something that I was hoping for. I was hoping not to see the word “<placeName>Vietnam</placeName>” in orders that I got, so it was quite scary. </u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And pride in—did you take pride in the fact that you would be involved in the war but not necessarily causing directly any harm to the opposition? </u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, a lot of pride in that sense.</u>
      <u who="LI">Was that a consideration?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">pride in this context doesn’t quite ring true, but I guess I—I had some pride that I hadn’t pulled strings or—or taken my bogus deferment, that I was doing my part, even though I didn’t believe in this war. I mean, it’s kind of a strange thing. I mean, pick a side. I think every single person of my generation, especially men but not just men, every single person was affected at some personal level by <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>. No matter what my peers did, the war was a looming presence in their lives. Most of them found a way not to go. That’s fine. I respect that. But many of those who didn’t go feel some guilt for not going. I felt some guilt being largely on a ship and not subject to being shot at, probably.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And how much time did you have between finding out where you were going to actually leaving?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I had <date>the remaining month</date> or so of <orgName>Officer Candidate School</orgName>, and we graduated. And, by the way, one of my most fun moments was when—since I was one of the four top bands in our regiment—I was marching up front, in all of our fancy white uniforms, and with a fake sword and all that stuff, and General [<persName>Lewis B.] Hershey</persName>, who was the head of [the] Selective Service [System] at the time (not exactly a loved figure) was there, watching our graduation, and as I marched by with my fellow graduates, I marched right by his reviewing stand. You do this maneuver with your sword where you flip it up and then you pull it up to your shoulder, and as you do that, the tip of my sword caught a rim of my cap, my hat, my cover, and knocked it off right in—right in front of General <persName>Hershey</persName>.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">And I was really embarrassed, and then I really thought that was an appropriate gesture.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I just threw it out, right in front of the head of <orgName>Selective Service</orgName>, the guy who ran the draft. My parents were there. I saw <orgName>Hershey</orgName> as my eyes drifted through the crowd, and he was scowling. You could tell—</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—he didn’t like somebody in the front messing up like that. And then I saw my parents, and they were kind of suppressing laughter. They thought it was wonderful. And that really reassured me. And I thought that was a good moment. I sort of gave a figurative finger to General <persName>Hershey</persName>, and my parents had it in perspective, so that was one of my—one of my more satisfying moments in <orgName>OCS</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] Certainly.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">So anyway, I did that, and then I got sent to <placeName>San Diego</placeName> for <date>about two more weeks</date> to do additional training in navigation and seamanship and preparing me to go to this ship.</u>
      <u who="LI">And mentally what were you—I’m sure there were so many things going through your head, but how did you at least try to prepare or think about being gone for <date>a year</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">You know, in some ways I didn’t. There were sort of—it was a little bit like what you put your finger on at <orgName>OCS</orgName>, which is I didn’t have any choice. I just did what I was told. And, you know, I didn’t know what to expect, really. I exchanged letters with the fellow that I was to relieve on the ship. Since everybody was there <date>only 365 days</date>, you know, we didn’t go over as a unit; we didn’t come back as a unit. Nobody—almost nobody in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> did. </u>
      <u who="LI">And what <date>year</date> was this? What period of time?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS"><date>The fall of 1968</date>.</u>
      <u who="LI">Okay. So how—how much was the impending election on your mind at this point?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Not—not too much. You know, I was so focused on my stuff. Dad was out of government then. I didn’t know he was going to end up back in government,—</u>
      <u who="LI">Okay.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—so I wasn’t terribly focused on it. I did have—of course, <persName>Nixon</persName> was the candidate, and <persName>Dad</persName> was an associate of <persName>Nixon</persName>, a long-time associate of <persName>Nixon</persName>, for better and for worse, and so I was aware of it in that regard, but it didn’t really become prominent until <date>the day</date> after I got to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, when <persName>Nixon</persName> was elected.</u>
      <u who="LI">Hmm. So can you tell me about, I guess, first arriving in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and experiencing the ship?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">You know, I should have asked you earlier: Are we able to take a five-minute break, or is that disruptive?</u>
      <u who="LI">Sure. No, we can absolutely pause.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Let’s—let’s do that, and that’s a good chance to do that because we’re just starting into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and so if we can just put it on hold for a minute, that’d be great.</u>
      <u who="LI">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="LI">This is <persName>Ellen Li</persName>, still in <orgName>Rauner Special Collections Library</orgName>, and we are back after a brief break. And I am on the phone with Mr. <persName>Jeff Rogers</persName>.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah. After my <date>three weeks</date> or so of additional training in <placeName>San Diego</placeName>, I reported to Travis Air Force Base outside of <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> and flew on military planes to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. The route was kind of symbolic of what the whole war was like. It was kind of a disjointed trip. I flew—we stopped—and the military plane stopped in <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, <placeName>Guam</placeName> and then the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, and then I traveled down from <placeName>Manila</placeName>, where we ended up, to [Naval Base] <placeName>Subic Bay</placeName>, where I was supposed to find the ship I was going to be on, the USS Repose , AH-16—and that’s hospital ship 16.</u>
      <u who="LI">And did this round-about process kind of create a sense of—or heighten the sense of anticipation, or was it more of a frustrating experience?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It was a puzzling experience. I mean, I would have expected things to be running a little more together than that, you know. I talked with the niece, who served in <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> not long ago, and she talks about how they had scheduled planes and it was more like commercial airlines in the kind of she had, whereas in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> it was this hit-and-miss sort of thing, and so it was kind of puzzling. Like, Hmm, this is kind of a weird way to get somebody to a war duty.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And could you describe the ship for me?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="LI">Physically.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">The ship was a little over 500 feet long. It was a converted <name type="event">World War II</name>—it originally was built in <date>the ’40s</date> as a cargo ship, but they later converted it and one other <orgName>Navy</orgName> ship to hospital ships, about 500 feet long. Painted white with a big red cross on it, indicating it’s a medical facility. Not a very sleek ship. We did not have guns. I mean, there were some personal guns on the ship, a few, but this was not a warship of a typical sort. It didn’t look like a typical <orgName>Navy</orgName> ship, and it was not particularly in great shape, although it had a very good hospital on it.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And how would these patients get to your ship?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">The largest number of them would be brought by helicopter, and we would stay close to the battle patients and to the onshore medical facilities. So some of them would be helicoptered out directly from the battlefields where they were injured, and we would be the first medical facility they would be brought to. Some of the others would go from the battlefields to the smaller, onshore medical facilities and then be flown out to us.</u>
      <u who="LI">Okay. And so you mentioned that you would serve anyone and help anyone. Did that mean that your ship was sort of a neutral space in terms of, you know, did any Vietnamese ever interact with Americans on board? What was that sort of culture like?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, anybody could interact with anybody. And, of course, it was reflective of part of the weirdness of that war, which is for most of the Vietnamese, if they were other than engaged in actual combat, you didn’t know which, quote, “side” they were on or what their background was. And many of the Vietnamese would be loyal to one side during <date>the day</date> and the other side at night, and it was kind of chaotic that way, so there was—there was this atmosphere on the ship of—what’s the word? Mixture, melting pot? Kind of like, Wow, this is sort of reflective of this war. We got a lot of soldiers and Marines, but then we got a little bit of all kinds of other—other people. And, you know, again, We don’t know. We can’t sort of it out. We’re here to provide medical care to people, and we’re gonna do it.</u>
      <u who="LI">And was it—you know, in some ways you’re so far removed from the warfront in the sense that you’re not doing any fighting, but you see the direct results with the wounded coming aboard your ship and your ship’s sole purpose being to help those who have been wounded, so what was that disparity like? Did you—did you think about it a lot? Was that on your mind?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Oh, yeah. And that’s another aspect of that surreal thing. Like you say, we were not in any direct combat. I mean, there was always some concern about that. We always had to have some guards out so that any sappers [<placeName>Viet Cong</placeName> or <orgName>NVA</orgName> solders who got inside a perimeter, armed with explosives; members of the Viet Cong elite <orgName>C-10 Sapper Battalion</orgName>] who might come—who might swim out to the ship and plant explosives or something wouldn’t do it. So we were always aware of some potential danger, even to the ship.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, it was bizarre.</u>
      <u who="LI">And did you ever, as an officer, not necessarily, you know, a doctor or a nurse treating these people directly—would you talk to the patients about what it was like out there, or was there not that much interaction?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, no, we had a reasonable amount of interaction, not a huge amount. We were mostly focused on our jobs. But, yeah, had some interaction, and we would—and the more you heard, the more you thought, This makes no sense whatsoever. And the more I realized that the news reports were so misleading. I mean, we didn’t have easy access to news because in <date>those days</date>, halfway around the world was a long [chuckles] ways away, so—but when we did get news, the reports were so contrary to what we were seeing and hearing.</u>
      <u who="LI">And so you think that those misleading news reports were intentionally misleading or, you know, where was the loss in translation? I mean, maybe you didn’t know, but it seem like they were just trying to—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I had some knowledge of that, but mostly speculative, but I think the government was being intentionally misleading, and the media was relying on the government. And, you know, eventually the media had fairly good access to what was actually going on in the war, and that assisted the growing protests. You know, [<orgName>CBS</orgName> journalist] <persName>Walter [  L.] Cronkite [Jr.</persName>] went over there and came back and basically started talking against the war. And that was huge in <date>those days</date> because <persName>Cronkite</persName> was a legendary figure. And when he was able to see for himself, the media started coming around more on it. </u>
      <u who="LI">And did you—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">[unintelligible].</u>
      <u who="LI">—convey these—these sentiments to your father at all, who was—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, I did to some extent. Yes, I did to some extent. Actually, the letters I wrote home became the subject of a chapter in a book written by a professor who happened to have my son as a student, and my son wrote a paper about letters home, and the professor liked the letters so much—and my son was on—. She wrote this chapter about my letters. And in the letters, I gave some—I gave to Dad some indications of how misleading I thought stuff was and how much of a waste I thought the war was.</u>
      <u who="LI">I actually read the letters that I could find online. And that definitely struck me, the sense that—you know, having so much frustration, of feeling like there were just two completely opposing viewpoints in terms of what was actually happening and what was being reported.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, at least for a long time. I think that changed some as the war went along, but, you know, I was there at the height of the war in the sense that when I got there, there was the largest number of Americans, 535,000 or something like that, so I was there right—right at the peak. And as it continued to drag on and on and on, people became more aware, I think, of what was going on, but it was a slow process, like worms.</u>
      <u who="LI">And were you ever privy to any more information than everyone else on your ship with you, because of your father being in <persName>Nixon</persName>’s administration?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I was not—not through Dad. <persName>Dad</persName> had an extremely high level of integrity and never told me anything confidential. On the other hand, because people were aware that <persName>Dad</persName> was secretary of state by that time, I was treated with kid gloves, and I was given privileges that I shouldn’t have been given, but—</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And did that create any sort of uncomfortable relationships on the ship as well?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No. For some reason, people were—nothing seemed to bother people. I really appreciated that. I like to think it’s because I wasn’t full of myself that way. I mean, I—I—I respected the people that I was working with a great deal, and I knew that the enlisted guys knew a hell of a lot more than I did about how to run a ship and all that, so I didn’t feel like, and I didn’t hold myself out to somehow be above anybody else. And I think people responded well to that. So I didn’t—I didn’t feel any tension. I mean, I got teased about it occasionally and that sort of thing, but—but it didn’t create a problem or me, thankfully.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And to kind of take a few steps back, what was the <date>daily</date> life like there? You were there for <date>365 days</date>. What were your main duties, and what was <date>the typical day</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Repetitious and boring, punctuated by moments of excitement, horror and so forth when the helicopters came in with the patients. My duties, although I worked up to them a little bit at the beginning of the time there—I ended up being navigator, so my duty in that regard was to make sure we knew where we were when we were sailing up and down the Vietnamese coast up to the <placeName>DMZ</placeName>, demilitarized zone, and back to <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, and in harbor and helping us head into the harbor and anchor in the right places. Also navigating our way over to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, were we went four times for upkeep during <date>the year</date>. So navigator was one of my primary duties.</u>
      <u who="LI">And being on a hospital ship, which obviously is concerned with medicine, how did that make you or did it make you reflect upon your decision to, you know, leave <orgName>Harvard Med</orgName> and leave, you know, the medical path?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, it kind of reinforced my decision. Basically—although I did spend some time in the hospital, basically I wanted to kind of stay away from it. I had this sense I wanted to get away from medicine. Well, hell, I wanted to get away from medicine and they sent me to a hospital ship. [Both chuckle.] Not quite as good an escape as I would have imagined, although it turned out to be very fortunate. So I think it reinforced my decisions that I was right. I felt no draw or actual—spending extra time as needed in the hospital, and I didn’t.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And did you—I mean, obviously you were so isolated, I would imagine, on that ship. Did you have much contact with the Vietnamese or the Vietnamese culture at that time?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, some. I mean, I’d go ashore fairly often. As <date>the year</date> went along, I’d go ashore more often. Only kind of superficial contact. I mean, be walking along the streets of <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> or other places in the country. When I flew up to <placeName>the Central Highlands</placeName>, we went and went to, you know, a couple of Montagnard [indigenous peoples of <placeName>the Central Highlands</placeName> of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>] settlements and had some contact with the Vietnamese there and took some photographs of them and talked with them some.</u>
      <u who="LI">And was that reassuring, feeling so—having the concept of American transplanted into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, or did it kind of contribute to how disorienting and bizarre and surreal the experience was?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">The latter, yeah. Yeah, it added to that. And it added to the sense of What the hell are we doin’ here? You know, a big, powerful country, who, by the way, is completely impotent in this war, but What are we doin’? We’re invading their country and destroying the countryside and a lot of them dying, and—yeah, it was disorienting, surreal and very distressing, in the sense that we had completely upended their <date>daily</date> lives, although fortunately we didn’t destroy their culture. But, yeah, it was not good.</u>
      <u who="LI">And I guess in terms of—who were your main lines of communication between—within <orgName>the American Navy</orgName> and the military? How did you receive your information?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">As an officer of the deck and so forth, we—we got intelligence—we got lots of intelligence information directly to us. Also received newspapers and <orgName>Armed Forces Radio</orgName> [and <orgName>Television Service</orgName>] and that sort of thing. So there were lots of sources of information. A lot of it was suspect in terms of we couldn’t necessarily rely on it, but there was big delay in information from the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>, to a large extent, [unintelligible] the newspapers stories [unintelligible]. I mean, we were a long ways away in <date>those days</date>. Halfway around the world was a very big thing, of course.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And did everyone on the ship have similar feelings about, you know, being so confused by the purpose of the war?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, I couldn't speak for any- —everyone, but, yeah, I think—I think—it was hard—it was hard to be over there without starting to wonder, What the hell is this all about? Nothing ever seemed to change. It was the same thing day after day, just more people getting injured and killed. You know, the whole body count philosophy made no sense whatsoever. We didn’t know who the enemy was, and who friends were.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah. So how did you kind of cope with that sense of being resigned to the current state of things and the monotony of your time there as well?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, again, you know, it’s like—there’s no way to cope other than to just do it. You know—how do I convey this?  It’s like—that’s what’s so different about the military. That’s what’s so different about war. You no longer really had any choices. You just do what you have to do. And you don’t think too much about it. You know, you try to count off <date>the days</date>, and you count <date>each day</date>, and if nothing terrible happens it’s a good day. You figure eventually it’ll end, but you had no choice.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And so were you thinking a lot about what you wanted to do once you came home? Were you thinking of home all the time?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I had already applied to law schools and been accepted, so I knew that was what I wanted to do. But, yeah, I was thinking about it, but you try not to think about it too much because you can’t speed it up.  You just try to find distractions. You try to find some things that are pleasurable. And what it was, it was unusually—unusually nice to have women on the ship. It wasn’t the whole heavy-duty fraternizing because it was against the rules, and you didn’t have time to do it, but humans are humans, so there was—you know, I hung out with some of the nurses, and that was a distraction, although often they’d be talking about the patients they were taking care of and how hard that was, so it wasn’t, like, it was a complete relief. But mostly, as I said, I had no choice.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">[Unintelligible]. I tried to sleep, and I tried to eat, tried to wait for <date>tomorrow</date>.</u>
      <u who="LI">And what were your favorite distractions then?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Nurses. [Chuckles.] Sorry.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">[Chuckles.] Yeah. But, as I say, sometimes the discussions with nurses were not uplifting.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] I can imagine. Wow.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I really admired the nurses and the medical people. I mean, <orgName>the Red Cross</orgName> workers and the nurses were—were amazing, amazing.</u>
      <u who="LI">And it must have been probably hard for the nurses in particular, I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Oh, yeah. But some of them were deeply affected.</u>
      <u who="LI">Did you—I mean, in terms of the range of—I’m sure it was traumatic to be constantly or, you know, frequently seeing all these people who were so badly injured. How did you sort of react to that or deal with that aspect?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, it was—it was complex, like everything out there. I mean, it was traumatic in one sense, but, you know, always remind yourself, Well, your trauma of seeing this is nothing like what that person you’re seeing is experiencing. But it was the waste of it. It was the utter waste.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I sort of forget what your question was, but that’s what happened.</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah.  And so this idea of waste and everything being so arbitrary—was it also difficult to reach <date>day 365</date>?  You know, it wasn’t like you were leaving after accomplishing some feat in the sense that there was a goal besides, you know, doing your job for <date>one year</date>. How did that feel?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Just like you—just the way your question suggests: a sense of futility, a sense of sadness, of loss, and a sense of yearn for not only the people so directly affected but for the country, really. And, of course, for me it was complicated additionally—I don’t mean complicated worse than another people. Not at all. But complicated additionally, in an unusual way by <persName>Dad</persName> being secretary of state and advising <persName>Nixon</persName>, who, contrary to <persName>Dad</persName>’s advice, was the primary mover of keeping this damn war going for <date>another five years</date> after he got elected, saying he had a plan to end the war. Just about as many people were killed during the time I was there and afterwards as they were before I was there. That’s hardly a quick end to the war.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">So it was—it was—added to the surreal quality for me was, you know, my dad was one of the few people in the governmental, fortunately—his advice consistently was to get out and get out quicker, but he and [<persName>Melvin R.] Laird</persName>—he and <persName>Laird</persName>, as secretary of defense, were not able to persuade <persName>Nixon</persName> and [<persName>Henry A.]</persName> <persName>Kissinger</persName> to do that.</u>
      <u who="LI">And did you talk to—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">So that would trigger— I’m sorry?</u>
      <u who="LI">I was just wondering: Did you—to what degree did you and your father exchange opinions on the war?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I told him mine, but he didn’t tell me his very much. I knew he was—I knew he thought it was a war that should be ended more quickly, but he never violated confidentiality. He never told me or my siblings about internal discussions. But I do know, when he took office in <date>the beginning of 1969</date>, that he had told one of my siblings that he thought we ought to get out entirely from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> within <date>six months</date>. And he was pushing that all along. But the result unfortunately—what actually happened was we didn’t get out for <date>five years</date>.</u>
      <u who="LI">Mmm. And, I mean, what was the process of coming back like?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Strange and relatively uneventful for me, compared to many people who came back to great contempt, [calling] names and so forth. I came back as an officer to a stable family situation. I tried to put <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> out of my mind, to a large extent. People didn’t ask me much about it. Typical kind of thing, where you don’t talk much about it. But it was relatively smooth for me. The people that make the best transition back tend to be ones like me that have strong social support. Then, of course, I was not in direct combat, so that’s quite a different thing.</u>
      <u who="LI">So you didn’t—you tried to resist thoughts about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> once you were home.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I’m sorry, I didn’t do what?</u>
      <u who="LI">You were saying you tried to put <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> out of your mind once you were home, which obviously, I’m sure, is the natural reaction. So did that mean—you know, once you were back, did you have any resulting obligations, or was it once your <date>one-year</date> tour was over, then you were—you were done?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, I had <date>another year</date> of active duty obligation. I was in the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>. After <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you get some preference in your assignments, so I was able to get into the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>. I was in a weird little program in which I was helping administer the exchange of officers from foreign navies to train for a while with <orgName>the U.S. Navy</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="LI">And what—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I got out after the end of that. I got out after <date>two years</date> and had no subsequent obligations other than being in the [<orgName>U.S. Navy</orgName>] Reserves, which didn’t amount to anything, really.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right. And when you went back, what did you—what was your assessment in terms of <orgName>Vietnamization</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Basically that it was a joke. I didn’t say it quite so directly, but, I mean, <orgName>the Vietnamese Navy</orgName> was very small anyway; it didn’t have a very big role. But the whole idea of turning the war over to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> made no more sense than turning <placeName>Iraq</placeName> or <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> over to the Iraqis or Afghanis. It’s a futile kind of concept. It just showed our ignorance then of other cultures, of what was really going on in that country.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And did you have any communication with people still on that hospital ship once you had left?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">A little bit, for a little while. Not very much. I didn’t really make good friends over there, again because we weren’t over there as a unit. People were constantly coming and going. We didn’t really get to know people all that well. But I kept in touch with a few.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="ROGERS">But not for too long.</u>
      <u who="LI">And then once you were home and, you know, free of all obligations, did you just go straight to law school?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, I started law school in <date>the fall of 1970</date>.</u>
      <u who="LI"><date>Nineteen seventy</date>, okay. And what was that contrast like? You know, you’ve gone from—they’re essentially polar opposites. You’re back learning in school.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah, I was back to “normal.” [Both chuckle.] I was going to <orgName>Yale Law School</orgName>, <orgName>Sidwell Friends</orgName>, <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. That was where I was more familiar. But my whole approach to life had changed. I was much less driven. I worked much less hard. I had things in a different perspective. I started having my motto be “Do it while you can” because I’d seen that life was unpredictable and short, in a way that I knew intellectually before but never really internalized. </u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I’d grown up with Republican officials and presidents and happened to know the <persName>Clintons</persName> and have stayed in touch with them to some extent ever since, so adding to the weird twists in terms of my life.</u>
      <u who="LI">And how did you even try to find a sense of purpose, you know, in law school or going into law thereafter, once you had seen what you had seen in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yeah. My career moved towards working with or helping individuals. I never became a corporate lawyer or went to a big law firm. I started out as a public defender after law school. I did other jobs working with mentally ill people. I became a manager of an office in the city of <placeName>Portland</placeName> and became a mental health counselor. So I found purpose in working with individuals rather than more abstractly, more principles, such as corporate law or appellate law. I respect people who do that a great deal. I’m not criticizing them in any way, but for me that wasn’t satisfying to me. What was satisfying is working more directly with people. And that was sort of consistent with my initial interest to be a doctor, and I think being in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> probably intensified that sense of trying to do something that made some kind of difference in the day-to-day lives of people.</u>
      <u who="LI"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. And going back a little bit, obviously you mentioned how you grew up knowing the <persName>Nixons</persName> well. Obviously, your father was his colleague. How did you interpret the whole <name type="event">Watergate</name> scandal?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">A complete, utter disaster by <persName>Nixon</persName>. </u>
      <u who="LI">Sure. [A slight pause.]</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Looking back at <persName>Nixon</persName>, he did a lot of good things at one level: opening to <placeName>China</placeName>, the <orgName>EPA</orgName> [<orgName>the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</orgName>], helped provide universal health care, and yet he was a strange, paranoid guy who destroyed himself and did so dishonestly. </u>
      <u who="LI">And when you say “an unfortunate American attitude towards public service,” did it personally tarnish your perception of the government, or did you sort of see it as an isolated event with one individual and that it didn’t reflect on government as an institution?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I don’t—I think at the time, it did not reflect on government as an institution—well, let me rephrase that. I don’t think <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> reflected on government as an institution. I think <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—I’m sorry, I don’t think <name type="event">Watergate</name> reflected on government as an institution. I think <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> did. I think we were still enamored of <name type="event">World War II</name> and were unable to save ourselves from getting mired down in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And that reflected poorly on <persName>Lyndon Johnson</persName>, on <persName>Richard Nixon</persName>, on <persName>Robert McNamara</persName>, and probably more than specifically the government, it reflected poorly on our country, the militaristic attitude that we can solve the world’s problems if we’re strong.</u>
      <u who="LI">Right.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I think it led to a real decline in government. I mean, I do think nowadays that there is, in the federal government, especially <orgName>Congress</orgName>, of course, there’s a pervasive problem. But I worked for <date>many years</date> in local government, and I—I greatly respect government over all. And most of the people who work in government, I respect. But there are some very huge flaws, especially in <orgName>Congress</orgName> <date>these days</date>, and I think that’s a direct result of the anti-government attitude that started back in <date>the years</date> we’re talking about.</u>
      <u who="LI">And have you perceived a change in that sort of American imperialistic mind-set that you know, might have started at <date>the turn of the 20th century</date>, now?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Well, the terrorists won, in a sense. I mean, <date>September 11th</date> [the attacks on <date>September 11, 2001</date>] threw up into a panic worse than any panic we’d been in since the communist era in <date>the ’50s</date>, and we have overreacted. And getting involved in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>—I mean, I marched against <placeName>Iraq</placeName>. People had started—it just was so obvious there was going to be another <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and I think it was and is. </u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] Yeah. I mean, definitely.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I practiced law for <date>30 years</date>. Graduated from law school in <date>’73</date>, retired as a lawyer in <date>2004</date>, got a master’s degree in counseling, became a mental health counselor for <date>the last 12 years</date>, and much of that time has been counseling combat vets who have <orgName>PTSD</orgName> [post-traumatic stress disorder] or related problems, the largest number of whom are <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> vets but also <placeName>Iraq</placeName>, <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> vets, <name type="event">World War II</name> and <placeName>Korea</placeName> [<name type="event">Korean War</name>] vets.</u>
      <u who="LI">Do you think it’s made it easier to digest and process all that’s happened by being in this field now for <date>12 years</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Yes, undoubtedly. And it’s part of the reason I wrote this life history originally, a memoir. And in doing that, I looked back over lots of records and a lot of stuff from <date>the Vietnam years</date> and put a lot of things together. That’s been very satisfying for me, to kind of write the narrative for myself of my life and seeing how all these threads—and they were woven together over <date>the years</date>. If you ever have a chance to do that, you ought to do it for yourself, too. It’s really worth—worth doing. And I think actually your interviewing—</u>
      <u who="LI">Yeah, I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—and what you’re doing in this project is—is a part of that, not only for me but to others you’re talking to, I think, and I think extremely valuable.</u>
      <u who="LI">I certainly hope so.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Like many <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> vets, I was just sort of drawn back, and my son really wanted to go. He’d heard enough about it. When we first got over there, I went to <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, like you did, and I didn’t have any strong reaction. I’d been in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> during the war. I traveled with my dad, by the way, when I was on there—over there for <date>a year</date>. He came over to do some studies of things going on, and I traveled with him around the country then, including flying down to <placeName>Saigon</placeName> to meet him and fly around the country with him by helicopter.</u>
      <u who="LI">Would you ever want to go back?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I would definitely go back if I had a—an appropriate time to do it. Yeah, I would go back. </u>
      <u who="LI">I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No matter what your role, it’s [chuckles], again,—</u>
      <u who="LI">To say the least.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—not like anything else. I have a sign on my wall in my counseling office that says: “Human combat is unlike any other human experience.” And I would broaden that to be “war is unlike any other human experience, no matter what your role is in the war.”</u>
      <u who="LI">What do you hope that <placeName>America</placeName> ultimately learns from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Oh, good question. Hmm! I don’t know, it’s hard to come up with anything that doesn’t sound like a cliché. We need to learn what war is really all about. We need to recognize that we don’t solve things with wars. We need to pay attention to other cultures. We need to be more humble. We need to be more a part of the world. We’ve been actually so arrogant. You know, this is a great country, but we’re not the greatest country on <placeName>earth</placeName>. There’s no such thing. We’re all part of—<orgName>we’re</orgName> all in this together. </u>
      <u who="LI">I’m sorry. I’ve been holding it for three hours.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">Those were last experiences I had, at least. I’m glad we did, but I don’t usually talk for three hours. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] Yeah. I definitely hope those materialize, for sure.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">It’s up to you.</u>
      <u who="LI">Well, I think that—that feels like a great place to stop. Yeah. Unless you have some final thoughts about other <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>—or your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">No, I really don’t.</u>
      <u who="LI">—that you want to say.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">I mean, I think we covered a lot of material. I really appreciate the time, and I’m impressed with the way you did this. Either you’re really smart or they trained you really well. These interviews are [unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="LI">I really appreciate—</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—a good interview—</u>
      <u who="LI">—you taking this time.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">—and very thoughtful questions.</u>
      <u who="LI">[Chuckles.] Well, thank you for answering so thoughtfully as well.</u>
      <u who="ROGERS">You’re welcome, <persName>Ellen</persName>.</u>
      <u who="LI">I really appreciate it.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
