<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="RUBUS"/>
        <person xml:id="FARKAS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="FARKAS">This is <persName>Sandor Farkas</persName> talking to General <persName>Gary [M.] Rubus</persName> over the phone. I’m calling from <persName>Webster Hall</persName> [in <orgName>Rauner Special Collections Library</orgName> at <orgName>Dartmouth College</orgName>], and Mr. <persName>Rubus</persName> is in his home. It’s <date>the 16th of January, 2016</date>. And this is part of <orgName>the Dartmouth Vietnam Project</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">My father was <persName>James William Rubus</persName>. My mother was <persName>Shirley Miriam Zook Rubus</persName>, and they met in <placeName>Southern California</placeName>, where my father had been sent for training as an enlisted tank mechanic in the—the [<orgName>U.S.] Army</orgName>. My mother had somewhat migrated from western <placeName>Nebraska</placeName> with the defense industries, and they met in a—a hospital where my father was getting treatment for an injury that ultimately took him out of military service before he deployed, and they settled in <placeName>Southern California</placeName> during the war but stayed there until my father died of a heart attack in 19-about-97, and my mother was put into assisted living in <placeName>Oregon</placeName>, with my younger brother.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you’re referring to <name type="event">World War II</name>? Your father was an enlisted mechanic in the <orgName>Army</orgName> during <name type="event">World War II</name>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Correct.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And when did he enlist? Did he enlist much prior to the war, or did he enlist during the war?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">He was drafted as soon as he became of age. I don’t know actually the—the specific history on that. My speculation would be, from the ages involved, that it was during the war and drafted.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So where exactly did you grow up?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">When I was born, my parents were living in <placeName>Corona</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>. I was born in <placeName>Riverside</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>, very close to <placeName>Corona</placeName>. They moved once to [Lake] <placeName>Elsinore</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>. My father had taken a job with an automobile parts distribution company, and the company asked him to move to Banning, <placeName>California</placeName>, while I was in <date>the middle of first</date> grade, and they did, and I lived from my—my home, my parents’ home is in <placeName>Banning</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>, for the next—oh, about, <date>25 years</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So it sounds like both of your parents met in a military context. I mean, you said your mother was in defense industries and your father was at that time an <orgName>Army</orgName> mechanic. So was that part of—did you hear that story growing up a lot? Was the military something you were very conscious of?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Your last statement, “reasonably conscious of” would be a better term. And no, the fact that my mother and father met in a—in a—in an <orgName>Army</orgName> hospital, where she had volunteered as a—what I think would colloquially be known as a <orgName>Donut Dolly</orgName>, had nothing to do with my entering into the military.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you said you had—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">But I did have—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I’m sorry.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I did—I did have an uncle, who spent <date>almost 40 years</date> in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Navy</orgName> and had—had joined in 19- —well, before the war, I think <date>1937</date> or <date>1939</date>, I don’t know which, and had had—he was on the cruiser [USS] Juneau in one of the battles off Guadalcanal [in <placeName>the Solomon Islands</placeName>], they were sunk—and he spent some time in the—in the water, waiting for rescue and was one of fewer than 30 people that survived off an 1,800-crew—a crew of 1,800 people on the <placeName>Juneau</placeName>. So was aware of that story, but I’m not sure that that had much of a—of an impact on my joining the military. We’ll get to that a little further in—in your interview, I’m sure.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Of course. And you said you had a brother, if I recall? Did you have any other siblings?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Two younger brothers.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Two younger brothers. So you were the eldest. <date>What year</date> were you born?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><date>Nineteen forty-five</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And your other brothers? What years were they born?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t know <date>the years</date>. You can do the math. <date>Three years and</date> <date>nine years</date> younger than me.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">One, the eld- —the older of my two brothers is still with us; the younger passed away <date>last year</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I’m sorry to hear that. Did either of them join the military?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, they did not.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So going back to the town that you—you grew up in—or, sorry, the latter town that you spent more time in, tell me about what it was like. What kind of town was it? Was it very suburban, rural?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It was a very small town, approximately maybe 80 to 90 miles east of <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>. It was a small town in <date>those days</date>. As <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName> has expanded, it’s become almost suburban <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>, but in <date>those days</date>,  it was a very small town, 12 to 15,000. The high school I graduated from graduated 100 members in my class. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sounds good.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">In <date>the summer</date> after my <date>eighth-grade year</date>—it might have been before or after; I’d have to look back—my family, who—my father’s family was from central <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName> in the coal mining country, and my mother’s was in the farming area of <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>—would, <date>every couple of years</date>, head east and spend some time in <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>, spend some time in <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName> and then come home. It was a—a way to keep track of a reasonably large and extended family in <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>, and my mother’s connections with her two siblings in <placeName>Nebraska</placeName> and <placeName>Wyoming</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, what kind of farm was it?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Varied. It was in the <orgName>Sandhills</orgName> [region of <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>]. It had irrigation for the <orgName>Greenleaf</orgName>, <persName>Atlas</persName>, [unintelligible], and sorghum and a lot of wheat and a lot of alfalfa, but not a large farm, <date>today</date>’s standards, not a large farm. It was, I believe, three sections at that point. I—I don’t know a western <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName> city type like yourself will know what a section is, but that’s approximately three-square miles and probably three to four hundred head of cattle. No horses. We didn’t have any cowboys. But there was lots of wheat, lots of <persName>Atlas</persName> [unintelligible] and sorghum, corn, and alfalfa for the—for the cattle. Hogs, sheep. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I have, I guess, two questions coming off of that, and they’re kind of connected. One is at what point did you decide that you didn’t want to be a farmer? And the other is did you always want to go to college? Had you been planning on that? Was that an expectation?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I had always been planning to go to college. I only applied to 40 schools.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry, did you say 40?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I had no- —<date>40</date>, four zero, yes. I had no—no intention of becoming a farmer, and relatively early in <date>my younger years</date>, based on a—I’m not sure where the idea first came from—I tried to expose myself to a number of different potential career paths or professions, and had been interested in the military and an interest in the law. So those were all very attractive enterprise—working on a farm was—was a means to an end. It was not—certainly not a—a career objection.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—at a very young age, <date>at least two summers</date> and sporadic visits before that, he talked the lifestyle, the career progression, the work environment of being a fighter pilot.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I see. And what <date>years</date> would that have—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><date>What years</date> were that?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So in other words, as a fighter pilot, what was he doing? Was he deployed anywhere?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No. His career turned out to be totally dissimilar from mine. He had been in—this was the—I think he was commissioned in—oh, let’s see, probably ’55, ’6, ’7 or ’8. Had gone from <orgName>ROTC</orgName> to pilot training to a convers- —well, a training program that qualified him in the [Convair] F-102 [Delta Dagger], which was one of the very first supersonic, missile-equipped, air defense aircraft fighters, and his first operation assignment was at Andrews Air Force Base [now part of <orgName>Join Base Andrews</orgName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>] in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, defending the nation<placeName>’s</placeName> capital from the Soviet whores. I’m being a little facetious, but that was his job.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, did you share those political views at that time?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, <date>you’re—you’re—you’re</date> leaping to a conclusion. This individual had been a staunch [President <persName>Franklin D.] Roosevelt</persName> New Deal Democrat for a number of <date>years</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">So there were a very diverse set of political views, and I would say I think the work environment and the lifestyle on the farm and the independence had far more impact on my—what are conservative political views, but certainly I was subjected to a good deal of Republican propaganda at that time. You—you need also to understand that I am an <orgName>Independent</orgName>. I’m not a registered Democratic or Republican. And the missteps of the [President <persName>George W.] Bush</persName> administration, in its international program, but the second <persName>Bush</persName>, <persName>W.</persName>, made me an <orgName>Independent</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">So don’t draw any conclusions. Don’t draw any conclusions from ancient history, okay?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no, no. I’m not—not going down that line, certainly. But—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I think you can tell from the trajectory of this—of this—of this conversation that I—I don’t have a very common—I don’t have a very—didn’t have a youth—a childhood through matriculating at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> that—that would reflect most people’s experience.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I guess that is my next question: Why <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? I mean, opposite ends of the country. It seems like you were towards the south; that was towards the north. Entirely different spheres. How did you come to apply to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I applied to four Ivy League schools. I knew I would probably graduate as the valedictorian, would probably have a good academic grade—academic record in a very small but not very impressively academically high school. And I applied for—to a very wide range of institutions. And I enjoyed being out of the house, out of the home, and had no inhibition at all about going to school in <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> or in <placeName>Boston</placeName> or a number of places. I applied to both <orgName>Harvard</orgName> [University] and <orgName>Yale</orgName> [University] and was in the <orgName>Harvard</orgName> acceptance track, I believe, until I went for my alumni interview. And my alumni interview in <orgName>Harvard</orgName>, in the <orgName>Harvard</orgName> system had created such a negative impression that I withdrew my application. Let’s put it that way. No reason to trash one of our esteemed Ivy League colleagues [sic].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, at that point in time, did you apply for [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Air Force ROTC prior to coming to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, or is that something you started once you got to campus?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I wanted to take a look at the <orgName>Dartmouth ROTC</orgName> program and see whether I wanted to participate. I knew I could be commissioned any number of ways, and no, I didn’t—didn’t consider any activity with <orgName>ROTC</orgName> before I got to the campus. I went in and looked at the system and decided I would start with that. And, in fact, I’m not sure—I don’t recall the terminology, but I was—I—it’s easier to describe the fact that <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> offered me some kind of financial assistance that they worked out with the college. They picked up some of the bills that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was paying for me. They—they picked up those bills when I was a junior.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So let’s—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, sorry. I didn’t want to cut you off.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So let’s wind backwards a little bit. How did you actually get to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? Did you fly or drive across the country?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, I was in <placeName>Nebraska</placeName> at the time just before. My parents were—were planning to come to <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName> <date>that year</date>, so they—I don’t remember how they got there, but sometimes they took the train, they flew, or they drove, so I don’t know. But I met them in <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>. They drove me up to the campus. We both—we all looked at the campus, and then they went home.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember when you first got to the campus what your first impression was?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, I really don’t. But my—my first impressions of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> were more formed at—in the <placeName>Connecticut</placeName> suburbs of <placeName>New York City</placeName>, where I had—I had been informed who my roommates would be, and corresponding with one of them, and went to visit him, but I think we drove up. I—I—but he was in let’s just say a very different social and economics strata. And I had a very good time with his family and met a number of people who were all headed off to universities for <date>a couple of days</date>, a couple of parties in <placeName>Stanford</placeName>, <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>, and then went on to <placeName>Hanover</placeName>. My parents came in. They were not there very long. And we started—you know, the round of events that crank up your <date>freshman year</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So tell me about—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t have any major, major, huge impressions of <placeName>Hanover</placeName> or of <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> or anything like that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about your freshman orientation, your <date>first couple of weeks</date> or month at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I apologize, but I don’t have very many distinct memories of that—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Or here’s a—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—of that program as well.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Here’s a more specific one: I—I saw in your yearbook that you were part of Green Key [Society]?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">At that time, was <orgName>Green Key</orgName> still doing freshman welcoming stuff?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yes, I believe so, but you’re not really a Green Key until <date>your sophomore year</date>, when you participate in those kind of programs, so—but I don’t remember much about the Green Key orientation at all, on <placeName>Hanover</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah. So at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, what was your major?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Russian language and literature. And that’s not very descriptive of my academic program, but it was Russian language and literature.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, over your academic career at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, did you come in knowing you wanted to do Russian language and literature? Did you come in with a different idea?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, you—you—you’ve not described what was actually happening. I had an absolutely miserable foreign language program at that very small, academically challenged high school. I made the decision to start a new language, which was acceptable at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, to fulfill the foreign language requirement that existed in <date>those days</date>. I have no idea what’s their—what the foreign language requirement is now. But as a sideline—you know, as a sideline, a peripheral interest, secondary interest, I decided to take a language that I thought would be useful to me. And—and I bounced around in the decision process from French to German to Russian. And since I did have an interest in being in the military already, I thought, Well, I can either be a pilot or a spy.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">And Russian seemed to be an interesting language to take. And as I got into it, I did find that I was interested in as many aspects of <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> and the Russian culture as I was the language, and what is written up as a Russian language and literature major, if you actually look at the course content of what I took, I was allowed to take the minimum number of Russian language and literature courses to satisfy the department, but I also took as many of the sociology, history, political science—those kind of courses that related to <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> or <placeName>Russia</placeName>. So I actually cobbled together accidentally, with no particular design or intent, what <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> would have called or <orgName>the State Department</orgName> [sic; <orgName>U.S. Department of State</orgName>] would have called an area studies program.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Now, that did absolutely nothing for me career wise in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> in <date>the first 20 years</date> of that career. The Russian language was put on the shelf, and I got totally absorbed with—in other—in other things in the military. But obviously, since you know my history, it was resurrected later.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, in terms of other academic interests at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, are there any other memorable academic things that stick out to you?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, I was—I was very—I mean, there were no epiphanies; there were no—there were several instructors that were—were—were very, very good, but I—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember any of—of your favorites?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><persName>[Charles B.] McLane</persName> in political science, [Basil] Milovsoroff from the Russian language program, [<persName>Dmitri] von Mohrenschildt</persName> from the language program. I—I basically bounced around and cherry picked, without a—I didn’t have—for example, my—the room I—I lived with one roommate, [<persName>Kenneth M.] “Ken” McConnochie</persName> for <date>all four years</date>. We were in triple rooms for <date>the first three years</date>, but we had—the third party in the room was—was different <date>each year</date>, and then we—we pledged a fraternity and had a double room in the fraternity. But he had—he’s a physician now. I believe he’s instructing at <orgName>the Dartmouth Med[ical] School</orgName> [now <orgName>Geisel School of Medicine</orgName>], but—if he’s not retired.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, going back for a brief moment to not just high school but things prior to high school, would you describe yourself as popular in high school?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I was a very active participant in student government, athletics. I don’t know that “popular,” Big Man on Campus, if you’re looking for that kind of—mmm, I would say no, I wasn’t in the—the most popular, but I was very visible and very active in—in just about everything the college— the college— the high school offered.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now—so—and—sorry.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Let me ask—I’d like to—I’d like to pursue in the finest [unintelligible] traditions—one is: How large was your high school graduating class?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Fifty.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Fifty. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Was it a public or private institution?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Private.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. May I ask where it was, what was the name of the school?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">A little bit unusual. It was <orgName>Valley Forge Military Academy [&amp;amp</orgName>; College].</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I know it. Okay. I know it. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. </u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, we have very, very different—very different—we come from very different parts of <placeName>the United States</placeName>, and you have a very different high school—I mean, high school is not even the correct term. I don’t think—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">A very different experience.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">To ask—to ask the question of a backwoods, small, <orgName>Banning Union High School</orgName>—institution—and then project in to where you were—was it an all-male school? </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I think it was.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes, it was.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah. I don’t know that you can associate or identify with it, so I’m not sure it’s a useful question, but I’m happy to answer it. I’m just trying to put it in context for you.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">It’s—it’s—what I’m actually more interested in—we can move into this—is at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so you mentioned you were in a fraternity. I see Psi U [Psi Upsilon]—did they call it Psi U when you were part of it?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah. <persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yup. So why did you pick Psi U? Did you—did you always know throughout freshman year that you were interested in rushing?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, I didn’t. <persName>Ken</persName> and I rushed or went in a visitation mode to Psi U because he had brothers there. He was—let’s see, one, two—third-generation <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, I think. I can’t remember. But that was the interest. I found the—the <orgName>brotherhood</orgName>, or whatever you want to call it now—I don’t have a continuing, close relationship with Psi U, and we’ll talk more about that later. But that was a sort of a familial, indirect familial—but I rushed a whole bunch of them, and I found, after I got into—into Psi U that the attitudes of the brothers were more closely aligned with mine in terms of intellectual curiosity and wide-ranging interest in the fraternity itself and the membership, and that was the attraction. And I’m not sure it was a hugely conscious decision, but I—I hope that answers your question.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">It answers it perfectly. So at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, as a member of the fraternity system, did you—did you have a very active social life in the kind of conventional fraternity sense?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t know if I was more or less active than most people, but I do know I would say I would say I was, you know, average in terms of activity. I participated at—I was a—I played freshman football and enjoyed that. I’m not a large man, and I didn't see any future—I wasn’t going to do anything in the football program. I had been a baseball player and had played baseball, both on the high school teams and, in <date>the summer</date>, in <placeName>Nebraska</placeName> as—as a semi-pro kind of adult. That’s a term that might be deceptive in terms of how good the baseball teams were, but I got a car to get to the games and so forth.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. So at that time, if I’m correct, President [<persName>John S.]</persName> <persName>Dickey</persName> [Class of <date>1929</date>] was president?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Correct.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What did you think of <persName>Dickey</persName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">He was president <date>all four years</date>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What did you think of <persName>Dickey</persName> and the way he and the other administrators ran the school?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t know that I have a well-formed opinion of <persName>Dickey</persName>. I enjoyed, thoroughly enjoyed my experience at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. I thoroughly—I was challenged positively by the academic experience. I was very satisfied with the social and athletic and student government opportunities I had, so on balance, since he was responsible for that, you’d have to say that I have a favorable opinion. But in terms of a—a—a sense or direct knowledge of his personal role in that, I can’t tell you. But having commanded large organizations, I would say he was doing a very good job.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">All right, so let’s move on to <placeName>ROTC</placeName>. Can you tell me how you first got involved in <placeName>ROTC</placeName> at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I went—I—I had been—I had intended to evaluate the Air Force ROTC program before I got to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so I went in to see how they ran the program, see what the opportunities were, and it seemed to be a very flexible program. And ROTC detachment commander was a colonel who had been a [<orgName>Boeing</orgName>] B-17 [Flying Fortress] pilot in <name type="event">World War II</name>. The other—they only had two officers, if I recall. The other one had been a transport pilot, and they seemed to be good people and running a good program, and it was not going to interfere with my other objectives at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so I signed on.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about the structure of the program, where it was located, how many other cadets were in it?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Sure. I believe—I can’t tell you the total number, but I think you can infer from the numbers I’ll give you now—I don’t believe there were more than six or seven Air Force ROTC participants in each of the class years that I was associated with. So there were probably no more than 20, maybe <date>30</date>, but I doubt it. And we graduated four in my—in my class.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">There’s some humor in there. Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no, no. I want to hear the humor in this.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">How many—how many cadets are there in your—your class year? You’re a junior. How many—how many juniors are there in the <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC program now?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">It varies, but probably around four. We probably graduate around four to five cadets a year.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. There were larger classes in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> and in the <orgName>Army</orgName> when I was at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but the humor is in comparison to other universities, that’s minuscule, as you probably well know.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Of course.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Some of the public schools have cadet corps with maybe two or three hundred per class. When I showed up at <orgName>ROTC summer camp</orgName>, I was already a cadet colonel because we were all colonels. It was like a confederate <orgName>Air Force</orgName>. [Both chuckle.] And my roommate was a cadet major, who was very impressed to be a roommate with a full colonel until he found out how large the corps was, because he had something like a hundred people, lucky for him, in his cadet corps, and I—I had nobody working for me and three colleagues at <orgName>my cadet corps</orgName>, all colonels. So, yeah, as a soon-to-be—well, you have a military—you have far more military experience <date>today</date> than I had at your point in the university, your college career, because of <placeName>Valley Forge</placeName> experience.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So that’s—that’s actually very interesting for me to hear because in many ways, you could say that is very similar to how it is now, so—or at least how it is in <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC now. Can you tell me what the unit culture was like?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It did not—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">You used the word “flexible” earlier.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It did not have a culture, okay? We—we—the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> program, as I recall, was not very intrusive. It was—it consisted of an academic program. Two of us became fighter pilots, and had a little bit of contact. I went to visit [<persName>Robert E.]</persName> “Bob” Fisher [Class of <date>1967</date>] in <placeName>Southern California</placeName> when I was on the leave they gave me when I extended my first tour in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>. We had—that’s the last time I saw him. So, I mean, in terms of a close-knit or a—a culture, there was none—none that I can remember. We were there to—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—to get done what was necessarily in minimalist fashion, in order to get a commission.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, did <orgName>ROTC</orgName> have a building? Did it have weapons they used for drill?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t recall drilling very much, if at all. The <orgName>ROTC</orgName> had a series of offices—you know where Psi U is, probably.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Of course, yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. Directly across the street, in the direction of the [<orgName>Dartmouth] Green</orgName>, there’s a building whose name I forgot. For reasons you will completely understand or at least I will inform you, whether you understand or not, I did not return to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for <date>18 years</date>,—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And I am very—I’m sorry. I didn’t mean to cut you off.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—<date>1970</date> through it was either <date>1997</date> or ’98; I can’t remember which. And I’ve only been back once. But the—the—the—I believe all of the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> detachments, or at least <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> was in that building that is directly across the street, towards the Green—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Would that be <orgName>College Hall</orgName>, Collis [Center for Student Involvement]?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I—if you’re curious—and now I am—I’m going to—I’m sitting in front of my computer. There’s nothing on the screen right now, but I may call up <orgName>Google Maps</orgName> and see what I can find. I don’t remember the name. <persName>Parkhurst</persName> [Hall]? <persName>Parkhurst</persName> is—that’s where the—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS"><orgName>Parkhurst</orgName> is the administration.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah, the administration building. Anyway, it was in that building or right next door.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, interesting, yeah. </u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I would say I was aware of that conflict as I arrived. I mean, I arrived at <placeName>Hanover</placeName> in <date>1963</date>, and in—’64 or ’5, ’6, ‘7 were very active <date>years</date>, so—and I was interested in foreign policy and studying <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName>. I can’t tell you <date>the first day</date>, but I—I doubt that I was unaware of that from the very beginning of—of being at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. So when the decisions [President <persName>John F.]</persName> <persName>Kennedy</persName> was making to get into that conflict were being made, I’m sure I was aware of them.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, was it in your mind that when you commissioned as an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> second lieutenant you were going to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> or go to some area in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The simple answer is yes, but it’s not in the context of what you just described.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I would love to hear the context.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Remember—well, what I’m trying to do is answer your questions and then clarify my answers.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That’s very interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">You will get an ex- —you will get an explanation because I had signed up for <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> to be a fighter pilot, plain and simple. That was my goal from the very beginning of signing the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> commitment. You go back to the experiences I had in—in <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>, and I was maintaining contact with these people throughout. I mean, I—I went back as a general officer and spoke at the son—spoke at the graduation ceremony where the son of the fellow I’d been working with graduated from pilot training—you know, flew in an F-15, conducted a—you know. So that—you know, I was committed to that kind of career track from the very beginning.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I—as an <orgName>ROTC</orgName> cadet, I fully understand. I mean, I think that’s even more interesting considering, as your Air Force biography says—and I do have to insert this here—where is that?—it says you were the last <orgName>U.S. Air Force</orgName> fighter-on-fighter—I’m sorry, you had the last U.S. Air Force fighter-on-fighter aerial victory with a cannon.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Correct.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I see, which I’d love to ask you about later, but it’s—it’s just very interesting for me to see that and see that that was something you were imagining at this point anyway.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, let me tell you, in all honesty, you just said I was imagining that, and I’m assuming you were—you were referring to the environment you asked the question, which was when I graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and—and got into <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>. No, that’s not what I was imagining at that point. I had been described a peacetime—peacetime environment in the fighter business, and I didn’t know any combat fighter pilots. I—I had read about some. I had read about a lot of them, and I’d read about some in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName> and was very familiar with the [Republic] F-105 [Thunderchief] loss rates and the kind of things that were coming up in the news when—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry, what is the F-105?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t want to divert you too much into the fighter business, but the—the most—the prestigious fighters are single seat and single engine. The F-105 was the most heavily employed single-seat, single-engine fighter in the initial stages of the war. They had hellacious loss rates, but they were—that was the—that was my objective as I was going through pilot training, and I looked very hard to be number one in my class because the selection—<orgName>the Air Force</orgName> offered the graduates of pilot training a list of potential aircraft they could fly, which were anything, you know, from fighters to bombers to tankers to whatever. Number one got first choice and number two, second choice, that sort of thing.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—that’s a very convoluted answer to your question, but I—I don’t think—I don’t think I can accurately explain the thought process without qualifying it to the specific circumstances in which I was making those decisions, okay?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, I think that’s a very—it’s a very important distinction.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t recall—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Let me—let me clarify. This is before you went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t recall— You’re beginning—your last statement, I didn’t—I couldn’t hear properly. What did you just say?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, sorry. I just wanted to clarify. I know there’s something that I’m very excited to talk about in <date>1970</date>, after you’ve already gone on one tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but this is during your time as an undergrad at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I understood your—your question as far as whether there were any protests and how did it affect my—my relationship with my peers. But you said something after that that I didn’t hear. I couldn’t understand.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh. I—I don’t recall, sorry. I’m just very interested in that question.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I—I don’t know that the—well, first, to answer the second part of your question, I don’t recall any major protests. There may have been some, but I did not—I don’t recall seeing them or hearing about them on campus through <date>1967</date>, although I’m sure there were some and there were—there were people who philosophically disagreed with the war, and I can tell you right now that in my advanced age and with my experience in the political arena—and I—I think you have my Air Force biography. You understand that I was on <orgName>the Joint Staff</orgName>, and I was in the strategic planning function of <orgName>the Joint Staff</orgName>, in—in particular as the deputy director for international negotiations. I was responsible for our treaty structure and also for the Russian portfolio. I worked very closely with <orgName>the State Department</orgName> and understand, to the extent that anyone can, how <orgName>the State Department</orgName>, <orgName>the White House</orgName> and <orgName>the Defense Department</orgName>, and [the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Congress</orgName>—I have testified up there—how we get ourselves into conflicts like <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>, not—not the philosophy, not the strategy but the process. I understand the process.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yep.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">That one is worth reading because it’s—it has a lot of references and background for how we got into the war and why we did and why we shouldn’t have, by inference. So <persName>Stanley Karnow</persName>, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>[: A History]. Anyway—so the point is no one has a single, perfect, correct, astute focus or opinion on a conflict at the same focus at any one point in their life, in my—in my experience. And if I’m branding myself as somewhat of a political chameleon, that’s going to have to be a problem for some people, but I was a willing, active participant for <date>two and a half years</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So going to the more technical side of things now, especially for those people who don’t—aren’t familiar with the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> commissioning process, can you tell me about I would say camp to graduation, the process by which you became a distinguished military graduate, what that means and what happened immediately prior to the training you went through after graduation?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t think I have an answer for that, frankly.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">All right. So I can—I can rephrase that and change that if you want.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><orgName>ROTC</orgName> was not—and I’m sure the chief of staff of <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> and the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> instructors would—would have—take issue with this—but <orgName>ROTC</orgName> was—was designed to—to, I think, prepare me to just an officer of any flavor. And with a very singular focus that I had on being a fighter pilot, there was very little relevance to being a fighter pilot in what you do in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>. I took a flight indoctrination program up at <orgName>Post Mills</orgName>, <placeName>Vermont</placeName>, that basically in—in—in a pilot’s context, assured <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> that I could walk and chew gum at the same time.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no, not at all.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Family came to town. Extended family came to town. No, nothing—nothing sticks out. I was excited about moving on and excited about the next steps. I had been accepted to pilot training, and—you know, my pursuit of a good record in the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> program in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> was specifically focused on making sure I got into pilot training, so there are motivations—I think maybe that puts—puts some of my earlier answers into context.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, can you tell me about the—the training you went through, pilot training: where it was, what exactly you did?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The pilot training was at <orgName>Webb</orgName> [Air Force Base, <placeName>Texas</placeName>].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did it consist of—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><placeName>Dallas</placeName>, east of <placeName>El Paso</placeName>. We flew an aircraft called the [<orgName>Cessna</orgName>] T-41 [<orgName>Mescalero</orgName>]., which you would know as the <orgName>Cessna</orgName> 172 [Skyhawk], for maybe 40 hours. And, again, this was, you know—in crude terms, was <orgName>the Air Force’s</orgName> last chance to weed out the people who couldn’t walk and chew gum at the same time. Didn’t really learn very much in that program. But it was a good elimination device. And that’s me looking back on, you know, <date>31 years</date> of flying airplanes. That’s what <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> did with the T-41.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, from the end of that training process, what happened—did you immediately—when you received that assignment, were you informed that you were deploying or were there intermediate steps between graduation from that process and going to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The—the process was this: You—you get into pilot—you qualify for pilot training, and you are—you receive an assignment to an aircraft, a specific—we label them <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>, weapon system. And you then go qualify in that weapon system and then are assigned to a unit that’s  employing the weapon system. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So that weapon system—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Did that answer your question? Does that have any—am I off base here or—?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no, no, no you’re—you’ve been giving great answers. It’s very good answers. Thank you for that.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I was—I—I had to select an F-4 [McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II], which is a fighter with two people in it and two engines, and I point that out for any of those who—who know the weapon systems. It was a difficult decision for me because having been focused on a single-seat, single-engine fighter career, or at least entry level, and having a—a strong desire to fly the F-105 initially, I really wanted an F-105, and there were no F-105s in the block of available assignments offered to me by <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I see.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">But there was—go ahead. You had a question.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no, no, I didn’t. Sorry.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">There was a—there was an F-4 front seat—and the F-4, for reasons that I strongly disagreed with, as—and <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> eventually changed—<orgName>the Air Force</orgName> for, I think, political reasons and force level reasons, was assigning—had been assigning pilots right out of pilot training to the back seat of the F-4, where they didn’t really do much flying. In fact, they shouldn’t have been doing any flying if they were employing the aircraft correctly and if the guy in the front seat did it, did all the flying. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now—yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I’m giving you an awful lot of—this is not just a—there are an awful lot of <orgName>Air Force</orgName> unique and pilot unique and fighter community unique considerations in that, and I’m trying to explain as much of that as I can without burdening you with a lot of fighter pilot lingo or attitudes. But go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, you’ve been doing—you’ve been doing a great job of that, so thank you for explaining those terms. That is one thing that the project tries to encourage, kind of, you know, explaining the more jargon-y terms and concepts that civilians might not necessarily get because whoever is listening to these tapes might not necessarily have a knowledge of that, so thank you again.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">None.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">None.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">You—you—an individual who graduates from pilot training by selecting his weapon system has narrowed down the aperture significantly on where he’s going to be assigned and what kind of unit he’s going to be in, but you lose control of that completely. You go where <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> needs you to go. And I knew that—that—you know, the range of assignments at that point, you knew what the F-4 locations were. You knew where they needed pilots. And the greatest demand was in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>. And—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, what was your first assignment? What unit?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, okay, my first assignment in the F-4 was the qualification program, and that was at George Air Force Base in <placeName>Southern California</placeName>, where I—I spent I think it was <date>four to six months</date> learning how to fly and employ the F-4 air-to-air gunnery, air-to-ground gunnery tactics, that sort of thing, so the first assignment in the F-4 was to learn how to fly the F-4 at George Air Force Base.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well, let’s go back a little bit to before you went over to <placeName>Thailand</placeName>. So before you went to <placeName>Thailand</placeName>—I guess when you received the assignment or the notification that you were going to go to <placeName>Thailand</placeName>, what did your parents think about this, your siblings? I don’t know if you had a significant other at that point, but if you did, what did they think?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, no one—no one was very pleased about that, and, no, there wasn’t a significant other. But the—they were all very aware from the very beginning—the very beginning being, you know, initial qualifications for pilot training and then certainly the selection of the F-4, they were all very aware that that was—was my objective, and so they were if not supportive, resigned to it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And what did—what did you think, given the prospect that you could have been assigned to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, itself, or another place? Would you say you were happy with the assignment or disappointed or neither?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It was what I wanted.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I was happy with it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. So before you went to <placeName>Thailand</placeName>, I’m curious what kind of contact you’d had with people from that region. I don’t know if there were many Asian or Southeast Asian students at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but did you know any Southeast Asian people?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">None. I’m sure I had encountered—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Had you—had you ever—yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—I’m sure I had encountered—I mean, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is—is—wasn’t that cosmopolitan. Certainly <orgName>Hanover</orgName> is not cosmopolitan.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">And certainly <name type="event">Big Spring</name>, <placeName>Texas</placeName>, is not cosmopolitan, and I can guarantee you that <placeName>Victorville</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>, is not cosmopolitan. Neither was the town I grew up in, Banning, nor was the environment in rural, central <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>. So, no, I—I did not have the advantage or disadvantage of, say, <placeName>Boston</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>, <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>, any of those experiences. And if—if I looked back at the consequences of my choices, of going to <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, going to <date>Big Spring</date>; the consequences of choosing the career trajectory that I did, I would say you have focused in on a—a major deficiency. I was not at all exposed, as I was very late in my career, when I went to live in <placeName>Moscow</placeName> for <date>four years</date>, to a variety of other races, cultures, religions, whatever. That’s not something you can create in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, in <placeName>Sodtown</placeName> or <placeName>Ravenna</placeName>, <placeName>Nebraska</placeName> or <placeName>Banning</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t know if it’s a deficiency, but it is a—a fact of my, you know, formative years.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So arriving in <placeName>Thailand</placeName>, what did you think, getting off the plane? Was it different than you expected? Was it exactly how you expected it to be?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I’ll offer you two—two factors in that, that formed that impression that you’re looking for. First and foremost, it was pretty much what I expected because all of my—all of my instructors in—well, no, most of my instructors in the qualification program in the F-4 had already been to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName> and were—were—we discussed what it was like over there as the context for the training I was going through.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">So I got off the airplane, and it was pretty much exactly what I expected.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, going to that, I would say—well, as—as you have phrased it, rather not academic, but I would say, in many ways, academic concept—what was the mission of the unit you were assigned to? What kinds of things did you do as a fighter pilot?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">For my first tour, the missions were almost exclusively focused on or limited to attacking ground targets in <placeName>Laos</placeName>, southern <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>, occasionally <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>, and occasionally <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And what <date>years</date> was that, by the way?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">From <date>February of 1969 through December</date> of ’70.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what does that mean as a pilot? </u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well,—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you kind of walk me through what one of those sorties would be like?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The sortie would involve a flight briefing, which you’d receive an intelligence assessment of the threats in the area, a specific briefing on the target that you were going to attack, and a briefing on the defenses that were expected in the target area. Then—that briefing would be by people who were not going to fly with you, but then the flight leader would determine what tactics he wanted to employ. And the flights were very seldom single-ship, mostly two- or four-ship formations in the target set, the mission set that we were given in <placeName>Laos</placeName>. It was not a large raid kind of thing. That occurred in my second tour, when we were going into <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What kinds of targets did you have?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">In that phase of the war—let me back up and give you—in the early phase of the war, most of the targets were <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>, and they ranged from factories to oil refineries to air bases to, you know, most of the kind of things that you associate in a—in a—with a heavily defended—well, you asked for the targets not the defenses. The targets were in <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName> in the first phase of the war. Any of the things that supported the transportation systems, the weapons production systems, the materiel storage area, that sort of thing, that supported their war effort.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, you mentioned one thing: defenses. And returning to something I mentioned earlier, which is the—the distinction I mentioned of being the last—having the last fighter-to-fight aerial victory with a cannon, and looking over your awards and decorations, you have a Silver Star, a Purple Heart, a Distinguished Flying Cross, a Defense Distinguished [sic; Meritorious] Service Medal, in addition to, of course, <name type="event">the Air Medal</name> with 24 oak leaf clusters. So aside from the amount of missions you’ve flown, and this is the official <orgName>Air Force</orgName> mission—it says you flew 375 combat missions in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>? Not necessarily on your first tour, but—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me more about how you were awarded <orgName>the Silver Star</orgName> or the Purple Heart or any of these medals? I don’t know if they happened during your time in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, but if they did, could you give me more information on that?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I could. I can describe the missions on which—or for which those missions—or those awards were made. I would prefer not to, but not from any—not from any false sense of modesty or so forth. Let me give you—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">It’s completely fine, by the way, if—yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, now, let—let me give you the context. I have—there are several—<orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is reaching out to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> veterans in a number of ways, one of which the—I don’t know—you’re probably not aware, but the Class of <date>1967</date> is encouraging written inputs from classmates, to be combined in a, you know, “What the War Did to Me” kind of—of document, for the class. So I have to be consistent throughout this. And your—the thrust of your question is a bit different than the—the—the direction that the class, the Class of <date>1967</date>, is taking, because everyone is allowed—you know, it’s more of a psychological—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">And if that’s the focus, then—then, you know, the medals and all that sort of thing are somewhat immaterial.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well, so there are a number of—this is a very broad project, so that—the reason it’s phrased that way is because we also have people in the project who were, for example, antiwar protesters, and I think the language is phrased to be inclusive of them. But we’re really interested in a much broader spectrum of things.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I respect that, and I—I—the antiwar protesters are one group you’re going to be interviewing, and you, as an <orgName>Army</orgName> officer, prospective <orgName>Army</orgName> officer, will I think read very carefully the infantry—the accounts of the war that are written by the <orgName>Marine</orgName> and <orgName>Army</orgName> people who participated in the ground war in <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>. And their—we probably share only one common experiences—and I’m talking pilots and infantrymen, and let’s just focus on those two for a second—and is that your—what is your—what combat arms objective in the <orgName>Army</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I haven’t quite decided yet. Probably—I want to eventually go <orgName>Civil Affairs</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><orgName>Civil Affairs</orgName>. Okay. The—the images that the people who have not fought in a—in a—in a military environment are mainly focused on the blood and <persName>gore</persName> and immediate watching your friends die, holding them in your arms as they die from legs and arms that are shot off and that sort of thing. I have been there only through books and only through conversations with people that I respect who actually had that experience.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">And the reason I—what I’m—what I’m trying to do is differentiate my experience in some fashion from the experience of the other people but—but give you the common objective. And that common set of objectives provides you a hell of a focus when you get to the theater, and it—it totally overshadows any political or other concern you might have at that point. People become usually apolitical in combat, I think. That’s my experience. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely. I’m thinking it’s around 11 o’clock. We could stop now and schedule another time to finish up our conversation. Would that work for you?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">If that’s best for you, that’s fine with me. I could give you another 30 minutes without destroying my schedule <date>today</date>, but I’m not sure—I’m not sure how that would fit with your interview objectives, and I’m perfectly happy to stick with your schedule.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I can also do 30 minutes, but I think, since we’re kind of at a natural stopping point, why don’t we wrap it up? So I’m going to stop the recording now.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">This is 9:12 a.m. on <date>March 5th, 2016</date>, and this is <persName>Sandor Farkas</persName> talking to <persName>Gary Rubus</persName>. I am in <persName>Webster Hall</persName> on <orgName>the Dartmouth College</orgName>—on <orgName>the Dartmouth College’s</orgName> campus, and he is in his home in <placeName>New Mexico</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Let’s break the first tour into two tours because if you want me to talk about my experience at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> during the time that I was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, in fact that occurred in <date>the middle of my first</date> tour. My first tour began in <date>February of 1969</date>. I had left <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, gone to pilot training, gone to the checkout program in the F-4, finished the checkout program just before <date>Christmas</date> in <date>’68</date>, and then did a couple of survival training courses and ended up at <placeName>Ubon Thailand</placeName> in <date>February of 1969</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. So let’s go back to that break. Obviously, you—I’m assuming you had accrued some leave, and what were you most looking forward to, going back to the <placeName>U.S.</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, let me go. I didn’t get to the end of the tape. Did—was I able to cover, in the last session, what happened to me just before I went back on this break?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, actually.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. There’s some humor, there’s some pathos, but there was an unusual circumstance. The <orgName>F-4</orgName> has two air crew members in it. Normally, it’s a—most of the time, it’s a pilot in the front seat and a navigator in the back seat. He’s called a weapon system operator, and he operates a number of systems that are accessible to the front seater but better done with a team of two people: radars, ground attack, avionics, that sort of thing.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, I haven’t, actually.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">[Laughs.] Well, you can imagine—I mean, I’m sure you have some weapons training for your <orgName>Army</orgName> background, but if a duck is flying perpendicular to your line of sight, you’d have to aim out in front of the duck. Can you visualize that?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, yeah. like when you’re shooting <persName>skeets</persName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">That’s exactly the same. Now, if the skeet is coming directly toward you, where do you aim? Right at the skeet, right?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">You don’t have to lead it. Well, If you’re attacking a gun, you’ve basically [chuckles] eliminated the problem for—for the—for the gunner because now all he has to do is aim straight at you. Well, on <date>about our fourth</date> or fifth pass against active gun sites—which we had a perfectly valid reason to be doing that. There were some other people on the ground, and we were trying to suppress an antiaircraft fire so helicopters could come in and pick these people up.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">So that event, which is, you know, something you expect in combat and is not surprising, but it’s certainly a little more exciting than—than a normal combat mission. That immediately preceded <persName>Jack</persName> and my trip to <placeName>Boston</placeName>, where his wife lived, and immediately preceded my trip to <placeName>Hanover</placeName>. So those are the circumstances leading up to the incident at <placeName>Hanover</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, so—so you did a water—well, did you bail out of the aircraft before it hit the water? I don’t quite know how these things—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Oh, yeah.  Yeah, the F-4 –the F-4 would not [chuckles]—not be a very good airplane to land in the water, period. Yes, bail out, relatively low altitude. The helicopters happened to be—actually, it was a very fortuitous circumstance: They happened to be airborne on a training mission and were just diverted up the coast to come pick us up. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And so going back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, do you remember—do you recall the date that you arrived on campus?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It was <date>three or four days</date> after [<orgName>the] Kent State [</orgName>University shootings on <date>May 4, 1970</date>]. You can look up <placeName>Kent State</placeName>. I do not recall the date.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">But that would be <date>1970</date>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Within <date>a week</date>—within <date>a week</date> of the incident where the students were killed at <placeName>Kent State</placeName> in <placeName>Ohio</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you know—were you following that news? What were your opinions on that at the time?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, this is—this is—this is where it’s going to be difficult for you to accept or comprehend my feelings at the time. And this is probably something that your reviewers of this thing would like to—to review. Let’s just say at the time, given what had just happened with the combat incident, I was not really monitoring or tuned into, while I was in <placeName>Thailand</placeName>, what’s going on in <placeName>the United States</placeName>. So I can’t—I can’t verify that I was totally unaware, but certainly the kind of news coverage and access you have and time you have and lack of other distractions would give an individual who was in <placeName>the United States</placeName> over that same period a different level of awareness of what was going on in—in <placeName>the United States</placeName> and specifically at <placeName>Kent State</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely. So going—yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Not to say that I didn’t—that I didn’t care [chuckles]. I was minimally aware and minimally conditioned to think about those kind of things, as I had been over the entire time I was in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>. Now, I can tell you now, at <date>age 70</date>, almost 71, my thoughts about the rationale for the war, the conduct of the war, my personal participation and all that sort of stuff are from a very different perspective and are very different than they were at that point in my life.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So going back to your arrival at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, did you have ay plans for that period of time? Were you planning to go to your fraternity or, you know, what—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I took my—my girlfriend that I had known and been with in <placeName>Hanover</placeName> and before. We were going to go up and enjoy some old times:—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—look at the fraternity, look at the campus, decompress, enjoy myself.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So those were the plans. Can you tell me about what actually happened?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yes. I happened to go up there at about the time that there were some let’s call them disturbances that you can prob- —you’re probably interviewing other people with that—and you’ll get a better understanding of what was going on there, because my memories are not that good—they’re not that pleasant, so I would say you’ll probably get far better reports on what was actually happening there from other people.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No problem.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">A somewhat chilly reception in my fraternity, <persName>Psi Upsilon</persName>, which happened to be relatively close to the building in which the <orgName>ROTC</orgName>—I think it’s <persName>Parkhurst</persName>—was [where] the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> offices were, and I’ve actually—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry, one <orgName>sec</orgName>. Was it perhaps <persName>Collis</persName>, the building right in front of Psi Upsilon?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Uh,—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Or <orgName>College Hall</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah. I actually don’t remember the name. It is the one right in front of—right across the street.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Awesome, so yeah that would be—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">You had some disturbances there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">College—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah, there were disturbances in a number of the buildings. I think <persName>Parkhurst</persName> was taken over for a period of time. But I [chuckles]—I did not remain there very long at all. It was clear that I was not welcome in the fraternity. It was clear that the campus was in somewhat of a turbulent state and that statistically I was in a very distinct minority, so I left. And quite honestly, I did not return again—that would have been in ’67—’8, ’9—it would have been have been in sixty- --no ’70. It would have been in ’<date>70</date>, and I did not return to the campus again for any activity until I believe it was <date>’86</date>, ’7 or ’8.  And I know know. I don’t have the dates on this. I can look it up, but I don’t know that it’s that material—for quite a while. It was not a pleasant experience.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you recall any specific incidents of interactions with students, protesters?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I have no names, no times, no dates, but there were a series of those. I was somewhat readily identifiable [chuckles] as a potential military officer with a short haircut and a different bearing and certainly a different attitude toward the things that were going on. I chose to detach, and I didn’t spend much time in the fraternity at all. It was very clear that—that I was not welcome. So I have no specific, exciting things to report. I was as disappointed with the—the institution’s response to what was going on as anything else and chose to depart and go back to <placeName>Boston</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So by “the institution’s response,” are you referring to how President [<persName>John G.]</persName> <persName>Kemeny</persName> handled—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The college.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The college. <orgName>You’re—you’re—you’re</orgName> personalizing this, and I—I don’t have personal, individual, by-name encounters to give you, nor do I have—it’s just the atmosphere and so forth. It was not a place I wanted to be. So rather than—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">How did you spend the rest of your—your leave after deciding you didn’t want to spend it at—on the campus?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I spent some time in—in <placeName>Boston</placeName>, spent some time in central <placeName>Nebraska</placeName>. I think I’ve told you about the contacts I had there, the previous military types, relatives. And also went to—went home to <placeName>Southern California</placeName> and traveled in <placeName>Southern California</placeName>. Spent some time with my parents, spent some time with the younger brother in <placeName>Northern California</placeName> just before I went back to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName> and essentially did—did family activities, saw old friends and bounced around <placeName>Southern California</placeName>. Rented an airplane and flew around a few different places. And I went to <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> and had another wonderful transit through the San Francisco International Airport, where people who were going to and coming back from the war were treated rather rudely. And then I went back to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So going back to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, you went to Ubon Air Force Base again?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah, I—I was—I was stationed at <orgName>Ubon</orgName> from—from <date>February of 1969</date> through <date>the end of 1970</date>. Same base, same location, U-b-o-n <orgName>Royal Thai Air Force Base</orgName>, <orgName>Ubon</orgName> pilots—named after the major town that’s by it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So did your experiences on leave affect how you looked at—at your deployment, coming back?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I don’t—how do you mean?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So your—your experiences on <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>’s campus, just traveling around the country, your experiences Stateside—did they make you look at what you were doing any differently or just did they give you a different attitude when you came back?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">[Laughs.] I will answer that question, but I want to put you on the spot and ask you if you think it should have.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Chuckles.] I would say—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I want to contrast—I want to—I want to go back to what I told you earlier about a focus on what you’re actually doing and staying alive and all of the—the—the intense concentration that it takes to be good at doing something like that, and why something—why—why you would frame that question the way you did.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I would say no. I would—if I had to guess, not just for you but for anyone in that position.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yes, with one additional qualifier. That is correct. What it forced me to do was put my life in <placeName>the United States</placeName>, which was my experience at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> as part of that, and to see—as I was bouncing around with my friends, I was seeing people who were leading lives undistracted—and I’m using that term very selectively—undistracted by the issues of combat, regardless of whatever rationale or why the mission is being conducted, how narrowly focused I had been. And I become a little concerned not about the answer to your original question—you need to go back and listen to that question [chuckles] yourself. I went back and put my—my life as I had known it in <placeName>the United States</placeName> in a box and put it on the shelf and went on about my combat business.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So, trying to understand kind of the format of that extended tour, the remaining time you spent during that extension at <orgName>Ubon</orgName>, flying more combat missions—are there any other things that stick out in that time?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No. I was not shot down again. I—I basically went through every mission that was flown by my squadron. I became—I actually changed missions a little bit. Most of the time, the F-4 is used as an attack aircraft, carrying bombs and other weapons and attacking targets. We had a very small detachment there, highly experienced pilots, highly experienced not necessarily in their overall flying time but experienced in the mission and in the area that we were flying, who were called forward air controllers, who went out with—with—with only weapons to mark targets and would seek out targets on the ground and lead other formations of similar airplanes, F-4s, F-105s, the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, followed their aircraft. We’d lead them against targets that we had found or had confirmed—you know, they might find some in photo reconnaissance and wanted us to go out and take a look at them and make sure that they were actually reasonable targets. Then we’d lead formations back in, meet them on a tanker, lead them in, mark the target.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">—in the mission, but not necessarily a major one.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So also I’m trying to understand kind of the rest of that time in <placeName>Thailand</placeName>. Did you also do pilot training or aid in training?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Not in the fashion that you would expect. We—we didn’t—we had no one there—well, let me state it positively: All of the pilots there had been through a training program in <placeName>the United States</placeName> to prepare them for the maneuvers and the techniques, of delivering weapons on a target and staying alive. So you weren’t—you weren’t training them. As a flight leader, I would take people who were relatively inexperienced in combat but perfectly qualified in the airplane—I would take them out on their initial combat missions. We’d got out, we’d usually try to fly them in a low—a low threat area on their first couple of rides and, you know, brief them a little more heavily, prepare them a little more differently, the briefings would be longer—so in a sense, yes, we were training, or I was training them. However, it’s not the “here is how you take off and land”; it’s “here’s how you employ this airplane as a weapons platform, which you’d already learned, but here’s how you do it, no kidding, in real combat.”</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah,—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—you were going to come back?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It was somewhat anticlimactic. I could have stayed—in fact, I should have stayed <date>two more months</date>. It cost me some career moves down the line. I should have stayed <date>two more months</date>. But I had—had basically done everything that the organization had done, and I was ready to go home and—and do something different. It wasn’t—it was more of a career future in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>, kind of, Okay, I’ve done everything I can here. Was getting a little stale, and that can be risky in combat. So I went home.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you had—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">My—my assignment—I went—I went back to a unit in <placeName>the United States</placeName> and became an instructor pilot in the—the activities that I was trained in. Remember, I went to pilot training. I graduated and went to an F-4 training program that taught me gunnery and—and maneuvering and that sort of thing. Well, I became an instructor in that environment, teaching people who had never flown the F-4 before and had had no experience dropping weapons or chasing other airplanes. I went back and became an instructor in the kind of program I’d been through immediately after pilot training.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Now, can you tell me what that was like, training pilots to go do what you had been doing?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I had, you know, experienced as a student, I was experienced—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Hello? I can’t hear you. Did you move the phone?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No. Can you hear me now?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely, yep.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. So it was a normal progression. It was something I—I thought I might end up having to do. I didn’t particularly want to do that, but I did it for another—oh, then for <date>another year</date>, then was sent off to another school. You know, I did it well. I’m—I’m certain of that. And I could—had no—no problems trying to describe that to you, but it—it was something you expected to do, and you did it, and it was flying, but it wasn’t as much fun as what I’d been doing in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what did you say you did next?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I left <orgName>Ubon</orgName> and went to Homestead Air Force Base [now Homestead Air Reserve Base] in <placeName>Florida</placeName> and become an instructor in the <orgName>F-4</orgName> replacement training unit that was training people for operational tours. They didn’t necessarily all go to combat. Some of them went to <placeName>Europe</placeName>; some of them went to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, where there were no—not participating in a conflict, but a fair number of them went to—along the same trajectory that I had taken: go from the replacement training unit into the combat squadron.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So after that, what were you saying you did next?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Then I went to a special school. I think it’s between 5 and 10 percent of the active fighter pilots, the qualified fighter pilots, go through a school called the Fighter Weapons Instructor Course and become instructors, more highly qualified instructors in the activity of selecting weapons and tactics for specific combat environments.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell—clear. So was that also at Ubon Air Force Base, or was that a different location?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No, it was—it was a different location, and it’s U-d-o-r-n, Udorn [Royal Thai Air Force Base] in the northern—northeastern section of <placeName>Thailand</placeName>. <persName>Ubon</persName>, the first one, was in the southeast section. We had about—you know, we had five major—four major fighter bases in—in <placeName>Thailand</placeName> flying most of the effort in <placeName>Laos</placeName> and <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName>: Udorn, Takhli [<orgName>Royal Thai Air Force Base</orgName>], <placeName>Korat</placeName> [<orgName>Royal Thai Air Force Base</orgName>] and <persName>Ubon</persName>. I was at <orgName>Ubon</orgName> the first time and <persName>Udorn</persName> the second. I was never stationed at <placeName>Korat</placeName> or <placeName>Takhli</placeName>. And that’s more history and more detail than you need. [Chuckles.] </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So at that point, what was your rank?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Captain. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And so—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">When I went to <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, I was a first lieutenant. I was a first lieutenant. When I finished my activity in <placeName>Thailand</placeName>, I was still a captain. I made captain when I was in—in <placeName>Thailand</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what was your role at that point in your squadron’s operations?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Because I was very highly experienced in combat and because I was a fighter weapons school graduate, I was asked to help select weapons and design tactics for whatever mission came down. We were tasked to do missions by a higher headquarters, and then what’s called a fragmentary order, or a frag, would come in, and then a group of people would sit down and figure out, “Okay, what’s the base going to do to execute the mission that’s been given?” I was taken out of a merely flying role, where I flew as either a flight leader or a wingman on a mission, to helping design what the flight was—was going to do: what weapons they take, how the fuses would be timed, how the package would be used, the delivery techniques, the integration of the avionics, that sort of thing.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So at that point in your career and your time in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, what were you—what were you thinking about? Were you—what were your hopes for your career in the Air Force?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I wanted to progress in the fighter business, and what I was doing—the total focus—you know, the combat focus is—is something you haven’t experienced yet (and hope you don’t), but where—where the combat focus and what I was doing there, the skills I was—was honing, the experience I was getting—all of those things fit perfectly with my focus on being a leader and getting promoted in the fighter community in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>. I was on a perfect step to keep moving forward in the fighter community. That’s what I thought about. And staying alive. [Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, I need to tell you also, killing people was—you know, that was our mission, was destroying targets and killing people. I know that’s hard—hard to think about, but that gives—that mission and then staying alive as you perform that mission and keeping other people alive as your perform that mission is a—is a very, very distinct pyramid, hierarchy of focus and needs. And I got pretty good at it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So at that point in the war, now that you were kind of on a slightly more tactical or—I know “tactical” and “strategic” have very specific implications or specific meanings, but on a little bit more of a conceptual level, did you start to think about the direction the war was going? I don’t want to say “worry,” but think about how it might be concluding?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">If <date>you’re</date>—if you’re trying to contrast the—the attitudes of someone in <placeName>the United States</placeName>, with no focus on combat, with no—no risk to themselves—and I’ll be brutally honest and say, you know, this is not something I had time to go sit in a coffeehouse or in a bar and—or in a fraternity and talk to my compatriots about it. It was something I was living <date>every day</date>. So to the extent that I did think about those things, it was I’m risking my life to do something. I wonder what kind of a contribution I’m making really to the overall effort. And what is the overall effort?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I have not.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">You should research that. I’m not going to give you the authors. You do that. It’s in some former senior <orgName>White House</orgName> and <orgName>Department of Defense</orgName> officials’ memoirs. You can imagine what—what effect that has on me now, but the reason I’m bringing that up is that I can tell you that it was not a—it was not something we had indications of or I didn’t—let me say I did not have any indications that that was happening. Certainly, the defenses we were facing were [chuckles]—were—were very, very good, and as I’ve learned more about the way the war was conducted—not the rationale for it but the way it was conducted—and I’ve got a whole rack of books that I’m looking up—up on my wall right now, that I have read, obviously, in retrospect. But those kind of things were—were only readily apparent to me in the combat environment to the effect that they forced me to avoid using tactics or strike targets that I could see as a trained weapons instructor would have contributed a hell of a lot more to the conduct of the war than some of the things we were doing. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So how—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">You know, I find it pathetic and laughable now, but that’s just the sad story.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So how did you wind up leaving <placeName>Thailand</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Just before the—there were several phases of the war. I don’t want to try to walk you through all of those, but in late—I think it was <date>October, November</date>, the—you’re probably aware of the B-52 raids that started going into <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName> in <date>1972</date>, <date>late 1972</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">As—as—as the—the strategic planners started to reposition forces—and by that, I mean the ratio of bombers and fighters and that sort of thing at the very, very highest level, well above anything I was worried about—as they started to reposition those, my squadron was redeployed back to <placeName>Florida</placeName> from <placeName>Thailand</placeName>, and I left <placeName>Thailand</placeName> with the squadron.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, at that point, did you expect that you’d be coming back to <placeName>Thailand</placeName>? Was that something you were thinking about?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I didn’t expect it. You know, I was—it—it—it was one of those—we didn’t really know what was going on. I was a little surprised to come back. You know, when you’re at the curb level it’s difficult to perceive the tactics and the strategies. But I actually don’t remember if I had any conscious expectation of what was going to happen. We were just going to go back to what we’d been doing at <placeName>Homestead</placeName> before my second tour and continue to do that, I assumed.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So after you arrived home, can you tell me about what time was like? What were you doing?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, let me—let me go back to—[Laughs.] You’re skipping all the good parts here, so [laughs] I want to go back.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, I apologize. Sorry about that.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">[Laughs.] I think I’ve emphasized to you how much—how focused I was on being a good fighter pilot and accumulating the credentials and the experience and the knowledge, proficiency to progress in the fighter business. One of the—one of the sort of crowning achievements in a fighter career—well, let me explain it in a different way. You’ve probably hear the term “ace,” have you not?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I have.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">An ace is someone who’s killed five airplanes (and probably five pilots, or more than five, (however many were on the airplanes) in aerial combat. It’s in the classic sense is with a cannon because that’s what started—that’s how people shot down other airplanes from the very beginning or at the very beginning. They started with a cannon, and then we progressed—in the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> era, we progressed up to having cannons and—and air-to-air missiles. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">So that—that was on my mind as I was coming back from <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName> at the finish of my last tour over there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So your other—your peers in <orgName>the Air Force I’m</orgName> assuming had a reaction to that, and—well, let me think how to ask this. Did—did you expect more of a reaction from those at home? Kind of can you contrast the reaction of your peers in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> to maybe your family, those at home, to that accomplishment?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah, the only people that really appreciate it are those that do it, so there’s—there’s—you know, they appreciated it. But the sense of accomplishment can only be shared by those people who—you know, when you [chuckles]—when you’re close enough to another airplane—and it may seem odd in—in <date>the days</date> of supersonic fighters and long-range weapons and so forth—when you get close enough to another airplane to see the pilot’s head moving around and know that he wants to kill you and you want to kill him, and then through the maneuvering you—you get behind and you actually kill him—and I’m being brutal with the language, because that is the experience. That is the psychology. I know this guy died, from a variety of reasons. He was in his ejection seat when he bailed out right in front of me. He was only, mmm, 800 feet in front of me. He bailed out. And when he went over my wing in his ejection seat, I know he hit the ground and never got out of the seat. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, absolutely. </u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Yeah. I went to <placeName>Florida</placeName>. Instructed in the same program I’d been in for quite a while, or for <date>the previous year and a half</date>, <date>two years</date>, and then was selected to go back and be an instructor in the—the—if you remember the fire weapons instructor course that I took just before I went back for my second tour—I went back and became an instructor in that same school.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And what <date>year</date> was that in?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS"><date>Seventy-three</date>. And in seventy- —oh, I’ve forgotten—’74  ’5, I went to—to <placeName>Korea</placeName> and spent <date>a year</date> in <placeName>Korea</placeName> as a fire weapons instructor in a fighter squadron there and sometime shortly after that, came back to a staff tour in <placeName>the United States</placeName>, Langley Air Force Base. So I did, after the second tour in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, a brief time as an RTU [replacement training unit] instructor at <orgName>Homestead</orgName>, then a fighter weapons instructor at <placeName>Nellis</placeName>, then a fighter weapons instructor at Osan Air Base in <placeName>Korea</placeName>, and then the headquarters staff of <orgName>Tactical Air Command</orgName> at <orgName>Langley Air Force Base</orgName>—I don’t know how far you want to go through it, but that’s—you can—if you <orgName>Google</orgName> my name on <orgName>the Air Force General Officers</orgName>—you can get this whole sequence off a document there, off that. They keep the retired general officers on there until—well, actually, they keep them there after they’re dead, too [chuckles], so you can—you can have my record for a long time.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I have that—I have that right here, and hopefully we can incorporate that into whatever the posting for this recording will look like. But I also just wanted to have it, you know, for whoever’s listening, in case we can’t.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">At that point, I was conflicted, not—you know, it wasn’t <orgName>PTSD</orgName> [post-traumatic stress disorder]. It wasn’t anything like that. It was, if anything, a lower-grade level of conflicted, not only on the larger issues that I think you’re looking for—the rationale for the war and that sort of thing—but I—I began to reflect on what my focus—and I want to—I’ve tried to use that term explicitly through our conversations—my focus on being a good or the best fighter pilot that I could be and progressing in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>—what that had done to my personal life.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I think that is a great answer. But just checking back on one thing, so did you have any specific reactions to the fall of <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and the publicity around that?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">It did call into question the—the futility of the effort, and one of the books I’ve got up here—<persName>Ted Morgan</persName>, <orgName>The Valley of Death</orgName>[: The Tragedy at <persName>Dien Bien Phu</persName> That Led American into <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>], the futility—as I started to read more and get out of the tactical curb level and question the rationale, it became more and more apparent to me, as a strategic planner—and remember, I went to the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> as a general officer and had served in the—in <orgName>the Joint Staff’s J-5 Strategic Planning</orgName> [and Transformation] function, and I—you know, I’d made the leap from first lieutenant fighter pilot to strategic planner and see some of the things that happened in the political environment inside <placeName>Washington</placeName> and how strategic decisions are made, so this is when I began to develop those kind of impressions on how the war might have been avoided and how the war should have been prosecuted had the strategic decisions been made intelligently on behalf of the national security interests of <placeName>the United States</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So before we get to your experience in the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName> and also before that, in the Russian or <orgName>the Russian Embassy</orgName>, I’m curious to know how—what it was like to be an officer in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> as those veterans who had left their respective services began to form veterans organizations and commemorate the war.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I’ve never been in one of those organizations. All of the organizations that—that—well, let me—let me—now, maybe I—I may not be answering your question, your specific question. The organizations that I associate with <date>today</date> and have associated with since my retirement do not contain or—or their membership is usually—and I’m trying to think of an exception to what I’m going to tell you, and I can’t. The people that I associate with are people who remained in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> for at least a 20-year career, sometimes a 30-year career, so they’re not people who left the service immediately after the war. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The people I associate with are essentially career officers who have a different attitude because they stayed in the military. You know, and it—it wasn’t necessarily that they couldn’t do anything else; it was a—a—a choice of alternatives at the time, the same kind of choice I made as a captain and a major when I could have gotten out of <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> and, say, gone to the airlines or gone to law school or, you know, I know—I have friends who went to med school, law school, that sort of thing after flying, having the same career trajectory up to that point. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I hope that’s an adequate—an adequate answer to your question.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, it’s a great answer. That was basically what I was asking.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, the first time I saw it, basically what I did—it is difficult for me to go there. But the difficulty is a combination of looking for the people that I lost and realizing how now—not at the time—as more and more information has come to light—how futile that whole effort really was. So it is a very difficult thing for me to do, to go down there, but I don’t come away with—with the same—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Understood.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Very simply. In pursuit of being the world’s finest and best fighter pilot, I had managed to screw up my—my progression as an officer, my promotion as an officer to the point that I was not going to be promoted beyond the rank of colonel without some radical departure from the operational field. My mistake. I can laugh at it now because the Soviets managed to schedule a revolution to salvage my career. But I had not done the things I needed to do to progress in rank and position, and had sacrificed those things to stay in the cockpit.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Understood.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">So that may sound an obtuse answer to how did the Russian thing come in it. I stayed in the cockpit, and as I was about to leave the cockpit as a colonel, I was running—I got the first two F-15E’s [<orgName>McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagles</orgName>] off the production line and—and flew—well, I designed the test and flew the test with two other pilots. Did the operation test and evaluation of the F-15E. The general I was working for at the time said, “Hey, you know, I gotta tell ya, you are going to probably have this kind of assignment, and then you’ll be ready for retirement.”</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Great answer. So your—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">[Laughs.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—time in the—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">That’s the truth.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Just coincidentally. Your time in <orgName>the Russian Embassy</orgName> as things were winding down. I think you know what incident I’m getting at. Can you tell me about the time kind of working up to that, if that was something you anticipated and then the incident, itself?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">What—what— incident are you talking to?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">The reception you went to at <orgName>the Vietnamese Embassy</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Oh, okay. Well, let me give you a little more background. I went—and don’t call it <orgName>the Russian Embassy</orgName>; it’s <orgName>the Moscow Embassy of the United States of America</orgName> [sic; Embassy of <placeName>the United States</placeName>, <placeName>Moscow</placeName>.] [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">All right. Sorry. I apologize for that.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">[Laughs.] I—I got to <placeName>Moscow</placeName> for a series of humorous reasons. I got to <placeName>Moscow</placeName> <date>about three weeks</date> before the unsuccessful coup in <date>August of 1991</date> that brought down—ultimately brought down <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName> in <date>December of 1991</date>. So I take—I take full responsibility and credit for <date>the fall</date> of <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">My tour started very, very spectacularly in that literally I was driving out, escorting a <orgName>U.S. Air Force</orgName> officer out to <placeName>Star City</placeName> [area in <placeName>Moscow Oblast</placeName>], and as we were driving out of town, there was a tank column driving into town. And I spent <date>the next month</date> or so trying to help <orgName>the U.S. Embassy</orgName> sort out who was on whose side amongst the various factions in <placeName>Russia</placeName> that were fighting over the remnants of <placeName>the Soviet Union</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. Well, you probably may have seen a short clip that <orgName>CNN</orgName> [<orgName>Cable News Network</orgName>] was running in <date>1993</date> to ’4, of a tank sitting on a bridge, shooting into the front of a bit white building in <placeName>Moscow</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, yes, yes.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Okay. Well, if the tank had turned its turret 30 degrees to the right and dropped its cannon 10 degrees, it would have blown out my apartment window in the Embassy compound. That’s how close the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> Embassy compound was, unfortunately, to “the White House.” It’s literally 100 yards away. And at that time, I was a senior military officer in the Embassy, and we—we had our families and everyone who lived on the compound and was there when the fracas started on the gym floor, and I was helping the ambassador coordinate how we were going to keep these people alive and hopefully get them out of the <orgName>Embassy</orgName>. That’s another political issue that—no relevant [sic] to this thing. But that’s the kind of experience I had in <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, okay?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So at that point, as the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> attaché, you were a colonel, and—let me see when your promotion was—[Turns pages.]—and it was in <date>1994</date> when you became the defense attaché that you were promoted to general?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">No.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">[Chuckles.] I was asked to remain behind for <date>an extra two years</date> in <placeName>Moscow</placeName>. When I left to go to <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, we took in <date>two years’</date> worth of food with us. There was no food available. You—you—you actually took your food in with you. It’s not like <placeName>Moscow</placeName> <date>today</date>. And it was a hardship tour. I went in early because my predecessor—when I went in as the air attaché, I went in <date>a year early</date> because my predecessor’s son attempted suicide in <placeName>Moscow</placeName>. It was a grim, dismal, dark place to live. I was followed 24 hours a day, <date>seven days</date> a week for <date>four years</date>. People would come in and change out the recording devices in my apartment. [Laughs.] It was an interesting tour. So when I went in, that was the environment. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That is a complicated answer. </u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I can’t tell you how I came to be invited to it. I was told to go [laughs] by the ambassador, and—and that—that invitation, if you want to characterize it as that, was—came out of <placeName>Washington</placeName> somewhere. I don’t know the context, and I don’t know the rationale. But he didn’t know if he was going, if I was going, we’re taking our wives, but Ambassador [<persName>Thomas R.]</persName> <persName>Pickering</persName> called me up and said, “You’re going to go by yourself, and you’re going to go in uniform.” And that’s how I got there. That was my “invitation.” You will learn about that  when you become a lieutenant. Things have a way of rolling downhill. [Laughs.] That’s how I got there. That’s the invitation.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what was it like going in uniform to <orgName>the Vietnamese Embassy</orgName>—I mean, wearing the ribbons you earned fighting them?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I wrestled with a whole slew of ironies as I was driving over. Most of them—you know, <placeName>they’re</placeName>—they’re subterranean, almost subconscious, but you think about them. At that point, the ironies of what was—what was happening were almost humorous, but there was some pathos involved also.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. So can you tell me what happened there? I mean, any conversations that stand out or—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, it was clear—it was clear that the conversations were preceded by an arrival [chuckles]. Some lights came on, and a camera came out, and I was recorded getting out of the—I had a driver. Got out of the car, sort of a little portico kind of veranda thing. And was met at the door by the ambassador, and very graciously but very distinctly led through the assembled guests—well, they weren’t assembled—led through and presented to each of the guests by the ambassadors, introduced. I think you can understand the situation.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Mmm.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I didn’t have the sense that—let me back up. The ambassador was a very—I don’t even remember his name, but he was a very sophisticated, well educated, articulate in at least four or five languages. The ones that I recall were, in addition to Vietnamese or whatever language he was speaking (because I don’t understand that one): German, French, English and Russian. And there may have been others. But he presented me in both English and the native language of the other ambassadors and so forth, in—in both English and their native language. So was very cordial, and it was a pleasant evening once you filtered out the—the ironies and the clear diplomatic objectives on both sides.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Any other things—</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">The conversations—well, the conversations were somewhat unremarkable until we encountered—I believe it was—I don’t remember being introduced to a minister, anyone from <orgName>the Ministry of Defense</orgName>, but in the Russian general staff system, ministry system, the fact that [<persName>Mikhail] Kolesnikov</persName>, the chief—or the—the chief of the general staff and <persName>Harshenko</persName> [archivist note: spelling uncertain], one of his senior assistants were there, you had the very top of the—the group.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you just walk me through your retirement and then what you’ve been up to since?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">I went back to the <orgName>Pentagon</orgName>. I’d been invited back for one assignment as a senior assistant to the secretary of <orgName>defense</orgName>. He, for a variety of reasons, retired before I—I was put into a holding pattern, and he retired before I got that position. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Are you still employed with <orgName>Lockheed Martin</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">In a manner of speaking, yes. <orgName>Lockheed Martin</orgName> combined its Atlas launch vehicle program, the one that uses the Russian engine—you’re probably, maybe seen a little press on that right now. Combined that program with <orgName>Boeing</orgName>’s [<orgName>the Boeing Company’s</orgName>] <placeName>Delta</placeName> program, in a joint venture called <orgName>United Launch Alliance</orgName>. And I’m still with the RD-180 Russian engine program, but I’m in a company called <orgName>United Launch Alliance</orgName>. It’s a joint <orgName>Lockheed Martin-Boeing</orgName> venture. So yes and no, I’m still employed by <orgName>Lockheed Martin</orgName>, their program, but not their company.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="RUBUS">Well, if—if—if you take anything from the thread, the common threads that run through the narrative on my <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience, I have no more confidence that the war in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was initiated or conducted in a fashion consistent with the interests of <placeName>the United States</placeName>, the real interests of <placeName>the United States</placeName> than <persName>George W. Bush</persName> #2’s invasion of <placeName>Iraq</placeName> with no plan for the consequences of that invasion. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So with that, thank you so much for this. I’m going to stop the recording. </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
