<?xml-model href="ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="0.1.1">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="WOMAN"/>
        <person xml:id="STEFFEN"/>
        <person xml:id="FARKAS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="FARKAS">This is <persName>Sandor Farkas</persName> interviewing <persName>Nicholas Steffen</persName>. I am in <orgName>Dartmouth College’s</orgName> Webster Hall, and <persName>Nicholas Steffen</persName> is at his home in <placeName>Henderson</placeName>, <placeName>Nevada</placeName>. It is 4:05 p.m., <date>August 12th, 2015</date>.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Okay, I was born in <placeName>Winona</placeName>, <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>. My parents were <persName>Robert</persName> and <persName>Betty Steffen</persName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And <date>what year</date> were you born in?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I was born <date>October 20th, 1944</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. And can you tell me more about your parents—like, what their jobs were?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">My mother was a homemaker, and my father worked in the investment business, selling mutual funds.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.  Did your father ever serve in the military?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">He was in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Navy</orgName>, an enlisted sailor in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> in <name type="event">World War II</name>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And do you know when he got out?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">He was medically discharged I believe in <date>1943</date> or so.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah, so he was around in <date>1944</date> when you were born?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. Yeah, he’d already been discharged when I was born.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So tell me about kind of your <date>early school days</date>—elementary—what your interests were, how you did in school.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Okay. Yeah, I grew up in a small Midwestern city, and so all of the schools I went to—elementary, junior high school (they didn’t call them middle schools in those days) and senior high school—were actually all within walking distance of the house and were actually close enough that I actually used to walk home for lunch all through school, from kindergarten till the time I went away to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So growing up in town—I mean, being born in <date>1944</date>, I’m assuming there were a lot of <name type="event">World War II</name> veterans, but can you tell me about the contact you had with returning <name type="event">World War II</name> veterans or if you had any?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No. I mean, back in those days I think, you know, most able-bodied males served, but it just wasn’t—you know, it wasn’t a big deal, I guess. So by the time I was old enough to be kind of aware [chuckles] of what was going on, the war was over. And as far as I know—plus a lot of my parents’—for whatever reason—my parents’ friends were older than they were, so they may not have served. I really don’t even know.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, were there any famous veterans or pilots or <orgName>Navy</orgName> men (as, you know, you later went in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>) that you knew or were aware of in your town?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, actually there was. There’s a very famous aviator—t least he was famous back then—called [<persName>Maximilian</persName>] “Max” <persName>Conrad</persName>, who set all sorts of aviation records flying small aircraft. I believe he didn’t work for <orgName>the Piper Aircraft [Inc.</orgName>] company. I don’t know that he was ever in the military. But some of the people that had taken flying lessons from him went on to go in the military.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you get to meet <persName>Max Conrad</persName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes, I did. Like I said, I did meet him. My dad knew him. He was approximately my father’s age. And being a small, fairly small town, you know, almost—not quite that everybody knew everybody, but it was close. And so my dad was visiting one time near his airplane, and he asked me if I wanted to go up for a ride, but I said no. [Laughs.] Like I said, I was <date>only four years old</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So in terms of your father’s own service record in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, you said you’re not sure quite how your father knew him, but do you know much about what your father did in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, he worked on—he was assigned to the [<orgName>U.S.] Naval Research Lab[oratory</orgName>] in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, and was working on developing radar, which was, of course, brand new back then, so he did a lot of—he was an electronics technician, so he was doing work with radar back then.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did you have any other family members who you specifically recall having served or told you stories about having served?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, my uncle, my father’s brother, was a lieutenant in the [U.S.] <orgName>Army</orgName>, and I believe was stationed in <placeName>Australia</placeName>, but I never really talked to him much about that at all. And my two other uncles on my mother’s side—one of them was a bombardier-navigator in the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] <orgName>Army Air Corps</orgName>, and, quite frankly, I don’t know very much about what his service was. And then her younger brother served in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> as an enlisted man during <name type="event">the Korean [War</name>] era, but I don’t think he was ever over by <placeName>Korea</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Now, can you tell me more about your mother, what kind of a person she is? You know, maybe she was involved in other things around town?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, prior to getting married—my mother was from the Iron Range in <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>. And looking back on it, I wish I would have asked her more questions. Neither of my parents are alive now. But when she was a young woman, she left <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> and went out to <placeName>California</placeName> and ended up working as a secretary for <orgName>Lockheed [Corporation</orgName>, now part of <orgName>Lockheed Martin</orgName>] at their <placeName>Burbank</placeName> plant. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That’s sounds quite adventurous.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So it sounds like your father—your father was in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, and your mother was involved certainly in some type of aeronautics stuff. Do you think that had any influence on your decision to join the <orgName>Navy</orgName> and become a naval aviator?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Not the naval aviator portion of it, because my mother was a secretary, so she was, I mean—could have ended up being a secretary for a car company, you know, as far as—but certainly my dad being in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> I think influenced me to want a career in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. And, as I mentioned before, I read a lot of books, some novels but mostly historical books about <name type="event">World War II</name>. I read a lot of—a lot of stuff about the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, the different aspects of it, and it just seemed like something that really appealed to me.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. I’d love to come back to that in a minute, but do you know anything about your family history of where your parents came from, grandparents?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. It’s funny you should ask that, because I’ve been doing some genealogy just recently. My father’s people were from <placeName>Luxembourg</placeName>, <placeName>Germany</placeName> and <placeName>Prussia</placeName> on my grandfather’s side, but on his mother’s side—kind of interesting—I started tracing them back, and it looks like I was able to trace them back to <placeName>Colonial America</placeName>, back to the <date>1620s</date>. One of them was—apparently was <persName>Deacon [William] Peck</persName>. And then I went even farther back to <placeName>England</placeName>. It turns out that there are <persName>Norman knights</persName> in the family tree, and I was able to get across the [English] Channel over to <placeName>France</placeName>. Long story short, apparently—I wouldn’t swear to this because I don’t know how accurate the research was and I’m just piggybacking on other people’s family trees—but I may possibly be a descendent from <persName>Charlemagne</persName> as well as <persName>Rollo</persName>, the Viking. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Very interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I found that [chuckles]—I found that kind of fascinating, so I’ve been trying to bone up on my European history, which was not ever my strong suit.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And on your mother’s side?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">My mother’s side. Her mother was Norwegian. Her parents were born in <placeName>Norway</placeName>. Her father was adopted, so it was a little hard to really figure out, but his parents were born in <placeName>Ireland</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, did you—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">That’s as far back as we’ve been able to trace anything.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, so with such recent immigrants on your mother’s side, did she speak any of those languages, have any cultural kind of holdouts from the fact that her parents were immigrants?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, she didn’t. And all of my grandparents were born in this country, so, yeah, the language— Occasionally, I think my grandmother would be known to curse in Norwegian, but—[Laughs.] But anyway, yeah, all of my grandparents were-were born in—in this country, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, in a small town like <placeName>Winona</placeName>—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about what politics were like and also your family politics? Was the town generally liberal, conservative? How did it kind of view various issues?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">My family was very conservative politically. The town in general was—that region of <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> is fairly conservative. At least it was back then. <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> in general is a fairly liberal state, but that congressional district traditionally went Republican.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. Now, was your family particularly religious?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No. They used to take my brother and myself and drop us off at <date>Sunday</date> School [chuckles] and they’d come back home, so, yeah, we were required to go to Sunday School, but they did not go to church, you know, normally.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What church would that be?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I was raised in the Episcopal faith or <orgName>the Episcopal Church</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So, now, going into high school, you said you were very interested in history, especially <name type="event">World War II</name> history. You also said you read a lot of books. Did that—did you feel like you were more academically engaged or interested in that than your classmates?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. Yeah, I was always I guess kind of considered a little bit of a—back in <date>those days</date>, the term was “bookworm.” I guess now it might be called a “nerd” or something like that.  But, yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And, so, [unintelligible] history was your, your primary or most—your favorite subject?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I’m sorry, could you repeat that?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. Was history your favorite subject?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, the science classes were always my favorite subject.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So the history was more something you did in your spare time?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, exactly. Yeah, just—that way I pick the particular areas that I was interested in. As I’ve gotten older, I’ve become more interested in history in general, but back then it was primarily—for some reason, I was just really interested in <name type="event">World War II</name>. Of course, it wasn’t—you know, when I was <date>10 years old</date>, it was only, like, <date>five, six years</date> after the war, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And were there any particular clubs or favorite teachers or classes you remember from high school?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, as far as clubs go, I was in the drama club, the science club. I’m trying to think of what else I was in. But I was also out for sports as well, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What sports?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I’m not a very big person, so [chuckles] that kind of limited me to what sports, so in the fall I was the manager of the football team, the student manager of the football team. But in the <date>winter</date> I was a diver on the swimming team. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">And then <date>one year</date>—one year I was out for track in <date>the spring</date>, but I attempted to become a pole vaulter, but the coach was only either interested or knowledgeable about coaching the track events and not the field events, so we were pretty much on our own, so I wasn’t able to teach myself how to pole vault, so after <date>one season</date> of that, I gave that up.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, do you remember how you got on with your fellow classmates? Any particular friendships from there that maybe carried over to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> or throughout the rest of your life?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, I still—I stayed in touch with a couple of my high school classmates. Some of them have already, unfortunately, passed on. And strangely enough, as small high school as I went to, I think our graduating class was only—I think it was less than 250 people in our graduating class. Two of my classmates went to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> with me, so there were three of us from our small high school at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> at the same time, in the same class, the Class of  ’66 there, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That’s almost unheard of now. So do you think you were generally considered popular? Can you tell me about the groups you hung out with in high school?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I didn’t hang out with the, for lack of a better term, I guess, the “cool” gang, the jocks or whatever. It was more the—more the—the guys that—the academic types, but all of us were out for sports, so it wasn’t like—yeah, we were all either on the swimming team or, you know, something—something like wrestling or something like that. So we were all engaged in sports, but we were probably considered more, I guess, the brainier kids, for lack of a better term, or the good kids as opposed to the jocks or something like that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So, now, going up to around your junior and senior year, when you’re starting to think about college, can you tell me about what you wanted to do, what your parents wanted you to do? Did you definitely know you wanted to go into college?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, yeah, there was never any question in my mind that I’d go on to college. I’m sure there was questions in my parents’ mind how they were going to be able to pay for it because I did not come from a wealthy family, by any stretch of the imagination. I have actually—starting about ninth grade, when I decided I wanted to become a naval officer—I was shooting for the [<orgName>U.S.] Naval Academy</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I want to go back when you mentioned—you mentioned that in ninth grade you wanted—you knew you wanted to be a naval officer. </u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes, I did.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That’s—that’s pretty early. Can you tell me about that?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, it just—prior to that time, I thought I wanted to do something somewhat related to chemistry or pharmacy or something like that. I didn’t really know. And then about toward the end of junior high school, I just started deciding that I wanted to be a naval officer.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—and actually one other question about that time: Did your father go to college, or either of your parents?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">He did. He went to <orgName>Hobart College</orgName> and then transferred to <orgName>the University of Minnesota</orgName>. And for whatever reason— I never really asked him—well, I asked him, but I never got a straight answer. He didn’t graduate. He had, like, one term left to go, and so I don’t know what the deal was there, but he did not graduate. My mother went to a junior high school up in <placeName>the Iron Range</placeName>—a college, rather.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, your father was—was he enlisted or was he an officer?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">He was enlisted. When he was discharged, he was a first class petty officer.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah. But that actually reminds me of one thing, which is kind of— for the record, they like to have the acronyms clarified, so can you just remind for posterity what <persName>NROTC</persName> Is?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN"><orgName>The Naval Reserve Officer</orgName> [sic; Officers] Training Corps.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Cool. And petty officer is obviously an enlisted rank. </u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, I wasn’t actually appointed to <orgName>West Point</orgName>. I was selected—I don’t know what they—I think they called it a nomination—but anyway, to take the physical, so I actually went to <placeName>Fort Sheridan</placeName>, <placeName>Illinois</placeName>, which is where they were doing the <orgName>Army</orgName> physicals for <placeName>West Point</placeName>. But I basically told my congressman, “Thanks, but no thanks,” that I’d rather go the <orgName>NROTC</orgName> route at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> and go to <placeName>West Point</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So do you remember what <date>year</date> your senior year in high school was?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Do I remember what <date>year</date> it was?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Or what it was like?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No, what <date>year</date> it was.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, yeah, sure. Yeah, I graduated in <date>1962</date>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So when you visited this military installation and you thought about, you know, to take your physical fitness test, and when you thought about going into the military, kind of looking back at <name type="event">the Korean War</name>, which had just recently happened, what kind of military did you think you were going into?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, back in <date>those days</date>, it was a peacetime military. Of course, <orgName>the Cuban Missile Crisis</orgName> and <placeName>the Bay of Pigs</placeName> [invasion] and all that hadn’t even happened yet, so, yeah, there was a little bit of a <name type="event">Cold War</name> going on, but, yeah, it was basically just a peacetime <orgName>Navy</orgName> back in the, you know, <date>late ’50s</date>, <date>early ’60s</date> type thing, so I didn’t really, you know, give a whole lot more thought than that. I mean, I always realized there’s a possibility, you know, that there could be a war again, but, yeah, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> hadn’t even raised its ugly head back in <date>those days</date>, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you know where <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was on the map? Do you recall being able—being conscious of that area of <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>, what was going on there?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, yeah, yeah, I was aware of it. I primarily knew it or maybe our textbooks in school probably weren’t that up to date, but it was French <placeName>Indochina</placeName>. So, yeah, I was aware of it. And I certainly heard about the French defeat at <persName>Dien Bien Phu</persName> [in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>] and all that, but, you know, it didn’t mean a whole lot to me [chuckles] back in <date>those days</date>. So, yeah, I was certainly aware of it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what did you think of the French, and—what did you think of the French? What did you think of the communists in general, as groups?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, I was certainly raised as just about everybody was back in <date>those days</date>—and I haven’t changed my mind a whole lot [chuckles]—that the communists were, you know, not to be trusted and certainly not our friends. And the French had been our allies in the past, so I was certainly—of course, <persName>Dien Bien Phu</persName> was in ’54, so I would have only been <date>about 10 years old</date> at the time, so I probably wasn’t super concerned with world events. And, like I said, we didn’t—back in <date>those days</date>, we did not have the TV in our house, so it would have been whatever I had heard in school or read in the newspapers, but, yeah, I would have been in favor of the French versus the—versus the communists.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And I had also asked kind of what your impression of the military was. I mean, you had a father in the military, and I don’t know how much he told you about being in the military, and obviously his military experience was much different than yours later would prove to be, but did you feel like the military lifestyle was something you wanted to live—you know, the discipline, the barracks life?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. My father always spoke very fondly of his time in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. I didn’t really get a chance to talk a whole lot with my uncles about their time in the service. But, yeah, my dad always spoke—he was only in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> <date>about three years or so</date>. He enlisted right after [the attack on] <placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName> [<placeName>Hawaii</placeName>]. He was fairly old, you know, for an enlistee. He was I think about 28 or so when he was enlisted, so he was always telling me that his fellow recruits at boot camp and all that would always—would call him <persName>Pappy</persName>. But, yeah, he spoke fondly of his time in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. But, on the other hand, he never saw any action, never went overseas, so he seemed to like his time in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName></u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about what the college search was like, what you looked for, how you even went back that back then before you had <orgName>Google</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I had heard about Dart- —our across-the-street neighbor, an attorney, had gone to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, so I’d heard about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> from him. I loved <date>winter</date> sports, growing up in <placeName>Minnesota</placeName>, not a whole lot—I guess you don’t have to love them, but if you don’t [chuckles], you’re really limiting what you can do there. So I loved to ski, so I was looking for a place where I could go skiing.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. Was <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> your first choice out of those two?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, yeah. Certainly <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was the first choice.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So in terms of the application process—I’m sure both the application process for <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and <orgName>NROTC</orgName> were both much different back then—and did you have to apply to <orgName>NROTC</orgName> ahead of time? Can you tell me about that process?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes, you did. You had to apply to <orgName>NROTC</orgName>. You had to be—actually, you had to be accepted kind of like three times. You had to be accepted by <orgName>NROTC</orgName>, you had to be accepted by <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, and then you had to be accepted into the <orgName>Dartmouth NROTC</orgName> unit, because I knew—I knew of I think at least one person that had been accepted into <orgName>NROTC</orgName>, been accepted into <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> but not into <orgName>the Dartmouth NROTC</orgName>. The quota had been filled, so he ended up going [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] Air Force ROTC instead of—because he wanted to go to <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. So you actually had to be accepted kind of like three ways.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me about the contact you had specifically with <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and <orgName>NROTC</orgName>, before you arrived at school?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I didn’t have any contact with <orgName>Dartmouth NROTC</orgName> before I got there, so I don’t know how the selection process worked. I’m sure it was just people looking at, you know, interviews and, you know—and all that. I did have—somebody from the—well, they weren’t active-duty <orgName>Navy</orgName>. They had I think volunteers I think had come down from <placeName>Minneapolis</placeName> or something like that to interview me for—or maybe I had gone somewhere else for the interview. I don’t really remember. Because I do remember going through interviews, one of them which was in my home, and I don’t remember—but I remember being interviewed by people from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> or representing <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, probably alumni, as well as people interviewing me for the <orgName>Navy</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, actually, I forgot to ask one thing: Did you have siblings?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes, a brother <date>two years</date> younger and a sister <date>twelve years</date> younger.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, interesting. And did you get along well with either or both of them, or none of them?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I kind of got along social with my younger [chuckles]—younger brother. He still annoys me, but—at times. But, yeah, we certainly stay in contact. And my sister—I stay in frequent contact with her. She was enough younger—she started kindergarten <date>the year</date> I started <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I’m going to pause the recording, and just tell me when you come back to us.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">All right.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">All right, coming back, this is <persName>Sandor Farkas</persName> and <persName>Nicholas Steffen</persName> resuming the interview on <date>August 12th, 2015</date>.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, he was a sophomore when I was a senior. And as I started to say before I got interrupted there, my sister started kindergarten <date>the same year</date> that I started <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I don’t know how the classes start now, but back then I think <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> didn’t start until, like, <date>the third week of September</date> or so, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Still the same.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, okay. So I actually walked my—walked my little sister to kindergarten, to the same school that I went to. It was only about four blocks away. So, yeah—I mean, yeah, we got along fine. I just didn’t have a whole lot of contact with her. You know, she was, you know, <date>four or five years old</date> when I was heading off to college 1,500 miles away, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Where did your brother end up going to college?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">He went to one of the local colleges, <placeName>Winona State</placeName>. Back in <date>those days</date>, it was <orgName>Winona State College</orgName>. It’s now <orgName>Winona State University</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did he end up serving in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> or serving in any capacity?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">My brother? No, he did not.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">All right. So going back to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, you’ve been accepted, and it is, I would guess, mid-, <date>late September</date>. Can you tell me when you left and how you left for <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes. My parents drove me—drove me out there, so—yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">You have good parents, very good parents.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">To drive that far.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">A road trip out to <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>, and they got the tour of the campus and see everything, got me settled into the dorm. My first dorm was at—I’m assuming it’s still there—Brown [Hall], one of the <orgName>Choate</orgName> row [sic; <orgName>Choate Cluster</orgName>] dorms.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Possibly. They’ve kind of—that area has a lot of dorms that I think have since been renamed. Tell me more about when you first got to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. Do you remember which way you approached the campus by, coming up over the Ledyard Bridge, from the south, north?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I don’t even really remember. We came through <placeName>Vermont</placeName>, I know, so I guess we would have probably come over the Ledyard Bridge. That was before the—they didn’t have any of the interstates where—in the <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName> area did not exist back then. So it would have been the equivalent of all back roads, I guess. We did have the—you know, the New York Turnpike [sic; <placeName>New York State</placeName> Thruway] and all that, but the interstate system was nowhere near like it is now, so I’m not really sure. I think we, you know, came through the center of probably <placeName>Rutland</placeName>, <placeName>Vermont</placeName>, and <placeName>White River Junction</placeName> [<placeName>Vermont</placeName>] and came in that way, I suppose.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember your first impression of the campus, the town?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I really don’t. It was maybe a little overwhelming, I guess, but, yeah, I don’t have [laughs] any real memory of a first impression.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Had you ever been away from home? Were you nervous about that aspect?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, that’s the farthest away from home I’d ever been. The only other places I’d been—up to northern <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> to go to either visit my grandparents or go to <placeName>YMCA</placeName> [<orgName>Young Men’s Christian Association</orgName>] camp. Used to go to camp—like, a new camp <date>every summer</date>. So, yeah, that’s as far away as I’d been except for when I went over to take that <orgName>Army</orgName> physical over in the <placeName>Chicago</placeName> area, so—yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you said your parents helped you settle in. Can you tell me more about your dorm, what that first kind of <date>week</date>, orientation was like?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, it was kind of—it was kind of hectic, you know, meeting all new people. I remember—I’m sure they probably don’t do that <date>these days</date>, but there was a kind of a get-together. The college even paid for either a keg or beer or a bunch of cases of beer or something. Of course, we were all under age, but that didn’t seem to bother the college back in <date>those days</date>. That was the first—that was the first time I had ever—ever had more than one beer. I never drank in high school, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I must say I’m shocked.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">[Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Not in a bad way, but—so did you have a roommate?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, I had a roommate, yeah, and he was from <placeName>Long Island</placeName> [<placeName>New York</placeName>]. We were just—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me more about him?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No. [Laughs.] He was from <placeName>Long Island</placeName>, and he smoked, and I didn’t, so that’s about all I—you know, we were friendly, but we weren’t friends, if you get the distinction.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, certainly.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">We got along fine, but other than that, we didn’t socialize outside of the dormitory, so I don’t really know—I got along well with him enough that we agreed to be roommates <date>the following year</date>, but I couldn’t—I mean, I remember his name, but I wouldn't be able to tell you what he ended up majoring in or what happened to him or anything else.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">If he—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I think he was in <orgName>Army</orgName> ROTC, I believe.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh. So actually—especially when there are people, you mentioned, that also served in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> or possibly served in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, <orgName>DVP</orgName>, <orgName>the Dartmouth Vietnam Project</orgName>, is very interested to hear their names. Do you think you could tell us his name?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes, it was [<persName>Edward F.]</persName> “Ed” Brown [Class of 1966].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS"><persName>Ed Brown</persName>. And so after that first kind of initial orientation—by the way, did you have a separate orientation week?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, I [unintelligible] we did—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—or an orientation period?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, we did, but I don't remember—I really don’t remember much about it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember what classes you took or any of the classes you took that first term?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, not without bringing up my old transcripts. I think I took some—I think I took a chemistry course because I was intending to be—at that time, I was intending to become a chemistry major. That didn’t last very long, but—I think I took a German course. I really don’t—and, of course, I had to take my naval science courses.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me more about what was required for <orgName>ROTC</orgName> at that time?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I’m sorry, could you—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me more about what kind of requirements there were for <orgName>ROTC</orgName> in terms of—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, sure.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. We were required to take—in addition to the naval science courses, we were required to take physics and calculus and psychology.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">And the rest of it, you know, we could take basically whatever we wanted. There were certain majors that were not accepted, but that wouldn't have been a big issue at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. Well, I guess—I guess <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> does have a religion major, but you couldn’t major in religion, couldn’t major in veterinary sciences or stuff like that, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">That’s very interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, it was fairly soon, and once again, they had, as I recall, probably a beer party or a cocktail party [laughs] to get us indoctrinated. So you met the commanding officer of the unit as well as the instructors that were all—they were all naval officers. But, yeah, they did have a social function to get us acquainted.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So it wasn’t—it wasn’t really the kind of off-the-bus drill structure—drill instructor kind of greeting? It was a very informal greeting?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, it was reasonably informal. I mean, we had to go over and, you know, get our uniforms and stuff like that. Back in <date>those days</date>, we were only required [unintelligible] on <date>Wednesdays</date>, which was <date>the drill day</date>. The rest of the time, we did not wear our uniforms. But there was no, like, any kind of a, you know, boot camp type atmosphere or anything like that. They did—on our <date>Wednesday</date> drill periods, they had, you know, indoctrinated us in the basics, and we had marching and stuff like that. But it was—it was pretty laid back. The <orgName>Navy</orgName> [chuckles] has never been quite so big on some of that stuff as I think maybe some of the other branches of the service are.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So was there an <placeName>ROTC</placeName> building or an office, any kind of central depot where they kept stuff, where the officers were?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, there was. It’s not—I don’t think the classrooms were in there. I’m trying to remember. I think a lot of our classrooms were actually over in—somewhere over there in <orgName>Dartmouth Row</orgName>, those little white buildings. But—what are the buildings that are opposite the white buildings on the Green? You got to keep in mind, this is <date>more than forty years ago</date>. <persName>McNutt</persName>?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No ways. <persName>Parkhurst</persName> [Hall]?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, <persName>Parkhurst</persName>, probably, one of the—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS"><orgName>College Hall</orgName>, Collis [now <orgName>Collis Center for Student Involvement</orgName>].</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, one of those was, like, the—where the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> offices were, but not the classrooms. So that’s where the—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, did you drill—did you drill with rifles and—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">We did. We used—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you drill with rifles?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, [M]1903 <persName>Springfields</persName>. Yeah, bolt-action <persName>Springfields</persName>. Actually, it was good—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Lucky you.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, it was a good rifle to drill with because it’s very nicely balanced. Never fired them, but we drilled with them.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Heh! And they were—now, this is a very small detail. I don’t expect you to remember this, but do you remember if the rifles had the bolts taken out or if the barrels were filled? I know they do that to a lot of drill rifles, but—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, they were fully functional.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Were they somewhat operable rifles?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, they were fully functional. That’s one reason I preferred drilling with the ’03 Springfields because when you went to inspection arms, you had to open the bolt. You didn’t have to worry about getting the “M1 thumb” [injury to the thumb when using M1 Garand]. If you were drilling with an M1, if you didn’t get your—when you opened up—yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">So you didn’t have to worry about the—I never did get the M1 thumb.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So to explain for—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Pardon?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[No comment.]</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I was just going to explain for people who might not know what the M1 thumb is—yeah. It’s when the bolt closes on your finger—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Right.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—when you’re trying to—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">That’s about all the more I know about it, because I never did drill with an M1.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember where they kept the rifles?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Pardon? Where they kept them? No, I—well, I think they had an armor—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you know where they kept the rifles?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Pardon? They had them—I think we—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember, by any chance, where that was?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">One of the field—we drilled in one of the—that’s probably where they kept the rifles, in one of the old field houses. I want to say <persName>Leverone</persName> [Field House], but I—I don’t know if that was it or not. But we did mostly—due to the weather there,—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, that’s where we drill <date>today</date>, actually.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">—we did most of our drill indoors.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. Oh, that’s actually very interesting. I’ve seen pictures—okay, sorry. I’ve seen pictures of them drilling on the <orgName>Green</orgName>. Did you ever—do you recall drilling on the <persName>Green</persName> ever?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, never. Yeah, as far as I know, it was all indoors. So, yeah, it was in the field house.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t really remember. Like I said, we did a fair amount of drilling. We might have done some physical type stuff. I do remember taking physical fitness tests once a year or so, but other than that, I don’t—I don’t really remember a whole lot about it, about the actual drills. Must not have impressed me too much.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What did you learn—what did you learn in <orgName>Navy</orgName> science class?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I’m sorry, could you repeat that?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Silence.]</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Could you repeat the question, please?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah, yes. What did you learn in <orgName>Navy</orgName> science class?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, well,—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry, I think there might be a little bit of a sound problem.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. Naval science classes. Some were about—leadership classes. Of course, at the very beginning it was kind of almost like an introduction to the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, where you learn the different ranks and naval courtesies and stuff like that. We also had classes in engineering. Learned about the boilers aboard ships. And had class. We had navigation classes. Learned some piloting. And by piloting I don’t mean aircraft piloting but naval vessel piloting, as opposed to navigation. Also learned navigation. Naval history.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you know by that time you were interested in being an aviator?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I didn’t even think about aviation until—we had to take training cruises <date>every summer</date>, and the <date>summer</date>—my second cruise, which was <date>the summer</date> between my sophomore and <name type="event">junior year</name>, was split <date>between three weeks</date> of <orgName>Marine</orgName> indoctrination down in [Naval Amphibious Base] Little Creek, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, and, quite frankly, it didn’t take me <date>three weeks</date> to know that I didn’t want to be a <orgName>Marine</orgName>, and <date>three weeks</date> of aviation indoctrination in <placeName>Corpus Christi</placeName>, <placeName>Texas</placeName>. And that’s when the aviation bug hit me, so that’s when I decided that I wanted to—wanted to be an aviator.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, I’d love to go back to that. Before we do, can you tell me about what your social life was like at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>? Did you ever go in a fraternity, by any chance?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I didn’t. I did rush. Apparently nobody was interested in me, so I was no big deal, so—yeah, I was not in a fraternity. It was a little hard, back in <date>those days</date>, to get dates since there weren’t any women on campus, so we would have to road trippie over to some of the girls’ colleges that were within driving distance, or down to <placeName>Boston</placeName> or whatever. So I didn’t date a whole lot until—until <date>my senior year</date>. And then I pretty much had I guess a date <date>almost every weekend</date>, so—that’s when I had to start—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Had you had any girlfriends in high school?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, I did. I didn’t have a girlfriend in high school, but I did end up with a hometown girl after my—when I went back in the <date>summer</date> break and actually had her come up for <name type="event">Winter Carnival</name> my senior year, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So your social life at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, you’re saying, didn’t really involve the fraternities all that much. Where did you go to hang out?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, no, I mean, I used to—I would go to the fraternities, you know, for parties and that, but I did not belong to one, so—you know, unless it was <date>a big weekend</date>—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">—the fraternities would have—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—your favorite fraternities to go to?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I sure don’t. I think whichever one the band sounded best as I was walking by or something. I really don’t—really don’t recall.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So sorry. The audio seems to have a slight delay, but—so I apologize that my questions are getting to you a little bit late. But can you tell me more about <date>the big weekends</date>, about those different festivals, what you remember about those?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t remember a whole lot. I just remember that there were, you know, big weekends. <name type="event">Winter Carnival</name>—if you didn’t have a date, <name type="event">Winter Carnival</name> [chuckles] wasn’t all that fun. But <orgName>the Green Key [Weekend</orgName>] and <persName>Dartmouth Night</persName>—because the weather was better [chuckles], they were a little bit more—more enjoyable. But I did—by my junior and senior year, I was able to—able to get dates for some of the—some of <date>those weekends</date>. Like I said, pickings were kind of limited back in those—those days.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I was going to say the college used to have mixers, where they would actually bus girls in from the colleges.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about which colleges you went to? Any particular that you remember?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I don’t know if they’re even still in exis- —there was <orgName>Colby Junior College</orgName> [no <orgName>Colby-Sawyer College</orgName>] over in—I think that was over in <placeName>New London</placeName>, <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>. <orgName>Green Mountain Junior College</orgName> [now <orgName>Green Mountain College</orgName>] over in <placeName>Vermont</placeName>. And, of course, if you wanted to step up in class, you’d go down to <orgName>Smith [College</orgName>] or <orgName>Vassar</orgName> [College] or <orgName>Wellesley</orgName> [College] or <orgName>Mount Holyoke [College</orgName>].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So here’s an interesting—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Silence.]</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Go ahead with the question.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry about this audio delay. It makes all my questions get to you after—when you’re already answering.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, it definitely didn’t give an advantage. I don’t know that it—that it hindered it, either. I remember my freshman year there, they took us on a—the <orgName>NROTC</orgName> unit took us on a field trip down to—down to <placeName>Boston</placeName> to go out on some sea trials on the USS Albany, a guided missile cruiser. And we went out  on the town the night before, and we had to—we had to wear our uniforms, as I recall, and trying to pick up <orgName>the Radcliffe [College</orgName>, now <orgName>Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study</orgName> at <orgName>Harvard University</orgName>] girls in our uniforms. But back in <date>those days</date>, the military was still reasonably popular, so it wasn’t—it wasn’t too bad a deal. But certainly by the time I graduated, if you wanted to impress a girl, you did not tell her you were in <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, that’s for sure.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So obviously—you previously mentioned that when—at the time you came into <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was not widely known, and you just said that the military still enjoyed at least some level of popularity. Can you tell me about the evolution of students’ sentiments toward the military—you know, when you first heard the word “Vietnam” being used?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, I don’t remember exactly the first time I heard the term “<placeName>Vietnam</placeName>” being used, but to put things in perspective, <placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin incident</placeName> was in <date>1964</date>, so that was approximately halfway through my stay at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>. And, of course, as the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> ramped up their involvement in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and increased the draft, that’s I think when the sediment—sentiment started turning. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about—yeah. Can you tell me about what it was like walking around campus wearing a <orgName>Navy</orgName> ROTC uniform? Did people ever jeer at you at all?</u>
      <u who="WOMAN"><persName>Bob</persName> come in?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, I think he’s left.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">This is <persName>Sandor Farkas</persName> interviewing <persName>Nicholas Steffen</persName>. I am in—I’m in Webster Hall on <orgName>Dartmouth College’s</orgName> campus. He is at his home in <placeName>Henderson</placeName>, <placeName>Nevada</placeName>. It is <date>Wednesday, August 26th, 2015</date>. And this is the second part of our oral history interview.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I worked there as an announcer and a disk jockey. I wasn’t on in prime time. Usually the early morning hours [chuckles], like 6 or so, 6 a.m. on <date>Saturday</date> morning or something like that. But, yeah, I enjoyed my time working there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did you ever cover news?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Just read it off the wire. We’d get the news copy off the teletype. That’s what they used in <date>those days</date>. It basically—as they used to say, rip it and read it, just pull off the printed stuff that came over the teletype and read it on the hour.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And do you recall ever reading any news about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> or <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t. I may have, but I don’t recall doing that. And I also don’t recall being on the air that often. I was on a few times but just a few occasions, so I don’t recall reading anything about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at the time.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So previously you had mentioned that you did <orgName>ROTC</orgName>, <placeName>Naval ROTC</placeName> training sessions during <date>the summer</date>, called cruises?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about especially that last cruise before your senior year and what happened then?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">The last cruise was on a [Allen M.] <persName>Sumner</persName>-class destroyer out of the naval base at <placeName>Newport</placeName>, <placeName>Rhode Island</placeName>. The destroyer was used for research and development. The time I was on there, they were testing I think a new fire control system for the 5-inch .38 caliber guns. We were—that being our first class cruise, we were treated as junior officers. We wore officer-style uniforms and ate the meals in the officers’ wardroom—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And your—.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">—aboard ship.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And your first class—that would mean your senior cruise.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">That’s correct.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes. So you’re saying you ate in the officers’—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">In the wardroom aboard the ship, with the officers, yes. And stood junior officers type watches on the bridge of the ship and stuff like that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And can you tell me about returning from the cruise to the home port of that ship?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">As I recall, we were probably back in port every night because, like I said, it was probably a research and development ship, so they would go out and test equipment and then come back in in the evening. So as far as getting to exotic ports of call, that didn’t happen. [Chuckles.] We didn’t go anywhere else other than <placeName>Newport</placeName>, <placeName>Rhode Island</placeName>, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Had you gotten to go anywhere interesting on previous cruises?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, we did. On my third class cruise, which was—the destroyer there was based out of <placeName>Norfolk</placeName>, <placeName>Virginia</placeName>. We were sent up to the destroyer squadron along with the aircraft carrier, [USS] Intrepid. Sent up to <placeName>Boston</placeName>, and our destroyer was detailed actually to pull into the port of <placeName>Salem</placeName>, <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>, because the destroyer, USS John W. Weeks, was named after—I believe it was the secretary of war or something, who was originally from <placeName>Salem</placeName>, <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>. And our post visit coincided with a town celebration they were having anyway, so we pulled into—into port. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And, again, remind me how many of you there were, as in how many <placeName>Naval ROTC</placeName> cadets there were. Approximately.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I want to say—I want to say that approximately there was—I’m guessing probably 20 to 25 all together aboard—aboard the ship.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did the number of <orgName>Dartmouth Naval ROTC</orgName> cadets increase or decrease as your time went on?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">It stayed pretty constant, as I recall. I don’t think we had too many—too many dropouts. Most of the—as I recall, most of the <orgName>NROTC</orgName> students were on scholarship. Some of them were not, but most of us I think were on scholarship, so that was a strong incentive to stay with the program.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did you get the sense that people were coming there because they were specifically interested in a military career, or was it for other reasons, such as financial reasons?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I think it was probably a combination of both, but primarily that they were interested in a naval career, and since we would have had to have committed to the program back in high school—we’re talking probably, you know, <date>1961</date> to actually file the applications for it and start taking the entrance exams and all that. This is long before <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you know, was—was an issue. Let me put it that way. It would have been <date>a good three years</date> before <placeName>the Gulf of Tonkin incident</placeName>. So people weren’t doing it as a way to avoid the draft or avoid serving in the <orgName>Army</orgName> as an enlisted soldier. So I think people were genuinely interested in going into the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, perhaps not necessarily making it a career. Certainly the financial aspects were significant. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">It changed gradually. Not a significant change. I think there was always probably some people that maybe looked down a little bit on the people in <orgName>NROTC</orgName> or RO- —any of the ROTCs as perhaps not being able to afford college on their own and therefore weren’t quite as good as some of the <orgName>Eastern</orgName> elite. But that wasn’t a significant issue. Generally, most people just accepted it. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">You never had much contact with that latter group, the people who—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, it wasn’t—I mean, there were people that maybe had some protest signs or something like that, but I don’t—I don’t recall anything of any significance going on. There might have been a little bit more on some of the other Ivy [League] campuses, but ’66—and, of course, I graduated—I forget the exact day, you know, where you got commissioned. But it was <date>the end of May</date> or beginning of <date>June</date>. It was still relatively early in <date>’66</date>, so I don’t think the protest movement had really picked up a lot of steam like it had by ’67 or <date>’68</date>. I remember hearing about some of the campus protests at <orgName>Columbia</orgName> [University] and all that in <date>’68</date> and that, but nothing like that was going on when I was at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, can you tell me a bit about your academics? I recall that we previously talked about your majors. Can you remind me of how you changed majors, if those classes helped you in the service?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I started off initially as a geology major and after a couple of courses in that decided that wasn’t really what I wanted, so I switched over to <orgName>the geography department</orgName>, and the department head was able to give me a modified major to physical geography so I was able to use my geology credits towards my geography major. But as I recall, I did take some courses in meteorology and oceanography, which did play a part in helping me in my career in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, when you were deciding what you wanted to go into in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>, with the branching process, can you tell me about what you wanted to do, how you applied to do that, and what you ended up getting?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, initially I was thinking that I probably wanted to go into submarines, but I had based that on my knowledge of <name type="event">World War II</name> submarines and that, and, of course, the <orgName>Navy</orgName> was switching over to nuclear powered submarines. Admiral [<persName>Hyman G.]</persName> <persName>Rickover</persName> was in charge of the program then, and it was going to require a lot more expertise in physics than I had. I’d be going to nuclear power school and all that. And I started losing interest in doing that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, can you tell me about commissioning and graduation, what that was like?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">We had our commissioning ceremony first. I believe it was <date>a day</date> prior to the graduation ceremony, and all of the <orgName>ROTC</orgName> units were there. Of course, most people had their parents there, and we were all in our dress uniforms and were commissioned as—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Where was—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Where was this taking place?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I believe it was at the Bema [Big Empty Meeting Area].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">It was outdoors, and I think it was at the <persName>Bema</persName>. And so people were either getting commissioned as second lieutenants in the Marines, <orgName>Army</orgName> or <orgName>Air Force</orgName>, or ensigns in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. And then I believe <date>the following day</date> was the college graduation, which was held on the lawn in front of <persName>Baker</persName> Library [not <persName>Baker-Berry Library</persName>].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you wear your uniform?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I have no—no, no, just a cap and gown thing. I have absolutely no recollection whatsoever [chuckles] who the speaker was, so it couldn't have been anybody who made much of an impression on me.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me where you went after graduation?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I took a couple—I went back home to <placeName>Minnesota</placeName> and had just literally <date>just a few days</date> of leave before I had to report down in <placeName>Pensacola</placeName>. I actually didn’t start flight training immediately. I was sent on a temporary duty basis to the USS Lexington, which was an aircraft carrier based out in <placeName>Pensacola</placeName> at the time. It was used for training and qualifying the student naval aviators. So I was part of ship’s company for <date>about three months</date> down in <placeName>Pensacola</placeName> while we were waiting to start the flight program. I was assigned the job as the assistant <orgName>B Division</orgName> officer, which was in charge of the boilers. When I wasn’t in an office doing paperwork, I was down in the boiler rooms, which was really hot, so I tried to spend as little time as possible [chuckles] down in the boiler rooms.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did any other <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students go into aviation? </u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes, they did. I’m trying to—I think there were probably about four or five of us that I recall went into the flight program. In fact, my roommate aboard ship was another <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> Class of ’66, so he and I went through flight training together.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember his name?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I do. <persName>Kirk [J.] Ditzler</persName>. He passed away <date>several years ago</date>. I don’t know what the cause was.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah. Do you remember the names of any of the other four [unintelligible]?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I do. There was [<persName>Peter B.]</persName> “Pete” Richardson [Class of <date>1966</date>]. Went through flight training the same time I did. As a matter of fact, we ended up in the same squadron, and he and I were roommates when we were stationed at Patuxent River in <placeName>Maryland</placeName>. And then our time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> overlapped a little bit, but we were over in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> together. But we did not fly together because we were both copilots, so we didn’t fly with each other.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you say high school reunion?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes. He and I—he was from my hometown, and I’ve known him since literally nursery school. We were sandbox playmates. His parents, my parents were very good friends of each other, and they only lived about—less than a couple hundred yards from our house, so we used to play in—literally play in the sandbox together when we were infants. Went all through elementary and junior high, high school, <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> together, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes. When I actually started my training after my <date>three months</date> aboard the <placeName>Lexington</placeName>, we started—as I recall, it was <date>about six weeks</date> of ground school in <placeName>Pensacola</placeName>. And upon completing the ground school, we were sent to an auxiliary air station that was in the <placeName>Pensacola</placeName> area, [Naval Air Station] Saufley Field, where we were flying the <orgName>Beechcraft</orgName> T-34 [Mentor] aircraft, a single-engine, propeller aircraft. It was there that we learned the basic flying and soloed after approximately ten hours.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So throughout this process, when did you realize that you were going to be going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I didn’t know for sure I was going to be going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. It was about the time I was going through the aircraft—or the carrier qualifications. We had to fill out what they called a dream sheet, where we would request what type aircraft we wanted to fly. I decided I wasn’t particularly interested in flying jets off of aircraft carriers, partly due to my experience of <date>three months</date> aboard the <placeName>Lexington</placeName>. It was not air conditioned, so I thought, Well, I don’t really know if I really want to do this anymore. And I had no burning desire to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at the time, and I knew that if I had gone into fighters or attack, flying jets, that I’d be going onto a carrier, for sure, and then fly in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Sorry, what instrument f—?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Somewhere along in that—pardon?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What is instrument flying?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, the instruments in flying. So you rely on the instruments as opposed to visual flying. In other words, if you were flying in bad weather, where the visibility was not sufficient to allow you to get a good visual horizon, you’d rely on the various instruments in the aircraft for your—conduct your flights.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I see. So—sorry, you were saying—you were telling me about when you realized that you were going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I requested assignment to a squadron—either first or second choice. VX-8, based out of <placeName>Patuxent River</placeName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>. And I got orders there, and I found out that they—in addition to doing oceanographic research, they also had a detachment over in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so I figured it was probably likely that I would be going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So it was I guess sometime near the completion of my flight training, I realized that there was probably a pretty good chance that I’d be going to—going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but not in a combat—not flying combat missions.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So you’d been assigned to the squadron VX- —what was it, VXN-8?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yes. Well, they actually changed their name. They added the “N” partly through the time I was there. It went from VX-8 to VXN-8. I’m not sure why they changed the designation, but—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What do those letters mean?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, V in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> squadron, V stands for fixed wing aircraft. X is, for lack of a better term, is a research or experimental squadron. And the N designation was a sub-designation, a modifier, if you were, as you will, for the X, meaning oceanographic. So basically it means an oceanographic research squadron.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I got to VX-8 in <date>April</date>, as I recall, of <date>1968</date>. And so for the rest of the time there, I was going through training to learn to fly the <orgName>Lockheed</orgName> [L-1049] Super Constellation, which is the type aircraft they were flying. So went through training there. Flew on some of their local missions. They had some oceanographic research missions based out of <placeName>Patuxent River</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So did you get a chance before you left to go back to your hometown or to meet with your parents or family?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I did. We had some leave, and I went home and visited my—my folks.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And were you worried about—about going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I wasn’t. Like I said, we weren’t going to be flying direct combat missions, although it was in a war zone. The billeting hotel that we stayed in was run by the <orgName>Army</orgName>, but it was in downtown <placeName>Saigon</placeName>—was fairly close to the presidential palace, the Vietnamese presidential palace. And that—the palace came under periodic rocket attacks, so we could hear the rockets hitting in the morning occasionally or so. We were certainly aware that there was a war going on, but it wasn’t nearly as dangerous as flying a fighter attack aircraft off of the carriers.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me about landing in—you said <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? What it was like getting off the plane, what the climate was like?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. When I first stepped off, the first thing I noticed was how hot and humid it was, and I still remember it. It’s kind of hard to describe, but there was a distinct aroma to the air, kind of a—almost an odor of decay or something like that. It wasn’t necessarily unpleasant, but it was certainly different from anything I’d experienced before. I definitely was aware that I was, you know, in a foreign country.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what did you do that first day? As soon as you got off the plane, where did you go and how were you briefed, or when were you briefed?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">One of my squadron mates, who had been over there for a while, met me and kind of showed me around. I think one of the first things he did was give me a cold beer. Of course, we were going through a pretty significant jet lag. I think the time zone difference between <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and <placeName>the East Coast</placeName> is probably almost 12 hours, so I was completely on the back side of my normal clock, so it took <date>a few days</date> to get used to that. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What kind of pistol?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">We had a choice, actually. The choice was between the <date>1911</date> Colt .45 [known in the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> era as the Pistol, Colt. 45, Automatic, M1011A1],automatic, semi-automatic pistol, or a .38 caliber revolver. I chose the revolver because it was—I didn’t figure I was probably going to be shooting it anyway, and the .38 weighed less than the .45, so I figured, Since hopefully I won’t need to use it anyway, I might as well carry something that’s more comfortable to carry, so I chose the .38 revolver. [Chuckles.] And I was right. Never had to use it. Never came close to using it. It was probably rusted when I turned it back in.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So then you were telling me about drawing fatigues?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Pardon?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">You were telling about drawing fatigues?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I still didn’t catch what you said there, <persName>Sandor</persName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, sorry. You were telling me about drawing your fatigues?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, drawing the fatigues. Okay. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yes.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, we wore uniforms—they were kind of a green—basically it’s like the <orgName>Navy</orgName> Seabees wore, as opposed to—normally, at a Stateside naval base, you would be wearing—officers would be wearing a khaki uniform. Over there, we wore just green utilities. They were easier to—easier to wash, had our rank and insignia just embroidered on so we didn’t have to worry about losing the—losing the insignia. And they weren’t as shiny. They were just black rank and insignia, so they didn’t stand out like a shiny lieutenant’s bars.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And you were a lieutenant at that point, as opposed to a second lieutenant or the <orgName>Navy</orgName> equivalent. I’m sorry, I forget <orgName>Navy</orgName> rank.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">The first time I was over in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>—because I went earlier, twice—I was a lieutenant junior grade up until—I got over there in <date>February</date> of ’69 and then actually <date>the 1st of July 1969</date> I got promoted to full lieutenant, which would be the equivalent of an <orgName>Army</orgName> captain, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me briefly what the timeline of that first tour was: when you got there, when you went to <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName> or to <persName>Da Nang</persName> and then when you got back? Just the first tour.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I got there toward <date>the end of February of 1969</date>, and I guess I spent <date>a couple months</date> flying out of—out of <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName>, flying <name type="event">the Super Constellations</name>. We were broadcasting airborne television. Our mission—we’d take off normally around five or so in the afternoon, fly partway up the coast of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> and orbit off shore at 10,000 feet for three or four hours, broadcasting videotapes, Vietnamese language videotapes for—we had television transmitters on board, and then after about three or four hours of that we’d fly back down the coast and land, usually around midnight, one in the morning, back at <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So in <persName>Tan</persName>—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">At <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName> were you broadcasting the Vietnamese language television to the <placeName>South</placeName> or to the <placeName>North</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">To the <placeName>South</placeName>. It was mostly public service type of stuff, like hygiene, but some cultural stuff: Chinese opera type stuff. I only watched a little bit of it. I was up in the cockpit, flying, most of the time, but I did—when I would take a little break from the cockpit I’d come back and watch a little bit of what was being broadcast, but since it was in Vietnamese, I really didn’t understand a whole lot of what was going on, but I could—I could tell enough that some of it was on hygiene, or they had Chinese opera. I mean, it was in the Vietnamese language, but it was referred to as Chinese opera type stuff.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And what type of plane were you flying, and can you tell me exactly what your role was as a pilot?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. The plane we flew was a <orgName>Lockheed</orgName> [L-1049] Super Constellation, a four-engine, propeller aircraft, reciprocating engines. That type aircraft had been used an airliner most famously by <orgName>TWA</orgName> [<orgName>Trans World Airlines</orgName>] but by a lot of the major airlines in <placeName>the United States</placeName> to carry passengers. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I’m kind of confused. Were you the pilot or were you the copilot? I actually really don’t know the difference between those two things, in the first place, so can you explain that?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, okay. All right. I was—the first—my first tour of duty over there, I was a copilot. We shared flying responsibilities. I made takeoffs and landings, but I was—I was not in command of the aircraft, is I guess the difference. We had an aircraft commander on board. He was responsible for the conduct of the flight, the safety of the flight and basically was the officer in charge of the crew.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, changing gears a little bit, can you tell me about the building you lived in: where that was, what it was like inside, what the living conditions were like, and the food?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I’m sorry, what the—could you repeat that, <persName>Sandor</persName>?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me what the building you lived in was like: where it was, how your—kind of what the arrangements were?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, sure. Yeah, the building we lived in was—I think it was originally—been a hotel, but I’m not positive on that. It about a eight-story building in downtown <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, just only a couple of blocks from the presidential palace. It was run as an officer billeting hotel, by the <orgName>Army</orgName>, and it was primarily used as a transient officer facility for people that were kind of coming and going, although our unit was over there more or less permanently.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">How proficient were you with an M16 and a grenade? Did you ever learn how to use those?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Nope, never got any training on it at all, which also struck me as a little strange. It was kind of a—kind of a screwed-up situation. We used to joke it may have been a messed-up war, but it was the only one we had. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So were you each given your own room? Did you have to have a roommate? What kind of living situation was it?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">It depended on your rank. When I was over there the first time, I was of insufficient rank to get my own room, so I guess I had—had a roommate, who was another copilot but, because, as I’ve mentioned earlier, copilots don’t fly together; copilots only fly with aircraft commanders, he and I were—I believe we had—there were two—as I recall, two copilots there and three aircraft commanders, so the copilots pretty much alternated flying, because the mission flew every night, so one of us would fly one night and then be off the next night, and so one of us was always flying, so we were rarely on the ground together, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you get along well? I mean, for the times that you were together?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Sure, absolutely. Good time. And occasionally we would get some time off together, and we got a chance to go to one of the—one of the clubs, either a local Vietnamese bar or one of the military officer clubs in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So before we get into the clubs, which I’m very interested to hear about, you flew <date>every other day</date>,  you’re saying? Can you tell me <date>about the days</date> when you did fly: when you woke up, where you went and got breakfast, did you eat at the hotel, when you arrived for your briefing at <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. We would—on <date>the days</date> that we were flying, we would normally go into work right after lunchtime, and the hotel was some distance away from the air base, so there was a Vietnamese driver that would pick us up and take us out to the air base in a <orgName>Navy</orgName> sedan. He worked for the detachment. I still remember his name, Mr. <persName>Lee</persName>. And would drive us out there. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So what kind of food did you have, and how was it, and what kind of beer did you have?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, interesting you should ask. [Chuckles.] The food—we didn’t eat in—the officers didn’t eat in a mess hall. When we were on base, we would normally go to the officers club. When we were back in the evening, we would usually walk down to one of the officers clubs in downtown <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, usually to a place called the Rex Hotel. Had an officers club there. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did you ever eat Vietnamese food?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">We did. Occasionally we would go out and eat in—in some of the nicer restaurants. We were forbidden from eating from the street vendors. They were worried about the health concerns of holding— from their—but occasionally we’d go—there were some real good French restaurants there because, you know, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> used to be a French colony. So you would go there occasionally. Some of the best French onion soup and French bread I’ve ever had anywhere was actually in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. There was a Chinese restaurant that we used to go to occasionally. But not to much just straight Vietnamese food, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, sorry. I had also asked what type of beer did you have? did you have Vietnamese beer or—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, the Vietnamese beer was horrible. It was Beer 33, or <persName>Ba Muoi Ba</persName> in the Vietnamese language. Supposedly it was introduced to the Vietnamese by the French. As far as I—I was coming—especially coming from <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName>, I was a fairly prodigious beer drinker, but that stuff, as far as I was concerned, was almost undrinkable. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So how many nights per week, approximately, did you—did you go out to the clubs, kind of have fun? You know, aside from dinner but really, you know, go out and—I don't want to say “party,” but—or possibly party. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. Well, pretty much every other night. Every night you weren’t flying, you were going off to the clubs. There was a little Vietnamese bar, kind of like a little corner bar, right across the street from the hotel, and we sometimes used to hang out there. I actually ended up with a Vietnamese girlfriend that worked in that bar. So we would socialize. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did you dance in these—so sorry.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Did you say did we dance?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, so would you go dancing at these clubs?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, no, just sit around because there wasn’t anybody to dance with [chuckles], especially at the officers club. It was just a bunch of guys there. Occasionally we would go to the Vietnamese bars on Tu Do Street, which was downtown <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. And, of course, they would have bar girls working there. And some of the clubs had dancing. Most of the guys that I knew that we’d go out with were not really into dancing, so I’d go there and just flirt with the bar girls and buy them drinks, so—<placeName>Saigon</placeName> tea, as it was referred to, which was outrageously expensive, so we didn’t do that very—very often, because we knew it usually didn’t—didn’t lead anywhere except to an empty wallet.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What is <placeName>Saigon</placeName> tea? Sorry.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">It was just—it was just regular tea, but they—it was served to them in a shot glass, so they would pretend like they were drinking whiskey, and they charged an outrageous price for it, but that was the—that’s what you had to pay if you wanted to, you know, talk with one of the—one of the girls there. They’d, you know, sit down and they’d say, “You buy me <placeName>Saigon</placeName> tea, <persName>G.I.</persName>?” Usually—quite frankly, usually we had more money to spend than we knew what to do with over there, so—we frequently would accommodate them and buy them some <placeName>Saigon</placeName> tea, but most of us didn’t go to the Vietnamese bars down on Tu Do Street that often, just because of the expense. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—and I don’t know if this is a difficult subject, but can you tell me how you came to meet your girlfriend?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, she worked in the bar, and we got, you know, talking with her, and I guess we were both somewhat attracted to each other, and so I would usually look her up when I would over—over to the bar. I always tried—tried to get her to go out outside of work, and she never agreed to it my first tour, but then when I came back the second time, <date>about a year later</date>, she was surprised to see me again, and so we started going out.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Do you remember her name?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. Now, whether this was her real name or not—because a lot of the girls that worked in the bar would use what they called a bar name, but certainly the name I knew her—the name was <persName>Mai Ly</persName> [pronounced MY LEE], so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And you said you got to meet her family. Can you tell me about them?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I didn’t meet her parents, but I met her brothers. Yeah, I don’t—I don’t remember what—you know, what they did for a living, but, yeah, they helped prepare the food, and some of my fellow squadron mates—like I said, most of them were—were flying, but a couple or three, the ones that were not flying that evening—we got together and put on our good uniforms. I take it back, actually, for that one. We just wore our regular green utilities, I think. But anyway, we had a birthday party over at her apartment, and they prepared a bunch of Vietnamese food. And, yeah, I had—had a nice time.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So shifting away from that—I feel like we’re going into the second tour now—can you tell me anything about going back home: when you went back home, how long you were at home, what you did there?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I went back—let’s see; I'm trying to think. I would have gone back I think probably for <date>Christmas</date> leave, went back there probably for <date>a couple of weeks</date> to my parents’—my parents’ house there. Went back and saw some of my old high school classmates. It was kind of—kind of strange sometimes trying to explain to people what I was doing, so I’d kind of avoid that. The conversation would usually go something like, “Hey, <persName>Nick</persName>, how are you doing?” “Good.” “What are you doing?” “Oh, I’m home on leave from the <orgName>Navy</orgName>.” “Oh, you’re in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. I thought you went to college.” “Yeah, I went to college.” “Well, why are you in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>?” “Well, I’m an officer in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>.” “Oh, so you’re aboard a ship.” “No, I fly airplanes.” “Oh, so you’re in <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>.” “No, I’m in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>.” “Oh, so what are you doing in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>?” “Well, I did a tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.” “<placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? Well, how many babies did you kill?” And that’s usually about the time I’d leave, so—so I got kind of tired of—that got old real quick, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So how long—what <date>years</date> were you—what span of time were you home for?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, just—just a few days and then went back in my squadron back at <placeName>Patuxent River</placeName>, <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, so—yeah, I guess maybe <date>ten days or so</date>, I guess.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—hmm. You described a little bit about encountering some of that antiwar sentiment. Is <date>this 1970</date> now? What year is this?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, it would have been, like, <date>1969</date>, <date>1970</date> timeframe, yeah. And it wasn’t universal. I mean, most of my—most of my friends were—were good. But I remember a couple that were downright nasty about it. They weren’t close friends of mine in high school, but they were, you know, people I’d grown up with and gone to, you know—through elementary school and junior high and high school, so I knew them well. They weren’t people that I, you know, hung out with in high school, but certainly people that I would normally say hi to, and vice versa, so—you know, when I would see them when I was—you know, when I was out on the town, to stop in at, you know, one of the local—local bars or, you know, hangouts in town, I’d run into them. A couple of them were, you know, really strong antiwar—which is—that’s fine. They were certainly entitled to their opinion, but no need to take it out on the—on the servicemen.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And did you feel that it was being taken out on you? How did you feel about the war at that point? Did you have an opinion?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, I had—I supported what we—what we were doing over there. I didn’t think it was being prosecuted correctly, but that was way above my pay grade. But I didn’t support the antiwar protestors. I felt that if people were against the war, the way to do it was at the ballot box, certainly not to protest and disrupt stuff. And I certainly—from a personal standpoint, I certainly didn’t like being insulted or called a baby killer, especially considering the fact that we were not doing direct combat missions or anything like that. So I’ve never killed a person in my life, so— probably saved more. So anyway—yeah, but that was just a couple people that brought that up, in my hometown. Generally speaking, it’s—it was a relative—a conservative Midwestern town that normally supported the—supported the military and all that. The knowledge of the—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about the kind of interim time you spent back at the base Stateside? What happened up until you deployed next?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. We were—when I was back at—at the parent squadron, back at <placeName>Patuxent River</placeName>, when I was flying—I wasn’t flying nearly as much as I—as I wanted to. But when I was flying, we were flying oceanographic support missions. We had different—different missions back there. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me a little bit about—oh, sorry, sorry. I didn’t mean to interrupt you.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I was just going to say basically that’s what I did up until <date>August of 1970</date>, when I went back for my second tour.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I was going to ask you: Did you have a question on what else I did back there, or—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no. I was curious of what <date>daily</date> life was like in that—in that interim period.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh. I lived off base. Rented a place off base with a couple of the other pilots, one of which was <persName>this Pete Richardson</persName> that I’d mentioned before, Class of ’66. And there were three of us renting a place. A pretty nice place, actually, right on—right on <placeName>Chesapeake Bay</placeName>. Had our own swimming pool. It was actually the guest house of, like, an estate, and we were renting the guest house. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now—I’m sorry. Sorry.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I was just going to say <placeName>the Patuxent River</placeName> is a town right outside the gate. It’s in southern <placeName>Maryland</placeName>. Very small town. Almost nothing to do there. They didn’t even have any fast food restaurants in the town when I was there, I think probably, like, one movie theater, I think one or two stoplights. There was just—it was not a really great place for a bachelor to be stationed. The married people seemed to love it. It was a great place to raise a family and all that, but just not much going on for—for a bachelor. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. So you go back in <date>August 1970</date>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Right.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And at this point, what’s your rank?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I was a lieutenant. I had gotten promotion when I was actually over there the first time, when I was up at <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>. And by this time, I was an aircraft commander, so I was in charge of the mission when we were flying. But it was—it was starting to wind down. We no longer had the <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> mission. That had shut down. So just the Tan Son Nhut mission. And I was supposed to be over there for <date>six months</date>, but we actually ended winding everything up in <date>about four months</date> and closing down the—closing down the mission. So about—actually, about <date>the last month</date> I was over there, we weren’t doing a whole lot of flying, just some training flights to stay proficient. Pretty much had stopped the mission.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Had anything else changed that you noticed when you came back, not necessarily just about your unit but about the feeling in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, the feeling among troops and among civilians?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t recall that there—that there was a really big difference. There might have been, but I—I don’t recall. Certainly, there was a little bit more—as <orgName>I’m</orgName> trying to think back—there was probably a little bit more hustle and bustle over there than when I was over there in ’69. They were already starting to draw down the troops by ’70, so there wasn’t quite as much stuff going on out of <persName>Tan Son Nhut</persName> as before. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">But other than that, not a whole lot of changes.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So going back to—to your girlfriend at the time, did you ever tell people back home at all about her?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, my family knew about her. I mean, she wasn’t a serious girlfriend.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, yeah.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Girl. Yeah, they knew—I think I had shown them pictures of her, stuff. Like, I probably still have pictures of her buried away in my slides somewhere.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Did many other of your fellow officers have Vietnamese girlfriends?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, they didn’t, as a matter of fact. A couple of them did, but most of them didn’t have any one particular one. They certainly spent time with the Vietnamese girls, but I don’t think any one specific one. But I found one I liked [chuckles], so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. So let’s see, when did you head back?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Came back in <date>December</date>. We ferried the airplane back in <date>December of 1970</date>. And that was a fun trip because the aircraft was scheduled to go to what we referred to as “the bone yard.” It was going to be scrapped. It was going to go up to <orgName>Davis-Monthan Air [Force] Base</orgName> in <placeName>Tucson</placeName>, <placeName>Arizona</placeName>, to be cut up into—into scrap. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. So before we—well, actually, so can you tell me what you did next, once you got home, what your assignment was?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. It ended up—yeah, I got back to the—my squadron back in <date>December of 1970</date>. I was due to—due to transfer back out of there, just normal rotation, normal transfer, in <date>April</date>, I believe it was. But I didn’t particularly want to go through the trouble of trying to find a place to live just for <date>three or four months</date>, you know, so before we actually got back to the States, I’d written a letter to my commanding officer, who was a super nice guy, one of the finest gentlemen I ever met in my life, asking him if he would object if I requested a early transfer. And he didn’t, because we were getting rid of the airplanes anyway, so the squadron probably needed to draw down personnel anyway.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Can you tell me about what you did in <placeName>California</placeName> and how long you were there?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I was there for about—hmm—<date>two and a half, three years</date>. Got there. Was flying the same kind of aircraft that I was back in <placeName>the East Coast</placeName>, so I didn’t have to go through any additional training. And I was assigned to the Pacific Missile Range [Facility], and we did work for—working with the—pretty much <orgName>the Air Force</orgName> for part of the space program. Every time they would test one of their ICBMs [intercontinental ballistic missiles] and shoot it downrange, we would go down to <placeName>the South Pacific</placeName> to get the reentry telemetry data from the missiles. So we’d usually go down to either <placeName>Kwajalein Atoll</placeName> in <placeName>the Marshall Islands</placeName> or down to <placeName>American Samoa</placeName>, down there, and take off prior to the space shot out of Vandenberg Air Force Base and be there to get the reentry telemetry data.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And so during that—during that time, were you thinking at all about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, about if you’d go back, about what was happening there?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No. <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was pretty much winding down by that—that time. I do remember that one of the pilots—yeah, it was at my <placeName>West Coast</placeName> station. This was at [the Naval Air Station at] <placeName>Point Mugu</placeName> in <placeName>California</placeName>. Was due to rotate, and he got orders to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, even though they were winding it down, and they were asking to volunteers to go out there, and he didn’t want to volunteer, so they offered him a spot promotion if he took it, and he still didn’t want to go, so they sent him anyway. [Laughs.] I don’t know how that worked out for him, but—but, yeah, by—this would have been—you know, by ’72 or so they were pretty much—[President <persName>Richard M.]</persName> <persName>Nixon</persName> had pretty much declared victory, and we were pulling out.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, what did you think about <persName>Nixon</persName> and that pullout?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I—I was in favor of <persName>Nixon</persName>. And, of course, this was before I found out about [<name type="event">the] Watergate</name> [scandal]. But, you know, I supported his policy. I was glad to see that he reinstituted the bombing of the <placeName>North</placeName>. I thought [President <persName>Lyndon B.]</persName> <persName>Johnson</persName>’s policy of starting up and starting the bombing of the <placeName>North</placeName> was just idiotic. I mean, it just gives the enemy a chance to rearm and resupply and regroup and all that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So in terms of that appetite, of course at that time the American public was pretty upset, and I’m curious to know if you heard anything about what was happening at <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> in terms of <orgName>the Parkhurst [Hall</orgName>] takeovers, the protests there and what you thought of that.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I did. I did hear about the sit-in at <orgName>Parkhurst</orgName>, and I was, quite frankly, somewhat disgusted at it, but it didn’t come as a major surprise to me. I was really disappointed, and still am, that when <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> got <orgName>ROTC</orgName> off the campus and for <date>years</date> and <date>years</date> afterwards, I refused to make any contributions to the alumni fund because of that, so I figure, I guess, If you can protest a war, I can protest the college, so I didn’t—but I’ve since kind of let bygones be bygones, and I make my token contribution to the alumni fund <date>every year</date> now, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well, of course, <orgName>ROTC</orgName> is back, too, so—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Right, but not <orgName>NROTC</orgName>, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Ah. I see. And that is, that is important—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">And my understanding is—correct me if I’m wrong—aren’t you kind of—isn’t <orgName>ROTC</orgName> kind of in conjunction with—oh, one of the other colleges up there? You don’t actually—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS"><placeName>Norwich</placeName> [pronounced NOR-itch] [University], <placeName>Norwich</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, <placeName>Norwich</placeName>. That’s the advantage of getting older, <persName>Sandor</persName>. Things flit in and out of my brain like moths flying around in an attic, I guess. But, yeah, so do you guys actually have an <orgName>ROTC</orgName> staff on campus?</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah, we have two staff members.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, but it’s nowhere near like what it was when I was there, when they had–</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Oh, no, no.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, so—yeah, so it’s a mere shadow of its former—former self.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. </u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I was disgusted by all of it. I was horrified to hear about the My Lai Massacre. There were—I know that there were some veterans or servicemen that spoke out and, you know, said,  you know, if you weren’t—if you weren’t there, you shouldn’t have an opinion on it or something like that, and I certainly understand, to a certain degree, where they’re coming from because certainly I wasn’t out in the swamps or out in the jungle carrying a rifle; I wasn’t out in the infantry. I had it pretty easy, you know, being in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, and flying aircraft and being able to eat steak or hamburgers every night if I wanted to, and going out and having a girlfriend and whatever.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—and actually, that brings up an interesting point. Earlier, last interview session, we briefly discussed the diversity at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> during your time there, which—as is obvious, there wasn’t much diversity there. In fact, I recall you saying—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. In fact, I recall you saying that you really hadn’t ever met an Asian person before going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So after you’ve had here two tours there, you’re seeing all this stuff throughout the country kind of going on and these race riots, what were your thoughts on that? Did going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> change your thoughts on anything?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t know if going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> changed things. I mean, I was certainly growing up without any exposure to other races, but I was entirely supportive of civil rights. But I’m not a supporter of violent riots and burning down the cities, so—and I’m still not, so—<persName>Ferguson</persName> [<placeName>Missouri</placeName>, referencing the shooting of <persName>Michael Brown</persName>] and <placeName>Baltimore</placeName> being the most recent. I don’t think that that’s an appropriate way to react. If you’re not happy—I mean, I think there—I certainly can sympathize with their frustration—you know, with frustrations on it, but I think there’s more productive ways to channel your energy.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, speaking of appropriate actions, can I get your thoughts on [actress and <name type="event">anti-Vietnam</name> war activist] <persName>Jane Fonda</persName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh, God! Yeah, “Hanoi Jane.” Yeah. I still haven’t forgiven her for what she’s done, and if I ever do forgive her, I’ll never forget. Yeah. I think she was a traitor. She claims now that she was misunderstood and didn’t fully understand what she was doing over there. To me, that’s a poor excuse. So, yeah, I’ve got absolutely no use whatsoever for that woman. And that’s all I’m going to say on that.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Yeah. No worries, I—.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Right. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So that would bring you to around <date>1972</date>, <date>1973</date>? Can you tell me what you did next?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. I got orders to a [<orgName>Lockheed</orgName>] P-3 [<orgName>Orion</orgName>] patrol squadron [at the Naval Air Station] in <orgName>Barbers Point</orgName>, <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, so after I finished up at <placeName>Point Mugu</placeName>, I had to start my flight training to transition to the P-3 aircraft. The training for that was at Moffett Field [Moffett Federal Airfield] in the <placeName>San Francisco Bay</placeName> area.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So actually, I must admit, I forgot to ask you about <orgName>SERE School</orgName> in the beginning. I was planning on it, and certainly it seems like an interesting, maybe, mistake. And I know <orgName>SERE School</orgName> can be a very rough time, so I don’t want to press you for any details, but are there any memories from <orgName>SERE School</orgName>, specifically any memories you think are really pertinent to your later experiences, that you want to share?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, yeah. I mean, it was tough. <date>The first few days</date> wasn’t that bad because it was primarily a survival situ- —you know, training. It was done in the high desert of <placeName>California</placeName> in the summertime. And they told us right off the bat. They said, “Don’t waste your energy going out there trying to find food. <date>Every week</date> we bring a class out here, so over <date>the year</date>, and it’s always out to the same area, so believe, me,” they said, “all of the animals have long since been either scared off or eaten, so don’t even waste your time trying to find that.” And I guess to make up for that, they did give us some very, very limited rations because there wasn’t any food out there to scrounge, but—but the first part wasn’t that—that bad. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I’m very curious about the fall, but I just want to ask a couple quick questions to frame that. So can you tell me more about the P-3 aircraft and exactly what unit you were with?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. Let’s see a <orgName>Lockheed</orgName> P-3 Orion aircraft. It’s a military version. It’s not identical, but it’s based on the <orgName>Lockheed</orgName> [<orgName>L-188</orgName>] Electra airliner, but modifications made to it. It’s primarily used for anti-submarine patrol, but it’s capable of doing a multitude of missions: maritime airborne surveillance. It’s also capable of mine laying and stuff like that. But primarily what we did was—well, primarily what we did was training, but when we were deployed, we did out there maritime surveillance, and we also did anti-submarine (<orgName>ASW</orgName>) [anti-submarine warfare] training. The aircraft itself is a four-engine turboprop. It carries a crew of about 15. And the squadron I was in was Patrol Squadron 17, VP-17.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So at what point did you find out that you were going to go to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, that <placeName>Saigon</placeName> was fallen? Can you tell me about that progression?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, yeah. We just found out probably <date>a couple, three days</date> before we actually went down to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>. I was happy to go down to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> because I’d been there before and loved the place. We flew every—every night or so for a couple—three or four nights in a—in a row, I guess, providing surveillance off the coast of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> for the [<placeName>U.S.</placeName>] 7th Fleet. I mean, it was a huge endeavor that they had. They had I believe it was two aircraft carriers out there and I don’t know how many other support ships. I think all together there were, like, 50—50 ships involved in it.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So tell me more about what you were thinking about, what you knew about, what was going on on the ground. Are there any—so aside from, as you mentioned, your girlfriend, are there any other people you were specifically worried about?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, yeah, I was worried about our Vietnamese driver, who was kind of an elderly gentleman. <persName>He’d</persName>—I believe he’d worked for <orgName>the French Foreign Legion</orgName> when they were there, so he’d been around for a while. Real nice older guy, but certainly since he’d worked for the Americans, he was at risk. I don’t know what happened to him, so I was concerned about—about him as well.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—so after you get back from this mission, can you tell me about getting back that night? Do you remember much about that night?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, well, we were tired. We landed around sunup back in the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> and went and—went and got breakfast at the base exchange snack bar. I felt like—even though it was morning and I’d been flying all night, I could have used a cold beer, but they weren’t selling beer at that time of day, so [laughs] I think I went with Iced tea instead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So how did you feel about the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> getting out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, I thought it was probably the—the best of a bad situation. I mean, it became obvious to me that—that we weren’t going to fight that war to win it, so if we’re not going to fight it, might as well get out, so, yeah—I mean, and we had basically—had pulled all our troops out by—I think it was about, like, ’73 or so, so there weren’t any combat troops left in—in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, which is why they were overrun. My understanding is that the agreement that they had signed, <persName>Nixon</persName> and the South Vietnamese and <placeName>the North Vietnamese  </placeName>and all that—that if the North Vietnamese violated the—the agreement, that the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> would go—go in there and support the South Vietnamese again. But after <name type="event">Watergate</name>, <orgName>Ford</orgName> took over and decided not to honor that agreement, so we basically just let <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> go down the tubes, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me about the next part of your military career? I’m also interested kind of when in your time in the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> you ended up meeting your future wife.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Okay. After—so after <placeName>Saigon</placeName> fell, we were down there for, like I said, probably <date>about a week or so</date>. We went back to <placeName>Okinawa</placeName> and finished up our deployment in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName> and went back to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>. At that time [chuckles], I had a girlfriend in <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, so—so I was glad to get back and see her, who, interestingly enough, was from the—from the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, but not the one I married.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">No. No.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Oh. The DC-3. It’s a real old airplane. It’s a twin-engine tail dragger, but the <orgName>Navy</orgName> still had a few of them left, and they were all overseas, so I was flying those. And I guess one of the reasons that I was recalled is that the <orgName>Navy</orgName> really was short of pilots. They were so short of pilots over there that—normally, a pilot at a air station doesn’t do that much flying; he just pretty much keeps his proficiency up, and that’s about it. But they were so short of pilots that I just—that’s about all I did now, was fly over there. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—sorry. How did you meet your wife?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Met her—I was out, actually, in town shopping for some furniture to kind of spruce up my BOQ room and stopped in at a little furniture store, and she was—she was working there, and asked me if I wanted a cold beer. I can’t imagine furniture stores in the <placeName>States</placeName> offering you a cold beer, but they do over in the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, or at least did then. And so we got talking, and so I kept coming back to her furniture store and just started—starting going out.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What’s her name, by the way?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Eledenia [H.] [pronounced el-uh-DEN-yuh], E-l-e-d-e-n-i-a. She goes by “<persName>Denya</persName>.” So—so we got engaged and got married <date>about six months later</date>. Nice military wedding on base, at the base chapel. Had the cross arms, you know, arch with the groomsmen and all that, everybody in their dress uniforms. And a real nice wedding reception. It was the officers club.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Was your father or your siblings there?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, I—I didn’t invite them because I didn’t want them to feel obligated to try and make the trip all the way out there. I knew the heat would just possibly literally but certainly figuratively kill my dad. He just did not—especially in his older age, he did not handle heat and humidity very well, so I think that the trip out to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> would have just been too much for him, because he would have been—I’m trying to think—eighty- —say, he would have been close to 70, and so about my age now [chuckles], but, quite frankly, I’m in a lot better physical shape than he was at the same age, so—so, no, my family wasn’t—wasn’t there, so—[unintelligible]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me about the remaining part of the service? I mean, the remaining part of your service, rather.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, sure. So after left the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, got orders to—because I was in the <orgName>Reserves</orgName>—I got orders to a <orgName>Reserve</orgName> base, to be—the <orgName>Navy</orgName> had a program called TAR. Stood for Training Administrator Reserves [sic; <orgName>Training and Administration of the Reserve</orgName>, now known as <orgName>FTS</orgName>, Full Time Support]. It’s for active duty people. And their job is to, like the name says, administer and train the—the weekend warriors.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And what did you retire as?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Retired as a lieutenant commander, O-4. The <orgName>Navy</orgName> doesn’t look real kindly on people who have been passed over a couple of times for promotion, so that was—that was—or for the type aircraft I was flying, so that was—that was as high as I got.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And can you tell me about your times with the airline? Were there many other pilots who had served in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">There were. It never ceases to amaze me how kind of small the world really is. I was going through my ground school for <orgName>Henson Airlines</orgName>, which later became—they changed their name to <orgName>Piedmont Airlines</orgName>. It’s actually a commuter airline for <orgName>US Airways</orgName> [now part of <orgName>American Airlines</orgName>], wholly-owned subsidiary of <orgName>US Airways</orgName>. So flew as <orgName>US Airways Express</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">What was his name?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN"><persName>[Stephen R.] “Steve” Farrow</persName>, F-a-r-r-o-w. Yeah, he’s Class of ’65. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Have you been in contact with him at all?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No. No, the airlines are kind of—kind of strange. I don’t know if you know how airlines work, but there’s an adversarial relationship between management and—we were union, strangely enough. It was in <orgName>the Air Line Pilots Association [ International</orgName> (<persName>ALPA</persName>)]. So there was kind of an adversarial relationship between the union and management, so [chuckles] I didn’t have much to do with the vice president, so—I mean, when I saw him I’d say hi to him, and we’d visit and chat about <placeName>Dartmouth</placeName> or something like that. But since I—since I retired from the airlines, I—I haven’t stayed in contact with anybody from—from the airlines at all. I just walked away from that job and basically never—never looked back, unlike—I’ve stayed in touch with people from the <orgName>Navy</orgName> and a couple—couple people, not very many, a couple people from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, a lot more from the <orgName>Navy</orgName> than I have from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but nobody from the airline. Even though I was with the airline for <date>nearly 17 years</date>, it’s just like, Okay, I’m outta here. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">When did you leave the airline?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN"><date>Two thousand four</date>. Back in <date>those days</date>, the <orgName>FAA</orgName> [<orgName>Federal Aviation Administration</orgName>] had a mandatory <date>age 60</date> retirement. It’s since been changed to 65, but back then you had to retire on your 60th birthday, so I retired in <date>October</date> of two thousand—2004, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, let’s see, so looking back over that—over that time after you got out of the military, you wrote on the sheet you brought initially, that initial interview that you joined <orgName>the Retired Officers Association</orgName> in <date>1990</date>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah, that sounds—yeah, that sounds about right, yeah, since—the name has since been changed to <orgName>the Military Officers Association of America</orgName>, <orgName>MOAA</orgName>. They wanted to expand I think their base to include active duty people. But it used to be <orgName>the Retired Officers Association</orgName>, and they changed their name to <orgName>MOAA</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So can you tell me about your involvement with that and any other veterans organizations or groups?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I wouldn’t say I’m really involved in it. I pay my dues, and I—and I read the <date>monthly</date> magazine, and that’s pretty much the extent of it. I think there may possibly be a local chapter out here, but I’ve never gone to any meetings or anything like that, so, yeah, that’s basically the extent of it: Pay my dues and read the magazine.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I have a few very scattered questions that I noted down or forgot to ask over at different points. I looked you up, and it says that you earned a Bronze Star during your time in the <orgName>Navy</orgName>. Can you tell me about that and what that was for?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I didn’t actually earn a Bronze Star. I’m not sure where that came from. I think that that might have come from—there was a little—a little <orgName>Bronze Star</orgName> in lieu of a second award or something, but I’m not even sure. No, I did not win the Bronze Star. I did—my highest award—I did get two—was awarded two—two <orgName>Air Medals</orgName> from flying over in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. But, no, I never—never got the Bronze Star.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And an Air Medal is for?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, it can be award—it can be awarded for an individual action, but in my case it’s what’s they called a strike/flight award. They had a point system set up based on the number and types of combat or combat support missions you flew over there, and depending on whether you encounter hostile fire or actually were—the aircraft was damaged or—well, it depended on how many points you got if you—if you flew a mission, you got so many points—you know, actually, you got a fraction of a point. If you were shot at but they missed, you got more points. If you got shot at and hit, you got still more points. [Chuckles.]</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">All right, so—and then at one point, I believe when you were doing the scientific flights on <placeName>the West Coast</placeName>, there was a little—little picture and description in the alumni magazine, in <orgName>the Dartmouth Alumni Magazine</orgName>, talking about what you were doing at that point. Did you submit that to the magazine? Did they call you up and ask for it—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No, the—I think that was actually when I was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, to be honest with you, but that picture—I remember the picture. No, the <orgName>Navy</orgName> submitted that. I had no idea that—but the public affairs office in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> apparently submitted it to—to the college, and the college decided to publish it, so—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Interesting. </u>
      <u who="STEFFEN"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">—I’ve heard—I’ve heard that there was a lot of antiwar, veteran antiwar sentiment going on in <placeName>Okinawa</placeName>. Were you exposed to any of that?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">No. There was—it wasn’t so much anti- —well, by the time I was over there, like I said, the war had pretty much wound down. <placeName>Saigon</placeName> had—well, was in the process of falling while I was there, but all of the combat troops had been pulled out of <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> <date>a couple years earlier</date>, so there really wasn’t anything to protest. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So I have a few questions for you, general questions, looking back on your service, on the time after your service, on current events as they relate to your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So have you ever considered going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? What do you think of the current Vietnamese government?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I wouldn’t mind going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but—I’d kind of like to go back there, but it’s—as far as higher travel priorities, I’ve never been to <placeName>Europe</placeName>, so if I was going to spend that kind of money, I’d probably rather go to <placeName>Europe</placeName> and see someplace that I haven’t already, you know, been to. But certainly I wouldn't—you know, I’d like to—if somebody wanted to pay for a trip, I’d [chuckles]—I’d go in a heartbeat. I know my wife would like to go back to the—go back to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>, so you can maybe kill two birds with one stone. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And the current government there?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Yeah. It is what it is. I actually think they’re still, you know, exercising too much control, and they’re still not completely free, but they’ve got—but they’re no longer communist, I guess, or something like that. They certainly opened, you know, up to foreign investment and a lot of foreign companies are over there now and a lot of tourism and all that. I liked <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> when I was over there. I loved the <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> people. I liked <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, a very vibrant city—you know, except for the occasional rocket attacks, so, you know, I liked being over there.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Now, speaking of <placeName>U.S.</placeName> foreign policy, a lot of people like to compare <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> to at least <placeName>America</placeName>’s later was, for example, <placeName>Iraq</placeName> or <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN"><persName>Mm-hm</persName>. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">I’m curious what you think about those comparisons, both on a personal level and on a more technical, historical level.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, I think there’s—I think there can be a basis of a certain, you know, comparison in the sense that, in a way, they were both kind of wars of choice on our part. I didn’t—I mean, we started sending advisers into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> before I really became really aware of what was going on. I was still in high school and all that. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Any—any lingering thoughts on the treatment you received as a veteran, on your interactions with people after <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Well, recently it’s been real good. You know, ever since the first <name type="event">Gulf War</name>, the one that we won in <date>three days</date>, or whatever it was, in <placeName>Kuwait</placeName>—and now it seems like the military is the darling of the American public. And even the left that’s opposed to the war, I guess has possibly learned a lesson from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that—you know, that it makes more sense from—if you’re going to oppose something from the strategical opposition, it makes more sense to oppose a policy and not the—and not the troops, whereas before, during <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, they opposed not only the policy but they opposed the government as well as the individual service members. And you’re in <placeName>ROTC</placeName>, so you got to know that normally privates and sergeants and lieutenants are—rarely make policy or strategy, so to take it out on them was just—was just foolish, you know. </u>
      <u who="FARKAS">And any thoughts on how your <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> experience has affected not only just your time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> but your time after <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and the rest of your life?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t know. I mean, I certainly got a really good education at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, but as far as—as—as helping me, especially in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> or the airline, you know, basically they don’t care where you went to school [chuckles], to be honest with you. I mean, in the <orgName>Navy</orgName> it probably would have helped a little bit if I had gone to <orgName>the Naval Academy</orgName>, but other than that, to be honest with you, I don’t know that most of the people were any more impressed with somebody that went to an Ivy League college and somebody that went to <placeName>Podunk State</placeName> [a term for an insignificant college, not a real institution].</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I’m not sure [unintelligible]—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">So my second-to-last question—</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">—all that great, but—yeah, go ahead.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">[Chuckles.] How’d you find out about <orgName>the Dartmouth Vietnam Project</orgName>, and what made you agree to do it?</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">I don’t remember. I must have seen something maybe on one of the e-mails or possibly the alumni magazine or something like that. I honestly don’t remember. I said, What the heck, I’ll throw my name in the hat, and if anybody’s interested—because I thought—I think it’s a worthwhile project, and especially in <date>this day</date> and age, I would think that there are probably relatively few <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> graduates that are going into the military now, with the limited <placeName>ROTC</placeName> on campus and certainly, you know, people don’t have to worry about the draft or anything like that, so I think that—</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well, I just wanted to thank you for your participation in this project, for agreeing to sit down, virtually sit down with me and do this interview. It’s been a pleasure getting to hear your story, and thank you so much.</u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Okay. Well, you’re welcome. And if you’ve got—if you’re going over your notes and you need to clarify anything, feel free to either call or e-mail. I’m available [chuckles], most of the time, anyway.</u>
      <u who="FARKAS">Well, thank you. </u>
      <u who="STEFFEN">Okay. </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
